<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="robustness.2" title="Writing Correct Programs">

<p><start><big>C</big>orrect programs don't</start> just happen. It takes
planning and attention to detail to avoid errors in programs. There are some
techniques that programmers can use to increase the likelihood that their
programs are correct.</p>

<subsection id="robustness.2.1" title="Provably Correct Programs">
   
<p>In some cases, it is possible to <b>prove</b> that a program is
correct. That is, it is possible to demonstrate mathematically that the
sequence of computations represented by the program will always produce the
correct result. Rigorous proof is difficult enough that in practice it can only
be applied to fairly small programs. Furthermore, it depends on the fact that
the "correct result" has been specified correctly and completely. As I've
already pointed out, a program that correctly meets its specification is not
useful if its specification was wrong. Nevertheless, even in everyday
programming, we can apply some of the ideas and techniques that are used in
proving that programs are correct.</p>

<p>The fundamental ideas are <newword>process</newword> and
<newword>state</newword>. A state consists of all the information
relevant to the execution of a program at a given moment during its execution.
The state includes, for example, the values of all the
variables in the program, the output that has been produced, any input that is
waiting to be read, and a record of the position in the program where the
computer is working. A process is the sequence of states that the computer goes
through as it executes the program. From this point of view, the meaning of a
statement in a program can be expressed in terms of the effect that the
execution of that statement has on the computer's state. As a simple example,
the meaning of the assignment statement "<code>x&nbsp;=&nbsp;7;</code>" is that
after this statement is executed, the value of the variable <code>x</code> will be
7. We can be absolutely sure of this fact, so it is something upon which we can
build part of a mathematical proof.</p>

<p>In fact, it is often possible to look at a program and deduce that some fact
must be true at a given point during the execution of a program. For example,
consider the <code>do</code> loop:</p>

<pre>do {
   System.out.print("Enter a positive integer: ");
   N = TextIO.getlnInt();
} while (N &lt;= 0);</pre>

<np>After this loop ends, we can be absolutely sure that the value of the
variable <code>N</code> is greater than zero. The loop cannot end until this
condition is satisfied. This fact is part of the meaning of the <code>while</code>
loop. More generally, if a <code>while</code> loop uses the test "<code>while
(<bnf>condition</bnf>)</code>", and if there are no <code>break</code>
statements in the loop, then after the loop ends, we can be
sure that the <code><bnf>condition</bnf></code> is false. We can then
use this fact to draw further deductions about what happens as the execution of
the program continues. (With a loop, by the way, we also have to worry about
the question of whether the loop will ever end. This is something that has to
be verified separately.)</np>


</subsection>

<subsection title="Preconditions and Postconditions" id="robustness.2.2">

<p>A fact that can be proven to be true after a given program segment has been
executed is called a <newword>postcondition</newword> of that program
segment. Postconditions are known facts upon which we can build further
deductions about the behavior of the program. A postcondition of a program as a
whole is simply a fact that can be proven to be true after the program has
finished executing. A program can be proven to be correct by showing that the
postconditions of the program meet the program's specification.</p>

<p>Consider the following program segment, where all the variables are of type
<ptype>double</ptype>:</p>

<pre>disc = B*B - 4*A*C;
x = (-B + Math.sqrt(disc)) / (2*A);</pre>

<np>The quadratic formula (from high-school mathematics) assures us that the
value assigned to <code>x</code> is a solution of the equation <code>A*x<sup>2</sup> +
B*x + C = 0</code>, provided that the value of <code>disc</code> is greater than or equal
to zero and the value of <code>A</code> is not zero. <b>If</b> we can
guarantee that <code>B*B-4*A*C&nbsp;&gt;=&nbsp;0</code> and that <code>A&nbsp;!=&nbsp;0</code>, then the
fact that <code>x</code> is a solution of the equation becomes a postcondition of
the program segment. We say that the condition, <code>B*B-4*A*C&nbsp;&gt;=&nbsp;0</code> is a
<newword>precondition</newword> of the program segment. The condition
that <code>A&nbsp;!=&nbsp;0</code> is another precondition. A precondition is defined to be a
condition that must be true at a given point in the execution of a program in
order for the program to continue correctly. A precondition is something that
you want to be true. It's something that you have to check or force to be true,
if you want your program to be correct.</np>

<p>We've encountered preconditions and postconditions once before, in <localref href="subroutines.6.1"/>.
That section introduced preconditions and
postconditions as a way of specifying the contract of a subroutine. As the
terms are being used here, a precondition of a subroutine is just a
precondition of the code that makes up the definition of the subroutine, and
the postcondition of a subroutine is a postcondition of the same code. In this
section, we have generalized these terms to make them more useful in talking
about program correctness in general.</p>

<p>Let's see how this works by considering a longer program segment:</p>

<pre>do {
   System.out.println("Enter A, B, and C.");
   System.out.println("A must be non-zero and B*B-4*A*C must be &gt;= 0.");
   System.out.print("A = ");
   A = TextIO.getlnDouble();
   System.out.print("B = ");
   B = TextIO.getlnDouble();
   System.out.print("C = ");
   C = TextIO.getlnDouble();
   if (A == 0 || B*B - 4*A*C &lt; 0)
      System.out.println("Your input is illegal.  Try again.");
} while (A == 0 || B*B - 4*A*C &lt; 0);

disc = B*B - 4*A*C;
x = (-B + Math.sqrt(disc)) / (2*A);</pre>

<np>After the loop ends, we can be sure that <code>B*B-4*A*C&nbsp;&gt;=&nbsp;0</code> and that
<code>A&nbsp;!=&nbsp;0</code>. The preconditions for the last two lines are fulfilled, so the
postcondition that <code>x</code> is a solution of the equation <code>A*x<sup>2</sup> +
B*x + C = 0</code> is also valid. This program segment correctly and provably computes
a solution to the equation. (Actually, because of problems with representing real
numbers on computers, this is not 100% true. The <b>algorithm</b> is correct,
but the <b>program</b> is not a perfect implementation of the algorithm. See
the discussion in <localref href="robustness.1.3"/>.)</np>

<p>Here is another variation, in which the precondition is checked by an
<code>if</code> statement. In the first part of the <code>if</code> statement, where a
solution is computed and printed, we know that the preconditions are fulfilled.
In the other parts, we know that one of the preconditions fails to hold. In any
case, the program is correct.</p>

<pre>System.out.println("Enter your values for A, B, and C.");
System.out.print("A = ");
A = TextIO.getlnDouble();
System.out.print("B = ");
B = TextIO.getlnDouble();
System.out.print("C = ");
C = TextIO.getlnDouble();

if (A != 0 &amp;&amp; B*B - 4*A*C &gt;= 0) {
   disc = B*B - 4*A*C;
   x = (-B + Math.sqrt(disc)) / (2*A);
   System.out.println("A solution of A*X*X + B*X + C = 0 is " + x);
}
else if (A == 0) {
   System.out.println("The value of A cannot be zero.");
}
else {
   System.out.println("Since B*B - 4*A*C is less than zero, the");
   System.out.println("equation A*X*X + B*X + C = 0 has no solution.");
}</pre>

<p>Whenever you write a program, it's a good idea to watch out for
preconditions and think about how your program handles them. Often, a
precondition can offer a clue about how to write the program.</p>

<p>For example, every array reference, such as <code>A[i]</code>, has a
precondition: The index must be within the range of legal indices for the
array. For <code>A[i]</code>, the precondition is that <code>0&nbsp;&lt;=&nbsp;i 
&lt;&nbsp;A.length</code>. The computer will check this condition when it evaluates
<code>A[i]</code>, and if the condition is not satisfied, the program will be
terminated. In order to avoid this, you need to make sure that the index has a
legal value. (There is actually another precondition, namely that <code>A</code> is
not <code>null</code>, but let's leave that aside for the moment.) Consider the
following code, which searches for the number <code>x</code> in the array
<code>A</code> and sets the value of <code>i</code> to be the index of
the array element that contains <code>x</code>:</p>

<pre>i = 0;
while (A[i] != x) {
   i++;
}</pre>

<np>As this program segment stands, it has a precondition, namely that
<code>x</code> is actually in the array. If this precondition is satisfied, then
the loop will end when <code>A[i]&nbsp;==&nbsp;x</code>. That is, the value of <code>i</code>
when the loop ends will be the position of <code>x</code> in the array. However, if
<code>x</code> is not in the array, then the value of <code>i</code> will just keep
increasing until it is equal to <code>A.length</code>. At that time, the reference
to <code>A[i]</code> is illegal and the program will be terminated. To avoid this,
we can add a test to make sure that the precondition for referring to
<code>A[i]</code> is satisfied:</np>

<pre>i = 0;
while (<newcode>i &lt; A.length</newcode> &amp;&amp; A[i] != x) {
   i++;
}</pre>

<np>Now, the loop will definitely end. After it ends, <code>i</code> will satisfy
<b>either</b> <code>i&nbsp;==&nbsp;A.length</code> or <code>A[i]&nbsp;==&nbsp;x</code>. 
An <code>if</code> statement
can be used after the loop to test which of these conditions caused the loop to
end:</np>

<pre>i = 0;
while (i &lt; A.length &amp;&amp; A[i] != x) {
   i++;
}

if (i == A.length)
   System.out.println("x is not in the array");
else
   System.out.println("x is in position " + i);</pre>

</subsection>


<subsection id="robustness.2.3" title="Invariants">

<p>Let's look at how loops work in more detail.  Consider a
subroutine for finding the sum of the elements in an array of <ptype>int</ptype>:</p>

<pre>static int arraySum( int[] A ) {
    int total = 0;
    int i = 0;
    while ( i &lt; A.length ) {
        total = total + A[i];
        i = i + 1;
    }
    return total;
}</pre>

<np>(Note, by the way, that the requirements that <code>A</code> is not 
<code>null</code> is a precondition of the subroutine.  If it is violated, the code in 
the subroutine will throw a <code>NullPointerException</code>.)</np>

<p>How can we be sure that this subroutine works?  We need to prove
that when the <code>return</code> statement is executed, the value
of <code>total</code> is the sum of all the elements in&nbsp;<code>A</code>.  One way
to think about this problem is in terms of <newword>loop invariants</newword>.</p>

<p>A loop invariant is, roughly, a statement that remains true as the
loop is executed.  More precisely, we can show that a statement is an 
invariant for a loop if the following holds: As long as the statement
is true <b>before</b> the code inside the loop is executed, then it will
also be true <b>after</b> the code inside the loop has been executed.  That is,
a loop invariant is both a precondition and a postcondition of
the body of the loop.</p>

<p>A loop invariant for the loop in the above subroutine is,
"<code>total</code> is equal to the sum of the first <code>i</code>
elements of&nbsp;<code>A</code>."  Suppose this is
true at the beginning of the <code>while</code> loop.  That is, before the statement
"<code>total = total + A[i]</code>" is executed, <code>total</code>
is the sum of the first <code>i</code> elements of the
array (namely <code>A[0]</code> through <code>A[i-1]</code>).
After <code>A[i]</code> is added to <code>total</code>,
<code>total</code> is now the sum of the first <code>i+1</code>
elements of the array.  At this point, the loop invariant
is <b>not</b> true.  However, as soon as the next statement,
"<code>i = i + 1</code>" is executed, replacing
<code>i</code> with <code>i+1</code>, the loop
invariant becomes true again.  We have checked that if the
loop invariant is true at the start of the body of the loop, then is
also true at the end.</p>

<p>Note that a loop invariant is not necessarily true at <b>every</b>
point during the execution of a loop.  Executing one of the statements
in the loop can make it false temporarily, as long as later statements
in the loop make it true again.</p>

<p>So, have we proved that the subroutine <code>arraySum()</code> is
correct?  Not quite.  There are still a few things to check.  First of
all, we need to make sure that the loop invariant is true before the
very first time the loop is executed. At that point, <code>i</code>
is zero, and <code>total</code> is also equal to zero,  which is the
correct sum of zero elements.  So the loop invariant is true
before the loop. Once we know that, we know that it remains true after each
execution of the loop (because it's an invariant), and in particular,
we know that it will still be true after the loop ends.</p>

<p>But for that to do us any good, we need to check that the
loop actually does end!  In each execution of the loop,
the value of <code>i</code> goes up by one.  That means that
eventually it has to reach <code>A.length</code>.  At that
point, the condition in the <code>while</code> loop
is false, and the loop ends.</p>

<p>After the loop ends, we know that <code>i</code> equals
<code>A.length</code>, and we know that the loop invariant
is true.  At that point, since <code>i</code> is <code>A.length</code>, the loop invariant says,
"<code>total</code> is the sum of the first <code>A.length</code>"
elements of&nbsp;A."  But that includes <b>all</b> of the
elements of <code>A</code>.  So, the loop invariant gives us
exactly what we wanted to show:  When <code>total</code> is
returned by the subroutine, it is equal to the sum of all the 
elements of the array!</p>

<p>This might seem like a lot of work to you to prove something
that's obvious.  But if you try to explain <i>why</i> it's
obvious that <code>arraySum()</code> works, you'll probably
find yourself using the logic behind loop invariants, even if
you don't use the term.</p>

<p>Let's look more quickly at a similar example.  Consider a
subroutine that finds the maximum value in an array of <ptype>int</ptype>,
where we assume that the array has length at least one:</p>

<pre>static int maxInArray( int[] A ) {
    int max = A[0];
    int i = 1;
    while ( i &lt; A.length ) {
        if ( A[i] > max )
            max = A[i];
        i = i + 1;
    }
    return max;
}</pre>

<np>In this case, we have a loop invariant that says,
"<code>max</code> is the largest value among the first
<code>i</code> elements of&nbsp;<code>A</code>."
Suppose this is true before the <code>if</code> statement.
After the <code>if</code> statement, <code>max</code>
is greater than or equal to <code>A[i]</code>, because
that is a postcondition of the <code>if</code> statement,
and it is greater than or equal to <code>A[0]</code>
through <code>A[i-1]</code>, because of the truth
of the loop invariant.  Put those two facts together,
and you get that <code>max</code> is the largest value
among the first <code>i+1</code> elements of <code>A</code>.
When <code>i</code> is replaced by <code>i+1</code> in the
next statement, the loop invariant becomes true again.
After the loop ends, <code>i</code> is <code>A.length</code>,
and the loop invariant tells us exactly
what we need to know:  <code>max</code> is the largest
value in the whole array.</np>

<p>Loop invariants are not just useful for proving that
programs are correct.  Thinking in terms of loop invariants
can be useful when you are trying to develop an algorithm.
As an example, let's look at the insertion sort algorithm
that was discussed in <localref href="arrays.4.3"/>.
Suppose that we want to sort an array <code>A</code>.
That is, at the end of the algorithm, we want it to be
true that</p>

<pre>A[0] &lt;= A[1] &lt;= ... &lt;= A[A.length-1]</pre>

<np>The question is, what step-by-step procedure can we use to make this statement true?
Well, can we come up with a loop invariant that, at the end, will become
the statement that we want to be true?  If we want all of the elements
to be sorted at the end, how about a loop invariant that says that
some of the elements are sorted&mdash;say, that the first <code>i</code>
elements are sorted.  This leads to an outline for the algorithm:</np>

<pre>i = 0;
while (i &lt; A.length ) {
   // Loop invariant:  A[0] &lt;= A[1] &lt;= ... &lt;= A[i-1]
      .
      .  // Code that adds A[i] to the sorted portion of the array
      .
   i = i + 1;
}
// At this point, i = A.length, and A[0] &lt;= A[1] &lt;= ... &lt;= A[A.length-1]</pre>

<np>The loop invariant is true before the <code>while</code> loop,
and when the loop ends, the loop invariant becomes precisely the statement
that we want to be true at the end of the algorithm.
We know what we have to do to complete the
algorithm:  Develop code for the inside of the loop that will preserve
the truth of the loop invariant.  If we can do that, the loop invariant
will assure us that the algorithm that we have developed is correct.
The algorithm for adding <code>A[i]</code> to the sorted portion of
the array will require its own loop, with its own loop invariant. I'll
leave you to think about that.</np>

<break/>

<p>There is another kind of invariant that is useful for thinking
about programs: <newword>class invariants</newword>.
A class invariant is, roughly, a statement that is always true
about the state of a class, or about objects created from that class.
For example, suppose we have a <classname>PairOfDice</classname> class
in which the values shown on the dice are stored in instance
variables <code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code>.
(See <localref href="OOP.2"/> for a variety of such classes.)
We might like to have a class invariant that says, "the values of
<code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code> are in the range 1 through&nbsp;6."
(This would be a statement about any object created from the
<classname>PairOfDice</classname> class, not about the class as such.)
After all, this is a statement that should always be true about
any pair of dice.
</p>

<p>But in order to be a class invariant, the statement has to be
guaranteed true at all times.  If <code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code>
are <code>public</code> instance variables, then no such guarantee is
possible, since there is no way to control what values a program that uses
the class might assign to them.
So, we are led to make <code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code>
<code>private</code>.  Then we just have to make sure that all of the
code in the class definition respects the class invariant.
That is, first of all, when a <classname>PairOfDice</classname> object
is constructed, the variables <code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code>
must be initialized to be in the range 1 to&nbsp;6.  Furthermore, every
method in the class must preserve the truth of the class invariant.
In this case, that means that any method that assigns a value to
<code>die1</code> or <code>die2</code> must ensure that the
value is in the range 1 to&nbsp;6.  For example, a setter method
would have to check that a legal value is being assigned.</p>

<p>In general, we can say that a class invariant is a postcondition
of every constructor and is both a precondition and a postcondition
of every method in the class.  When you are writing a class, a
class invariant is something that you <i>want be be true</i> at
all times.  When you write a method, you need to make sure that
the code in that method respects the invariant:  Assuming that
the class invariant is true when the method in called, you need to
ensure that it will still be true after the code in the method is
executed.  This kind of thinking can be a very useful tool
for class design.</p>

<p>As another example, consider a dynamic array class, 
like the one in <localref href="arrays.2.4"/>.  That class uses
an ordinary array to store values and a counter to keep track
of how many items have been added to the dyanmic array:</p>

<pre>private int[] items = new int[8];
private int itemCount = 0;</pre>

<np>Class invariants include the facts that "<code>itemCount</code> is the number of items,"
that "<code>0&nbsp;&lt;=&nbsp;itemCount&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;items.length</code>," and that "the items are in
the array elements <code>items[0]</code> through <code>items[itemCount-1]</code>."
Keeping these invariants in mind can be helpful when writing the class.  When writing a method
for adding an item, the first invariant reminds you to increment <code>itemCount</code>
in order to ensure that the invariant remains true.  The second invariant tells you
where the new item has to be stored.  And the third invariant tells you that if
incrementing <code>itemCount</code> makes it equal to <code>items.length</code>,
then you will need to do something to avoid violating the invariant.  (Since <code>itemCount</code>
has to be incremented, the invariant means that you will have to make the array bigger.)</np>

<p>In future chapters, I will occasionally point out how it can be useful to
think in terms of preconditions, postconditions, and invariants.</p>

<p>I should note that reasoning about invariants becomes much more complicated in parallel
programs, when several threads that are running at the same time and are accessing the
same data.  This will be an issue when we encounter threads in <localref href="threads"/>.</p>

</subsection>

   
<subsection id="robustness.2.4" title="Robust Handling of Input">

<p>One place where correctness and robustness are important&mdash;and especially
difficult&mdash;is in the processing of input data, whether that data is typed in
by the user, read from a file, or received over a network. Files and networking
will be covered in <localref href="IO"/>, which will
make essential use of material that will be covered in the <localref href="robustness.3">next section</localref> 
of this chapter. For now, let's look at an example of processing user input.</p>

<p>Examples in this textbook use my <classname>TextIO</classname> class for reading input
from the user. This class has built-in error handling. For example, the
function <code>TextIO.getDouble()</code> is guaranteed to return a legal value of
type <ptype>double</ptype>. If the user types an illegal value, then
<classname>TextIO</classname> will ask the user to re-enter their response; your
program never sees the illegal value.  However, this approach can be
clumsy and unsatisfactory, especially when the user is entering complex data.
In the following example, I'll do my own error-checking.</p>

<p>Sometimes, it's useful to be able to look ahead at what's coming up in the
input without actually reading it. For example, a program might need to know
whether the next item in the input is a number or a word. For this purpose, the
<classname>TextIO</classname> class includes the function <code>TextIO.peek()</code>. This
function returns a <ptype>char</ptype> which is the next character in the user's
input, but it does not actually read that character. If the next thing in the
input is an end-of-line, then <code>TextIO.peek()</code> returns the new-line
character, <code>'\n'</code>.</p>

<p>Often, what we really need to know is the next <b>non-blank</b>
character in the user's input. Before we can test this, we need to skip past
any spaces (and tabs). Here is a function that does this. It uses
<code>TextIO.peek()</code> to look ahead, and it reads characters until the next
character in the input is either an end-of-line or some non-blank character.
(The function <code>TextIO.getAnyChar()</code> reads and returns the next character
in the user's input, even if that character is a space. By contrast, the more
common <code>TextIO.getChar()</code> would skip any blanks and then read and return
the next non-blank character. We can't use <code>TextIO.getChar()</code> here since
the object is to skip the blanks <b>without</b> reading the next
non-blank character.)</p>

<pre>/**
 * Reads past any blanks and tabs in the input.
 * Postcondition:  The next character in the input is an
 *                 end-of-line or a non-blank character.
 */
static void skipBlanks() {
   char ch;
   ch = TextIO.peek();
   while (ch == ' ' || ch == '\t') {
         // Next character is a space or tab; read it
         // and look at the character that follows it.
      ch = TextIO.getAnyChar();
      ch = TextIO.peek();
   }
} // end skipBlanks()</pre>
   
<np>(In fact, this operation is so common that it is built into 
<code>TextIO</code>.  The method <code>TextIO.skipBlanks()</code>
does essentially the same thing as the <code>skipBlanks()</code> method
presented here.)</np>

<p>An example in <localref href="control.5.3"/> allowed the user to
enter length measurements such as "3 miles" or "1ft". It would then convert
the measurement into inches, feet, yards, and miles. But people commonly use
combined measurements such as "3 feet 7 inches". Let's improve the program so
that it allows inputs of this form.</p>

<p>More specifically, the user will input lines containing one or more
measurements such as "1 foot" or "3 miles 20 yards 2 feet". The legal units of
measure are inch, foot, yard, and mile. The program will also recognize plurals
(inches, feet, yards, miles) and abbreviations (in, ft, yd, mi). Let's write a
subroutine that will read one line of input of this form and compute the
equivalent number of inches. The main program uses the number of inches to
compute the equivalent number of feet, yards, and miles. If there is any error
in the input, the subroutine will print an error message and return the value
<code>-1</code>. The subroutine assumes that the input line is not empty. The main program
tests for this before calling the subroutine and uses an empty line as a signal
for ending the program.</p>

<p>Ignoring the possibility of illegal inputs, a pseudocode algorithm for the
subroutine is</p>

<pre>inches = 0    // This will be the total number of inches
while there is more input on the line:
    read the numerical measurement
    read the units of measure
    add the measurement to inches
return inches</pre>

<np>We can test whether there is more input on the line by checking whether the
next non-blank character is the end-of-line character. But this test has a
precondition: We have to make sure that the next character in the input is
in fact either an end-of-line or is a non-blank.  To ensure that, we
need to skip over any blank characters. So, the algorithm becomes</np>

<pre>inches = 0
skipBlanks()
while TextIO.peek() is not '\n':
    read the numerical measurement
    read the unit of measure
    add the measurement to inches
    skipBlanks()
return inches</pre>

<np>Note the call to <code>skipBlanks()</code> at the end of the <code>while</code>
loop. The call to <code>skipBlanks()</code> ensures that the precondition 
for the test is again true.  More generally, if the test in a <code>while</code>
loop has a precondition, then you have to make sure that this precondition
holds at the <b>end</b> of the while loop, before the computer jumps
back to re-evaluate the test, as well as before the start of the loop.</np>

<p>What about error checking? Before reading the numerical measurement, we have
to make sure that there is really a number there to read. Before reading the
unit of measure, we have to test that there is something there to read. (The
number might have been the last thing on the line. An input such as "3",
without a unit of measure, is not acceptable.) Also, we have to check that the unit of
measure is one of the valid units: inches, feet, yards, or miles. Here is an
algorithm that includes error-checking:</p>

<pre>inches = 0
skipBlanks()

while TextIO.peek() is not '\n':

    if the next character is not a digit:
       report an error and return -1
       
    Let measurement = TextIO.getDouble();

    skipBlanks()    // Precondition for the next test!!
    if the next character is end-of-line:
       report an error and return -1                   
    Let units = TextIO.getWord()
    
    if the units are inches:
        add measurement to inches
    else if the units are feet:
        add 12*measurement to inches
    else if the units are yards:
        add 36*measurement to inches
    else if the units are miles:
        add 12*5280*measurement to inches
    else
        report an error and return -1
 
    skipBlanks()

return inches</pre>

<p>As you can see, error-testing adds significantly to the complexity of the
algorithm. Yet this is still a fairly simple example, and it doesn't even
handle all the possible errors. For example, if the user enters a numerical
measurement such as <code>1e400</code> that is outside the legal range of values of type
<ptype>double</ptype>, then the program will fall back on the default error-handling
in <classname>TextIO</classname>. 
Something even more interesting happens if the measurement is "1e308 miles".
The number <code>1e308</code> is legal, but the corresponding number of inches is outside
the legal range of values for type <ptype>double</ptype>. As mentioned in the 
<localref href="robustness.1.3">previous section</localref>, 
the computer will get the value <code>Double.POSITIVE_INFINITY</code>
when it does the computation. You might want to run the program and try this out.</p>

<p>Here is the subroutine written out in Java:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Reads the user's input measurement from one line of input.
 * Precondition:   The input line is not empty.
 * Postcondition:  If the user's input is legal, the measurement
 *                 is converted to inches and returned.  If the
 *                 input is not legal, the value -1 is returned.
 *                 The end-of-line is NOT read by this routine.
 */
static double readMeasurement() {

   double inches;  // Total number of inches in user's measurement.
   
   double measurement;  // One measurement, 
                        //   such as the 12 in "12 miles"
   String units;        // The units specified for the measurement,
                        //   such as "miles"
   
   char ch;  // Used to peek at next character in the user's input.

   inches = 0;  // No inches have yet been read.

   skipBlanks();
   ch = TextIO.peek();
   
   /* As long as there is more input on the line, read a measurement and
      add the equivalent number of inches to the variable, inches.  If an
      error is detected during the loop, end the subroutine immediately
      by returning -1. */

   while (ch != '\n') {
   
       /* Get the next measurement and the units.  Before reading
          anything, make sure that a legal value is there to read. */
   
       if ( ! Character.isDigit(ch) ) {
           System.out.println(
                 "Error:  Expected to find a number, but found " + ch);
           return -1;
       }
       measurement = TextIO.getDouble();
       
       skipBlanks();
       if (TextIO.peek() == '\n') {
           System.out.println(
                 "Error:  Missing unit of measure at end of line.");
           return -1;
       }
       units = TextIO.getWord();
       units = units.toLowerCase();
       
       /* Convert the measurement to inches and add it to the total. */
       
       if (units.equals("inch") 
               || units.equals("inches") || units.equals("in")) {
           inches += measurement;
       }
       else if (units.equals("foot") 
                  || units.equals("feet") || units.equals("ft")) {
           inches += measurement * 12;
       }
       else if (units.equals("yard") 
                  || units.equals("yards") || units.equals("yd")) {
           inches += measurement * 36;
       }
       else if (units.equals("mile") 
                  || units.equals("miles") || units.equals("mi")) {
           inches += measurement * 12 * 5280;
       }
       else {
           System.out.println("Error: \"" + units 
                             + "\" is not a legal unit of measure.");
           return -1;
       }
     
       /* Look ahead to see whether the next thing on the line is 
          the end-of-line. */
      
       skipBlanks();
       ch = TextIO.peek();
       
   }  // end while
   
   return inches;
   
} // end readMeasurement()
</pre>

<np>The source code for the complete program can be found in the file 
<sourceref href="LengthConverter2.java"/>.</np>
   
</subsection>

</section>