<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE exercises SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<exercises>

<exercise>
   <exercise-question><p>Write a program that will
print your initials to standard output in letters that are nine lines tall.
Each big letter should be made up of a bunch of *'s. For example, if your
initials were "DJE", then the output would look something like:</p>

<pre>******           *************        **********
**    **                **            **
**     **               **            **
**      **              **            **
**      **              **            ********
**      **       **     **            **
**     **         **    **            **
**    **           **  **             **
*****               ****              ********** </pre>
   </exercise-question>
   <exercise-discuss>
<p>This is a very simple program. It consists of nothing but a sequence of
<code>System.out.println</code> statements.  The hard part is designing the letters. You have to
experiment in your text editor until you get letters that look right to you.
Add <code>System.out.println("</code> at the beginning of the first line, then
copy-and-paste it to the beginning of each of the other lines. (You don't need
to type it out on each line! Creative use of copy-and-paste can save you a lot
of work.) Then add <code>");</code> to the end of each line. In my program, I've
also added a <code>System.out.println()</code> statement at the beginning and the
end. The extra blank lines make the output look better.</p>

<p>Don't forget that in order to have a complete program, you have to put the
program statements in a <code>main</code> subroutine and put that subroutine in a
<code>public</code> <code>class</code>.  Also, the name of the file must correspond to the
name of the class; in this case, the file must be named PrintInitials.java.</p>
   </exercise-discuss>
   <exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="PrintInitials">
    public class PrintInitials {
      
       /*  This program prints my initials (DJE) in big letters,
           where each letter is nine lines tall.
       */
    
       public static void main(String[] args) {
          System.out.println();
          System.out.println("           ******           *************        **********");
          System.out.println("           **    **                **            **");
          System.out.println("           **     **               **            **");
          System.out.println("           **      **              **            **");
          System.out.println("           **      **              **            ********");
          System.out.println("           **      **       **     **            **");
          System.out.println("           **     **         **    **            **");
          System.out.println("           **    **           **  **             **");
          System.out.println("           *****               ****              **********");
          System.out.println();
       }  // end main()

    }  // end class
   </prog></pre>
   </exercise-code> 
</exercise>


   
<exercise id="basics.ex.2">
   <exercise-question><p> Write a program that
simulates rolling a pair of dice. You can simulate rolling one die by choosing
one of the integers 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, or 6 at random. The number you pick
represents the number on the die after it is rolled. As pointed out in <localref href="basics.5"/>, the expression</p>

<pre>(int)(Math.random()*6) + 1</pre>

<np>does the computation to select a random integer between 1 and 6.
You can assign this value to a variable to represent one of the dice that are
being rolled. Do this twice and add the results together to get the total roll.
Your program should report the number showing on each die as well as the total
roll. For example:</np>

<pre>The first die comes up 3
The second die comes up 5
Your total roll is 8</pre>
   </exercise-question>
   <exercise-discuss>
<p>When designing a program, one of the first things you should ask yourself
is, "What values do I need to represent?" The answer helps you decide what
variables to declare in the program. This program will need some variables to
represent the numbers showing on each die and the total of the two dice. Since
these numbers are all integers, we can use three variables of type
<ptype>int</ptype>. I'll call the variables <code>die1</code>, <code>die2</code>, and
<code>roll</code>. The program begins by declaring the variables:</p>

<pre>int die1;
int die2;
int roll;</pre>

<np>In the actual program, of course, I've added a comment to explain the
purpose of each variable. The values of <code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code> can be
computed using the expression given in the exercise:</np>

<pre>die1 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1;
die2 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1;</pre>

<np>Note that even though the expressions on the right-hand sides of these
assignment statements are the same, the values can be different because the
function <code>Math.random()</code> can return different values when it is called
twice.</np>

<p>We can then compute <code>roll = die1 + die2</code> and use three
<code>System.out.println</code> statements to display the three lines of
output:</p>

<pre>System.out.println("The first die comes up " + die1);
System.out.println("The second die comes up " + die2);
System.out.println("Your total roll is " + roll);</pre>

<np>Note that I've chosen to use the concatenation operator, <code>+</code>, to
append the value of <code>die1</code> onto the string "The first die comes up".
Alternatively, I could use two output statements:</np>

<pre>System.out.print("The first die comes up ");
System.out.println(die1);</pre>

<np>Yet another possibility is to use <code>System.out.printf</code>:</np>

<pre>System.out.printf("The first die comes up %d%n", die1);</pre>

<np>I'll also note that I could get away without the variable <code>roll</code>,
since I could output the value of the expression <code>die1 + die2</code>
directly:</np>

<pre>System.out.println("Your total roll is " + (die1 + die2));</pre>

<np>However, it's generally better style to have a meaningful name for a
quantity. By the way, the parentheses around <code>(die1 + die2)</code> are
essential because of the precedence rules for the <code>+</code> operator. You
might try to experiment with leaving them out and see what happens.</np>
   </exercise-discuss>
   <exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="RollTheDice">
public class RollTheDice {
   
    /*  This program simulates rolling a pair of dice.
        The number that comes up on each die is output,
        followed by the total of the two dice.
    */
 
    public static void main(String[] args) {
    
        int die1;   // The number on the first die.
        int die2;   // The number on the second die.
        int roll;   // The total roll (sum of the two dice).
        
        die1 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1;
        die2 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1;
        roll = die1 + die2;
        
        System.out.println("The first die comes up " + die1);
        System.out.println("The second die comes up " + die2);
        System.out.println("Your total roll is " + roll);

    }  // end main()
 
}  // end class
</prog></pre>
   </exercise-code> 
</exercise>


   
<exercise>
   <exercise-question><p>Write a program that asks
the user's name, and then greets the user by name. Before outputting the user's
name, convert it to upper case letters. For example, if the user's name is
Fred, then the program should respond "Hello, FRED, nice to meet you!".</p>
   </exercise-question>
   <exercise-discuss>
<p>In order to read the name typed in by the user, this program uses one of the
input routines from the non-standard <classname>TextIO</classname> class. So, this program
can only be run if that class is available to the program.  I will use <code>System.out</code>
for output.  (Although it is possible to use <code>TextIO</code> for output as
well as for input, I will generally avoid that option in my examples.)</p>

<p>A name is a sequence of characters, so it is a value of type
<classname>String</classname>. The program must declare a variable of type <classname>String</classname> to
hold the user's name. I declare another variable to hold the user's name with
all the letters in the name converted to upper case. The conversion might be
difficult, except that <classname>String</classname> objects have a function that lets you do the
conversion with one line of code. If <code>usersName</code> is the variable that refers to the name that
the user enters, then the function call <code>usersName.toUpperCase()</code>
returns the string obtained by replacing any lower case letters in the name
with upper case letters.</p>

<p>There are several functions in the <classname>TextIO</classname> class that can be used for
reading <code>Strings</code>: <code>getWord()</code>, <code>getlnWord()</code>, and
<code>getln()</code>. The first two routines only read a single word, so if the
user entered "David J. Eck", they would only read the first name, "David". The
<code>getln()</code> routine will read the entire line, and so would get the whole
name. For this program, I use <code>getln()</code>, but you might prefer to use just
the first name.</p>

<p>I also give a version of the program that uses the built-in
class <classname>Scanner</classname>, instead of <classname>TextIO</classname>, for
reading input from the user.  See <localref href="basics.4.6"/> for a discussion of
the <classname>Scanner</classname> class.  In the second version of the program,
a <classname>Scanner</classname> named <code>stdin</code> is created, and
the user's input is read using the function <code>stdin.nextLine()</code>, which
has essentially the same functionality as <code>TextIO.getln()</code>.</p>

<p>(For this program, by the way, <code>TextIO.getWord()</code> and <code>TextIO.getlnWord()</code>
would be equivalent. They return the same value. The second version of the
routine, <code>getlnWord()</code>, would then discard the rest of the user's line
of input. However, since this program is only doing one input operation, it
doesn't matter whether it's discarded. It would only matter when it came time
to read a second value from input.)</p>

   </exercise-discuss>
   <exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="Greeting">
public class Greeting {
   
    /*  This program asks the user's name and then
        greets the user by name.  This program depends
        on the non-standard class, TextIO.
    */
 
    public static void main(String[] args) {
    
        String usersName;      // The user's name, as entered by the user.
        String upperCaseName;  // The user's name, converted to upper case letters.
        
        System.out.print("Please enter your name: ");
        usersName = TextIO.getln();
        
        upperCaseName = usersName.toUpperCase();
        
        System.out.println("Hello, " + upperCaseName + ", nice to meet you!");
    
    }  // end main()
 
}  // end class
</prog></pre>

<np><b><u>A version using <classname>Scanner</classname> for input:</u></b>
</np>

<pre><prog name="GreetingWithScanner"><newcode>import java.util.Scanner;</newcode>

public class GreetingWithScanner {
    
    public static void main(String[] args) {
    
        <newcode>Scanner stdin = new Scanner( System.in );</newcode>
    
        String usersName;      // The user's name, as entered by the user.
        String upperCaseName;  // The user's name, converted to upper case letters.
        
        System.out.print("Please enter your name: ");
        usersName = <newcode>stdin.nextLine()</newcode>;
        
        upperCaseName = usersName.toUpperCase();
        
        System.out.println("Hello, " + upperCaseName + ", nice to meet you!");
    
    }  // end main()
 
}  // end class
</prog></pre>
   </exercise-code> 
</exercise>


   
<exercise>
   <exercise-question><p>Write a program that helps
the user count his change. The program should ask how many quarters the user
has, then how many dimes, then how many nickels, then how many pennies. Then
the program should tell the user how much money he has, expressed in
dollars.</p>
   </exercise-question>
   <exercise-discuss>
<p>The program will need variables to represent the number of each type of
coin. Since the number of coins has to be an integer, these variables are of
type <ptype>int</ptype>. I'll call the variables <code>quarters</code>, <code>dimes</code>,
<code>nickels</code>, and <code>pennies</code>.</p>

<p>The total value of the coins, when expressed in dollars, can be a
non-integer number such as 1.57 or 3.02. Since the total value in dollars is a
real number, I will use a variable of type <ptype>double</ptype> to represent it. The
variable is named <code>dollars</code></p>

<p>The outline of the program is clear enough:</p>

<pre>Declare the variables.
Ask the user for the number of each type of coin, and read the responses.
Compute the total value of the coins, in dollars.
Display the result to the user.</pre>

<np>The function <code>TextIO.getlnInt()</code> can be used to read each of the
user's responses. The alternative function <code>TextIO.getInt()</code> could also
be used, but it is less safe. Suppose, for example, that the user responds to
the request to type in the number of quarters by entering "7 quarters". After
<code>TextIO.getlnInt()</code> reads the number 7, it will discard the extra input
"quarters". <code>TextIO.getInt()</code> will read the 7 correctly, but the extra
input is not discarded. Later, when the program tries to read the number of
dimes, it sees the left-over input and tries to read that, without giving the
user a chance to type in another response. You might want to experiment and see
what happens if you change <code>getlnInt()</code> to <code>getInt()</code>. (Of
course, if the user's response is "I have 7 quarters" or "seven", then you are
out of luck in any case.)</np>

<p>Since one quarter is worth 0.25 dollars, the number of dollars in N quarters
is 0.25*N. Similarly, a dime is worth 0.10 dollars, a nickel is 0.05 dollars,
and a penny is 0.01 dollars. So, to get the total value of all the user's
coins, I just have to add up <code>(0.25*quarters) + (0.10*dimes) +
(0.05*nickels) + (0.01*pennies)</code>. This value is assigned to the variable,
<code>dollars</code>, and that is the result that is displayed to the user.
Formatted output, using <code>System.out.printf</code>,
can be used to specify that the output value should be printed with two
digits after the decimal point.</p>

<p>Alternatively, I could first have computed the total number of cents in all
the coins, and then divided by 100 to convert the amount into dollars:</p>

<pre>int totalCents;   // Total number of cents in the coins.

totalCents = 25*quarters + 10*dimes + 5*nickels + pennies;
dollars = totalCents/100.0;</pre>

<np>Since <code>totalCents</code> is of type <ptype>int</ptype>, it is essential here that
I compute <code>dollars</code> as <code>totalCents/100.0</code> and not as
<code>totalCents/100</code>. The value computed by <code>totalCents/100</code> is an
integer. For example, if <code>totalCents</code> is 397, then
<code>totalCents/100</code> is 3. Using <code>totalCents/100.0</code> forces the
computer to compute the answer as a real number, giving 3.97.</np>

<p>A second version of the program, using a <classname>Scanner</classname> for input,
is also given.  (See <localref href="basics.4.6"/>.)  A <classname>Scanner</classname>
named <code>stdio</code> is created, and integers are read using the function
<code>stdio.nextInt()</code>.  This method corresponds to <code>TextIO.getInt()</code>,
not <code>TextIO.getlnInt()</code>.  To get something equivalent to <code>TextIO.getlnInt()</code>,
we can follow the call to <code>stdio.nextInt()</code> with a call to <code>stdio.nextLine()</code>.
The call to <code>stdio.nextLine()</code> will read and discard any extra characters on the
same line after the integer that was read by <code>stdio.nextInt()</code>.  If you are not
worried about the user typing extra stuff on a line, you can leave out the calls to
<code>stdio.nextInt()</code>.</p>

   </exercise-discuss>
   <exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="CountChange">public class CountChange {
  
   /*  This program will add up the value of a number of quarters,
       dimes, nickels, and pennies.  The number of each type of 
       coin is input by the user.  The total value is reported
       in dollars.  This program depends on the non-standard class,
       TextIO.
   */

   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
      int quarters;   // Number of quarters, to be input by the user.
      int dimes;      // Number of dimes, to be input by the user.
      int nickels;    // Number of nickels, to be input by the user.
      int pennies;    // Number of pennies, to be input by the user.
      
      double dollars; // Total value of all the coins, in dollars.
      
      /* Ask the user for the number of each type of coin. */
      
      System.out.print("Enter the number of quarters:  ");
      quarters = TextIO.getlnInt();
      
      System.out.print("Enter the number of dimes:     ");
      dimes = TextIO.getlnInt();
      
      System.out.print("Enter the number of nickels:   ");
      nickels = TextIO.getlnInt();
      
      System.out.print("Enter the number of pennies:   ");
      pennies = TextIO.getlnInt();
      
      /* Add up the values of the coins, in dollars. */
      
      dollars = (0.25 * quarters) + (0.10 * dimes) 
                          + (0.05 * nickels) + (0.01 * pennies); 
      
      /* Report the result back to the user. */
      
      System.out.println();
      System.out.print("The total in dollars is $");
      System.out.printf("%1.2f", dollars);  // Formatted output!
      System.out.println();
   
   }  // end main()
 
}  // end class
</prog></pre>


<np><b><u>A version using <classname>Scanner</classname> for input:</u></b>
</np>

<pre><prog name="CountChangeWithScanner"><newcode>import java.util.Scanner;</newcode>

public class CountChangeWithScanner {
  
   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
      int quarters;   // Number of quarters, to be input by the user.
      int dimes;      // Number of dimes, to be input by the user.
      int nickels;    // Number of nickels, to be input by the user.
      int pennies;    // Number of pennies, to be input by the user.
      
      <newcode>Scanner stdio = new Scanner( System.in );</newcode>
      
      double dollars; // Total value of all the coins, in dollars.
      
      /* Ask the user for the number of each type of coin. */
      
      System.out.print("Enter the number of quarters:  ");
      quarters = <newcode>stdio.nextInt();
      stdio.nextLine();</newcode>
      
      System.out.print("Enter the number of dimes:     ");
      dimes = <newcode>stdio.nextInt();
      stdio.nextLine();</newcode>
      
      System.out.print("Enter the number of nickels:   ");
      nickels = <newcode>stdio.nextInt();
      stdio.nextLine();</newcode>
      
      System.out.print("Enter the number of pennies:   ");
      pennies = <newcode>stdio.nextInt();
      stdio.nextLine();</newcode>
      
      /* Add up the values of the coins, in dollars. */
      
      dollars = (0.25 * quarters) + (0.10 * dimes) 
                          + (0.05 * nickels) + (0.01 * pennies); 
      
      /* Report the result back to the user. */
      
      System.out.println();
      System.out.print("The total in dollars is $");
      System.out.printf("%1.2f", dollars);  // Formatted output!
      System.out.println();
   
   }  // end main()
 
}  // end class
</prog></pre>

   </exercise-code> 
</exercise>


   
<exercise>
   <exercise-question><p>If you have <code>N</code>
eggs, then you have <code>N/12</code> dozen eggs, with <code>N%12</code> eggs left
over. (This is essentially the definition of the <code>/</code> and <code>%</code>
operators for integers.) Write a program that asks the user how many eggs she
has and then tells the user how many dozen eggs she has and how many extra eggs
are left over.</p>
<p>A gross of eggs is equal to 144 eggs. Extend your program so that it will
tell the user how many gross, how many dozen, and how many left over eggs she
has. For example, if the user says that she has 1342 eggs, then your program
would respond with</p>

<pre>Your number of eggs is 9 gross, 3 dozen, and 10</pre>

<np>since 1342 is equal to 9*144 + 3*12 + 10.</np>
   </exercise-question>
   <exercise-discuss>
<p>All the variables for the program will be of type <ptype>int</ptype>. The
quantities that we have to represent are: the number of eggs, the number of
dozens in that many eggs, and the number of left over eggs. I will declare
variables named <code>eggs</code>, <code>dozens</code>, and <code>extras</code> to
represent these quantities.</p>

<p>The number of eggs can be read from the user's input using <code>eggs =
TextIO.getlnInt()</code>.</p>

<p>The description of the problem already tells us that <code>dozens</code> can be
computed as <code>eggs/12</code> and <code>extras</code> can be computed as
<code>eggs%12</code>. So, the first version of the program is easy to write.
Note that the entire output from this program could have been done with
one <code>System.out.printf</code>:</p>

<pre>System.out.print("Your number of eggs is %d dozen and %d extras%n", 
                                 dozens, extras);</pre>

<p>The improved version requires a little thought. Given a pile of eggs that
you want to divide into gross, dozens, and extras, you could first remove as
many gross as possible, leaving a pile of between 0 and 143 eggs. This is just
like dividing the pile into dozens, except that the unit of measure is 144 eggs
instead of 12. So, <code>eggs/144</code> will give the number of gross, and
<code>eggs%144</code> is the number of eggs left over. Next, the eggs in the left-over
pile still have to be divided into dozens, plus some extra number of eggs
between 0 and 11. Of course, we already know how to do this: If there are
<code>N</code> eggs in the pile, the number of dozens is <code>N/12</code> and the
number of extra eggs is <code>N%12</code>. This leads to the computation in the
improved version of the program, shown below. (Note that this program uses the
variable named <code>aboveGross</code> to represent a quantity that is not
mentioned explicitly in the problem description. This is far from being
unusual.)</p>
   </exercise-discuss>
   <exercise-code>
<pre>
<prog name="Dozens">public class Dozens {
  
   /*  This program will convert a given number of eggs into
       the number of dozens plus the number of left over eggs.
       For example, 57 eggs is 4 dozen eggs plus 9 eggs left over.
       The number of eggs is input by the user, and the computed
       results are displayed. 
   */

   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
      int eggs;    // Number of eggs, input by user.
      int dozens;  // How many dozens in that number of eggs?
      int extras;  // How many eggs are left over, above an integral
                   //    number of dozens?  This value is in the
                   //    range 0 to 11, and it is computed as
                   //    the remainder when eggs is divided by 12.
   
      System.out.print("How many eggs do you have?  ");
      eggs = TextIO.getlnInt();
      
      dozens = eggs / 12;
      extras = eggs % 12;
      
      System.out.print("Your number of eggs is ");
      System.out.print(dozens);
      System.out.print(" dozen and ");
      System.out.print(extras);
      System.out.println();
   
   }  // end main()

}  // end class
</prog></pre>

<np><b><u>Improved version:</u></b>
</np>

<pre><prog name="GrossAndDozens">
public class GrossAndDozens {
  
   /*  This program will convert a given number of eggs into
       the number of gross plus the number of dozens plus the
       number of left over eggs.
          For example, 1342 eggs is 9 gross plus 3 dozen plus 10.
       The number of eggs is input by the user, and the computed
       results are displayed. 
   */

   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
      int eggs;         // Number of eggs, input by user.
      int gross;        // How many gross in that number of eggs?
      int aboveGross;   // How many eggs are left over, above an
                        //    integral number of gross?  This number
                        //    can be computed as eggs % 144, and is
                        //    in the range 0 to 143.  This number will
                        //    be divided into dozens and extras.
      int dozens;       // How many dozens in aboveGross?
      int extras;       // How many eggs are left over, above integral
                        //    numbers of gross and dozens? 
   
      System.out.print("How many eggs do you have?  ");
      eggs = TextIO.getlnInt();
      
      gross = eggs / 144;
      aboveGross = eggs % 144;
      
      dozens = aboveGross / 12;
      extras = aboveGross % 12;          
      
      System.out.print("Your number of eggs is ");
      System.out.print(gross);
      System.out.print(" gross, ");
      System.out.print(dozens);
      System.out.print(" dozen, and ");
      System.out.print(extras);
      System.out.println();
   
   }  // end main()

}  // end class
</prog></pre>

   </exercise-code> 
</exercise>



<exercise>
<exercise-question><p>This exercise asks you to write a program that tests
some of the built-in subroutines for working with <classname>Strings</classname>.
The program should ask the user to enter their first name and their last name, separated
by a space.  Read the user's response using <code>TextIO.getln()</code>.
Break the input string up into two strings, one containing the first name
and one containing the last name.  You can do that by using the <code>indexOf()</code>
subroutine to find the position of the space, and then using <code>substring()</code>
to extract each of the two names.  Also output the number of characters in each 
name, and output the user's initials.  (The initials are the first letter of
the first name together with the first letter of the last name.)
 A sample run of the program should look something like this:</p>
<pre>Please enter your first name and last name, separated by a space.
? <newcode>Mary Smith</newcode>
Your first name is Mary, which has 4 characters
Your last name is Smith, which has 5 characters
Your initials are MS</pre>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss>
<p>Once you have the first name and the last name in separate <classname>String</classname>
variables, it's easy to produce the desired output.  The length of a string, <code>str</code>,
can be obtained by calling the function <code>str.length()</code>.  To get the first
character of <code>str</code>, you can call <code>str.charAt(0)</code>.  (Remember that
characters are numbered starting from zero.)  If the first and last names are in the
variables <code>firstName</code> and <code>lastName</code>, then the output of the
program can be produced using</p>
<pre>System.out.println("Your first name is " + firstName + ", which has "
                          + firstName.length() + " characters.");
System.out.println("Your last name is " + lastName + ", which has "
                          + lastName.length() + " characters.");
System.out.println("Your initials are " + firstName.charAt(0) + lastName.charAt(0));</pre>
<np>Or, using formatted output to make it easier to read:</np>
<pre>System.out.printf( "Your first name is %s, which has %d characters.%n",
                                   firstName, firstName.length() );
System.out.printf( "Your last name is %s, which has %d characters.%n",
                                   lastName, lastName.length() );
System.out.print( "Your initials are %s%s%n", 
                                   firstName.charAt(0), lastName.charAt(0) );</pre>
<np>Note that it is not necessary to put values like <code>firstName.length()</code>
and <code>firstName.charAt(0)</code> into their own variables, if all that you want
to do with them is print them out.  (But some people might consider it better style
to use variables.)</np>
<p>The harder part of the problem is breaking up the input string to get the first
and last name.  If the user's input is in a <classname>String</classname> named
<code>input</code>, then <code>input.indexOf('&nbsp;')</code> is an <ptype>int</ptype>
that gives the position of the space in the string.  (Note that the space
character is written as a literal that consists of a space between two left single 
quotation marks.)</p>
<p>Once you have the position of the space, you have to figure out how to use it to
get the first and last name.  Let's look at exactly how the characters in a
string are numbered:</p>
<pre>         M  a  r  y     S  m  i  t  h
         0  1  2  3  4  5  6  7  8  9</pre>
<np>In this example, the space is at index 4.  We have to extract the substring in 
positions 0 through 3 and the substring in positions 5 through 9.
The value of <code>input.substring(start,end)</code>  will be a string that
starts in position <code>start</code> and ends in position <code>end-1</code>.
Note that the value of the second parameter is the position <b>after</b>
the end of the substring.  So, the fist name in this case is <code>input.substring(0,4)</code>
and the last name is <code>input.substring(5,10)</code>. (Even though there is no character
in position 10, that's the correct value for the position after the end of the substring that
we want.)  In fact, there's an easier way to get the last name, using another version 
of <code>substring</code>: The value of <code>input.substring(start)</code>
is the substring starting at position <code>start</code> and extending to the end
of the string, so the last name in this example is <code>input.substring(4)</code>.</np>
<p>The important thing to note here is that the "4" in <code>input.substring(0,4)</code>
is the index of the space character, and the "5" in 
<code>input.substring(5)</code> is that index plus&nbsp;1.  So we can
get the first and last names using:</p>
<pre>space = input.indexOf(' ');
firstName = input.substring(0,space);  // Everything <b>before</b> the space
lastName = input.substring(space+1);   // Everything <b>after</b> the space</pre>
<p>By the way, this program will only work correctly if the user follows the
instructions.  If the user's input does not contain a space, then the value of
<code>input.indexOf('&nbsp;')</code> will be -1, and the -1 will cause the program
to crash when used in the substring function.  And if the input doens't have exactly one
space, then the program output won't be correct.  For now, you don't have any way
to test the user's input to see whether it is correct.  To do that, you need to
know about <code>if</code> statements, which you will learn about very soon.</p>
<p>One more remark:  Instead of using <code>TextIO.getln()</code> to read a line
of text and then breaking that line into two words, you could simply use
<code>TextIO.getWord()</code> twice to read the two words from the same line of
input&mdash;except that the exercise says to use <code>getln()</code>.</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code><pre><prog name="FirstNameLastName">/**
 * This program reads the user's first name and last name,
 * separated by a space.  It then prints the user's first and
 * last names separately, along with the number of characters
 * in each name.  It also prints the user's initials.  Note that
 * this program will crash if the user's input does not contain
 * a space.
 */
public class FirstNameLastName {
    
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        
        String input;     // The input line entered by the user.
        int space;        // The location of the space in the input.
        String firstName; // The first name, extracted from the input.
        String lastName;  // The last name, extracted from the input.
        
        System.out.println();
        System.out.println("Please enter your first name and last name, separated by a space.");
        System.out.print("? ");
        input = TextIO.getln();
        
        space = input.indexOf(' ');
        firstName = input.substring(0, space);
        lastName = input.substring(space+1);
        
        System.out.println("Your first name is " + firstName + ", which has "
                                  + firstName.length() + " characters.");
        System.out.println("Your last name is " + lastName + ", which has "
                                  + lastName.length() + " characters.");
        System.out.println("Your initials are " + firstName.charAt(0) + lastName.charAt(0));
        
    }

}
</prog>
</pre></exercise-code>
</exercise>



   
<exercise>
   <exercise-question><p>Suppose that a file named "testdata.txt" contains the following information:
      The first line of the file is the name of a student.  Each of the next three
      lines contains an integer.  The integers are the student's scores on three
      exams.  Write a program that will read the information in the file
      and display (on standard output) a message that contains the name of
      the student and the student's average grade on the three exams.
      The average is obtained by adding up the individual exam grades and
      then dividing by the number of exams.
      </p>
   </exercise-question>
   <exercise-discuss>
      <p><classname>TextIO</classname> can be used to read data from a file; this is discussed
      in <localref href="basics.4.4"/>.  To read data from a file named
      "testdata.txt", all you need to do is say <code>TextIO.readFile("testdata.txt")</code>.
      From then on, the input functions in <classname>TextIO</classname> will read from the file
      instead of reading data typed in by the user.  (Note that this assumes that
      the file is in the same directory with the program.)  In this case, we
      can use <code>TextIO.getln()</code> to read the student's name from the first
      line of the file, and then we can read the exam grades by calling
      <code>TextIO.getln()</code> three times.</p>
      <p>The average should be computed as a value of type double.  Don't forget
      that if you divide an integer by an integer in Java, the result is an integer
      and the remainder of the division is discarded.  To get the correct
      average in this case, the program divides the sum of the three grades by
      3.0 rather than by 3.
      </p>
      <p>One final technicality is that simply outputting a <ptype>double</ptype>
      value might print out something like 83.333333333333333.  By default, all
      significant digits in the number are output.  In this case, one digit
      after the decimal point is probably sufficient.  The program
      uses formatted output to achieve this:</p>
      
      <pre>System.out.printf("The average grade for %s was %1.1f", name, average);</pre>
    
      <np>The format string
      "The average grade for %s was %1.1f" is used
      to format the name and the average.  The name is substituted for the
      format specifier <code>%s</code>, which means that the name is
      printed as a string, with no extra spaces.  The average is substituted
      for <code>%1.1f</code>, which means that the average
      is printed as a floating point number with no extra spaces and with
      1 digit after the decimal point.</np>
      <p>You might want to run this program with no data file, or with a
      data file that is not in the correct format, to see what happens.
      (The program will crash and print an error message.)</p>
   </exercise-discuss>
   <exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="FindAverage">
public class FindAverage {

   public static void main(String[] args) {

       String name;     // The student's name, from the first line of the file.
       int exam1, exam2, exam3;     // The student's grades on the three exams.
       double average;  // The average of the three exam grades.

       TextIO.readFile("testdata.txt");  // Read from the file.

       name = TextIO.getln();  // Reads the entire first line of the file.
       exam1 = TextIO.getlnInt();
       exam2 = TextIO.getlnInt();
       exam3 = TextIO.getlnInt();

       average = ( exam1 + exam2 + exam3 ) / 3.0;

       System.out.printf("The average grade for %s was %1.1f", name, average);
       System.out.println();

   }

}
</prog>
</pre>
   </exercise-code>
</exercise>

</exercises>