<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="subroutines.1" title="Black Boxes and Procedural Abstraction" shorttitle="Black Boxes">
   
<p><start><big>A</big> subroutine consists of instructions</start> for
performing some task, chunked together and given a name. "Chunking" allows you
to deal with a potentially very complicated task as a single concept. Instead
of worrying about the many, many steps that the computer might have to go
though to perform that task, you just need to remember the name of the
subroutine. Whenever you want your program to perform the task, you just call
the subroutine. Subroutines are a major tool for dealing with complexity.</p>

<p>A subroutine is sometimes said to be a "black box" because you can't see
what's "inside" it (or, to be more precise, you usually don't
<b>want</b> to see inside it, because then you would have to deal
with all the complexity that the subroutine is meant to hide). Of course, a
black box that has no way of interacting with the rest of the world would be
pretty useless. A black box needs some kind of <newword>interface</newword> 
with the rest of the world, which allows some
interaction between what's inside the box and what's outside. A physical black
box might have buttons on the outside that you can push, dials that you can
set, and slots that can be used for passing information back and forth. Since
we are trying to hide complexity, not create it, we have the first rule of
black boxes:</p>

<narrower>
<p><b>The interface of a black box should be fairly straightforward,
well-defined, and easy to understand.</b>
</p>
</narrower>

<p>Are there any examples of black boxes in the real world? Yes; in fact, you
are surrounded by them. Your television, your car, your mobile phone, your
refrigerator&dots;. You can turn your television on and off, change channels, and
set the volume by using elements of the television's interface&mdash;on/off switch, remote
control, don't forget to plug in the power&mdash;without understanding anything
about how the thing actually works. The same goes for a mobile phone, although
the interface in that case is a lot more complicated.</p>

<p>Now, a black box does have an inside&mdash;the code in a subroutine that
actually performs the task, or all the electronics inside your television set. The
inside of a black box is called its <newword>implementation</newword>. 
The second rule of black boxes is that:</p>

<narrower>
<p><b>To use a black box, you shouldn't need to know anything about its
implementation; all you need to know is its interface.</b>
</p>
</narrower>

<p>In fact, it should be possible to <b>change</b> the
implementation, as long as the behavior of the box, as seen from the outside,
remains unchanged. For example, when the insides of TV sets went from using
vacuum tubes to using transistors, the users of the sets didn't need to
know about it&mdash;or even know what it means. Similarly, it should be possible
to rewrite the inside of a subroutine, to use more efficient code for example,
without affecting the programs that use that subroutine.</p>

<p>Of course, to have a black box, someone must have designed and built the
implementation in the first place. The black box idea works to the advantage of
the implementor as well as the user of the black box. After all, the black
box might be used in an unlimited number of different situations. The
implementor of the black box doesn't need to know about any of that. The
implementor just needs to make sure that the box performs its assigned task and
interfaces correctly with the rest of the world. This is the third rule of
black boxes:</p>

<narrower>
<p><b>The implementor of a black box should not need to know anything about the
larger systems in which the box will be used.</b>
</p>
</narrower>

<p>In a way, a black box divides the world into two parts: the inside
(implementation) and the outside. The interface is at the boundary, connecting
those two parts.</p>

<break/>

<p>By the way, you should <b>not</b> think of an interface as just
the physical connection between the box and the rest of the world. The
interface also includes a <newword>specification</newword> of what
the box does and how it can be controlled by using the elements of the physical
interface. It's not enough to say that a TV set has a power switch; you need to
specify that the power switch is used to turn the TV on and off!</p>

<p>To put this in computer science terms, the interface of a subroutine has a
semantic as well as a syntactic component. The syntactic part of the interface
tells you just what you have to type in order to call the subroutine. The
semantic component specifies exactly what task the subroutine will accomplish.
To write a legal program, you need to know the syntactic specification of the
subroutine. To understand the purpose of the subroutine and to use it
effectively, you need to know the subroutine's semantic specification. I will
refer to both parts of the interface&mdash;syntactic and semantic&mdash;collectively
as the <newword>contract</newword> of the subroutine.</p>

<p>The contract of a subroutine says, essentially, "Here is what you have to do
to use me, and here is what I will do for you, guaranteed." When you write a
subroutine, the comments that you write for the subroutine should make the
contract very clear. (I should admit that in practice, subroutines' contracts
are often inadequately specified, much to the regret and annoyance of the
programmers who have to use them.)</p>

<p>For the rest of this chapter, I turn from general ideas about black boxes
and subroutines in general to the specifics of writing and using subroutines in
Java. But keep the general ideas and principles in mind. They are the reasons
that subroutines exist in the first place, and they are your guidelines for
using them. This should be especially clear in <localref href="subroutines.6"/>,
where I will discuss subroutines as a tool in program development.</p>

<p>You should keep in mind that subroutines are not the only example of black
boxes in programming. For example, a class is also a black box. We'll see that
a class can have a "public" part, representing its interface, and a "private"
part that is entirely inside its hidden implementation. All the principles of
black boxes apply to classes as well as to subroutines.</p>

<break/>

<p><localref href="control.1.3a"/> introduced the idea of "control abstraction" to 
express the fact that a Java control structure lets the user work on a
higher level than machine language, hiding the details of the process
in the CPU that implements the control structure.
</p>

<p>In a similar way, we say that a subroutine is a <newword>procedural abstraction</newword>.
The interface of a subroutine is an abstraction that you can use to carry out some
procedure without worrying about the details of how the procedure is actually implemented.
This is just another, fancier way of saying that the subroutine can be used as a
black box, but it brings us back to abstraction as a central concept in computer science.</p>

<p>An important aspect of abstraction in general is <newword>information hiding</newword>.
An abstraction hides information about what is behind the abstraction, in its implementation.
Information hiding by control abstractions is what makes it possible to use the same
Java control structures on different types of CPU, with different underlying machine
language implementations.  Information hiding by procedural abstractions is what makes
it possible for the inside of a subroutine to be changed without affecting the programs
in which the subroutine is used.  Again, this is just another term for the black box principle.
</p>


</section>