<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="subroutines.4a" title="Lambda Expressions">

<p><start><big>I</big>n a running program, a subroutine is just</start> a bunch of
binary numbers (representing instructions) stored somewhere in the computer's memory.
Considered as a long string of zeros and ones,
a subroutine doesn't seem all that different from a data value such as, for example, 
as an integer, a string, or an array, which is also represented as a string of
zeros and ones in memory.  We are used to thinking of subroutines and data as
very different things, but inside the computer, a subroutine is just another
kind of data.  Some programming languages make it possible to work with a
subroutine as a kind of data value.  In Java&nbsp;8, that ability was added to
Java in the form of something called <newword>lambda expressions.</newword></p>

<p>Lambda expressions are becoming more and more common in Java programs.
They are especially useful for working with the stream API that will be
covered in <localref href="generics.6"/><fx> and with
the JavaFX GUI toolkit. It will definitely be useful to know about them before we 
cover GUI programming in <localref href="GUI1"/></fx>.  However, 
we won't encounter them again until near the end
of <localref href="OOP"/>, so you can skip this section for now if you want.</p>

<subsection title="First-class Functions" id="subroutines.4a.1">

<p>Lambda is a letter in the Greek alphabet that was used by the mathematician
Alonzo Church in his study of computable functions.  His lambda notation makes
it possible to define a function without giving it a name.  For example, you
might think that the notation <i>x</i><sup>2</sup> is a perfectly good way of
representing a function that squares a number, but in fact, it's an
expression that represents the result of squaring <i>x</i>, which leaves
open the question of what <i>x</i> represents.  We can define a function
with <i>x</i> as a dummy parameter:</p>

<pre>static double square( double x ) {
    return x*x;
}</pre>

<np>but to do that, we had to name the function <i>square</i>, and that name becomes
a permanent part of the program&mdash;which is overkill if we just want to use the
function once.  Alonzo Church introduced the notation <i>lambda</i>(<i>x</i>).<i>x</i><sup>2</sup>
to represent "the function of <i>x</i> that is given by <i>x</i><sup>2</sup>" (except using
the Greek letter instead of the word "lambda").  This notation is a kind of function literal
that represents a value of type "function" in the same way that 42 is an integer literal 
that represents a value of type <ptype>int</ptype>.</np>

<p>Having function literals is the starting point for thinking of a function as just
another kind of data value. Once we do that, we should be able to do the same things
with functions that we can do with other values, such as assign a function to a variable,
pass a function as a parameter to a subroutine, return a function as the value of
subroutine, or even make an array of functions.  A programming language that allows
you to do all those things with functions is said to have "first-class functions" or
"functions as first-class objects."</p>

<p>In fact, you can do all of those things with Java lambda expressions.  Java's notation
is different from the one used by Alonzo Church, and in spite of the name "lambda expression"
it does not even use the word lambda.  In Java, the lambda expression for a squaring function 
like the one above can be written</p>

<pre>x  -&gt;  x*x</pre>

<np>The operator <code>-&gt;</code> is what makes this a lambda expression.  The dummy parameter
for the function is on the left of the operator, and the expression that computes the value of
the function is on the right. You might see an expression like this one being passed as an
actual parameter to a subroutine, assigned to a variable, or returned by a function.</np>

<p>So are functions now first-class in Java?  I'm not quite sure.  There are some cool things that can be done in
other languages but can't be done in Java.  For example, in Java we can assign the above expression
to a variable named, say, <i>sqr</i>, but we can't then use <i>sqr</i> as if it actually
is a function.  For example, we can't say <i>sqr</i>(42).  The problem, really, is that
Java is a strongly typed language; to have a variable named <i>sqr</i>, we must declare that
variable and give it a type.  But what sort of type would be appropriate for a value that
is a function?  The answer in Java is something called a <newword>functional interface</newword>,
which we turn to next.</p>

<p>But first one more note:  Lambda expressions in Java can actually represent arbitrary
subroutines, not just functions.  Nevertheless, it is the term "function" that is usually
associated with them, rather than "subroutine" or "method."</p>

</subsection>


<subsection title="Functional Interfaces" id="subroutines.4a.2">

<p>To know how a subroutine can be legally used, you need to know its
name, how many parameters it requires, their types, and the return type of the subroutine.
A functional interface specifies this information about one subroutine.  A functional
interface is similar to a class, and it can be defined in a .java file, just like a
class.  However, its content is just a specification for a single subroutine.
Here is an example:</p>

<pre>public interface FunctionR2R {
    double valueAt( double x );
}</pre>

<np>This code would be in a file named <classname>FunctionR2R.java</classname>.  It specifies a
function named <i>valueAt</i> with one parameter of type <ptype>double</ptype>
and a return type of <ptype>double</ptype>.  (The <b>name</b> of the parameter, <i>x</i>, is
not really part of the specification, and it's a little annoying that it has to be there.)
Here is another example:</np>

<pre>public interface ArrayProcessor {
    void process( String[] array, int count );
}</pre>

<np>Java comes with many standard functional interfaces.  One of the most important is
a very simple one named <classname>Runnable</classname>, which is already defined in
Java as</np>

<pre>public interface Runnable {
    public void run();
}</pre>

<np>I will use these three functional interfaces for examples in this section.</np>

<p>"Interfaces" in Java can be much more complicated than functional interfaces.  You will
learn more about them in <localref href="OOP.7"/>.  But it is only functional interfaces that
are relevant to lambda expressions: a functional interface provides a template for a subroutine
that might be represented by a lambda expression.  The name of a functional interface is
a <b>type</b>, just as <classname>String</classname> and <ptype>double</ptype> are types.
That is, it can be used to declare variables and parameters and to specify the return type
of a function.  When a type is a functional interface, a value for that type can be given
as a lambda expression.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection title="Lambda Expressions" id="subroutines.4a.3">

<p>A lambda expression represents an anonymous subroutine, that is, one without a name.
But it does have a formal parameter list and a definition.  The full syntax is:
</p>

<pre>( <bnf>parameter-list</bnf> )  -&gt;  { <bnf>statements</bnf> }</pre>

<np>As with a regular subroutine, the <bnf>parameter-list</bnf> can be
empty, or it can be a list of parameter declarations, separated by commas,
where each declaration consists of a type followed by a parameter name.
However, the syntax can often be simplified.  First of all, the parameter
types can be omitted, as long as they can be deduced from the context.
For example, if the lambda expression is known to be of type <classname>FunctionR2R</classname>,
then the parameter type must be <ptype>double</ptype>, so it is unnecessary to specify
the parameter type in the lambda expression. Next, if there is exactly
one parameter and if its type is not specified, then the parentheses around
the parameter list can be omitted.  On the right-hand side of the <code>-&gt;</code>,
if the only thing between the braces, <code>{</code>&nbsp;and <code>}</code>, is a 
single subroutine call statement, then the braces can be omitted.  And if
the right-hand side has the form <code>{</code>&nbsp;<code>return</code>&nbsp;<bnf>expression</bnf>;&nbsp;<code>}</code>,
then you can omit everything except the <bnf>expression</bnf>.</np>

<p>For example, suppose that we want a lambda expression to represent a function that
computes the square of a <ptype>double</ptype> value.  The type of such a function
can be the <classname>FunctionR2R</classname> interface given above.  If <i>sqr</i>
is a variable of type <classname>FunctionR2R</classname>, then the value of
the function can be a lambda expression, which can be written in any of the following
forms:</p>

<pre>sqr = (double x) -> { return x*x; }; // The full lambda expression syntax!
sqr = (x) -> { return x*x; };
sqr = x -> { return x*x; };
sqr = x -> x*x;
sqr = (double fred) -> fred*fred;
sqr = (z) -> z*z;</pre>

<np>The last two statements are there to emphasize that the parameters in a lambda expression
are dummy parameters; their names are irrelevant.  The six lambda expressions in these statements
all define exactly the same function.  Note that the parameter type <ptype>double</ptype> can be
omitted because the compiler knows that <code>sqr</code> is of type <classname>FunctionR2R</classname>,
and a <classname>FunctionR2R</classname> requires a parameter of type <ptype>double</ptype>.
A lambda expression can only be used in a context where the compiler can deduce its type,
and the parameter type has to be included only in a case where leaving it out would make
the type of the lambda expression ambiguous.</np>

<p>Now, in Java, the variable <i>sqr</i> as defined here is not quite a function.
It is a value of type <classname>FunctionR2R</classname>, which means that it <b>contains</b>
a function named <i>valueAt</i>, as specified in the definition of interface
<classname>FunctionR2R</classname>.  The full name of that function is <i>sqr.valueAt</i>,
and we must use that name to call the function.  For example:  <code>sqr.valueAt</code>(42)
or <code>sqr.valueAt(x)&nbsp;+ sqr.valueAt(y)</code>.</p>

<p>When a lambda expression has two parameters, the parentheses are not optional.
Here is an example of using the <classname>ArrayProcessor</classname> interface,
which also demonstrates a lambda expression with a multiline definition:</p>

<pre>ArrayProcessor concat;
concat = (A,n) -&gt; { // parentheses around (A,n) are required!
    String str;
    str = "";
    for (int i = 0; i &lt; n; i++)
        str += A[i];
    System.out.println(str);
};  // The semicolon marks the end of the assignment statement;
    //      it is not part of the lambda expression.

String[] nums;
nums = new String[4];
nums[0] = "One";
nums[1] = "Two";
nums[2] = "Three";
nums[3] = "Four";
for (int i = 1; i &lt; nums.length; i++) {
   concat.process( nums, i );
}</pre>

<np>This will print out</np>

<pre>One
OneTwo
OneTwoThree
OneTwoThreeFour</pre>

<p>Things get more interesting when a lambda expression is used as an actual parameter, which
is the most common use in practice.  For example,
suppose that the following function is defined:</p>

<pre>/** 
 *  For a function f, compute f(start) + f(start+1) + ... + f(end).
 *  The value of end should be &gt;= the value of start.
 */
static double sum( FunctionR2R f, int start, int end ) {
    double total = 0;
    for (int n = start; n &lt;= end; n++) {
        total = total + f.valueAt( n );
    }
    return total;
}</pre>

<np>Note that since <i>f</i> is a value of type <classname>FunctionR2R</classname>,
the value of <i>f</i> at <i>n</i> is actually written as <i>f.valueAt</i>(<i>n</i>).
When the function <i>sum</i> is called, the first parameter can be given as
a lambda expression that matches the type <classname>FunctionR2R</classname>.  For example:</np>

<pre>System.out.print("The sum of n squared for n from 1 to 100 is ");
System.out.println( sum( <newcode>x -> x*x</newcode>, 1, 100 ) );
System.out.print("The sum of 2 raised to the power n, for n from 1 to 10 is ");
System.out.println( sum( <newcode>num -> Math.pow(2,num)</newcode>, 1, 10 ) );</pre>

<p>As another example, suppose that we have a subroutine that performs a
given task several times.  The task can be specified as a value of type
<classname>Runnable</classname>:</p>

<pre>static void doSeveralTimes( Runnable task, int repCount ) {
    for (int i = 0; i &lt; repCount; i++) {
        task.run();  // Perform the task!
    }
}</pre>

<np>We could then say "Hello World" ten times by calling</np>

<pre>doSeveralTimes( <newcode>() -&gt; System.out.println("Hello World")</newcode>, 10 );</pre>

<np>Note that for a lambda expression of type <classname>Runnable</classname>,
the parameter list is given as an empty pair of parentheses.  Here is an
example in which the syntax is getting rather complicated:</np>

<pre>doSeveralTimes( () -&gt; { 
        // count from 1 up to some random number between 5 and 25
    int count = 5 + (int)(21*Math.random()); 
    for (int i = 1; i &lt;= count; i++) { 
        System.out.print(i + " ");
    }
    System.out.println();
}, 100);</pre>

<np>This is a single subroutine call statement in which the first parameter
is a lambda expression that extends over multiple lines.  The second
parameter is 100, and the semicolon on the last line ends the subroutine
call statement.</np>

<p>We have seen examples of assigning a lambda expression to a variable and
of using one as an actual parameter.  Here is an example in which a lambda expression
is the return value of a function:</p>

<pre>static FunctionR2R makePowerFunction( int n ) {
   return x -&gt; Math.pow(x,n);
}</pre>

<np>Then <i>makePowerFunction</i>(2) returns a <classname>FunctionR2R</classname> that
computes the square of its parameter, while <i>makePowerFunction</i>(10)
returns a <classname>FunctionR2R</classname> that computes the 10-th power of its parameter.
This example also illustrates the fact that a lambda expression can use other variables
in addition to its parameter, such as <i>n</i> in this case (although there are some
restrictions on when that can be done).</np>

</subsection>

<subsection title="Method References" id="subroutines.4a.4">

<p>Suppose that we want a lambda expression to represent the square root function as
a value of type <classname>FunctionR2R</classname>.  We could write it as
<code>x&nbsp;-&gt;&nbsp;Math.sqrt(x)</code>.  However, this lambda expression is a
simple wrapper for a <i>Math.sqrt</i> function that already exists.  Instead of
writing out the lambda expression, that function can be written as a
<newword>method reference</newword>, which takes the form <code>Math::sqrt</code>.
(Recall that in Java, "method" is another word for "subroutine.")
This method reference is just a shorthand for the lambda expression, and it
can be used wherever that lambda expression could be used, such as in the
<i>sum</i> function defined above:</p>

<pre>System.out.print("The sum of the square root of n for n from 1 to 100 is ");
System.out.println( sum( <newcode>Math::sqrt</newcode>, 1, 100 ) );</pre>

<np>It would be nice if we could simply use the name <i>Math.sqrt</i> here
instead of introducing a new notation with&nbsp;<code>::</code>, 
but the notation <i>Math.sqrt</i> was already defined to mean a <b>variable</b>
named <i>sqrt</i> in the <classname>Math</classname> class.</np>

<p>More generally, a lambda expression that simply calls an existing
static method can be written as a method reference of the form</p>

<pre><bnf>classname</bnf> :: <bnf>method-name</bnf></pre>

<np>Furthermore, this notation extends to methods that are in
objects rather than classes.  For example, if <i>str</i> is a
<classname>String</classname>, then <i>str</i> contains the
method <i>str.length</i>().  The method reference <code>str::length</code>
could be used as a lambda expression of type <classname>SupplyInt</classname>,
where <classname>SupplyInt</classname> is the functional interface
</np>

<pre>public interface SupplyInt {
    int get( );
}</pre>


</subsection>

</section>
