<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE exercises SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<exercises>


<exercise id="control.ex.1">
<exercise-question><p>How many times do you have
to roll a pair of dice before they come up snake eyes? You could do the
experiment by rolling the dice by hand. Write a computer program that simulates
the experiment. The program should report the number of rolls that it makes
before the dice come up snake eyes. (Note: "Snake eyes" means that both dice
show a value of 1.) <localref href="basics.ex.2"/> explained how to simulate rolling a pair of dice.</p>
</exercise-question>   
<exercise-discuss><p>Since we want to roll the dice at least once, a <code>do..while</code> is
appropriate. A pseudocode algorithm for the program is</p>

<pre>Let countRolls = 0
do:
    roll the dice
    count this roll by adding 1 to countRolls
while the roll is not snake eyes
Output the value of countRolls</pre>

<np>As in <localref href="basics.ex.2"/>, we can simulate
rolling one die by computing <code>(int)(Math.random()*6)&nbsp;+&nbsp;1</code>.</np>

<p>We want to <b>stop</b> rolling the dice when the roll is a double
1. We want to <b>continue</b> rolling the dice while the roll is
<b>not</b> a double 1. If <code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code> are
variables representing the values of the dice, the condition for continuing to
roll can be expressed as</p>

<pre>while ( ! (die1 == 1 &amp;&amp; die2 == 1) )</pre>

<np>The exclamation point means "not", so the condition says that it is not the
case that (both <code>die1</code> is 1 and <code>die2</code> is 1). That is, it is not
the case that the dice came up snake eyes. Another way to express the same
condition is that at least one of the dice is <b>not</b> 1, that is, that either
<code>die1</code> is not 1 <b>or</b> <code>die2</code> is not 1. In Java
code, this is written:</np>

<pre>while ( die1 != 1  ||  die2 != 1 )</pre>

<np>This is the test that I use in my program. Students often get the
<code>&amp;&amp;</code> and <code>||</code> operators mixed up, especially when
negation is involved. (In this case, we could have avoided the problem by
testing <code>while (die1+die2 != 2)</code>.)</np>

<p>Filling in some details gives an algorithm that can be easily converted into
a program, which is shown below:</p>

<pre>Let countRolls = 0
do:
    die1 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1
    die2 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1
    count this roll by adding 1 to countRolls
while die1 is not 1 or die2 is not 1
Output the value of countRolls</pre>

<p>You could of course write the program using a regular <code>while</code> loop
instead of <code>do..while</code>.  But if you move the test to the start of the
loop, you have to make sure that the variables are given values before you try to
test those values.  You need to "prime" the loop that exist only to ensure that it runs the
first time.  The pseudocode then becomes</p>
<pre>Let countRolls = 0
Let die1 = 0 // Prime the loop with any value except 1
Let die2 = 0
while die1 is not 1 or die2 is not 1:
    die1 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1
    die2 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1
    count this roll by adding 1 to countRolls
Output the value of countRolls</pre>
<np>Another option would be to use a "while(true)" loop.  In that case, the test that
is needed is the condition for stopping the loop, which is often easier to come up with
than the test for continuing the loop, and no priming is necessary:</np>
<pre>Let countRolls = 0
while true:
    die1 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1
    die2 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1
    count this roll by adding 1 to countRolls
    if die1 is 1 and die2 is 1
        break
Output the value of countRolls</pre>

</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="SnakeEyes">/**  
 * This program simulates rolling a pair of dice until they
 * come up snake eyes.  It reports how many rolls were needed.
 */

public class SnakeEyes {
  
   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
       int die1, die2;   // The values rolled on the two dice.
       
       int countRolls;   // Used to count the number of rolls.
       
       countRolls = 0;
       
       do {
          die1 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1;   // roll the dice
          die2 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1;
          countRolls++;                        // and count this roll
       } while ( die1 != 1 || die2 != 1 );
       
       System.out.println("It took " + countRolls + " rolls to get snake eyes.");
   
   }  // end main()

}  // end class</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>


<exercise id="control.ex.2">
<exercise-question><p>Which integer between 1
and 10000 has the largest number of divisors, and how many divisors does it
have? Write a program to find the answers and print out the results. It is
possible that several integers in this range have the same, maximum number of
divisors. Your program only has to print out one of them.  An example in
<localref href="control.4.2"/> discussed divisors. The source code for
that example is <sourceref href="CountDivisors.java"/>.</p>

<p>You might need some hints about how to find a maximum value. The basic idea
is to go through all the integers, keeping track of the largest number of
divisors that you've seen <i>so far</i>. Also, keep track of the integer that
had that number of divisors.</p>
</exercise-question>   
<exercise-discuss>
<p>Let's use a variable named <code>maxDivisors</code> to keep track of the largest
number of divisors we have seen so far and use <code>numWithMax</code> to store the
number that had that many divisors. We have to compute the number of divisors
of each integer from 1 to 10000. Whenever we find a larger number of divisors
than <code>maxDivisors</code>, we have to make note of that fact by changing the
values of <code>maxDivisors</code> and <code>numWithMax</code>. At the end of the
process, <code>maxDivisors</code> will be the absolute maximum number of divisors
and <code>numWithMax</code> will be a number that had that many divisors. These are
the values we want to print out. We can express this with a pseudocode
algorithm</p>

<pre>for each integer N from 1 to 10000:
   Count the number of divisors of N
   If that number is greater than maxDivisors:
       Let maxDivisors = the number of divisors of N
       Let numWithMax = N
Output maxDivisors and numWithMax</pre>

<p>However, there is a problem here: The very first time <code>maxDivisors</code>
is used in the test "If that number is greater than maxDivisors," the variable
<code>maxDivisors</code> hasn't yet been assigned a value. The computer will report
this as an error. This can be fixed by assigning a value to
<code>maxDivisors</code> before the beginning of the <code>for</code> loop. One way to
do this is to handle <code>N=1</code> as a special case before the loop and then to
let <code>N</code> go from 2 to 10000 in the for loop. We know that <code>N=1</code>
has just 1 divisor:</p>

<pre>Let maxDivisors = 1  // number of divisors of 1
Let numWithMax = 1
for each integer N from 2 to 10000:
   Count the number of divisors of N
   If that number is greater than maxDivisors:
       Let maxDivisors = the number of divisors of N
       Let numWithMax = N
Output maxDivisors and numWithMax</pre>

<p>Here's a curious thing: If you leave out the line "<code>numWithMax = 1</code>"
from the program, the computer will report a syntax error where you try to
output the value of <code>numWithMax</code>. It will say that the variable
<code>numWithMax</code> might not have been initialized. That is, it might never
have been assigned a value. Now, <b>you</b> know that it will be
assigned a value (since when <code>N=2</code> is processed, <code>numWithMax</code>
will become 2). However, when the computer compiles the program,
<b>it</b> doesn't know whether the body of the <code>if</code> statement
will ever be executed, so it doesn't know whether <code>numWithMax</code> will ever
be assigned a value. The syntax rule is that every variable must be "definitely
assigned" before its value is used. This means that it is assigned a value on
every possible execution path through the program.  Definite assignment was
discussed in <localref href="control.1.4"/>.</p>

<p>We still have to expand the step "Count the number of divisors of N." This
was already done in <localref href="control.4.2"/> for the example program
<code>CountDivisors.java</code>. This step requires another <code>for</code> loop, so
we have here an example of one <code>for</code> loop nested inside another. Here is
a complete algorithm, which can be translated into a program:</p>

<pre>Let maxDivisors = 1  // number of divisors of 1
Let numWithMax = 1
for each integer N from 2 to 10000:
    Let divisorCount = 0
    for each D from 1 to N:
        if D is a divisor of N:
            add 1 to divisorCount
    If divisorCount is greater than maxDivisors:
        Let maxDivisors = the number of divisors of N
        Let numWithMax = N
Output maxDivisors and numWithMax</pre>

<p>This can be translated pretty much directly into a program. By the way, the
maximum number of divisors is 64. There are two numbers between 1 and 10000
that have 64 divisors, 7560 and 9240. The program will output the first of
these. (It would output the second if the test "<code>if (divisorCount &gt;
maxDivisors)</code>" were changed to "<code>if (divisorCount &gt;=
maxDivisors)</code>". Do you see why?)</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="MostDivisors">/**
 * This program finds an integer between 1 and 10000 that has
 * the largest number of divisors.  It prints out the maximum
 * number of divisors and an integer that has that many divisors.
 */

public class MostDivisors {

   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
       int N;            // One of the integers whose divisors we have to count.
       int maxDivisors;  // Maximum number of divisors seen so far.
       int numWithMax;   // A value of N that had the given number of divisors.
       
       maxDivisors = 1;  // Start with the fact that 1 has 1 divisor.
       numWithMax = 1;

       /* Process all the remaining values of N from 2 to 10000, and
          update the values of maxDivisors and numWithMax whenever we
          find a value of N that has more divisors than the current value
          of maxDivisors.
       */
       
       for ( N = 2;  N &lt;= 10000;  N++ ) {
       
           int D;  // A number to be tested to see if it's a divisor of N.
           int divisorCount;  // Number of divisors of N.
           
           divisorCount = 0;
           
           for ( D = 1;  D &lt;= N;  D++ ) {  // Count the divisors of N.
              if ( N % D == 0 )
                 divisorCount++;
           }
           
           if (divisorCount &gt; maxDivisors) {
              maxDivisors = divisorCount;
              numWithMax = N;
           }
       
       }
       
       System.out.println("Among integers between 1 and 10000,");
       System.out.println("The maximum number of divisors is " + maxDivisors);
       System.out.println("A number with " + maxDivisors + " divisors is " + numWithMax);
   
   } // end main()

}</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>



<exercise>
<exercise-question><p>Write a program that will
evaluate simple expressions such as 17 + 3 and 3.14159 * 4.7. The expressions
are to be typed in by the user. The input always consists of a number, followed
by an operator, followed by another number. The operators that are allowed are
+, -, *, and /. You can read the numbers with <code>TextIO.getDouble()</code> and
the operator with <code>TextIO.getChar()</code>. Your program should read an
expression, print its value, read another expression, print its value, and so
on. The program should end when the user enters 0 as the first number on the
line.</p>
</exercise-question>   
<exercise-discuss>
<p>We need a loop to read and evaluate expressions. It's easiest to use a
<code>break</code> statement to end the loop at the appropriate time:</p>

<pre>Repeat indefinitely:
    Get the user's input.
    if the first number is 0:
        Break out of the loop
    Find the value of the expression
    Display the value.</pre>

<p>Getting the user's input involves reading three data values. We need three
variables to store these values. It's best to test whether the first number is
0 right after we read it, so the user will just have to type a 0 to end the
program, not a complete expression such as 0 + 0. "Repeat indefinitely" can be
written as "<code>while (true)</code>":</p>

<pre>while (true):
    Let firstNum = TextIO.getDouble()
    if firstNum is 0:
        Break out of the loop
    Let operator = TextIO.getChar()
    Let secondNum = TextIO.getlnDouble()
    Find the value of the expression
    Display the value.</pre>

<p>To evaluate the user's expression, we have to test the <code>operator</code> to
find out which operation to compute. We can do this with either a multiway
<code>if</code> statement or with a <code>switch</code> statement. In the program
below, I use a <code>switch</code>. The <code>if</code> statement would be:</p>

<pre>if ( operator == '+' )
   value = firstNum + secondNum;
else if ( operator == '-' )
   value = firstNum - secondNum;
else if ( operator == '*' )
   value = firstNum * secondNum;
else if ( operator == '/' )
   value = firstNum / secondNum;
else {
   System.out.println("Unknown operator: " + operator);
   continue;  // back to start of loop
}</pre>

<np>The computer won't let you get away without the <code>else</code> part of the
<code>if</code> statement or the <code>default</code> case in the <code>switch</code>,
since that would leave a possibility that the variable, <code>value</code>, is not
assigned a value before it is printed out, which violates the definite assignment rule.  
Note that <ptype>char</ptype> values are
tested for equality using the <code>==</code> operator.  Chars are not Strings!
Strings would have to be compared using the <code>equals()</code> method from
the <classname>String</classname> class; <ptype>chars</ptype> however are primitive
type values, and they don't even include any methods.</np>

<p>This program could be improved by having it print out an error message if
the user tries to divide by zero.</p>

<p>(This program could use a <classname>Scanner</classname> instead of <classname>TextIO</classname>
for input, replacing <code>TextIO.getDouble()</code> with <code>stdin.nextDouble()</code>
and <code>TextIO.getChar()</code> with <code>stdin.next()</code>, where <code>stdin</code>
is the <classname>Scanner</classname>.  (See <localref href="basics.4.6"/>)  One difference between the
behavior of the two versions of the program would be that the <code>TextIO</code> version
would accept expressions that have no spaces, such as <code>17+42</code>, whereas the
<code>Scanner</code> version would give an error for such an expression.  Another is that
<code>scanner.next()</code> returns a <classname>String</classname> rather than
a <ptype>char</ptype>, and the character that you want would be the first, and only,
character in that string.)</p>

</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="SimpleCalculator">import textio.TextIO;

/**
 *  This program evaluates simple expressions such as 2 + 2
 *  and 34.2 * 7.81, consisting of a number, an operator,
 *  and another number.  The operators +, -, *, / are allowed.
 *  The program will read and evaluate expressions until
 *  the user inputs a line that starts with the number 0.
 */

public class SimpleCalculator {

   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
      double firstNum;    // First number in the expression.
      double secondNum;   // Second number in the expression.
      char operator;      // The operator in the expression.
      double value;       // The value of the expression.
      
      System.out.println("Enter expressions such as  2 + 2  or  34.2 * 7.81");
      System.out.println("using any of the operators +, -, *, /.");
      System.out.println("To end, enter a 0.");
      System.out.println();
      
      while (true) {
          
          /* Get user's input, ending program if first number is 0. */
      
          System.out.print("? ");
          firstNum = TextIO.getDouble();
          if (firstNum == 0)
             break;
          operator = TextIO.getChar();
          secondNum = TextIO.getlnDouble();
          
          /* Compute the value of the expression. */
          
          switch (operator) {
              case '+' -> value = firstNum + secondNum;
              case '-' -> value = firstNum - secondNum;
              case '*' -> value = firstNum * secondNum;
              case '/' -> value = firstNum / secondNum;
              default -> {
                 System.out.println("Unknown operator: " + operator);
                 continue;  // Back to start of loop!
              }
          } // end switch
          
          /* Display the value. */
          
          System.out.println("Value is " + value);
          System.out.println();
                    
      } // end while
      
      System.out.println("Good bye");
   
   }  // end main()

}  // end class SimpleCalculator</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>



<exercise id="control.ex.4">
<exercise-question><p>Write a program that reads
one line of input text and breaks it up into words. The words should be output
one per line. A word is defined to be a sequence of letters. Any characters in
the input that are not letters should be discarded. For example, if the user
inputs the line</p>

<pre>He said, "That's not a good idea."</pre>

<np>then the output of the program should be</np>

<pre>He
said
That
s
not
a
good
idea</pre>

<np>An improved version of the program would list "that's" as a single word. An
apostrophe can be considered to be part of a word if there is a letter on each
side of the apostrophe.</np>

<p>To test whether a character is a letter, you might use <code>(ch &gt;= 'a'
&amp;&amp; ch &lt;= 'z') || (ch &gt;= 'A' &amp;&amp; ch &lt;= 'Z')</code>.
However, this only works in English and similar languages. A better choice is
to call the standard function <code>Character.isLetter(ch)</code>, which returns a
boolean value of <code>true</code> if <code>ch</code> is a letter and <code>false</code> if
it is not. This works for any Unicode character.</p>
</exercise-question>   
<exercise-discuss><p>There are many ways to approach this problem, and probably all of them are
sort of tricky to get right. Here's a simple idea that almost works: Go through
all the characters in the string. If the character is a letter, write it out.
If it's not a letter, write a carriage return instead. If <code>line</code> is a
<classname>String</classname> variable representing the line of text, this algorithm can be
coded as</p>

<pre>for ( i = 0;  i &lt; line.length(); i++ ) {
   ch = line.charAt(i);
   if ( Character.isLetter(ch) )
      System.out.print(ch);
   else
      System.out.println();   
}</pre>

<np>This prints all the letters in a word on the same line of output. Since
words in the string are separated by non-letter characters, and the computer
prints a carriage return when it finds a non-letter, words in the output are
separated by carriage returns. But there is a problem with this: If two
words in the string are separated by <b>several</b> non-letters, then
there will be one or more blank lines between the words in the output. We don't
want to output two carriage returns in a row. To avoid this, we can keep track
of whether the previous output was a letter or a carriage return. When we find
a non-letter, we will output a carriage return only if the previous output was
<b>not</b> a carriage return. To keep track of the necessary
information, I'll use a <ptype>boolean</ptype> variable named <code>didCR</code>. The
value of this variable will be true if the previous output was a carriage
return. I have to remember to set the value of <code>didCR</code> each time I
output something. With this modification, the code becomes:</np>

<pre>for ( i = 0;  i &lt; line.length(); i++ ) {
   ch = line.charAt(i);
   if ( Character.isLetter(ch) ) {
      System.out.print(ch);
      didCR = false;  // previous output was not a CR
   }
   else {
      if ( didCR == false ) {  // output CR, if previous output was NOT a CR
         System.out.println();
         didCR = true;  // previous output was a CR
      }
   }
}</pre>

<p>The program requires an initial value for <code>didCR</code>. In the program
below, I output a carriage return before the <code>for</code> loop and set
<code>didCR</code> to true. You should be able to follow the rest of the
program.</p>

<p>An entirely different approach to this problem is given by the algorithm,
"while there are more words in the string, get the next word and print it."
This turns out to be even harder to implement than the above.</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="ListWordsInString">import textio.TextIO;

/**  
 *  This program will read one line of input typed by the user.
 *  It will print the words from the input, one word to a line.
 *  A word is defined to be a sequence of letters.  All non-letters
 *  in the input are discarded.
 */

public class ListWordsInString {

   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
       String line;    // A line of text, typed in by the user.
       int i;          // Position in line, from 0 to line.length() - 1.
       char ch;        // One of the characters in line.
       boolean didCR;  // Set to true if the previous output was a carriage return.
       
       System.out.println("Enter a line of text.");
       System.out.print("? ");
       line = TextIO.getln();
       
       System.out.println();
       didCR = true;
       
       for ( i = 0;  i &lt; line.length();  i++ ) {
          ch = line.charAt(i);
          if ( Character.isLetter(ch) ) {
             System.out.print(ch);
             didCR = false;
          }
          else {
             if ( didCR == false ) {
                System.out.println();
                didCR = true;
             }
          }
       }
       
       System.out.println();  // Make sure there's at least one carriage return at the end.
         
   }  // end main()

}  // end class ListWordsInString</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>


<exercise>
<exercise-question><p>Suppose that a file contains information about sales 
figures for a company in various cities.
Each line of the file contains a city name, followed by a colon&nbsp;(:) followed by the data for that
city.  The data is a number of type <ptype>double.</ptype>
However, for some cities, no data was available.  In these lines, the data is replaced by
a comment explaining why the data is missing.  For example, several lines from the file might
look like:</p>
<pre>San Francisco:  19887.32
Chicago:  no report received
New York: 298734.12</pre>
<np>Write a program that will compute and print the total sales from all the cities together. The
program should also report the number of cities for which data was not available.  The name of the
file is "sales.dat".</np>
<p>To complete this program, you'll need one fact about file input with <classname>TextIO</classname>
that was not covered in <localref href="basics.4.4"/>.  Since you don't know in advance how many
lines there are in the file, you need a way to tell when you have gotten to the end of the file.
When <classname>TextIO</classname> is reading from a file, the function <code>TextIO.eof()</code>
can be used to test for <newword>end of file</newword>.  This <ptype>boolean</ptype>-valued
function returns <code>true</code> if the file has been entirely read and returns <code>false</code>
if there is more data to read in the file.  This means that you can read the lines of the
file in a loop <code>while&nbsp;(TextIO.eof()&nbsp;==&nbsp;false)&dots;</code>. The loop will end
when all the lines of the file have been read.</p>
<p>Suggestion:  For each line, read and ignore characters up to the colon.  Then read the rest
of the line into a variable of type <classname>String</classname>.  Try to convert the string
into a number, and use <code>try..catch</code> to test whether the conversion succeeds.</p>
</exercise-question>   
<exercise-discuss>
<p>The statement <code>TextIO.readFile("sales.dat")</code> can be used at the beginning of
the program to make <classname>TextIO</classname> read from the file instead of from the user's input.
This statement throws an <classname>IllegalArgumentException</classname> if the file can't be
found.  Although it's not required by the statement of the problem, it would be nice to detect
the exception and print an error message about the missing file.  This can be done as follows,
using <code>System.exit</code> to end the program if the error occurs:</p>
   
<pre>try {
   TextIO.readFile("sales.dat");
}
catch (IllegalArgumentException e) {
   System.out.println("Can't open file \"sales.dat\" for reading!");
   System.out.println("Please make sure the file is present before");
   System.out.println("running the program.");
   System.exit(1);  // Terminates the program.
}</pre>
   
<p>We have two main quantities to keep track of in the program:  The total amount of sales and
the number of cities for which data is missing.  These quantities can be represented by
two variables, <code>salesTotal</code> of type <ptype>double</ptype> and <code>missingCount</code>
of type <ptype>int</ptype>.  These variables are initialized to zero before processing any data
from the file, and their values are output at the end of the program, after reading the
entire file.</p>
   
<p>The main processing loop of the program is the <code>while</code> loop mentioned in the
statement of the exercise, which begins <code>while&nbsp;(TextIO.eof()&nbsp;==&nbsp;false)</code>.  
(In my program, I've chosen to use the equivalent but more elegant test
<code>while&nbsp;(&nbsp;!&nbsp;TextIO.eof()&nbsp;)</code>; you should try to understand why
this is equivalent&mdash;and why it is more elegant!)  In pseudocode form, we want a loop
that does the following:</p>

<pre>while there are more lines in the file:
   read the name of the city and the colon that follows it
   read the rest of the line into a string
   try to convert the string into a number
      if the conversion succeeds, add the number to the total sales
      otherwise add 1 to the count of missing data</pre>
   
<np>To read past the name of the city, we can simply read characters using
<code>TextIO.getChar()</code> until we get to the colon:</np>
   
<pre>do {  // Read past characters up to the ':'.
   ch = TextIO.getChar();
} while (ch != ':');</pre>
   
<np>where <code>ch</code> is a variable of type <ptype>char</ptype>.  We can read the rest
of the line using <code>TextIO.getln()</code>.  (As a side note, it's important here
that we read the entire line, including the carriage return at the end.  <code>TextIO.getln()</code>
does this.  If we neglected to read the carriage return at the end of the line,
<code>TextIO.eof()</code> would not detect the end of the file correctly.  After the
data from the last line is read, the carriage return character would still be there in
the file waiting to be read; since there is still something left to read in the file,
<code>TextIO.eof()</code> would be <code>false</code> and the while loop would
continue, even though all the cities have already been processed.  In fact, the program
would crash while looking for the next&nbsp;':', which is not there.  Text processing
can be surprisingly subtle!)</np>
   
<p>Once we have the information in the form of a <classname>String</classname>, we can try to
convert the string into a number with <code>Double.parseDouble</code>.  If the string is
not a number, this will throw an exception of type <classname>NumberFormatException</classname>.
We can catch the error in a <code>try..catch</code> statement.  The "missing data"
processing is done in the <code>catch</code> part of this statement.  In the program,
this takes the form:</p>
<pre>try {
   sales = Double.parseDouble(dataString);
   salesTotal += sales;  // This is skipped if the conversion fails.
}
catch (NumberFormatException e) {
       // The dataString is not a number, so it counts as
       // missing data.  Add 1 to the missing data count.
   missingCount++;
}</pre>
   
<p>(Note that my solution assumes that the data file (if it exists at all) has exactly the
format that is specified in the problem.  The problem would be more difficult if we had
to check the format of the file, to see whether it conforms to the specification.)</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre>import textio.TextIO;

/**
 * This program reads from a file named "sales.dat".  Each line of the
 * file contains the name of a city, followed by a colon, followed by
 * either a number giving the amount of sales in that city or by a
 * message saying why the sales figure is not available.  The program
 * prints the total sales for all cities and the number of cites for
 * which the figure was not available.
 */
   
public class SalesFigures {
   
   public static void main( String[] args ) {
      
      /* Open file for reading; if it can't be opened, end the program */
      
      try {
         TextIO.readFile("sales.dat");
      }
      catch (IllegalArgumentException e) {
         System.out.println("Can't open file \"sales.dat\" for reading!");
         System.out.println("Please make sure the file is present before");
         System.out.println("running the program.");
         System.exit(1);  // Terminates the program.
      }
      
      /* Read the file, keeping track of total sales and missing data. */
      
      double salesTotal;  // Total of all sales figures seen so far.
      int missingCount;   // Number of cities for which data is missing.
      
      salesTotal = 0;
      missingCount = 0;
      
      while ( ! TextIO.eof() ) {  // process one line of data.
         
         char ch;  // For reading past the name of the city.
         String dataString;  // Contents of line, after the city name.
         double sales;  // The sales figure for the city.
         
         do {  // Read past characters up to the ':'.
            ch = TextIO.getChar();
         } while (ch != ':');
         
         dataString = TextIO.getln();  // Get the rest of the line.
         
         try {
            sales = Double.parseDouble(dataString);
            salesTotal += sales;  // This is skipped if the conversion fails.
         }
         catch (NumberFormatException e) {
                // The dataString is not a number, so it counts as
                // missing data.  Add 1 to the missing data count.
            missingCount++;
         }
   
      } // end while
      
      /* Report the results. */
      
      System.out.printf("Total sales recorded from all cities: $%1.2f\n\n", salesTotal);
      if (missingCount == 0)
         System.out.println("Data was received from all cities.");
      else if (missingCount == 1)
         System.out.println("Data was missing from 1 city.");
      else
         System.out.printf("Data was missing from %d cities.\n", missingCount);
      
   } // end main()
   
} // end class SalesFigures
</pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>


<exercise>
<exercise-question><p><localref href="control.ex.2"/> asked you to find the
number in the range 1 to 10000 that has the largest number of divisors.  You
only had to print out one such number.  Revise the program so that it will
print out <b>all</b> numbers that have the maximum number of divisors.  Use an
array as follows:  As you count the divisors for each number, store each
count in an array.  Then at the end of the program, 
you can go through the array and print out all the numbers
that have the maximum count.  The output from the program should look
something like this:</p>
<pre>Among integers between 1 and 10000,
The maximum number of divisors was 64
Numbers with that many divisors include:
   7560
   9240</pre>
</exercise-question>   
<exercise-discuss>
<p>This is a fairly straightforward exercise in using arrays. We need to save 10000
numbers in an array.  The numbers are the divisor counts for the numbers 1 through 10000.
The numbers that we want to store in the array are of type <ptype>int</ptype>,
so <ptype>int</ptype> is the base type of the array.
In the program, I use an array named <code>saveCount</code> of type <atype>int[]</atype>
to store the data.  It seems natural to store the divisor count for N in
array element <code>saveCount[N]</code>, but note that in that case, we don't use
array element number 0, and we need an array element number 10000.  Ignoring element
0 is fine, but for <code>saveCount[10000]</code> to exist, the length of the array
must be at least 10001.  I use an array of length 10001:</p>
<pre>saveCount = new int[10001];</pre>
<np>(An alternative would be to store the advisor count for N in
<code>saveCount[N-1]</code>.  In that case, we wouldn't need the extra array element,
and the length of the array would be 10000.)</np>
<p>After computing each divisor count, we store the count in the array.  At the same
time, we are keeping track of the maximum number of divisors.  After the end of the <code>for</code>
loop that does the counting, we know the divisor count for each number and we know the
maximum number of divisors.  We just have to go through the array and print out
every integer N for which the divisor count is equal to the maximum:</p>
<pre>System.out.println("Numbers with that many divisors include:");
for ( N = 1; N &lt;= 10000; N++ ) {
    if ( saveCount[N] == maxDivisors ) {
        System.out.println( "   " + N );
    }
}</pre>
<np>Note that this code checks whether the number in the array, <code>saveCount[N]</code>,
is equal to the maximum, but it prints the array index, <code>N</code>, which is the
integer that has that many divisors.</np>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<p>New code that involves the array is shown in &newcodestyle;.</p>
<pre><prog name="MostDivisorsWithArray">import textio.TextIO;

/**
 * This program counts the number of divisors for integers in the range
 * 1 to 10000.  It finds the maximum divisor count.  It outputs the
 * maximum divisor count and a list of all integers in the range that 
 * have the maximum number of divisors.
 */

public class MostDivisorsWithArray {

   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
       int N;            // One of the integers whose divisors we have to count.
       int maxDivisors;  // Maximum number of divisors seen so far.
       
       <newcode>int[] saveCount;  // Store the number of divisors for each number
       
       saveCount = new int[10001];</newcode>
       
       maxDivisors = 1;  // Start with the fact that 1 has 1 divisor.
       <newcode>saveCount[1] = 1;</newcode>

       /* Process all the remaining values of N from 2 to 10000, and store
          all the divisor counts in the array.  Update the value of maxDivisor
          whenever we find a value of N that has more divisors than the current
          value.
       */
       
       for ( N = 2;  N &lt;= 10000;  N++ ) {
       
           int D;  // A number to be tested to see if it's a divisor of N.
           int divisorCount;  // Number of divisors of N.
           
           divisorCount = 0;
           
           for ( D = 1;  D &lt;= N;  D++ ) {  // Count the divisors of N.
              if ( N % D == 0 )
                 divisorCount++;
           }
           
           <newcode>saveCount[N] = divisorCount;  // Record the count for N in the array</newcode>
           
           if (divisorCount &gt; maxDivisors) {
              maxDivisors = divisorCount;
           }
       
       }
       
       System.out.println("Among integers between 1 and 10000,");
       System.out.println("The maximum number of divisors was " + maxDivisors);
       <newcode>System.out.println("Numbers with that many divisors include:");
       for ( N = 1; N &lt;= 10000; N++ ) {
           if ( saveCount[N] == maxDivisors ) {
               System.out.println( "   " + N );
           }
       }</newcode>
   
   } // end main()

}</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>


<exercise>
<exercise-question><p>An example in <localref href="control.7a.3"/>
tried to answer the question, How many random people
do you have to select before you find a duplicate birthday? The source code for
that program can be found in the file
<sourceref href="BirthdayProblem.java"/>. Here are
some related questions:</p>
<ul>
<li>How many random people do you have to select before you find <b>three</b>
people who share the same birthday? (That is, all three people were born on the
same day in the same month, but not necessarily in the same year.)</li>
<li>Suppose you choose 365 people at random. How many different birthdays will
they have? (The number could theoretically be anywhere from 1 to 365).</li>
<li>How many different people do you have to check before you've found at least
one person with a birthday on each of the 365 days of the year?</li>
</ul>
<p>Write <b>three</b> programs to answer these questions. Each of your programs should simulate
choosing people at random and checking their birthdays. (In each case, ignore
the possibility of leap years.)</p>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss>
<p>The original program and the three programs for this exercise have some similarities,
and we will use ideas from the original program.  However, each part of this exercise
presents its own problem.</p>
<p>The first question asks how many people you have to choose at random before
finding three who share the same birthday. This is similar to the original
program, but instead of just checking whether or not a given birthday has
already been found, we need to keep track of how many people have been found
with each birthday. Where the original program used an array of
<code>booleans</code>, here we need an array of <code>ints</code>. We still want to
count the number of people we check and output that count at the end. An
algorithm for the simulation is:</p>

<pre>Let count = 0
Repeat:
   Select a birthday at random
   Add one to count
   If this is the third time that birthday has occurred:
       break out of the loop
   Add one to the number of times that birthday has been found
Output the count</pre>

<p>The original program used a <ptype>boolean</ptype> array to keep track of whether
or not each day had been seen.  For this proble, we need to know <i>how many times</i>
each day has been seen.  That means that instead of one boolean value for each day,
we need one integer value for each day.  So,
to do the counting, we need an array "<code>int[] numFound</code>", where
<code>numFound[i]</code> will be the number of times the <code>i</code>-th day of the
year has occurred as a birthday. Since <code>numFound[i]</code> can be used in any
way that any <ptype>int</ptype> variable can be used, we can add one to the number
stored in <code>numFound[i]</code> by saying "<code>numFound[i]++</code>"
or "<code>numFound[i]&nbsp;=&nbsp;numFound[i]&nbsp;+&nbsp;1</code>". When we
create the array with the command "<code>numFound&nbsp;=&nbsp;new&nbsp;int[365]</code>", all the
elements of the array are automatically initialized to zero. This is the
initial value that we want. (This is an important thing to remember! In some
programming languages, arrays are not automatically filled with zeros, so it
would be necessary to use a <code>for</code> loop to store a zero into each place
in the array. Even in Java, if you reuse
the same array rather than creating a new one for each use, you would
have to remember to set initialize each element of the array before reusing it.)</p>

<p>Given all this, we can translate the algorithm into Java as follows:</p>

<pre><newcode>int[] numFound;  // numFound[i] will be the number of people
                 // who have been found who have a birthday
                 // on the i-th day of the year</newcode>

int count;       // The number of people who have been checked.

<newcode>numFound = new int[365];  // Initially, all entries are 0.</newcode>

count = 0;

while (true) {
       // Select a birthday at random, from 0 to 364.
       // If the same birthday was already seen twice
       // before, then quit.  Otherwise, add one to
       // the corresponding entry in the numFound array
       // to record that a person with that birthday
       // has been found.
   int birthday;  // The selected birthday.
   birthday = (int)(Math.random()*365);
   count++;
   <newcode>if ( numFound[birthday] == 2 )
       break;  // It's the third time we've found this birthday.
   numFound[birthday]++;</newcode>
}

System.out.println("It took " + count + 
        " tries to find three people with the same birthday.");</pre>

<np>The lines shown in &newcodestyle; are the ones that differ significantly from the
original program. This becomes the body of the <code>main()</code>
subroutine in the first program.</np>


<break/>

<p>For the second program, we know exactly how many people we want to check:
365. This calls for using a for loop. The information we need for each birthday
is whether or not that birthday has occurred. For that, we can use an array of
<ptype>booleans</ptype>.  After the <code>for</code> loop,
value stored in position <code>i</code> of the array will
<code>true</code> if the <code>i</code>-th day of the year has occurred as a birthday
and is <code>false</code> if not. After checking 365 people, we have to go through
the boolean array and count the number of entries in the array that are <code>true</code>.
This is the number of different birthdays that have been found. The algorithm
can be expressed as:</p>

<pre>Let used = new boolean[365]
Repeat 365 times:
   Select a birthday at random
   Store true into the corresponding location in the array, used
Let count = 0
for day = 0 to 364:
   If used[day] is true:
      Add 1 to count
Output the value of count</pre>

<np>This translates easily into Java code:</np>

<pre>boolean used[];  // used[i] will be true if a person is found
                 // whose birthday is the i-th day of the year.

used = new boolean[365];  // <b>Initially, all entries are false!</b>

for (i = 0; i &lt; 365; i++) {
      // Select a random birthday and record it.
   int birthday;  // The selected birthday.
   birthday = (int)(Math.random()*365);
   used[birthday] = true;
}

int count = 0;

for (day = 0; day &lt; 365; day++) {
       // If this day occurred as a birthday, count it.
   if (used[day] == true)
      count++;
}

System.out.println("Among 365 people, there were " + count
                                + " different birthdays.");</pre>

<p>It might be worth noting that the test "<code>if&nbsp;(used[day]&nbsp;==&nbsp;true)</code>" can
be written more simply&mdash;and elegantly&mdash;as 
"<code>if&nbsp;(used[day])</code>". Also, the three lines in
the first <code>for</code> loop could be reduced to the single command
"<code>used[(int)(Math.random()*365)]&nbsp;=&nbsp;true;</code>". Of course, this one-line
version is harder to understand.</p>

<break/>

<p>The third program is just a little bit trickier. We have to continue
selecting people at random until we have found 365 different birthdays. We can
use a counter to keep track of how many different birthdays we have found. We
have to continue until this counter reaches 365. We need a second counter to
keep track of how many different people we have checked. It's the second
counter whose value we want to output at the end. Now, we have to be able to
recognize whether a birthday we've just found is new, or whether we've
encountered it previously. For this, we can again use an array of
<ptype>booleans</ptype>. An algorithm for the simulation is:</p>

<pre>Let used = new boolean[365]
Let count = 0   // The number of people checked
Let birthdaysFound = 0   // The number of different birthdays found
while birthdaysFound &lt; 365:
   Add one to count
   Select a birthday at random
   if used[birthday] is false:
       Add one to birthdaysFound  // since this is a new birthday
   Let used[birthday] = true   // so we don't count it again
Output the value of count</pre>

<np>In Java, this algorithm becomes:</np>

<pre>boolean[] used;  // For recording the possible birthdays
                 //   that have been seen so far.
int count;       // The number of people who have been checked.
int birthdaysFound;   // The number of different birthdays that
                      // have been found.

used = new boolean[365];  // Initially, all entries are false.
count = 0;
birthdaysFound = 0;

while (birthdaysFound &lt; 365) {
       // Select a birthday at random, from 0 to 364.
       // If the birthday has not already been used,
       // add 1 to birthdaysFound.
   int birthday;  // The selected birthday.
   birthday = (int)(Math.random()*365);
   count++;
   if ( used[birthday] == false )
      birthdaysFound++;
   used[birthday] = true;
}

System.out.println( count + " people were checked." );</pre>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<p><b>Finding three people with the same birthday:</b>
</p>

<pre><prog name="BirthdayProblem2">/**
 *  How many random people do you have to select before you find
 *  THREE with the same birthday (that is, three people who were born 
 *  on the same day of the same month, but not necessarily in the 
 *  same year).  This program simulates the process.  (It ignores the
 *  possibility of people born on leap day.)
 */

public class BirthdayProblem2 {

   /**
    * Simulate choosing people at random and checking the
    * day of the year they were born on.  If the person is
    * the third who was born on that day of the year, stop,
    * and output the number of people who were checked.
    */
   public static void main(String[] args) {

      int[] numFound;  // numFound[i] will be the number of people
                       // who have been found who have a birthday
                       // on the i-th day of the year
      
      int count;       // The number of people who have been checked.

      numFound = new int[365];  // Initially, all entries are 0.
      
      count = 0;

      while (true) {
             // Select a birthday at random, from 0 to 364.
             // If the same birthday was already seen twice
             // before, then quit.  Otherwise, add one to
             // the corresponding entry in the numFound array 
             // to record that a person with that birthday
             // has been found.
         int birthday;  // The selected birthday.
         birthday = (int)(Math.random()*365);
         count++;
         if ( numFound[birthday] == 2 )
            break;
         numFound[birthday]++;
      }

      System.out.println("It took " + count + 
               " tries to find three people with the same birthday.");

   }
 
   
} // end class BirthdayProblem2</prog>
   
</pre>

<p><b>How many different birthdays do 365 people have?</b>
</p>

<pre><prog name="BirthdayProblem3">/**
 * This program simulates selecting 365 people at random and finding
 * how many different birthdays they have among them.
 */

public class BirthdayProblem3 {

   /**
    * Simulate choosing people at random and checking the
    * day of the year they were born on.  The number of
    * different days found among 365 people is counted
    * and output.
    */
   public static void main(String[] args) {
      
      boolean used[];  // used[i] will be true if a person is found
                       // whose birthday is on the i-th day of the year.
      
      used = new boolean[365];  // Initially, all entries are false.
      
      /* Choose 365 days at random, and mark each day by
         setting the corresponding entry in the array, used,
         to true.  (If the value is already true, it doesn't 
         matter.  We are only interested in whether or not
         the birthday occurs, not how many times it occurs.)
      */
      
      int i;
      for (i = 0; i &lt; 365; i++) {
         int birthday;  // The selected birthday.
         birthday = (int)(Math.random()*365);
         used[birthday] = true;
      }
      
      /* Now, count how many entries in the used array are true.
         This is how many different birthdays were found.
      */
      
      int count = 0;
      int day;
      
      for (day = 0; day &lt; 365; day++) {
             // If this day occurred as a birthday, count it.
         if (used[day] == true)
            count++;
      }

      System.out.println("Among 365 people, there were " + count
                                      + " different birthdays.");

   } 
 
   
} // end class BirthdayProblem3</prog>


</pre>

<p><b>Finding 365 different birthdays:</b>
</p>

<pre><prog name="BirthdayProblem4">/**
 * How many random people do you have to select before you 
 *  have found someone with every possible birthday (ignoring
 *  leap years)?  This program simulates the process.
 */
 
public class BirthdayProblem4 {
 
    /**
     * Simulate choosing people at random and checking the
     * day of the year they were born on.  People are chosen
     * until all 365 possible birthdays (ignoring leap years)
     * have been found.  Then the number of people surveyed
     * is output.
     */
   public static void main(String[] args) {
 
       boolean[] used;  // For recording the possible birthdays
                        //   that have been seen so far.  A value
                        //   of true in used[i] means that a person
                        //   whose birthday is the i-th day of the
                        //   year has been found.
 
       int count;       // The number of people who have been checked.
       
       int birthdaysFound;   // The number of different birthdays that
                             // have been found.
 
       used = new boolean[365];  // Initially, all entries are false.
       
       count = 0;
       
       birthdaysFound = 0;
 
       while (birthdaysFound &lt; 365) {
              // Select a birthday at random, from 0 to 364.
              // If the birthday has not already been used,
              // add 1 to birthdaysFound.
          int birthday;  // The selected birthday.
          birthday = (int)(Math.random()*365);
          count++;
          if ( used[birthday] == false )
             birthdaysFound++;
          used[birthday] = true;
       }
 
       System.out.println( count + " people were checked." );
 
    }
  
    
} // end class BirthdayProblem4</prog>
</pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>   

   

<exercise id="control.ex.6">
<exercise-question><p>Write a GUI program that draws
a checkerboard.  Base your solution on the sample program
<sourceref href="SimpleGraphicsStarter.java"/>  You will draw
the checkerboard in the <code>drawPicture()</code> subroutine, after
erasing the code that it already contains.</p>

<p>The checkerboard should be 400-by-400  pixels.  You can change the size of
the drawing area in <code>SimpleGraphicsStarter.java</code> by modifying the
<fx>first two lines of the <code>start()</code> subroutine to set <code>width</code>
and <code>height</code></fx><swing>line in <code>main()</code> that says
<code>drawingArea.setPreferredSize(new Dimension(800,600))</code> to change the numbers</swing> to 400 
instead of 800 and 600.  A checkerboard
contains 8 rows and 8 columns of squares.  If the size of the drawing area is 400,
that means that each square should be 50-by-50 pixels.  
The squares are red and black (or whatever other colors you choose). Here is a tricky way
to determine whether a given square should be red or black: The rows and columns can be
thought of as numbered from 0 to 7.  If the row number of the square and the
column number of the square are either both even or both odd, then the square is red.
Otherwise, it is black. Note that a square is just a rectangle in which the
height is equal to the width, so you can use the subroutine
<code>g.fillRect()</code> to draw the squares. Here is a reduced-size image of the
checkerboard that you want to draw:</p>

<img src="checkerboard.png" alt="checkerboard" width="170" height="169" tex="checkerboard.eps"/>

</exercise-question>   
<exercise-discuss>
<p>The basic algorithm is obvious:</p>

<pre>for each row of the checkerboard:
    Draw all the squares in that row</pre>

<np>Since any given row contains eight squares, one in each column of the
checkerboard, we can expand the body of the for loop into another for loop:</np>

<pre>for each of the eight rows of the checkerboard:
    for each of the eight columns:
        Draw the square in that row and column</pre>

<p>Each square is a rectangle with height 50 and width 50, so it can be drawn
with the command <code>g.fillRect(x,y,50,50)</code>, where <code>x</code> and
<code>y</code> are the coordinates of the top-left corner of the square. Before
drawing the square, we have to determine whether it should be red or black, and
we have to set the correct color with <code>g.set<fx>Fill</fx><swing>Color</swing></code>. So, the algorithm
becomes</p>

<pre>for each row on the checkerboard:
    for each of the eight columns:
        Compute x,y for the top-left corner of the square
        if it's a red square:
           g.set<fx>Fill</fx><swing>Color</swing>(Color.RED)
        else
           g.set<fx>Fill</fx><swing>Color</swing>(Color.BLACK)
        g.fillRect(x,y,50,50)</pre>

<p>The top of the first row of squares is at <code>y=0</code>. Since each square is
50 pixels high, the top of the second row is at <code>y=50</code>, followed by 100
for the third row, then 150, 200, 250, 300, and 350. If we assume that the rows
are numbered 0, 1, 2, &dots;, 7, then the tops are given by <code>y&nbsp;=&nbsp;row*50</code>,
where <code>row</code> is the row number. (If you number the rows 1, 2, &dots;, 8, the
formula would be <code>(row-1)*20</code>. The simpler formula in this and in many
similar cases is one reason why computer scientists like to start counting with
0 instead of 1.) Similarly, the left edge of the squares in column <code>col</code>
is given by <code>x&nbsp;=&nbsp;col*50</code>, where again the columns are numbered 0, 1, 2,
&dots;, 7. I'll use "<code>for&nbsp;(row=0;&nbsp;row&lt;8;&nbsp;row++)</code>" to count off the rows,
rather than the equivalent "<code>for (row=0;&nbsp;row&lt;=7;&nbsp;row++)</code>". The 8
reminds me that I am counting off the <b>eight</b> numbers 0, 1, 2,
&dots;, 7. Again, this is typical computer science style.</p>

<p>The only problem remaining is how to determine whether the square is red. As
noted in the exercise, a square is red if <code>row</code> and <code>col</code> are
either both even or both odd. Since an integer <code>N</code> is even if
<code>N%2</code> is 0, the test could be expressed as</p>

<pre>if ((row%2 == 0 &amp;&amp; col%2 == 0) || (row%2 == 1 &amp;&amp; col%2 == 1))</pre>

<np>However,
note that this is the same as asking whether <code>row%2</code> and <code>col%2</code>
have the same value. So the test can be written more simply as 
"<code>if&nbsp;(row%2&nbsp;==&nbsp;col%2)</code>". Putting this all together into syntactically correct Java
code, the algorithm becomes</np>

<pre>for ( row = 0;  row &lt; 8;  row++ ) {
   for ( col = 0;  col &lt; 8;  col++ ) {
       x = 50*col;
       y = 50*row;
       if ( (row % 2) == (col % 2) )
          g.set<fx>Fill</fx><swing>Color</swing>(Color.RED);
       else
          g.set<fx>Fill</fx><swing>Color</swing>(Color.BLACK);
       g.fillRect(x,y,50,50);
   }
}</pre>

<p>Of course, the variables <code>row</code>, <code>col</code>, <code>x</code>, and
<code>y</code> have to be declared to be of type <ptype>int</ptype>. Then, the code goes
into the body of the <code>drawPicture()</code>subroutine.</p>

<p>The complete program is shown below.  In the original program, the size of the
drawing area was 800-by-600.  I changed this to 400-by-400, as noted in the exercise.  
And I changed the title of the window to "Checkerboard" in another
line in <code><swing>main</swing><fx>start</fx>()</code>.</p>

<p>I also changed the name of the class from
<classname>SimpleGraphicsStarter</classname> to <classname>Checkerboard</classname>.
Remember that this also requires changing the name of the file from
<code>SimpleGraphicsStarter.java</code> to <code>Checkerboard.java</code>.
</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="Checkerboard" scope="fx">
import javafx.application.Application;
import javafx.scene.layout.BorderPane;
import javafx.scene.Scene;
import javafx.stage.Stage;
import javafx.scene.canvas.Canvas;
import javafx.scene.canvas.GraphicsContext;
import javafx.scene.paint.Color;

/**
 *  This program draws a checkerboard
 */
public class Checkerboard extends Application {

    /**
     * Draws a picture.  The parameters width and height give the size 
     * of the drawing area, in pixels.  
     */
    public void drawPicture(GraphicsContext g, int width, int height) {

          int row;   // Row number, from 0 to 7
          int col;   // Column number, from 0 to 7
          int x,y;   // Top-left corner of square

          for ( row = 0;  row &lt; 8;  row++ ) {

             for ( col = 0;  col &lt; 8;  col++) {
                x = col * 50;
                y = row * 50;
                if ( (row % 2) == (col % 2) )
                   g.setFill(Color.RED);
                else
                   g.setFill(Color.BLACK);
                g.fillRect(x, y, 50, 50);
             } 

          }

    } // end drawPicture()

    //------ Implementation details: DO NOT EXPECT TO UNDERSTAND THIS ------


    public void start(Stage stage) {
        int width = 400;   // The width of the image.  You can modify this value!
        int height = 400;  // The height of the image. You can modify this value!
        Canvas canvas = new Canvas(width,height);
        drawPicture(canvas.getGraphicsContext2D(), width, height);
        BorderPane root = new BorderPane(canvas);
        root.setStyle("-fx-border-width: 4px; -fx-border-color: #444");
        Scene scene = new Scene(root);
        stage.setScene(scene);
        stage.setTitle("Checkerboard"); // STRING APPEARS IN WINDOW TITLEBAR!
        stage.show();
        stage.setResizable(false);
    } 

    public static void main(String[] args) {
        launch();
    }

} // end Checkerboard
</prog></pre>
<pre><prog name="Checkerboard" scope="swing">
import java.awt.*;
import java.awt.event.*;
import javax.swing.*;

public class Checkerboard extends JPanel implements ActionListener {

   public void drawFrame(Graphics g, int frameNumber, int width, int height) {

      int row;   // Row number, from 0 to 7
      int col;   // Column number, from 0 to 7
      int x,y;   // Top-left corner of square

      for ( row = 0;  row &lt; 8;  row++ ) {

         for ( col = 0;  col &lt; 8;  col++) {
            x = col * 50;
            y = row * 50;
            if ( (row % 2) == (col % 2) )
               g.setColor(Color.RED);
            else
               g.setColor(Color.BLACK);
            g.fillRect(x, y, 50, 50);
         } 

      }
      
   }
   
   //------ Implementation details: DO NOT EXPECT TO UNDERSTAND THIS ------
   
   
   public static void main(String[] args) {
      
      JFrame window = new JFrame("Checkerboard");
      Checkerboard drawingArea = new Checkerboard();
      drawingArea.setBackground(Color.WHITE);
      window.setContentPane(drawingArea);
      drawingArea.setPreferredSize(new Dimension(400,400));
      window.pack();
      window.setLocation(100,50);
      window.setDefaultCloseOperation(JFrame.EXIT_ON_CLOSE);
      window.setResizable(false); // The user can't change the size.
      Timer frameTimer = new Timer(20,drawingArea);
      window.setVisible(true);
      //frameTimer.start(); // commented out so we don't get an animation

   } // end main

   private int frameNum;
   
   public void actionPerformed(ActionEvent evt) {
      frameNum++;
      repaint();
   }
   
   protected void paintComponent(Graphics g) {
      super.paintComponent(g);
      drawFrame(g, frameNum, getWidth(), getHeight());
   }

}
</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>


<exercise>
<exercise-question><p>Often, some element of an animation repeats over and over, every so many frames.
Sometimes, the repetition is "cyclic,"  meaning that at the end it jumps back to the start.
Sometimes the repetition is "oscillating," like a back-and-forth motion where the second
half is the same as the first half played in reverse.</p>
<p>Write an animation that demonstrates both cyclic and oscillating motions at various speeds.
For cyclic motion, you can use a square that moves across the drawing area, then jumps back to
the start, and then repeats the same motion over and over.  For oscillating motion, you can do something
similar, but the square should move back and forth between the two edges of the drawing area; that is,
it moves left-to-right during the first half of the animation and then backwards from right-to-left
during the second half.  To write the program, you can start with a copy of
the sample program <sourceref href="SimpleAnimationStarter.java"/>.</p>
<p>A cyclic motion has to repeat every N frames for some value of N.  What you draw in some
frame of the animation depends on the <code>frameNumber</code>.  The <code>frameNumber</code> just keeps
increasing forever.  To implement cyclic motion, what you really want is a "cyclic frame number" that
takes on the values 0, 1, 2, &dots;, (N-1), 0, 1, 2, &dots;, (N-1), 0, 1, 2, &dots;.  You can derive
the value that you need from <code>frameNumber</code> simply by saying</p>
<pre>cyclicFrameNumber = frameNumber % N;</pre>
<np>Then, you just have to base what you draw on <code>cyclicFrameNumber</code> instead of on
<code>frameNumber</code>.  Similarly, for an oscillating animation, you need an
"oscillation frame number" that takes on the values  0, 1, 2, &dots; (N-1), N, (N-1), (N-2), &dots; 2, 1, 0, 1, 2, 
and so on, repeating the back and forth motion forever.  You can compute the value that you need with</np>
<pre>oscilationFrameNumber = frameNumber % (2*N);
if (oscillationFrameNumber &gt; N)
   oscillationFrameNumber = (2*N) - oscillationFrameNumber;</pre>
<p>Here is a screen shot from my version of the program.  I use
six squares.  The top three do cyclic motion at various speeds, while the bottom three do
oscillating motion.  I drew black lines across the drawing area to separate the squares and to give
them "channels" to move in.
</p>
<img src="motion-demo.png" width="320" height="120" alt="screenshot from CyclicAndOscillatingMotionDemo"
      tex="motion-demo.eps" texscale="0.8"/>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss>
<p>This exercise exists mostly to introduce you to cyclic and oscillating motion and the formulas
that are used to implement them.  But it's also a good exercise in designing an animation
and working with coordinates.</p>
<p>Some decisions have to be made before you can start writing code.  I decided to use
rather small squares.  (Actually, I tried it with big squares and didn't like the appearance
as much.)  The size of my squares is 20-by-20 pixels.  For my first cyclic motion, I decided 
to make the length of the animation 300 frames, or about 5 seconds.  This means that 
<code>cyclicFrameNumber</code> can be computed as <code>frameNumber&nbsp;%&nbsp;300</code>.
And I decided to move the
square at one pixel per frame; that lets me use <code>cyclicFrameNumber</code> as
the x-coordinate for the square.  The top square moves along the top edge of the
window, so its y-coordinate is 0.  The code for the first square is:</p>
<pre>cyclicFrameNum = frameNumber % 300;  // Repeats every 300 frames
g.setFill(Color.RED);
g.fillRect( cyclicFrameNum, 0, 20, 20 );</pre>
<p>The exercise asks for cyclic motion at different speeds.  If the second square
is to be faster than the first, it should cross the drawing area in a smaller
number of frames.  If it is twice as fast, it will only need half as many frames to
make it across the drawing area.  For the second square, I use a cycle length of 150
instead of 300.  To cross the entire area, the x-coordinate of the square must
get to 300 after just 150 frames.  We can accomplish that by using
<code>2*cyclicFrameNumber</code> as the x-coord.  (Another way to think about it:
A square with x-coord <code>2*cyclicFrameNumber</code> moves twice as fast as
one with x-coord <code>cyclicFrameNumber</code>.  And it will finish the journey after
150 frames instead of 300, so the length of the cycle should be 150 frames.)  The
code for the second square is</p>
<pre>cyclicFrameNum = frameNumber % 150;  // Repeats every 150 frames
g.setFill(Color.GREEN);
g.fillRect( 2*cyclicFrameNum, 20, 20, 20 );</pre>
<p>The y-coord is 20, since the top square occupies 20 pixels at top of the window.
The third square moves three times as fast as the first, and its code is similar.</p>
<p>For the fourth square, I want an oscillating motion.  Like the first square, it takes
300 frames to move across the window from left to right.  But then it takes another
300 frames to move back from right to left.  The total length of the motion is 600.
(In the formula given in the exercise, N is 300 and 2*N is 600.)  The formula for the
oscillation frame number is</p>
<pre>oscilationFrameNum = frameNumber % 600;
if (oscilationFrameNum > 300)
    oscilationFrameNum = 600 - oscilationFrameNum;</pre>
<np>You should study how this works.  When <code>oscilationFrameNumber</code> is between
300 and 600, the formula <code>600-oscilationFrameNumber</code> gives an answer between
0 and 300.  And as <code>oscilationFrameNumber</code> gets bigger, 
<code>600-oscilationFrameNumber</code> gets smaller (which will mean that the x-coord
of the square is decreasing).  From there, you should be able to figure out the
rest of the program.</np>
<p>One more small issue is the size of the drawing area.  Since there are 6 squares,
and each is 20 pixels high, the height of the drawing area must be 120.
You might think at first that the width should be 300, since the x-coordinate of
the square goes up to 300.  But that x-coordinate is actually where the left edge
of the square is.  When the left edge is at 300, the right edge is at 320.  So for the
entire square to be visible, we have to make the width 320.</p>
<fxdiv>
<p>For drawing the horizontal black lines, the program uses the statement</p>
<pre>g.strokeLine(0,y+0.5,320,y+0.5);</pre>
<np>(I should explain the "+ 0.5".  The coordinates in <code>g.strokeLine()</code> give
the position of the <b>centers</b> of the endpoints of the line.  Without the "+&nbsp;"0.5", 
the top half of the line drawn here would lie in one row of pixels, and the bottom half
would lie in the next row.  The pixels in each row are only half covered by the line!
The computer might, depending on the environment, color a partially covered pixel by blending the drawing color with the
color of the background, so in this case, we would actually get a two pixel wide gray 
line instead of a one pixel wide black line.  This is an example of something called
"antialiasing," which you will encounter again later in the text.  By moving the line down 0.5 pixels, it
will exactly cover one row of pixels, which will be filled with solid black.)
</np>
</fxdiv>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="CyclicAndOscillatingMotionDemo" scope="fx">
import javafx.animation.AnimationTimer;
import javafx.application.Application;
import javafx.scene.layout.BorderPane;
import javafx.scene.Scene;
import javafx.stage.Stage;
import javafx.scene.canvas.Canvas;
import javafx.scene.canvas.GraphicsContext;
import javafx.scene.paint.Color;

/**
 *  This file can be used to create very simple animations.  Just fill in
 *  the definition of drawFrame with the code to draw one frame of the 
 *  animation, and possibly change a few of the values in the rest of
 *  the program as noted below.
 */
public class CyclicAndOscillatingMotionDemo extends Application {

    /**
     * Draws one frame of an animation. This subroutine should be called
     * about 60 times per second.  It is responsible for redrawing the
     * entire drawing area. The parameter g is used for drawing. The frameNumber 
     * starts at zero and increases by 1 each time this subroutine is called.  
     * The parameter elapsedSeconds gives the number of seconds since the animation
     * was started.  By using frameNumber and/or elapsedSeconds in the drawing
     * code, you can make a picture that changes over time.  That's an animation.
     * The parameters width and height give the size of the drawing area, in pixels.  
     */
    public void drawFrame(GraphicsContext g, int frameNumber, double elapsedSeconds, int width, int height) {

        g.setFill(Color.WHITE);
        g.fillRect(0, 0, width, height); // First, fill the entire image with a background color!

        /* Show cyclic motion at three speeds.  In each case, a square 
         * moves across the drawing area from left to right, then jumps
         * back to the start.
         */

        int cyclicFrameNum;
        
        cyclicFrameNum = frameNumber % 300;  // Repeats every 300 frames
        g.setFill(Color.RED);
        g.fillRect( cyclicFrameNum, 0, 20, 20 );
        
        cyclicFrameNum = frameNumber % 150;  // Repeats every 150 frames
        g.setFill(Color.GREEN);
        g.fillRect( 2*cyclicFrameNum, 20, 20, 20 );
        
        cyclicFrameNum = frameNumber % 100;  // Repeats every 100 frames
        g.setFill(Color.BLUE);
        g.fillRect( 3*cyclicFrameNum, 40, 20, 20 );
        

        /* Show oscillating motion at three speeds.  In each case, a square 
         * moves across the drawing area from left to right, then reverses
         * direction to move from right to left back to its starting point.
         */
        
        int oscillationFrameNum;
        
        oscillationFrameNum = frameNumber % 600;  // repeats every 600 frames
        if (oscillationFrameNum > 300)
            oscillationFrameNum = 600 - oscillationFrameNum; // after 300, the values go backwards back to 0
        g.setFill(Color.CYAN);
        g.fillRect( oscillationFrameNum, 60, 20, 20 );
        
        oscillationFrameNum = frameNumber % 300; // repeats every 300 frames
        if (oscillationFrameNum > 150)
            oscillationFrameNum = 300 - oscillationFrameNum; // after 150, the values go backwards back to 0
        g.setFill(Color.MAGENTA);
        g.fillRect( 2*oscillationFrameNum, 80, 20, 20 );
        
        oscillationFrameNum = frameNumber % 200; // repeats every 200 frames
        if (oscillationFrameNum > 100)
            oscillationFrameNum = 200 - oscillationFrameNum; // after 100, the values go backwards back to 0
        g.setFill(Color.YELLOW);
        g.fillRect( 3*oscillationFrameNum, 100, 20, 20 );
        
        
        /* Draw horizontal black lines across the window to separate the
         * regions used by the six squares.  Also draw a box around the outside,
         * mostly for the picture that I need for the web page!
         */
        
        int y;
        g.setStroke(Color.BLACK);
        for ( y = 20; y &lt; 120; y = y + 20 )
            g.strokeLine(0,y+0.5,320,y+0.5);
     }

    //------ Implementation details: DO NOT EXPECT TO UNDERSTAND THIS ------


    public void start(Stage stage) {
        int width = 320;   // The width of the image.  You can modify this value!
        int height = 120;  // The height of the image. You can modify this value!
        Canvas canvas = new Canvas(width,height);
        drawFrame(canvas.getGraphicsContext2D(), 0, 0, width, height);
        BorderPane root = new BorderPane(canvas);
        root.setStyle("-fx-border-width: 4px; -fx-border-color: #444");
        Scene scene = new Scene(root);
        stage.setScene(scene);
        stage.setTitle("Motion demo"); // STRING APPEARS IN WINDOW TITLEBAR!
        stage.show();
        stage.setResizable(false);
        AnimationTimer anim = new AnimationTimer() {
            private int frameNum;
            private long startTime = -1;
            private long previousTime;
            public void handle(long now) {
                if (startTime &lt; 0) {
                    startTime = previousTime = now;
                    drawFrame(canvas.getGraphicsContext2D(), 0, 0, width, height);
                }
                else if (now - previousTime > 0.95e9/60) {
                       // The test in the else-if is to guard against a bug that has shown
                       // up in some versions of JavaFX on some computers.  The bug allows
                       // the handle() method to be called many times more than the 60 times
                       // per second that is specified in the JavaFX documentation.
                    frameNum++;
                    drawFrame(canvas.getGraphicsContext2D(), frameNum, (now-startTime)/1e9, width, height);
                    previousTime = now;
                }
            }
        };
        anim.start();
    } 

    public static void main(String[] args) {
        launch();
    }

} // end CyclicAndOscillatingMotionDemo
</prog></pre>
<pre><prog name="CyclicAndOscillatingMotionDemo" scope="swing">import java.awt.*;
import java.awt.event.*;
import javax.swing.*;

/**
 * This program demonstrates cyclic and oscillating animations.  For cyclic animation,
 * it repeats itself every N frames, for some value of N.  An oscillating animation also
 * repeats, but the repetition is "back-and-forth."  That is, the second half
 * of the repeated animation is the same as the first half played backwards.
 */
public class CyclicAndOscillatingMotionDemo extends JPanel implements ActionListener {

    public void drawFrame(Graphics g, int frameNumber, int width, int height) {

        
        /* Show cyclic motion at three speeds.  In each case, a square 
         * moves across the drawing area from left to right, then jumps
         * back to the start.
         */

        int cyclicFrameNum;
        
        cyclicFrameNum = frameNumber % 300;  // Repeats every 300 frames
        g.setColor(Color.RED);
        g.fillRect( cyclicFrameNum, 0, 20, 20 );
        
        cyclicFrameNum = frameNumber % 150;  // Repeats every 150 frames
        g.setColor(Color.GREEN);
        g.fillRect( 2*cyclicFrameNum, 20, 20, 20 );
        
        cyclicFrameNum = frameNumber % 100;  // Repeats every 100 frames
        g.setColor(Color.BLUE);
        g.fillRect( 3*cyclicFrameNum, 40, 20, 20 );
        

        /* Show oscillating motion at three speeds.  In each case, a square 
         * moves across the drawing area from left to right, then reverses
         * direction to move from right to left back to its starting point.
         */
        
        int oscillationFrameNum;
        
        oscillationFrameNum = frameNumber % 600;  // repeats every 600 frames
        if (oscillationFrameNum &gt; 300)
            oscillationFrameNum = 600 - oscillationFrameNum; // after 300, the values go backwards back to 0
        g.setColor(Color.CYAN);
        g.fillRect( oscillationFrameNum, 60, 20, 20 );
        
        oscillationFrameNum = frameNumber % 300; // repeats every 300 frames
        if (oscillationFrameNum &gt; 150)
            oscillationFrameNum = 300 - oscillationFrameNum; // after 150, the values go backwards back to 0
        g.setColor(Color.MAGENTA);
        g.fillRect( 2*oscillationFrameNum, 80, 20, 20 );
        
        oscillationFrameNum = frameNumber % 200; // repeats every 200 frames
        if (oscillationFrameNum &gt; 100)
            oscillationFrameNum = 200 - oscillationFrameNum; // after 100, the values go backwards back to 0
        g.setColor(Color.YELLOW);
        g.fillRect( 3*oscillationFrameNum, 100, 20, 20 );
        
        
        /* Draw horizontal black lines across the window to separate the
         * regions used by the six squares.  Also draw a box around the outside,
         * mostly for the picture that I need for the web page!
         */
        
        int y;
        g.setColor(Color.BLACK);
        for ( y = 20; y &lt; 120; y = y + 20 )
            g.drawLine(0,y,320,y);
        g.drawRect(0,0,319,119);  // Why not (0,0,320,120)? This is a technicality.
                                  // If you use 320 and 120, the right and bottom edges
                                  // of the rect will actually be outside the drawing area.        
    }
    
    //------ Implementation details: DO NOT EXPECT TO UNDERSTAND THIS ------
    
    
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        
        JFrame window = new JFrame("Cyclic and Oscillating Motion");
        CyclicAndOscillatingMotionDemo drawingArea = new CyclicAndOscillatingMotionDemo();
        drawingArea.setBackground(Color.WHITE);
        window.setContentPane(drawingArea);
        drawingArea.setPreferredSize(new Dimension(320,120));  // size is 320 by 120
        window.pack();
        window.setLocation(100,50);
        window.setDefaultCloseOperation(JFrame.EXIT_ON_CLOSE);
        window.setResizable(false); // The user can't change the size.
        Timer frameTimer = new Timer(20,drawingArea);
        window.setVisible(true);
        frameTimer.start();

    } // end main

    private int frameNum;
    
    public void actionPerformed(ActionEvent evt) {
        frameNum++;
        repaint();
    }
    
    protected void paintComponent(Graphics g) {
        super.paintComponent(g);
        drawFrame(g, frameNum, getWidth(), getHeight());
    }

}
</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>


</exercises>