<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE quiz SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<quiz>
   
<question>
<ques><p>What is an <i>algorithm</i>?</p></ques>
<ans><p>An algorithm is an unambiguous, step-by-step procedure for performing
a certain task, which is guaranteed to finish after a finite number of steps.
(An algorithm is not the same thing as a program, but it can be the <i>idea</i>
behind a program.)</p></ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>Explain briefly what is
meant by "pseudocode" and how is it useful in the development of
algorithms.</p></ques>
<ans><p>Pseudocode refers to informal
descriptions of algorithms, written in a language that imitates the structure
of a programming language, but without the strict syntax. Pseudocode can be
used in the process of developing an algorithm with stepwise refinement. You
can start with a brief pseudocode description of the algorithm and then add
detail to the description through a series of refinements until you have
something that can be translated easily into a program written in an actual
programming language.</p></ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>What is a <i>block
statement?</i> How are block statements used in Java programs?</p></ques>
<ans><p>A block statement is just a
sequence of Java statements enclosed between braces, { and }. The body of a
subroutine is a block statement. Block statements are often used in control
structures. A block statement is generally used to group together several
statements so that they can be used in a situation that only calls for a single
statement. For example, the syntax of a while loop calls for a single
statement: "while (condition) do statement". However, the statement can be a
block statement, giving the structure: "while (condition) { statement;
statement;&nbsp;&dots;}".</p></ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>What is the main difference
between a <code>while</code> loop and a <code>do..while</code> loop?</p></ques>
<ans><p>Both types of loop repeat a
block of statements until some condition becomes false. The main difference is
that in a <code>while</code> loop, the condition is tested at the beginning of the
loop, and in a <code>do..while</code> loop, the condition is tested at the end of
the loop. It is possible that the body of a <code>while</code> loop might not be
executed at all. However, the body of a <code>do..while</code> loop is executed at
least once since the condition for ending the loop is not tested until the body
of the loop has been executed.</p></ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>What does it mean to
<i>prime</i> a loop?</p></ques>
<ans><p>The condition at the beginning
of a while loop has to make sense even the first time it is tested, before the
body of the loop is executed. To prime the loop is to set things up before the
loop starts so that the test makes sense (that is, the variables that it
contains have reasonable values). For example, if the test in the loop is
"while the user's response is yes," then you will have to prime the loop by
getting a response from the user (or making one up) before the loop.</p></ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Explain what is meant by an
<i>animation</i> and how a computer displays an animation.</p></ques>
<ans><p>An animation consists of a
series of "frames." Each frame is a still image, but there are slight
differences from one frame to the next. When the images are displayed rapidly
one frame after another, the eye perceives motion. A computer displays an
animation by showing one image on the screen, then replacing it with the next
image, then the next, and so on.</p></ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Write a <code>for</code> loop
that will print out all the multiples of 3 from 3 to 36, that is: 3 6 9 12 15
18 21 24 27 30 33 36.</p></ques>
<ans><p>Here are two possible answers.
Assume that <code>N</code> has been declared to be a variable of type
<ptype>int</ptype>:</p>
<pre>        for ( N = 3;  N &lt;= 36;  N = N + 3 ) {
            System.out.println( N );
        }
  
or
        for ( N = 3;  N &lt;= 36;  N++ ) {
            if ( N % 3 == 0 )
                System.out.println( N );
        }</pre></ans>
</question>
   

<question>
<ques><p>Fill in the following
<code>main()</code> routine so that it will ask the user to enter an integer, read
the user's response, and tell the user whether the number entered is even or
odd. (You can use <code>TextIO.getInt()</code> to read the integer. Recall that an
integer <code>n</code> is even if <code>n&nbsp;%&nbsp;2&nbsp;==&nbsp;0</code>.)</p>
<pre>public static void main(String[] args) {
 
         // Fill in the body of this subroutine!
 
}</pre>
</ques>
<ans><p>The problem already gives an
outline of the program. The last step, telling the user whether the number is
even or odd, requires an <code>if</code> statement to decide between the two
possibilities.</p>
<pre>import textio.TextIO;

public static void main (String[] args) {

   int n;  // the number read from the user

   TextIO.put("Type an integer: ");  // ask the use to enter an integer
 
   n = TextIO.getInt();   // read the user's response
 
   if (n % 2 == 0)        // tell the user whether the number is even or odd
      System.out.println("That's an even number.");
   else
      System.out.println("That's an odd number.");
}</pre>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Write a code segment that will print out two <i>different</i> random integers
selected from the range 1 to 10.  All possible outputs should have the same probability.
Hint:  You can easily select two random numbers, but you have to account for the
fact that the two numbers that you pick might be the same.</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>The code for selecting two random integers has to be wrapped in a loop that
will end only when the two selected numbers are different.  This can be done easily with
a <code>do..while</code> loop.  A <code>while</code> loop can also be used, but it
must be "primed" in some way.  Note that by using a loop to choose the numbers, we can
be absolutely sure that after the loop ends, the two numbers are different.
Here are three possible solutions:</p>
<pre>(1)     int x,y; // Two random integers.
        do {
            x = (int)(10*Math.random() + 1);
            y = (int)(10*Math.random() + 1);
        } while (x == y);  // continue if x and y are the same number.
        System.out.println(x + " " + y);
        
(2)     int x,y;  // Two random integers.
        x = y = 0;  // Give them junk value to "prime" the loop to make sure it runs.
        while (x == y) {
            x = (int)(10*Math.random() + 1);
            y = (int)(10*Math.random() + 1);
        }
        System.out.println(x + " " + y);
        
(3)     int x,y; // Two random integers.
        x = (int)(10*Math.random() + 1);  // Pick x, and keep its value.
        do { // The loop finds a y with a different value from x.
            y = (int)(10*Math.random() + 1);
        } while (x == y);
        System.out.println(x + " " + y);</pre>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Suppose that <code>s1</code> and <code>s2</code> are variables of type
<classname>String</classname>, whose values are expected to be string representations
of values of type <ptype>int</ptype>.  Write a code segment that will compute and print
the integer sum of those values, or will print an error message if the values cannot
successfully be converted into integers.  (Use a <code>try..catch</code> statement.)</p></ques>
<ans><p>The function <code>Integer.parseInt</code> can be used to convert the strings
into integers.  This function will throw an exception of type <classname>NumberFormatException</classname>
if the conversion fails.  A <code>try..catch</code> statement can catch this exception and
print an error message.  So, the code segment can be written:</p>
<pre>try {
   int n1, n2;  // The values of s1 and s2 as integers.
   int sum;     // The sum of n1 and n2.
   n1 = Integer.parseInt(s1);
   n2 = Integer.parseInt(s2);
   sum = n1 + n2;   // (If an exception occurs, we don't get to this point.)
   System.out.println("The sum is " + sum);
}
catch ( NumberFormatException e ) {
    System.out.println("Error!  Unable to convert strings to integers.");  
}</pre>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Show the exact output that
would be produced by the following <code>main()</code> routine:</p>
<pre>public static void main(String[] args) {
    int N;
    N = 1;
    while (N &lt;= 32) {
       N = 2 * N;
       System.out.println(N);   
    }
}</pre>
</ques>
<ans><p>The exact output printed by this
program is:</p>
<pre>2
4
8
16
32
64</pre>
<np>(The hard part to get right is the 64 at the end. The value of N doubles
each time through the loop. For the final execution of the loop, N starts out
with the value 32, but N is doubled to 64 before it is printed.)</np></ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Show the exact output
produced by the following <code>main()</code> routine:</p>
<pre>public static void main(String[] args) {
   int x,y;
   x = 5;
   y = 1;
   while (x &gt; 0) {
      x = x - 1;
      y = y * x;
      System.out.println(y);
   }
}</pre>
</ques>
<ans><p>The way to answer this question
is to trace exactly what the program does, step-by-step. The output is shown
below on the right. On the left is a table that shows the values of the
variables x and y as the program is being executed.</p>
<pre> value of x   |   value of y                 OUTPUT
--------------|--------------             -------------
      5       |     1  [ before loop]
      4       |     4  [ = 1*4 ]               4
      3       |    12  [ = 4*3 ]               12
      2       |    24  [ = 12*2 ]              24
      1       |    24  [ = 24*1 ]              24
      0       |     0  [ = 24*0 ]              0</pre>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>What output is produced by
the following program segment? <b>Why?</b> (Recall that <code>name.charAt(i)</code>
is the i-th character in the string, <code>name</code>.)</p>
<pre>String name;
int i;
boolean startWord;

name = "Richard M. Nixon";
startWord = true;
for (i = 0; i &lt; name.length(); i++) {
   if (startWord)
      System.out.println(name.charAt(i));
   if (name.charAt(i) == ' ')
      startWord = true;
   else
      startWord = false;
}</pre>
</ques>
<ans><p>This is a tough one! The output
from this program consists of the three lines:</p>
<pre>    R
    M
    N</pre>
<np>As the <code>for</code> loop in this code segment is executed,
<code>name.charAt(i)</code> represents each of the characters in the string
"Richard M. Nixon" in succession. The statement
<code>System.out.println(name.charAt(i))</code> outputs the single character
<code>name.charAt(i)</code> on a line by itself. However, this output statement
occurs inside an <code>if</code> statement, so only some of the characters are
output. The character is output if <code>startWord</code> is true. This variable is
initialized to true, so when <code>i</code> is 0, startWord is true, and the first
character in the string, 'R', is output. Then, since 'R' does not equal ' ',
<code>startWorld</code> becomes false, so no more characters are output until
<code>startWord</code> becomes true again. This happens when
<code>name.charAt(i)</code> is a space, that is, just <i>before</i> the 'M' is
processed and again just before the 'N' is processed. In fact whatever the
value of <code>name</code>, this <code>for</code> statement would print the first
character in <code>name</code> and every character in <code>name</code> that follows a
space. (It is <i>almost</i> true that this for statement prints the first
character of each word in the string, but something goes wrong when the first
character is a space or when there are
two spaces in a row. What happens in these cases?)
</np></ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>Suppose that <code>numbers</code> is an array of type <atype>int[]</atype>.
Write a code segment that will count and output the number of times that the
number 42 occurs in the array.</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>Use a <code>for</code> loop to go through the array and test each array element.
If the value is 42, add 1 to a counter:</p>
<pre>int count42;  // The number of 42s in the array
count42 = 0;
int i;  // loop control variable
for ( i = 0; i &lt; numbers.length; i++ ) {
    if ( numbers[i] == 42 ) {
        count42++;
    }
}
System.out.println("There were " + count42 + " 42s in the array.")</pre>
</ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>Define the <newword>range</newword> of an array of numbers to be
the maximum value in the array minus the minimum value.  Suppose that
<code>raceTimes</code> is an array of type <atype>double[]</atype>.
Write a code segment that will find and print the range of <code>raceTimes</code>.</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>We need both the minimum and the maximum value in the array.  We can compute both
using one <code>for</code> loop.</p>
<pre>double max;    // maximum value from the array
double min;    // minimum value from the array
double range;  // the range of the array, max - min
int i;         // for-loop variable
max = min = raceTimes[0];  // start with both equal to the first element
for ( i = 1; i &lt; raceTimes.length; i++ ) {
    if ( raceTimes[i] &gt; max )
        max = raceTimes[i];
    if ( raceTimes[i] &lt; min )
        min = raceTimes[i];
}
range = max - min;
System.out.println("The range is " + range);</pre>
</ans>
</question>


</quiz>