<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="control.1" title="Blocks, Loops, and Branches">

<p><start><big>T</big>he ability of a computer to perform</start> complex tasks
is built on just a few ways of combining simple commands into control
structures. In Java, there are just six such structures that are used to determine the normal
flow of control in a program&mdash;and, in fact, just
three of them would be enough to write programs to perform any task. The six
control structures are: the <newword>block</newword>, the
<newword>while loop</newword>, the <newword>do..while loop</newword>, the 
<newword>for loop</newword>, the <newword>if statement</newword>, and the 
<newword>switch statement</newword>.  Each of these structures is considered to be a single
"statement," but a <b>structured</b> statement that
can contain one or more other statements inside itself.</p>

<subsection id="control.1.1" title="Blocks">

<p>The <newword>block</newword> is the simplest type of structured
statement. Its purpose is simply to group a sequence of statements into a
single statement. The format of a block is:</p>

<pre>{
     <bnf>statements</bnf>
}</pre>

<np>That is, it consists of a sequence of statements enclosed between a pair of
braces, "{" and "}". In fact, it is possible for a block to contain no
statements at all; such a block is called an <newword>empty block</newword>, 
and can actually be useful at times. An empty block consists of
nothing but an empty pair of braces. Block statements usually occur inside
other statements, where their purpose is to group together several statements
into a unit. However, a block can be legally used wherever a statement can
occur. There is one place where a block is required: As you might have already
noticed in the case of the <code>main</code> subroutine of a program, the
definition of a subroutine is a block, since it is a sequence of statements
enclosed inside a pair of braces.</np>

<p>I should probably note again at this point that Java is what is called a
free-format language. There are no syntax rules about how the language has to
be arranged on a page. So, for example, you could write an entire block on one
line if you want. But as a matter of good programming style, you should lay out
your program on the page in a way that will make its structure as clear as
possible. In general, this means putting one statement per line and using
indentation to indicate statements that are contained inside control
structures. This is the format that I will use in my examples.</p>

<p>Here are two examples of blocks:</p>

<pre>{
   System.out.print("The answer is ");
   System.out.println(ans);
}
  
 
{  // This block exchanges the values of x and y
   int temp;      // A temporary variable for use in this block.
   temp = x;      // Save a copy of the value of x in temp.
   x = y;         // Copy the value of y into x.
   y = temp;      // Copy the value of temp into y.
}</pre>

<np>In the second example, a variable, <code>temp</code>, is declared inside the
block. This is perfectly legal, and it is good style to declare a variable
inside a block if that variable is used nowhere else but inside the block. A
variable declared inside a block is completely inaccessible and invisible from
outside that block. When the computer executes the variable declaration
statement, it allocates memory to hold the value of the variable (at least conceptually). When the
block ends, that memory is discarded (that is, made available for reuse). The
variable is said to be <newword>local</newword> to the block. There
is a general concept called the "scope" of an identifier. The <newword>scope</newword> 
of an identifier is the part of the program in which
that identifier is valid. The scope of a variable defined inside a block is
limited to that block, and more specifically to the part of the block that
comes after the declaration of the variable.</np>

</subsection>
<subsection id="control.1.2" title="The Basic While Loop">

<p>The block statement by itself really doesn't affect the flow of control in a
program. The five remaining control structures do. They can be divided into two
classes: loop statements and branching statements. You really just need one
control structure from each category in order to have a completely
general-purpose programming language. More than that is just convenience. In
this section, I'll introduce the <code>while</code> loop and the <code>if</code>
statement. I'll give the full details of these statements and of the other
three control structures in later sections.</p>

<p>A <newword>while loop</newword> is used to repeat a given
statement over and over. Of course, it's not likely that you would want to keep
repeating it forever. That would be an <newword>infinite loop</newword>, which is 
generally a bad thing. (There is an old story about
computer pioneer Grace Murray Hopper, who read instructions on a bottle of
shampoo telling her to "lather, rinse, repeat." As the story goes, she claims
that she tried to follow the directions, but she ran out of shampoo. (In case
you don't get it, she was making a joke about the way that computers mindlessly follow
instructions.))</p>

<p>To be more specific, a <code>while</code> loop will repeat a statement over and
over, but only so long as a specified condition remains true. A <code>while</code>
loop has the form:</p>

<pre>while (<bnf>boolean-expression</bnf>)
     <bnf>statement</bnf></pre>

<np>Since the statement can be, and usually is, a block, most <code>while</code>
loops have the form:</np>

<pre>while (<bnf>boolean-expression</bnf>) {
    <bnf>statements</bnf>
}</pre>

<np>Some programmers think that the braces should always be included as a matter
of style, even when there is only one statement between them, but I don't always
follow that advice myself.</np>

<p>The semantics of the <code>while</code> statement go like this: When the computer comes to a
<code>while</code> statement, it evaluates the <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf>, 
which yields either <code>true</code> or
<code>false</code> as its value. If the value is <code>false</code>, the computer skips
over the rest of the <code>while</code> loop and proceeds to the next command in
the program. If the value of the expression is <code>true</code>, the computer
executes the <bnf>statement</bnf> or block of <bnf>statements</bnf> inside the loop. Then it returns to the
beginning of the <code>while</code> loop and repeats the process. That is, it
re-evaluates the <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf>, ends the
loop if the value is <code>false</code>, and continues it if the value is
<code>true</code>. This will continue over and over until the value of the
expression is <code>false</code> when the computer evaluates it; if that never happens, then there will be an
infinite loop.</p>

<p>Here is an example of a <code>while</code> loop that simply prints out the
numbers 1, 2, 3, 4, 5:</p>

<pre>int number;   // The number to be printed.
number = 1;   // Start with 1.
while ( number &lt; 6 ) {  // Keep going as long as number is &lt; 6.
    System.out.println(number);
    number = number + 1;  // Go on to the next number.
}
System.out.println("Done!");</pre>

<np>The variable <code>number</code> is initialized with the value&nbsp;1. So 
when the computer evaluates the
expression "<code>number&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;6</code>" for the first time, 
it is asking whether 1 is less than 6, which is
<code>true</code>. The computer therefore proceeds to execute the two statements
inside the loop. The first statement prints out "1". The second statement adds
1 to <code>number</code> and stores the result back into the variable
<code>number</code>; the value of <code>number</code> has been changed to 2. The
computer has reached the end of the loop, so it returns to the beginning and
asks again whether <code>number</code> is less than 6. Once again this is true, so
the computer executes the loop again, this time printing out 2 as the value of
<code>number</code> and then changing the value of <code>number</code> to 3. It
continues in this way until eventually <code>number</code> becomes equal to 6. At
that point, the expression "<code>number&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;6</code>" evaluates to <code>false</code>. So, the
computer jumps past the end of the loop to the next statement and prints out
the message "Done!". Note that when the loop ends, the value of <code>number</code>
is 6, but the last value that was printed was 5.</np>

<p>By the way, you should remember that you'll never see a <code>while</code> loop
standing by itself in a real program. It will always be inside a subroutine
which is itself defined inside some class. As an example of a <code>while</code>
loop used inside a complete program, here is a little program that computes the
interest on an investment over several years. This is an improvement over
examples from the previous chapter that just reported the results for one
year:</p>

<pre>import textio.TextIO;

/**
 *  This class implements a simple program that will compute the amount of 
 *  interest that is earned on an investment over a period of 5 years.  The 
 *  initial amount of the investment and the interest rate are input by the 
 *  user.  The value of the investment at the end of each year is output.
 */ 
public class Interest3 {
     
 
   public static void main(String[] args) {
  
      double principal;  // The value of the investment.
      double rate;       // The annual interest rate.
      
      /* Get the initial investment and interest rate from the user. */
      
      System.out.print("Enter the initial investment: ");
      principal = TextIO.getlnDouble();
      
      System.out.println();
      System.out.println("Enter the annual interest rate.");
      System.out.print("Enter a decimal, not a percentage: ");
      rate = TextIO.getlnDouble();
      System.out.println();
      
      /* Simulate the investment for 5 years. */
      
      int years;  // Counts the number of years that have passed.
      
      years = 0;
      while (years &lt; 5) {
         double interest;  // Interest for this year.
         interest = principal * rate;
         principal = principal + interest;     // Add it to principal.
         years = years + 1;    // Count the current year.
         System.out.print("The value of the investment after ");
         System.out.print(years);
         System.out.print(" years is $");
         System.out.printf("%1.2f", principal);
         System.out.println();
      } // end of while loop
                       
   } // end of main()
        
} // end of class Interest3
</pre>
   
<np>You should study this program, and make sure that you understand what the
computer does step-by-step as it executes the <code>while</code> loop.</np>


</subsection>

<subsection id="control.1.3" title="The Basic If Statement">

<p>An <newword>if statement</newword> tells the computer to take one
of two alternative courses of action, depending on whether the value of a given
boolean-valued expression is true or false. It is an example of a "branching"
or "decision" statement. An <code>if</code> statement has the form:</p>

<pre>if ( <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> )
    <bnf>statement1</bnf>
else
    <bnf>statement2</bnf></pre>

<np>When the computer executes an <code>if</code> statement, it evaluates the
boolean expression. If the value is <code>true</code>, the computer executes the
first statement and skips the statement that follows the "<code>else</code>". If
the value of the expression is <code>false</code>, then the computer skips the
first statement and executes the second one. Note that in any case, one and
only one of the two statements inside the <code>if</code> statement is executed.
The two statements represent alternative courses of action; the computer
decides between these courses of action based on the value of the boolean
expression.</np>

<p>In many cases, you want the computer to choose between doing something and
not doing it. You can do this with an <code>if</code> statement that omits the
<code>else</code> part:</p>

<pre>if ( <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> )
    <bnf>statement</bnf></pre>

<np>To execute this statement, the computer evaluates the expression. If the
value is <code>true</code>, the computer executes the <bnf>statement</bnf> that is contained inside the <code>if</code>
statement; if the value is <code>false</code>, the computer skips over that <bnf>statement</bnf>.  In either
case, the computer then continues with whatever follows the <code>if</code> statement in the program.</np>

<p>Sometimes, novice programmers confuse <code>while</code> statements with simple
<code>if</code> statements (with no <code>else</code> part), although their meanings are
quite different.  The <bnf>statement</bnf> in an <code>if</code> is executed at most once,
while the <bnf>statement</bnf> in a <code>while</code> can be executed any number of times.
It can be helpful to look at diagrams of the flow of control for <code>while</code> and
simple <code>if</code> statements:</p>

<img src="while-and-if-flow-control.png" alt="Control flow diagrams for while and simple if"
   width="512" height="357" bordered="true" tex="while-and-if-flow-control.eps" texscale="0.8"/>
   
<np>In these diagrams, the arrows represent the flow of time as the statement is executed.
Control enters the diagram at the top and leaves at the bottom.
Similarly, a flow control diagram for an <code>if..else</code> statement makes it clear
that exactly one of the two nested statements is executed:</np>

<img src="if-else-flow-control.png" alt="Control flow diagram for if..else statement"
    width="320" height="376" bordered="true" tex="if-else-flow-control.eps" texscale="0.8"/>
   
<break/>

<p>Of course, either or both of the <bnf>statements</bnf>
in an <code>if</code> statement can be a block, and again many programmers
prefer to add the braces even when they contain just a single statement.
So an <code>if</code> statement often looks like:</p>

<pre>if ( <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> ) {
    <bnf>statements</bnf>
}
else {
    <bnf>statements</bnf>
}</pre>

<np>or:</np>

<pre>if ( <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> ) {
    <bnf>statements</bnf>
}</pre>

<p>As an example, here is an <code>if</code> statement that exchanges the value of
two variables, <code>x</code> and <code>y</code>, but only if <code>x</code> is greater
than <code>y</code> to begin with. After this <code>if</code> statement has been
executed, we can be sure that the value of <code>x</code> is definitely less than
or equal to the value of <code>y</code>:</p>

<pre>if ( x &gt; y ) {
    int temp;      // A temporary variable for use in this block.
    temp = x;      // Save a copy of the value of x in temp.
    x = y;         // Copy the value of y into x.
    y = temp;      // Copy the value of temp into y.
}</pre>

<p>Finally, here is an example of an <code>if</code> statement that includes an
<code>else</code> part. See if you can figure out what it does, and why it would be
used:</p>

<pre>if ( years &gt; 1 ) {  // handle case for 2 or more years
    System.out.print("The value of the investment after ");
    System.out.print(years);
    System.out.print(" years is $");
}
else {  // handle case for 1 year
    System.out.print("The value of the investment after 1 year is $");
}  // end of if statement
System.out.printf("%1.2f", principal);  // this is done in any case</pre>


<p>I'll have more to say about control structures later in this chapter. But
you already know the essentials. If you never learned anything more about
control structures, you would already know enough to perform any possible
computing task. Simple looping and branching are all you really need!</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="control.1.4" title="Definite Assignment">

<p>I will finish this introduction to control structures with a somewhat technical
issue that you might not fully understand the first time you encounter it.
Consider the following two code segments, which seem to be entirely equivalent:</p>

<pre>int y;                          int y;
if (x &lt; 0) {                    if (x &lt; 0) {
    y = 1;                           y = 1;
}                               }
else {                          if (x &gt;= 0) {
    y = 2;                           y = 2;
}                               }
System.out.println(y);          System.out.println(y);</pre>

<np>In the version on the left, <code>y</code> is assigned the value 1 if <code>x&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;0</code>
and it is assigned the value 2 otherwise, that is, if <code>x&nbsp;&gt;=&nbsp;0</code>.  Exactly the same is true of the
version on the right.  However, there is a subtle difference.  In fact, the Java compiler will report
an error for the <code>System.out.println</code> statement in the code on the right, while the
code on the left is perfectly fine!  
</np>

<p>The problem is that in the code on the right, the computer can't tell that the
variable <code>y</code> has definitely been assigned a value.  When an <code>if</code>
statement has no <code>else</code> part, the statement inside the <code>if</code>
might or might not be executed, depending on the value of the condition.  The compiler can't
tell whether it will be executed or not, since the condition will only be evaluated when
the program is running.  For the code on the right above, as far as the compiler is concerned,
it is possible that <b>neither</b> statement, <code>y&nbsp;=&nbsp;1</code> or <code>y&nbsp;=&nbsp;2</code>,
will be evaluated, so it is possible that the output statement is trying to print an undefined value.
The compiler considers this to be an error.  The value of a variable can only be used if the
compiler can <b>verify</b> that the variable will have been assigned a value at that point when the
program is running.  This is called <newword>definite assignment</newword>.  (It doesn't matter
that <b>you</b> can tell that <code>y</code> will always be assigned a value in this example.
The question is whether the compiler can tell.)</p>

<p>Note that in the code on the left above, <code>y</code> is definitely assigned a value,
since in an <code>if..else</code> statement, one of the two alternatives will be executed
no matter what the value of the condition in the <code>if</code>.  
It is important that you understand that there is a 
difference between an <code>if..else</code> statement and a pair of plain <code>if</code> statements.
Here is another pair of code segments that might seem to do the same thing,
but don't.  What's the value of <code>x</code> after each code segment is executed?</p>

<pre>
int x;                             int x;
x = -1;                            x = -1;
if (x &lt; 0)                         if (x &lt; 0)
    x = 1;                             x = 1;
else                               if (x &gt;= 0)
    x = 2;                             x = 2;
</pre>

<np>After the code on the left is executed, <code>x</code> is 1; after the code on the
right, <code>x</code> is&nbsp;2.  If you don't believe this, work though the code step-by-step,
doing exactly what the computer does when it executes each step.</np>

</subsection>

</section>
