<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="control.5" title="The if Statement">

<p><start><big>T</big>he first of the two branching statements</start> in Java
is the <code>if</code> statement, which you have already seen in <localref href="control.1"/>. It takes the form</p>

<pre>if (<bnf>boolean-expression</bnf>)
     <bnf>statement-1</bnf>
else
     <bnf>statement-2</bnf></pre>

<np>As usual, the statements inside an <code>if</code> statement can be blocks. The
<code>if</code> statement represents a two-way branch. The <code>else</code> part of an
<code>if</code> statement&mdash;consisting of the word "else" and the statement that
follows it&mdash;can be omitted.</np>

<subsection id="control.5.1" title="The Dangling else Problem">
   
<p>Now, an <code>if</code> statement is, in particular, a statement. This means
that either <bnf>statement-1</bnf> or <bnf>statement-2</bnf> in the above <code>if</code> statement can itself
be an <code>if</code> statement. A problem arises, however, 
if <bnf>statement-1</bnf> is an <code>if</code> statement that has no
<code>else</code> part. This special case is effectively forbidden by the syntax of
Java. Suppose, for example, that you type</p>

<pre>if ( x &gt; 0 )
    if (y &gt; 0)
       System.out.println("First case");
else
    System.out.println("Second case");</pre>

<np>Now, remember that the way you've indented this doesn't mean anything at all
to the computer. You might think that the <code>else</code> part is the second half
of your "<code>if&nbsp;(x&nbsp;&gt;&nbsp;0)</code>" statement, but the rule that the computer
follows attaches the <code>else</code> to "<code>if&nbsp;(y&nbsp;&gt;&nbsp;0)</code>", which is
closer. That is, the computer reads your statement as if it were formatted:</np>

<pre>if ( x &gt; 0 )
    if (y &gt; 0)
       System.out.println("First case");
    else
        System.out.println("Second case");</pre>

<np>You can force the computer to use the other interpretation by enclosing the
nested <code>if</code> in a block:</np>

<pre>if ( x &gt; 0 ) {
    if (y &gt; 0)
       System.out.println("First case");
}
else
    System.out.println("Second case");</pre>

<np>These two <code>if</code> statements have different meanings: In the case when <code>x&nbsp;&lt;=&nbsp;0</code>, the
first statement doesn't print anything, but the second statement prints "Second
case".</np>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="control.5.2" title="Multiway Branching">   
   
<p>Much more interesting than this technicality is the case where <bnf>statement-2</bnf>, 
the <code>else</code> part of the <code>if</code>
statement, is itself an <code>if</code> statement. The statement would look like
this (perhaps without the final else part):</p>

<pre>if (<bnf>boolean-expression-1</bnf>)
     <bnf>statement-1</bnf>
else
     if (<bnf>boolean-expression-2</bnf>)
         <bnf>statement-2</bnf>
     else
         <bnf>statement-3</bnf></pre>

<np>However, since the computer doesn't care how a program is laid out on the
page, this is almost always written in the format:</np>

<pre>if (<bnf>boolean-expression-1</bnf>)
     <bnf>statement-1</bnf>
else if (<bnf>boolean-expression-2</bnf>)
     <bnf>statement-2</bnf>
else
     <bnf>statement-3</bnf></pre>

<p>You should think of this as a single statement representing a three-way
branch. When the computer executes this, one and only one of the three
statements&mdash;<bnf>statement-1</bnf>, <bnf>statement-2</bnf>, or <bnf>statement-3</bnf>&mdash;will 
be executed. The computer starts by evaluating <bnf>boolean-expression-1</bnf>. If it is <code>true</code>, the computer
executes <bnf>statement-1</bnf> and then jumps all the way
to the end of the outer if statement, skipping the other two <bnf>statements</bnf>. If <bnf>boolean-expression-1</bnf> 
is <code>false</code>, the computer skips
<bnf>statement-1</bnf> and executes the second, nested if
statement. To do this, it tests the value of <bnf>boolean-expression-2</bnf> and uses it to decide between
<bnf>statement-2</bnf> and <bnf>statement-3</bnf>.</p>

<p>Here is an example that will print out one of three different messages,
depending on the value of a variable named <code>temperature</code>:</p>

<pre>if (temperature &lt; 50)
   System.out.println("It's cold.");
else if (temperature &lt; 80)
   System.out.println("It's nice.");
else
   System.out.println("It's hot.");</pre>

<np>If <code>temperature</code> is, say, 42, the first test is <code>true</code>. The
computer prints out the message "It's cold", and skips the rest&mdash;without even
evaluating the second condition. For a temperature of 75, the first test is
<code>false</code>, so the computer goes on to the second test. This test is
<code>true</code>, so the computer prints "It's nice" and skips the rest. If the
temperature is 173, both of the tests evaluate to <code>false</code>, so the
computer says "It's hot" (unless its circuits have been fried by the heat, that
is).</np>

<p>You can go on stringing together "else-if's" to make multiway branches with
any number of cases:</p>

<pre>if (<bnf>test-1</bnf>)
     <bnf>statement-1</bnf>
else if (<bnf>test-2</bnf>)
     <bnf>statement-2</bnf>
else if (<bnf>test-3</bnf>)
     <bnf>statement-3</bnf>
  .
  . // (more cases)
  .
else if (<bnf>test-N</bnf>)
     <bnf>statement-N</bnf>
else
     <bnf>statement-(N+1)</bnf></pre>

<np>The computer evaluates the tests, which are boolean expressions, one after the other until it
comes to one that is <code>true</code>. It executes the associated statement and
skips the rest. If none of the boolean expressions evaluate to <code>true</code>,
then the statement in the <code>else</code> part is executed. This statement is
called a multiway branch because one and only one of the statements will be executed.
The final <code>else</code> part can be omitted. In that case, if all the boolean
expressions are false, none of the statements are executed. Of course, each of
the statements can be a block, consisting of a number of statements enclosed
between { and }. Admittedly, there is lot of syntax here; as you study and
practice, you'll become comfortable with it.  It might be useful to look at a 
flow control diagram for the general "if..else&nbsp;if" statement shown above:</np>

<img src="multiway-if-flow-control.png" alt="Flow control diagram for a multiway if statement"
   width="547" height="463" bordered="true" tex="multiway-if-flow-control.eps" texscale="0.75"/>

</subsection>

<subsection id="control.5.3" title="If Statement Examples">

<p>As an example of using <code>if</code> statements, let's suppose that <code>x</code>,
<code>y</code>, and <code>z</code> are variables of type <ptype>int</ptype>, and that each
variable has already been assigned a value. Consider the problem of printing
out the values of the three variables in increasing order. For example, if the
values are 42, 17, and 20, then the output should be in the order 17, 20,
42.</p>

<p>One way to approach this is to ask, where does <code>x</code> belong in the
list? It comes first if it's less than both <code>y</code> and <code>z</code>. It comes
last if it's greater than both <code>y</code> and <code>z</code>. Otherwise, it comes
in the middle. We can express this with a 3-way <code>if</code> statement, but we
still have to worry about the order in which <code>y</code> and <code>z</code> should
be printed. In pseudocode,</p>

<pre>if (x &lt; y &amp;&amp; x &lt; z) {
    output x, followed by y and z in their correct order
}
else if (x &gt; y &amp;&amp; x &gt; z) {
    output y and z in their correct order, followed by x
}
else {
    output x in between y and z in their correct order
}</pre>

<np>Determining the relative order of <code>y</code> and <code>z</code> requires another
<code>if</code> statement, so this becomes</np>

<pre>if (x &lt; y &amp;&amp; x &lt; z) {        // x comes first
    if (y &lt; z)
       System.out.println( x + " " + y + " " + z );
    else
       System.out.println( x + " " + z + " " + y );
}
else if (x &gt; y &amp;&amp; x &gt; z) {   // x comes last
    if (y &lt; z)
       System.out.println( y + " " + z + " " + x );
    else
       System.out.println( z + " " + y + " " + x );
}
else {                       // x in the middle
    if (y &lt; z)
       System.out.println( y + " " + x + " " + z);
    else
       System.out.println( z + " " + x + " " + y);
}</pre>

<np>You might check that this code will work correctly even if some of the
values are the same. If the values of two variables are the same, it doesn't
matter which order you print them in.</np>

<p>Note, by the way, that even though you can say in English "if x is less than
y and z," you can't say in Java "<code>if (x &lt; y &amp;&amp; z)</code>". The
<code>&amp;&amp;</code> operator can only be used between boolean values, so you
have to make separate tests, <code>x&lt;y</code> and <code>x&lt;z</code>, and then
combine the two tests with <code>&amp;&amp;</code>.</p>

<p>There is an alternative approach to this problem that begins by asking,
"which order should <code>x</code> and <code>y</code> be printed in?" Once that's
known, you only have to decide where to stick in <code>z</code>. This line of
thought leads to different Java code:</p>

<pre>if ( x &lt; y ) {  // x comes before y
   if ( z &lt; x )   // z comes first
      System.out.println( z + " " + x + " " + y);
   else if ( z &gt; y )   // z comes last
      System.out.println( x + " " + y + " " + z);
   else   // z is in the middle
      System.out.println( x + " " + z + " " + y);
}
else {          // y comes before x
   if ( z &lt; y )   // z comes first
      System.out.println( z + " " + y + " " + x);
   else if ( z &gt; x )  // z comes last
      System.out.println( y + " " + x + " " + z);
   else  // z is in the middle
      System.out.println( y + " " + z + " " + x);
}</pre>

<p>Once again, we see how the same problem can be solved in many different
ways. The two approaches to this problem have not exhausted all the
possibilities. For example, you might start by testing whether <code>x</code> is
greater than <code>y</code>. If so, you could swap their values. Once you've done
that, you know that <code>x</code> should be printed before <code>y</code>.</p>

<break/>

<p>Finally, let's write a complete program that uses an <code>if</code> statement
in an interesting way. I want a program that will convert measurements of
length from one unit of measurement to another, such as miles to yards or
inches to feet. So far, the problem is extremely under-specified. Let's say
that the program will only deal with measurements in inches, feet, yards, and
miles. It would be easy to extend it later to deal with other units. The user
will type in a measurement in one of these units, such as "17 feet" or "2.73
miles". The output will show the length in terms of <b>each</b> of
the four units of measure. (This is easier than asking the user which units to
use in the output.) An outline of the process is</p>

<pre>Read the user's input measurement and units of measure
Express the measurement in inches, feet, yards, and miles
Display the four results</pre>

<p>The program can read both parts of the user's input from the same line by
using <code>TextIO.getDouble()</code> to read the numerical measurement and
<code>TextIO.getlnWord()</code> to read the unit of measure. The conversion into
different units of measure can be simplified by first converting the user's
input into inches. From there, the number of inches can easily be converted into feet, yards, and miles.
Before converting into inches, we have to test the input to determine which unit of measure the user has
specified:</p>

<pre>Let measurement = TextIO.getDouble()
Let units = TextIO.getlnWord()
if the units are inches
   Let inches = measurement
else if the units are feet
   Let inches = measurement * 12         // 12 inches per foot
else if the units are yards
   Let inches = measurement * 36         // 36 inches per yard
else if the units are miles
   Let inches = measurement * 12 * 5280  // 5280 feet per mile
else
   The units are illegal!
   Print an error message and stop processing
Let feet = inches / 12.0
Let yards = inches / 36.0
Let miles = inches / (12.0 * 5280.0)
Display the results</pre>

<p>Since <code>units</code> is a <classname>String</classname>, we can use
<code>units.equals("inches")</code> to check whether the specified unit of measure
is "inches". However, it would be nice to allow the units to be specified as
"inch" or abbreviated to "in". To allow these three possibilities, we can check
<code>if (units.equals("inches") || units.equals("inch") ||
units.equals("in"))</code>. It would also be nice to allow upper case letters, as
in "Inches" or "IN". We can do this by converting <code>units</code> to lower case
before testing it or by substituting the function
<code>units.equalsIgnoreCase</code> for <code>units.equals</code>.</p>

<p>In my final program, I decided to make things more interesting by allowing
the user to repeat the process of entering a measurement and seeing the
results of the conversion for each measurement.  The program will end only
when the user inputs 0. To program that, I just had to wrap the above algorithm
inside a <code>while</code> loop, and make sure that the loop ends when the user
inputs a&nbsp;0. Here's the complete program:</p>

<pre>import textio.TextIO;

/**
 * This program will convert measurements expressed in inches,
 * feet, yards, or miles into each of the possible units of
 * measure.  The measurement is input by the user, followed by
 * the unit of measure.  For example:  "17 feet", "1 inch", or
 * "2.73 mi".  Abbreviations in, ft, yd, and mi are accepted.
 * The program will continue to read and convert measurements
 * until the user enters an input of 0.
 */
 public class LengthConverter {
 
    public static void main(String[] args) {
       
       double measurement;  // Numerical measurement, input by user.
       String units;        // The unit of measure for the input, also
                            //    specified by the user.
       
       double inches, feet, yards, miles;  // Measurement expressed in
                                           //   each possible unit of
                                           //   measure.
       
       System.out.println("""
                Enter measurements in inches, feet, yards, or miles.
                For example:  1 inch    17 feet    2.73 miles
                You can use abbreviations:   in   ft  yd   mi
                I will convert your input into the other units
                of measure.
                """);
       
       while (true) {
          
          /* Get the user's input, and convert units to lower case. */
          
          System.out.print("Enter your measurement, or 0 to end:  ");
          measurement = TextIO.getDouble();
          if (measurement == 0)
             break;  // Terminate the while loop.
          units = TextIO.getlnWord();            
          units = units.toLowerCase();  // convert units to lower case
          
          /* Convert the input measurement to inches. */
          
          if (units.equals("inch") || units.equals("inches") 
                                          || units.equals("in")) {
              inches = measurement;
          }
          else if (units.equals("foot") || units.equals("feet") 
                                          || units.equals("ft")) {
              inches = measurement * 12;
          }
          else if (units.equals("yard") || units.equals("yards") 
                                           || units.equals("yd")) {
              inches = measurement * 36;
          }
          else if (units.equals("mile") || units.equals("miles") 
                                             || units.equals("mi")) {
              inches = measurement * 12 * 5280;
          }
          else {
              System.out.println("Sorry, but I don't understand \"" 
                                                   + units + "\".");
              continue;  // back to start of while loop
          }
          
          /* Convert measurement in inches to feet, yards, and miles. */
          
          feet = inches / 12;
          yards = inches / 36;
          miles = inches / (12*5280);
          
          /* Output measurement in terms of each unit of measure. */
          
          System.out.printf("""
                    That's equivalent to:
                    %14.5g inches
                    %14.5g feet
                    %14.5g yards
                    %14.5g miles
                    """, inches, feet, yards, miles);

          System.out.println();
       
       } // end while
       
       System.out.println();
       System.out.println("OK!  Bye for now.");
       
    } // end main()
    
 } // end class LengthConverter
</pre>

   
<p>(Note that this program uses text blocks for multiline outputs (see <localref href="basics.3.3a"/>;
text blocks require Java&nbsp;17).
It also uses formatted output with the "g" format specifier.  In this program,
we have no control over how large or how small the numbers might be.  It could easily make
sense for the user to enter very large or very small measurements.  The "g" format will
print a real number in exponential form if it is very large or very small, and in the usual decimal form
otherwise.  Remember that in the format specification <code>%14.5g</code>, the 5 is the total
number of significant digits that are to be printed, so we will always get the same number of
significant digits in the output, no matter what the size of the number.  If we had used an
"f" format specifier such as <code>%14.5f</code>, the output would be in decimal form with
5 digits after the decimal point.  This would print the number 0.000000000745482 as <code>0.00000</code>,
with no <b>significant</b> digits at all!
With the "g" format specifier, the output would be <code>7.4549e-10</code>.)</p>
   
</subsection>

<subsection id="control.5.4" title="The Empty Statement">

<p>As a final note in this section, I will mention one more type of statement
in Java: the <newword>empty statement</newword>. This is a statement
that consists simply of a semicolon and which tells the computer to
do nothing. The existence of the empty statement makes
the following legal, even though you would not ordinarily see a semicolon after
a&nbsp;}&nbsp;:</p>

<pre>if (x &lt; 0) {
    x = -x;
};</pre>

<p>The semicolon is legal after the }, but the computer considers it to be an
empty statement, not part of the <code>if</code> statement. Occasionally, you might
find yourself using the empty statement when what you mean is, in fact, "do
nothing." For example, the rather contrived <code>if</code> statement</p>
   
<pre>if ( done )
   ;  // Empty statement
else
   System.out.println( "Not done yet.");</pre>
   
<np>does nothing when the <ptype>boolean</ptype> variable <code>done</code> is true,
and prints out "Not done yet" when it is false. You can't just leave out the semicolon
in this example, since Java syntax requires an actual statement between the <code>if</code>
and the <code>else</code>.   I prefer, though, to use an empty block, consisting 
of&nbsp;{&nbsp;and&nbsp;} with nothing between, for such cases.</np>

<p>Occasionally, stray empty statements can cause annoying, hard-to-find errors
in a program. For example, the following program segment prints out "Hello"
just <b>once</b>, not ten times:</p>

<pre>for (i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++);
    System.out.println("Hello");</pre>

<np>Why? Because the ";" at the end of the first line is a statement, and it is
this empty statement that is executed ten times. The <code>System.out.println</code>
statement is not really inside the <code>for</code> statement at all, so it is
executed just once, after the <code>for</code> loop has completed.  The
<code>for</code> loop just does nothing, ten times!</np>

</subsection>
</section>