<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="GUI1.6" title="Basic Components">
   
<p><start><big>I</big>n preceding sections</start>, you've seen how to use a
graphics context to draw on the screen and how to handle mouse events and
keyboard events. In one sense, that's all there is to GUI programming. If
you're willing to program all the drawing and handle all the mouse and keyboard
events, you have nothing more to learn. However, you would either be doing a
lot more work than you need to do, or you would be limiting yourself to very
simple user interfaces. A typical user interface uses standard GUI components
such as buttons, scroll bars, text-input boxes, and menus. These components
have already been written for you, so you don't have to duplicate the work
involved in developing them. They know how to draw themselves, and they can
handle the details of processing the mouse and keyboard events that concern
them.</p>

<p>Consider one of the simplest user interface components, a push button. The
button has a border, and it displays some text. This text can be changed.
Sometimes the button is disabled, so that clicking on it doesn't have any
effect. When it is disabled, its appearance changes. When the user clicks on
the push button, the button changes appearance while the mouse button is
pressed and changes back when the mouse button is released. In fact, it's more
complicated than that. If the user moves the mouse outside the push button
before releasing the mouse button, the button changes to its regular
appearance. To implement this, it is necessary to respond to mouse exit or
mouse drag events. Furthermore, on many platforms, a button can receive the
input focus. The button changes appearance when it has the focus. If the button
has the focus and the user presses the space bar, the button is triggered. This
means that the button must respond to keyboard and focus events as well.</p>

<p>Fortunately, you don't have to program <b>any</b> of this, provided you
use an object belonging to the standard class <code>javax.swing.JButton</code>. A
<classname>JButton</classname> object draws itself and processes mouse, keyboard, and focus
events on its own. You only hear from the <classname>JButton</classname> when the user
triggers it by clicking on it or pressing the space bar while the button has
the input focus. When this happens, the <classname>JButton</classname> object creates an
event object belonging to the class <code>java.awt.event.ActionEvent</code>. The
event object is sent to any registered listeners to tell them that the button
has been pushed. Your program gets only the information it needs&mdash;the fact
that a button was pushed.</p>
   
<break/>
   
<p>The standard components that are defined as part of the Swing graphical user interface
API are defined by subclasses of the class <classname>JComponent</classname>, which is 
itself a subclass of <classname>Component</classname>.  (Note that this includes the
<classname>JPanel</classname> class that we have already been working with extensively.)
Many useful methods are
defined in the <classname>Component</classname> and <classname>JComponent</classname>
classes and so can be used with any Swing component.  We begin by looking at a
few of these methods.  Suppose that <code>comp</code> is a variable that refers
to some <classname>JComponent</classname>.  Then the following methods can be
used:</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>comp.getWidth()</codedef> and <codedef>comp.getHeight()</codedef> are functions that
give the current size of the component, in pixels.  One warning: When a component is first
created, its size is zero. The size will be set later, probably by a layout
manager. A common mistake is to check the size of a component before that size
has been set, such as in a constructor.</li>

<li><codedef>comp.setEnabled(true)</codedef> and
<codedef>comp.setEnabled(false)</codedef> can be used to
enable and disable the component. When a component is disabled, its appearance
might change, and the user cannot do anything with it.  There is a boolean-valued
function, <codedef>comp.isEnabled()</codedef> that you can
call to discover whether the component is enabled.</li>

<li><codedef>comp.setVisible(true)</codedef> and
<codedef>comp.setVisible(false)</codedef> can be called to
hide or show the component.</li>

<li><codedef>comp.setFont(font)</codedef> sets the font that
is used for text displayed on the component. See <localref href="GUI1.3.3"/>
for a discussion of fonts.</li>

<li><codedef>comp.setBackground(color)</codedef> and
<codedef>comp.setForeground(color)</codedef> set the
background and foreground colors for the component.  See <localref href="GUI1.3.2"/>.</li>

<li><codedef>comp.setOpaque(true)</codedef> tells the
component that the area occupied by the component should be filled with the
component's background color before the content of the component is painted. By
default, only <classname>JLabels</classname> are non-opaque. A non-opaque,
or "transparent", component ignores its background color and simply paints its
content over the content of its container. This usually means that it inherits
the background color from its container.</li>

<li><codedef>comp.setToolTipText(string)</codedef> sets the
specified string as a "tool tip" for the component. The tool tip is displayed
if the mouse cursor is in the component and the mouse is not moved for a few
seconds. The tool tip should give some information about the meaning of the
component or how to use it.</li>

<li><codedef>comp.setPreferredSize(size)</codedef> sets the
size at which the component should be displayed, if possible. The parameter is
of type <code>java.awt.Dimension</code>, where an object of type <classname>Dimension</classname>
has two public integer-valued instance variables, <code>width</code> and <code>height</code>.
A call to this method usually looks something
like "<code>setPreferredSize( new Dimension(100,50)&nbsp;)</code>". The preferred
size is used as a hint by layout managers, but will not be respected in all
cases.  Standard components generally compute a correct
preferred size automatically, but it can be useful to set it in some cases. For
example, if you use a <classname>JPanel</classname> as a drawing surface, it is usually a good
idea to set a preferred size for it, since its default preferred size is zero.</li>

</ul>

   
<p>Note that using
any component is a multi-step process. The component object must be created
with a constructor. It must be added to a container. In many cases, a listener
must be registered to respond to events from the component. And in some cases,
a reference to the component must be saved in an instance variable so that the
component can be manipulated by the program after it has been created.
In this section, we will look at a few of the basic standard components that are
available in Swing. In the <localref href="GUI1.7">next section</localref>
we will consider the problem of laying out components in containers.</p>

   
<subsection id="GUI1.6.1" title="JButton">
   
<p>An object of class <classname>JButton</classname> is a push button that the user
can click to trigger some action. You've already seen
buttons used in <localref href="GUI1.1"/>, but we consider
them in much more detail here.  To use any component effectively, there are several
aspects of the corresponding class that you should be familiar with.  For
<classname>JButton</classname>, as an example, I list these aspects explicitly:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Constructors</b>: The <classname>JButton</classname> class has a constructor that
takes a string as a parameter. This string becomes the text displayed on the
button. For example: <code>stopGoButton = new&nbsp;JButton("Go")</code>.  This creates
a button object that will display the text, "Go" (but remember that the button must still
be added to a container before it can appear on the screen).</li>

<li><b>Events</b>: When the user clicks on a button, the button generates an
event of type <classname>ActionEvent</classname>. This event is sent to any listener that has
been registered with the button as an <classname>ActionListener</classname>.</li>

<li><b>Listeners</b>: An object that wants to handle events generated by
buttons must implement the <classname>ActionListener</classname> interface. This interface
defines just one method, "<code>public void actionPerformed(ActionEvent
evt)</code>", which is called to notify the object of an action event.</li>

<li><b>Registration of Listeners</b>: In order to actually receive notification
of an event from a button, an <classname>ActionListener</classname> must be registered with
the button. This is done with the button's <code>addActionListener()</code> method.
For example: <code>stopGoButton.addActionListener( buttonHandler&nbsp;);</code></li>

<li><b>Event methods</b>: When <code>actionPerformed(evt)</code> is called by the
button, the parameter, <code>evt</code>, contains information about the event. This
information can be retrieved by calling methods in the <classname>ActionEvent</classname>
class. In particular, <code>evt.getActionCommand()</code> returns a <classname>String</classname>
giving the command associated with the button. By default, this command is the
text that is displayed on the button, but it is possible to set it to some other string. 
The method <code>evt.getSource()</code>
returns a reference to the object that produced the event, that is, to
the <classname>JButton</classname> that was pressed. The return value is of type
<classname>Object</classname>, not <classname>JButton</classname>, because other types of components can
also produce <classname>ActionEvents</classname>.</li>

<li><b>Component methods</b>: Several useful methods are defined in the
<classname>JButton</classname> class, in addition to the standard <classname>Component</classname> methods.
For example, <code>stopGoButton.setText("Stop")</code>
changes the text displayed on the button to "Stop". And
<code>stopGoButton.setActionCommand("sgb")</code> changes the action command
associated with this button for action events. 
The <code>setEnabled()</code> and <code>setText()</code> methods are
particularly useful for giving the user information about what is going on in
the program. A disabled button is better than a button that gives an obnoxious
error message such as "Sorry, you can't click on me now!"</li>
</ul>


</subsection>
   
   
<subsection id="GUI1.6.2" title="JLabel">

<p><classname>JLabel</classname> is certainly the simplest type of component. An object of
type <classname>JLabel</classname> exists just to display a line of text. The text cannot be edited
by the user, although it can be changed by your program. The constructor for a
<classname>JLabel</classname> specifies the text to be displayed:</p>

<pre>JLabel message = new JLabel("Hello World!");</pre>

<np>There is another constructor that specifies where in the label the text is
located, if there is extra space. The possible alignments are given by the
constants <code>JLabel.LEFT</code>, <code>JLabel.CENTER</code>, and
<code>JLabel.RIGHT</code>. For example,</np>

<pre>JLabel message = new JLabel("Hello World!", JLabel.CENTER);</pre>

<np>creates a label whose text is centered in the available space. You can
change the text displayed in a label by calling the label's <code>setText()</code>
method:</np>

<pre>message.setText("Goodbye World!");</pre>

<p>Since the <classname>JLabel</classname> class is a subclass of <classname>JComponent</classname>, 
you can
use methods such as <code>setForeground()</code> and <code>setFont()</code> with labels. If you want the
background color to have any effect, you should call <code>setOpaque(true)</code>
on the label, since otherwise the <classname>JLabel</classname> might not fill in its
background. For example:</p>

<pre>JLabel message = new JLabel("Hello World!", JLabel.CENTER);
message.setForeground(Color.RED);   // Display red text...
message.setBackground(Color.BLACK); //    on a black background...
message.setFont(new Font("Serif",Font.BOLD,18));  // in a big bold font.
message.setOpaque(true);  // Make sure background is filled in.</pre>
   
</subsection>
   
   
   
<subsection id="GUI1.6.3" title="JCheckBox">
   
<p>A <classname>JCheckBox</classname> is a component that has two states: selected or
unselected. The user can change the state of a check box by clicking on it. The
state of a checkbox is represented by a <ptype>boolean</ptype> value that is
<code>true</code> if the box is selected and is <code>false</code> if the box is
unselected. A checkbox has a label, which is specified when the box is
constructed:</p>

<pre>JCheckBox showTime = new JCheckBox("Show Current Time");</pre>

<p>Usually, it's the user who sets the state of a <classname>JCheckBox</classname>, but you
can also set the state programmatically. The current state of a checkbox is set
using its <code>setSelected(boolean)</code> method. For example, if you want the
checkbox <code>showTime</code> to be checked, you would say
"<code>showTime.setSelected(true)"</code>. To uncheck the box, say
"<code>showTime.setSelected(false)"</code>. You can determine the current state of
a checkbox by calling its <code>isSelected()</code> method, which returns a boolean
value.</p>

<p>In many cases, you don't need to worry about events from checkboxes. Your
program can just check the state whenever it needs to know it by calling the
<code>isSelected()</code> method. However, a checkbox does generate an event when
its state is changed by the user, and you can detect this event and respond to it if you want
something to happen at the moment the state changes. When the state of a
checkbox is changed by the user, it generates an event of type
<classname>ActionEvent</classname>. If you want something to happen when the user changes the
state, you must register an <classname>ActionListener</classname> with the
checkbox by calling its <code>addActionListener()</code> method. (Note that if you change the state by calling the
<code>setSelected()</code> method, no <classname>ActionEvent</classname> is generated. However,
there is another method in the <classname>JCheckBox</classname> class, <code>doClick()</code>,
which simulates a user click on the checkbox and does generate an
<classname>ActionEvent</classname>.)</p>

<p>When handling an <classname>ActionEvent</classname>, you can call <code>evt.getSource()</code>
in the <code>actionPerformed()</code> method to find out which object generated the
event. (Of course, if you are only listening for events from one component, you
don't have to do this.) The returned value is of type <code>Object</code>, but
you can type-cast it to another type if you want. Once you know the object that
generated the event, you can ask the object to tell you its current state. For
example, if you know that the event had to come from one of two checkboxes,
<code>cb1</code> or <code>cb2</code>, then your <code>actionPerformed()</code> method might
look like this:</p>

<pre>
          public void actionPerformed(ActionEvent evt) {
             Object source = evt.getSource();
             if (source == cb1) {
                boolean newState = cb1.isSelected();
                ... // respond to the change of state
             }
             else if (source == cb2) {
                boolean newState = cb2.isSelected();
                ... // respond to the change of state
             }
          }
</pre>

<p>Alternatively, you can use <code>evt.getActionCommand()</code> to retrieve the
action command associated with the source. For a <classname>JCheckBox</classname>, the action
command is, by default, the label of the checkbox.</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="GUI1.6.4" title="JTextField and JTextArea">
   
<p>The <classname>JTextField</classname> and <classname>JTextArea</classname> classes 
represent components that contain text that can be edited by the user.  
A <classname>JTextField</classname> holds a single line of text, while a
<classname>JTextArea</classname> can hold multiple lines.   It is also possible to set a
<classname>JTextField</classname> or <classname>JTextArea</classname> 
to be read-only so that the user can read the text that it contains but
cannot edit the text. Both classes are subclasses of an abstract class, 
<classname>JTextComponent</classname>, which defines their common properties.</p>
   
<p><classname>JTextField</classname> and <classname>JTextArea</classname> have many
methods in common.  The instance method <code>setText()</code>, which takes a parameter
of type <classname>String</classname>, can be used to change the text that is
displayed in an input component.  The contents of the component can be retrieved by calling its
<code>getText()</code> instance method, which returns a value of type <classname>String</classname>.
If you want to stop the user from modifying the text, you can
call <code>setEditable(false)</code>.  Call the same method with a parameter
of <code>true</code> to make the input component user-editable again.</p>
   
<p>The user can only type into a text component when it has
the input focus.  The user can give the input focus to a text component by clicking
it with the mouse, but sometimes it is useful to give the input focus to a
text field programmatically.  You can do this by calling its
<code>requestFocusInWindow()</code> method.  For example, when I discover an error
in the user's input, I usually call <code>requestFocusInWindow()</code> on the text
field that contains the error.  This helps the user see where the error occurred
and lets the user start typing the correction immediately.</p>
   
<p>By default, there is no space between the text in a text component and the
edge of the component, which usually doesn't look very good.  You can use
the <code>setMargin()</code> method of the component to add some
blank space between the edge of the component and the text.
This method takes a parameter
of type <code>java.awt.Insets</code> which contains four integer instance variables
that specify the margins on the top, left, bottom, and right edge of the component.
For example,</p>
   
<pre>textComponent.setMargin( new Insets(5,5,5,5) );</pre>
   
<np>adds a five-pixel margin between the text in <code>textComponent</code> and each edge of
the component.</np>
      
<break/>

<p>The <classname>JTextField</classname> class has a constructor</p>

<pre>public JTextField(int columns)</pre>

<np>where <code>columns</code> is an integer that specifies the number of characters that should be
visible in the text field. This is used to determine the preferred width of the
text field. (Because characters can be of different sizes and because the preferred
width is not always respected, the actual number of
characters visible in the text field might not be equal to
<code>columns</code>.) You don't have to specify the number of columns; for
example, you might use the text field in a context where it will expand to fill whatever
space is available. In that case, you can use the default constructor
<code>JTextField()</code>, with no parameters. You can also use the following
constructors, which specify the initial contents of the text field:</np>

<pre>public JTextField(String contents);
public JTextField(String contents, int columns);</pre>
   
<np>The constructors for a <classname>JTextArea</classname> are</np>

<pre>public JTextArea()
public JTextArea(int rows, int columns)
public JTextArea(String contents)
public JTextArea(String contents, int rows, int columns)</pre>
   
<np>The parameter <code>rows</code> specifies how many lines of text should be
visible in the text area. This determines the preferred height of the text
area, just as <code>columns</code> determines the preferred width.  However,
the text area can actually contain any number of lines; the text area
can be scrolled to reveal lines that are not currently visible.  It is common
to use a <classname>JTextArea</classname> as the <code>CENTER</code>
component of a BorderLayout. In that
case, it is less useful to specify the number of lines and columns, since the
TextArea will expand to fill all the space available in the center area of the
container.</np>

<p>The <classname>JTextArea</classname> class adds a few useful methods to those inherited
from <classname>JTextComponent</classname>.  For example, the instance method <code>append(moreText)</code>,
where <code>moreText</code> is of type <classname>String</classname>, adds the 
specified text at the end of the current content of the text area.  (When using <code>append()</code>
or <code>setText()</code> to add text to a <classname>JTextArea</classname>, line breaks
can be inserted in the text by using the newline character,&nbsp;<code>'\n'</code>.)  And
<code>setLineWrap(wrap)</code>, where <code>wrap</code> is of type <ptype>boolean</ptype>,
tells what should happen when a line of text is too long to be displayed in the
text area.  If <code>wrap</code> is true, then any line that is too long will be
"wrapped" onto the next line; if <code>wrap</code> is false, the line will simply
extend outside the text area, and the user will have to scroll the text area
horizontally to see the entire line.  The default value of <code>wrap</code> is
false.</p>
   

<p>Since it might be necessary to scroll a text area to see all the text that it
contains, you might expect a text area to come with scroll bars.  Unfortunately,
this does not happen automatically.  To get scroll bars for a text area, you
have to put the <classname>JTextArea</classname> inside another component,
called a <classname>JScrollPane</classname>.  This can be done as follows:</p>

<pre>JTextArea inputArea = new JTextArea();
JScrollPane scroller = new JScrollPane( inputArea );</pre>

<np>The scroll pane provides scroll bars that can be used to scroll the text
in the text area.  The scroll bars will appear only when needed, that is 
when the size of the text exceeds the size of the text area.  Note that when
you want to put the text area into a container, you should add the scroll pane,
not the text area itself, to the container. See the program
<sourceref href="TextAreaDemo.java"/> for a very short example of using a text area
in a scroll pane.</np>
   
<break/>
   
<p>When the user is typing in a <classname>JTextField</classname> and presses
return, an <classname>ActionEvent</classname> is generated.  If you want to respond
to such events, you can register an <classname>ActionListener</classname> with
the text field, using the text field's <code>addActionListener()</code> method.
(Since a <classname>JTextArea</classname> can contain multiple lines of text,
pressing return in a text area does not 
generate an event; it simply begins a new line of text.)</p>

<p><classname>JTextField</classname> has a subclass, <classname>JPasswordField</classname>, which is
identical except that it does not reveal the text that it contains. The
characters in a <classname>JPasswordField</classname> are all displayed as asterisks (or some
other fixed character). A password field is, obviously, designed to let the
user enter a password without showing that password on the screen.</p>
   
<p>Text components are actually quite complex, and I have covered only their
most basic properties here.  I will return to the topic of text components
in <localref href="GUI2"/>.</p>
   
</subsection>
   

   
<subsection id="GUI1.6.6" title="JSlider">
<p>A <classname>JSlider</classname> provides a way for the user to select an integer value
from a range of possible values. The user does this by dragging a "knob" along
a bar. A slider can, optionally, be decorated with tick marks and with labels.
This picture, from the sample program <sourceref href="SliderDemo.java"/>, shows 
three sliders with different decorations and with different ranges of values:</p>

<img src="slider-demo.png" width="348" height="175" alt="three sliders with and without labels and tick marks"
       tex="slider-demo.eps" texscale="0.6"/>


<np>Here, the second slider is decorated with tick marks, and the third one
is decorated with labels. It's possible for a single slider to have both types
of decorations.</np>

<p>The most commonly used constructor for <classname>JSliders</classname> specifies the start
and end of the range of values for the slider and its initial value when it
first appears on the screen:</p>

<pre>public JSlider(int minimum, int maximum, int value)</pre>

<np>If the parameters are omitted, the values 0, 100, and 50 are used. By
default, a slider is horizontal, but you can make it vertical by calling its
method <code>setOrientation(JSlider.VERTICAL)</code>. The current value of a
<classname>JSlider</classname> can be read at any time with its <code>getValue()</code> method,
which returns a value of type <ptype>int</ptype>. If you want to change the
value, you can do so with the method <code>setValue(n)</code>, which takes a
parameter of type <ptype>int</ptype>.</np>

<p>If you want to respond immediately when the user changes the value of a
slider, you can register a listener with the slider. <code>JSliders</code>, unlike
other components we have seen, do not generate <code>ActionEvents</code>. Instead,
they generate events of type <classname>ChangeEvent</classname>. 
<classname>ChangeEvent</classname> and
related classes are defined in the package <code>javax.swing.event</code> rather
than <code>java.awt.event</code>, so if you want to use <code>ChangeEvents</code>, you
should <code>import javax.swing.event.*</code> at the beginning of your program.
You must also define some object to implement the <classname>ChangeListener</classname>
interface, and you must register the change listener with the slider by calling
its <code>addChangeListener()</code> method. A <classname>ChangeListener</classname> must provide
a definition for the method:</p>

<pre>public void stateChanged(ChangeEvent evt)</pre>

<np>This method will be called whenever the value of the slider changes. Note
that it will be called when you change the value with the <code>setValue()</code>
method, as well as when the user changes the value. In the
<code>stateChanged()</code> method, you can call <code>evt.getSource()</code> to find
out which object generated the event. If you want to know whether the user
generated the change event, call the slider's <code>getValueIsAdjusting()</code>
method, which returns true if the user is dragging the knob on the slider.</np>

<p>Using tick marks on a slider is a two-step process: Specify the interval
between the tick marks, and tell the slider that the tick marks should be
displayed. There are actually two types of tick marks, "major" tick marks and
"minor" tick marks. You can have one or the other or both. Major tick marks are
a bit longer than minor tick marks. The method <code>setMinorTickSpacing(i)</code>
indicates that there should be a minor tick mark every <code>i</code> units along
the slider. The parameter is an integer. (The spacing is in terms of values on
the slider, not pixels.) For the major tick marks, there is a similar command,
<code>setMajorTickSpacing(i)</code>. Calling these methods is not enough to make
the tick marks appear. You also have to call <code>setPaintTicks(true)</code>. For
example, the second slider in the above illustration was created and configured using
the commands:</p>

<pre>slider2 = new JSlider();  // (Uses default min, max, and value.)
slider2.addChangeListener(this);
slider2.setMajorTickSpacing(25);
slider2.setMinorTickSpacing(5);
slider2.setPaintTicks(true);</pre>

<p>Labels on a slider are handled similarly. You have to specify the labels and
tell the slider to paint them. Specifying labels is a tricky business, but the
<classname>JSlider</classname> class has a method to simplify it. You can create a set of labels and
add them to a slider named <code>sldr</code> with the command:</p>

<pre>sldr.setLabelTable( sldr.createStandardLabels(i) );</pre>

<np>where <code>i</code> is an integer giving the spacing between the labels. To
arrange for the labels to be displayed, call <code>setPaintLabels(true)</code>. For
example, the third slider in the above illustration was created and configured with
the commands:</np>

<pre>slider3 = new JSlider(2000,2100,2014);
slider3.addChangeListener(this);
slider3.setLabelTable( slider3.createStandardLabels(50) );
slider3.setPaintLabels(true);</pre>
   
</subsection>
   
   
</section>