<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="GUI1.8" title="Menus and Dialogs">

<p><start><big>W</big>e have already encountered</start> many of the basic
aspects of GUI programming, but professional programs use many
additional features.  We will cover some of the advanced features
of Java GUI programming in <localref href="GUI2"/>, but in this
section we look briefly at a few more features that are
essential for writing GUI programs.  I will discuss these features
in the context of a
"MosaicDraw" program that is shown in this picture:</p>
   
<img src="mosaic-draw.png" width="300" height="321" alt="a face drawn with MosaicDraw"
      tex="mosaic-draw.eps" texscale="0.6"/>
   
<np>The source code for the program is in the file <sourceref href="MosaicDraw.java"/>.
The program also requires <sourceref href="MosaicPanel.java"/> and 
<sourceref href="MosaicDrawController.java"/>.  You will want to try it out!</np>

<p>As the user clicks-and-drags the
mouse in the large drawing area of this program, it leaves a trail of little colored
squares. There is some random variation in the color of the squares.  (This is meant
to make the picture look a little more like a real mosaic, which is a picture made out of 
small colored stones in which there would be some natural color variation.)
There is a menu bar above the drawing area.  The "Control" menu contains
commands for filling and clearing the drawing area, along with a few options that affect
the appearance of the picture.  The "Color" menu lets the user select the color that will
be used when the user draws.  The "Tools" menu affects the behavior of the mouse.
Using the default "Draw" tool, the mouse leaves a trail of single squares.  Using the
"Draw&nbsp;3x3" tool, the mouse leaves a swath of colored squares that is three squares wide.
There are also "Erase" tools, which let the user set squares back to their default
black color.</p>
   
<p>The drawing area of the program is a panel that belongs to the <classname>MosaicPanel</classname>
class, a subclass of <classname>JPanel</classname> that is defined in <sourceref href="MosaicPanel.java"/>.
<classname>MosaicPanel</classname> is a highly reusable class for representing mosaics of colored
rectangles.  It was also used behind the scenes in the sample program in <localref href="subroutines.6.3"/>.
The <classname>MosaicPanel</classname> class
does not directly support drawing on the mosaic, but it does support setting
the color of each individual square.  The MosaicDraw program installs a mouse listener on
the panel; the mouse listener responds to mousePressed and mouseDragged events on the
panel by setting the color of the square that contains the mouse.  This is a nice example of
applying a listener to an object to do something that was not programmed into the object
itself.</p>

<p>The file  <sourceref href="MosaicDraw.java"/> is a simple class that contains only the <code>main()</code>
routine for the program.
Most of the programming for MosaicDraw can be found in <sourceref href="MosaicDrawController.java"/>.
(It might have gone into the <classname>MosaicPanel</classname> class, if I had not decided to
use that pre-existing class in unmodified form.)  It is the <classname>MosaicDrawController</classname>
class that creates a <classname>MosaicPanel</classname> object and adds a mouse listener to
it.  It also creates the menu bar that is shown at the top of the program, and it implements all
the commands in the menu bar.  It has an instance method <code>getMosaicPanel()</code> that
returns a reference to the mosaic panel that it has created, and it has another instance
method <code>getMenuBar()</code> that returns a menu bar for the program.  These methods are
used to obtain the panel and menu bar so that they can be added to the program's window.</p>
   
<p>I urge you to study MosaicDrawController.java and MosaicDraw.java.  I will not be discussing all aspects
of the code here, but you should be able to understand it all after reading this section. As for
MosaicPanel.java, it uses some techniques that you would not understand at this
point, but I encourage you to at least read the comments in this file to learn about the API
for mosaic panels.</p>
   
<subsection title="Menus and Menubars" id="GUI1.8.1">
   
<p>MosaicDraw is the first example that we have seen that uses a menu bar.  Fortunately,
menus are very easy to use in Java.  The items in a menu are represented by the
class <classname>JMenuItem</classname> (this class and other menu-related classes are
in package <code>javax.swing</code>).  Menu items are used in almost exactly the
same way as buttons.  In fact, <classname>JMenuItem</classname> and <classname>JButton</classname>
are both subclasses of a class, <classname>AbstractButton</classname>, that defines their
common behavior. In particular, a <classname>JMenuItem</classname> is created using
a constructor that specifies the text of the menu item, such as:</p>
   
<pre>JMenuItem fillCommand = new JMenuItem("Fill");</pre>
   
<np>You can add an <classname>ActionListener</classname> to a <classname>JMenuItem</classname>
by calling the menu item's <code>addActionListener()</code> method.  
The <code>actionPerformed()</code> method of the
action listener is called when the user selects the item from the menu.  
You can change the text of the item by calling its <code>setText(String)</code> method,
and you can enable it and disable it using the <code>setEnabled(boolean)</code> method.
All this works in exactly the same way as for a <classname>JButton</classname>.</np>
   
<p>The main difference between a menu item and a button, of course, is that a menu
item is meant to appear in a menu rather than in a panel.  A menu in Java is
represented by the class <classname>JMenu</classname>.  A <classname>JMenu</classname> has a name,
which is specified in the constructor, and it has an <code>add(JMenuItem)</code> method that
can be used to add a <classname>JMenuItem</classname> to the menu. For example, the "Tools"
menu in the MosaicDraw program could be created as follows, where <code>listener</code>
is a variable of type <code>ActionListener</code>:</p>

<pre>JMenu toolsMenu = new JMenu("Tools");  // Create a menu with name "Tools"

JMenuItem drawCommand = new JMenuItem("Draw");   // Create a menu item.
drawCommand.addActionListener(listener);         // Add listener to menu item.
toolsMenu.add(drawCommand);                      // Add menu item to menu.

JMenuItem eraseCommand = new JMenuItem("Erase"); // Create a menu item.
eraseCommand.addActionListener(listener);        // Add listener to menu item.
toolsMenu.add(eraseCommand);                     // Add menu item to menu.
   .
   .  // Create and add other menu items.
   .</pre>
   
<np>Once a menu has been created, it must be added to a menu bar.  A menu bar is represented
by the class <classname>JMenuBar</classname>.  A menu bar is just a container for menus.
It does not have a name, and its constructor does not have any parameters. It has an
<code>add(JMenu)</code> method that can be used to add menus to the menu bar.  The name of
the menu then appears in the menu bar.  For example,
the MosaicDraw program uses three menus, <code>controlMenu</code>, <code>colorMenu</code>,
and <code>toolsMenu</code>.  We could create a menu bar and add the menus to it with
the statements:</np>
   
<pre>JMenuBar menuBar = new JMenuBar();
menuBar.add(controlMenu);
menuBar.add(colorMenu);
menuBar.add(toolsMenu);</pre>

<p>The final step in using menus is to use the menu bar in a window such as a <classname>JFrame</classname>.  
We have already seen that a frame has a
"content pane."  The menu bar is another component of the frame, 
not contained inside the content pane.  The <classname>JFrame</classname> class has
an instance method <code>setMenuBar(JMenuBar)</code> that can be used to set the menu bar.
(There can only be one, so this is a "set" method rather than an "add" method.)
In the MosaicDraw program, the menu bar is created by a <classname>MosaicDrawController</classname>
object and can be obtained by calling that object's <code>getMenuBar()</code> method.
The <code>main()</code> routine in MosaicDraw.java gets the menu bar from the controller and
adds it to the window.
Here is the basic code that is used (in somewhat modified form) to set up the interface:</p>

<pre>MosaicDrawController controller = new MosaicDrawController();

MosaicPanel content = controller.getMosaicPanel();
window.setContentPane( content );  // Use panel from controller as content pane.
   
JMenuBar menuBar = controller.getMenuBar();
window.setJMenuBar( menuBar );    // Use the menu bar from the controller.</pre>
     
<p>Using menus always follows the same general pattern:  Create a menu bar.  Create menus
and add them to the menu bar.  Create menu items and add them to the menus (and set up
listening to handle action events from the menu items).  Use the menu bar in a
window by calling the window's <code>setJMenuBar()</code> method.</p>
   
<break/>
   
<p>There are other kinds of menu items, defined by subclasses of <classname>JMenuItem</classname>,
that can be added to menus.  One of these is <classname>JCheckBoxMenuItem</classname>,
which represents menu items that can be in one of two states, selected or not selected.
A <classname>JCheckBoxMenuItem</classname> has the same functionality and is used in
the same way as a <classname>JCheckBox</classname> (see <localref href="GUI1.6.3"/>).
Three <classname>JCheckBoxMenuItems</classname> are used in the "Control" menu
of the MosaicDraw program.  One is used to turn the random color variation of
the squares on and off.  Another turns a symmetry feature on and off; when symmetry is
turned on, the user's drawing is reflected horizontally and vertically to produce
a symmetric pattern.  And the third checkbox menu item shows and hides the
"grouting" in the mosaic; the grouting is the gray lines that are drawn around each
of the little squares in the mosaic.  The menu item that corresponds to the
"Use Randomness" option in the "Control" menu could be set up with the statements:</p>
       
<pre>JMenuItem useRandomnessToggle = new JCheckBoxMenuItem("Use Randomness");
useRandomnessToggle.addActionListener(listener);  // Set up a listener.
useRandomnessToggle.setSelected(true);  // Randomness is initially turned on.
controlMenu.add(useRandomnessToggle);   // Add the menu item to the menu.</pre>
   
<p>In my program, the "Use Randomness" <classname>JCheckBoxMenuItem</classname>
corresponds to a boolean-valued instance variable named <code>useRandomness</code>
in the <classname>MosaicDrawController</classname> class.
This variable is part of the state of the controller object.
Its value is tested whenever the user draws one
of the squares, to decide whether or not to add a random variation to the color of
the square.  When the user selects the "Use Randomness" command
from the menu, the state of the <classname>JCheckBoxMenuItem</classname> is reversed,
from selected to not-selected or from not-selected to selected.  The <classname>ActionListener</classname>
for the menu item checks whether the menu item is selected or not, and it changes the
value of <code>useRandomness</code> to match.  Note that selecting the menu command
does not have any immediate effect on the picture that is shown in the window.  It just
changes the state of the program so that future drawing operations on the part of
the user will have a different effect.  The "Use Symmetry" option in the "Control"
menu works in much the same way.  The "Show Grouting" option is a little different.
Selecting the "Show Grouting" option does have an immediate effect: The picture is
redrawn with or without the grouting, depending on the state of the menu item.</p>
   
<p>My program uses a single <classname>ActionListener</classname> to respond to
all of the menu items in all the menus.  This is not a particularly good design, but it
is easy to implement for a small program like this one.  The <code>actionPerformed()</code> method
of the listener object uses the statement</p>

<pre>String command = evt.getActionCommand();</pre>
   
<np>to get the action command of the source of the event; this will be the text of
the menu item.  The listener tests the value of <code>command</code> to determine
which menu item was selected by the user.  If the menu item is a
<classname>JCheckBoxMenuItem</classname>, the listener must check the state of
the menu item.  The menu item is the source of the event that is being processed.
The listener can get its hands on the menu item object by
calling <code>evt.getSource()</code>.  Since the return value of <code>getSource()</code>
is of type <classname>Object</classname>, the return value must be type-cast to
the correct type.  Here, for example, is the code that handles the "Use Randomness"
command:</np>
      
<pre>if (command.equals("Use Randomness")) {
        // Set the value of useRandomness depending on the menu item's state.
   JCheckBoxMenuItem toggle = (JCheckBoxMenuItem)evt.getSource();
   useRandomness = toggle.isSelected();
}</pre>

<np>(The <code>actionPerformed()</code> method uses a rather long <code>if..then..else</code>
statement to check all the possible action commands.  It might be more natural and efficient
use a <code>switch</code> statement with <code>command</code> as the selector and
all the possible action commands as cases.)</np>
   
<break/>

<p>In addition to menu items, a menu can contain lines that separate the menu items
into groups.  In the MosaicDraw program, the "Control" menu contains such a separator.
A <classname>JMenu</classname> has an instance method <code>addSeparator()</code>
that can be used to add a separator to the menu.  For example, the separator in the
"Control" menu was created with the statement:</p>
   
<pre>controlMenu.addSeparator();</pre>
   
<p>A menu can also contain a submenu.  The name of the submenu appears as an item
in the main menu.  When the user moves the mouse over the submenu name, the submenu
pops up.  (There is no example of this in the MosaicDraw program.)  It is very easy
to do this in Java:  You can add one <classname>JMenu</classname> to another
<classname>JMenu</classname> using a statement such as
<code>mainMenu.add(submenu)</code>, and it becomes a submenu.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection title="Dialogs" id="GUI1.8.2">
 
<p>One of the commands in the "Color" menu of the MosaicDraw program is
"Custom Color&dots;".  When the user selects this command, a new window
appears where the user can select a color.  This window is an example
of a <newword>dialog</newword> or <newword>dialog box</newword>.
A dialog is a type of window that is generally
used for short, single purpose interactions with the user. For example, a
dialog box can be used to display a message to the user, to ask the user a
question, to let the user select a file to be opened,
or to let the user select a color. In Swing, a dialog box is
represented by an object belonging to the class <classname>JDialog</classname>
or to a subclass.</p>

<p>The <classname>JDialog</classname> class is very similar to <classname>JFrame</classname>
and is used in much the same way.
Like a frame, a dialog box is a separate window. Unlike a frame, however, a
dialog is not completely independent. Every dialog is associated with a
frame (or another dialog), which is called its <newword>parent window</newword>. 
The dialog box is dependent on its parent. For
example, if the parent is closed, the dialog box will also be closed. It is
possible to create a dialog box without specifying a parent, but in that case
an invisible frame is created by the system to serve as the parent.</p>

<p>Dialog boxes can be either <newword>modal</newword> or
<newword>modeless</newword>. When a modal dialog is created, its
parent frame is blocked. That is, the user will not be able to interact with
the parent until the dialog box is closed. Modeless dialog boxes do not block
their parents in the same way, so they seem a lot more like independent
windows. In practice, modal dialog boxes are easier to use and are much more
common than modeless dialogs. All the examples we will look at are modal.</p>

<p>Aside from having a parent, a <classname>JDialog</classname> can be created and used in
the same way as a <classname>JFrame</classname>. However, I will not give any examples here of using
<classname>JDialog</classname> directly. Swing has many convenient methods for creating 
common types of dialog boxes. For example, the color choice dialog that appears
when the user selects the "Custom Color" command in the MosaicDraw program belongs
to the class <classname>JColorChooser</classname>, which is a subclass of
<classname>JDialog</classname>.  The <classname>JColorChooser</classname> class has
a static method that makes color choice dialogs very easy to use:</p>

<pre>Color JColorChooser.showDialog(Component parentComp, 
                                        String title, Color initialColor)</pre>

<np>When you call this method, a dialog box appears that allows the user to
select a color. The first parameter specifies the parent of the dialog; the parent
window of the dialog will be the window (if any) that contains <code>parentComp</code>;
this parameter can be <code>null</code> and it can itself be a frame or dialog object.
The second parameter is a string that appears in the title bar of the dialog box.
And the third parameter, <code>initialColor</code>, specifies the color that is
selected when the color choice dialog first appears.
The dialog has a sophisticated interface that allows the user to
select a color. When the user presses an "OK" button, the dialog box
closes and the selected color is returned as the value of the method. The user
can also click a "Cancel" button or close the dialog box in some other way; in
that case, <code>null</code> is returned as the value of the method. This is a modal
dialog, and <code>showDialog()</code> does not return until the user dismisses
the dialog box in some way.  By using this
predefined color chooser dialog, you can write one line of code that will let
the user select an arbitrary color.  Swing also has a <classname>JFileChooser</classname>
class that makes it almost as easy to show a dialog box that lets the user select
a file to be opened or saved.</np>

<break/>

<p>The <classname>JOptionPane</classname> class includes a variety of methods for
making simple dialog boxes that are variations on three basic types: a
"message" dialog, a "confirm" dialog, and an "input" dialog. (The variations
allow you to provide a title for the dialog box, to specify the icon that
appears in the dialog, and to add other components to the dialog box. I will
only cover the most basic forms here.)</p>


<p>A message dialog simply displays a message string to the user. The user
(hopefully) reads the message and dismisses the dialog by clicking the "OK"
button. A message dialog can be shown by calling the static method:</p>

<pre>void JOptionPane.showMessageDialog(Component parentComp, String message)</pre>

<np>The message can be more than one
line long. Lines in the message should be separated by newline characters, <code>\n</code>.
New lines will not be inserted automatically, even if the message is very
long.  For example, assuming that the special variable <code>this</code>
refers to a <classname>Component</classname>:</np>

<pre>JOptionPane.showMessageDialog( this, "This program is about to crash!\n"
                                      + "Sorry about that.");</pre>

<p>An input dialog displays a question or request and lets the user type in a
string as a response. You can show an input dialog by calling:</p>

<pre>String JOptionPane.showInputDialog(Component parentComp, String question)</pre>

<np>Again, <code>parentComp</code> can be <code>null</code>, and
the question can include newline
characters. The dialog box will contain an input box, an "OK" button, and a
"Cancel" button. If the user clicks "Cancel", or closes the dialog box in some
other way, then the return value of the method is <code>null</code>. If the user
clicks "OK", then the return value is the string that was entered by the user.
Note that the return value can be an empty string (which is not the same as a
<code>null</code> value), if the user clicks "OK" without typing anything in the
input box. If you want to use an input dialog to get a numerical value from the
user, you will have to convert the return value into a number (see <localref href="control.7.2"/>).
As an example,</np>

<pre>String name;
name = JOptionPanel.showInputDialog(null, "Hi!  What's your name?");
if (name == null)
   JOptionPane.showMessageDialog(null, "Well, I'll call you Grumpy.");
else
   JOptionPane.showMessageDialog(null, "Pleased to meet you, " + name);</pre>

<p>Finally, a confirm dialog presents a question and three response buttons:
"Yes", "No", and "Cancel". A confirm dialog can be shown by calling:</p>

<pre>int JOptionPane.showConfirmDialog(Component parentComp, String question)</pre>

<np>The return value tells you the user's response. It is one of the following
constants:</np>

<ul>
<li><code>JOptionPane.YES_OPTION</code> &mdash; the user clicked the "Yes" button</li>
<li><code>JOptionPane.NO_OPTION</code> &mdash; the user clicked the "No" button</li>
<li><code>JOptionPane.CANCEL_OPTION</code> &mdash; the user clicked the "Cancel" button</li>
<li><code>JOptionPane.CLOSE_OPTION</code> &mdash; the dialog was closed in some other way.</li>
</ul>

<p>By the way, it is possible to omit the Cancel button from a confirm dialog
by calling one of the other methods in the <code>JOptionPane</code> class. Just
call:</p>

<pre>JOptionPane.showConfirmDialog(
                parent, question, title, JOptionPane.YES_NO_OPTION )</pre>

<np>The final parameter is a constant which specifies that only a "Yes" button
and a "No" button should be used. The third parameter is a string that will be
displayed as the title of the dialog box window.</np>


<p>A small demo program,
<sourceref href="SimpleDialogDemo.java"/> is available to demonstrate
JColorChooser and several JOptionPane dialogs.
</p>
 
</subsection>
   
<subsection title="Fine Points of Frames" id="GUI1.8.3">
   
<p>In previous sections, whenever I used a frame, I created a <classname>JFrame</classname>
object in a <code>main()</code> routine and installed a panel as the content pane of
that frame.  This works fine, but a more object-oriented approach is to define a subclass
of <classname>JFrame</classname> and to set up the contents of the frame in the constructor
of that class.  This is what I did in the case of the
MosaicDraw program.  <classname>MosaicDraw</classname> is defined as a subclass of
<classname>JFrame</classname>.  The definition of this class is very short, but it illustrates
several new features of frames that I want to discuss:</p>
   
<pre>public class MosaicDraw extends JFrame {
   
   public static void main(String[] args) {
      JFrame window = new MosaicDraw();
      window.setDefaultCloseOperation(JFrame.EXIT_ON_CLOSE);
      window.setVisible(true);
   }
   
   public MosaicDraw() {
      super("Mosaic Draw");
      MosaicDrawController controller = new MosaicDrawController();
      setContentPane( controller.getMosaicPanel() );
      setJMenuBar( controller.getMenuBar() );
      pack();
      Dimension screensize = Toolkit.getDefaultToolkit().getScreenSize();
      setLocation( (screensize.width - getWidth())/2, 
                                 (screensize.height - getHeight())/2 );
   }
   
}</pre>
   
<p>The constructor in this class begins with the statement <code>super("Mosaic Draw")</code>,
which calls the constructor in the superclass, <classname>JFrame</classname>.  The parameter
specifies a title that will appear in the title bar of the window.  The next three lines
of the constructor set up the contents of the window; a <classname>MosaicDrawController</classname>
is created, and the content pane and menu bar of the window are obtained from the
controller.  The next line is something new.  If <code>window</code> is a variable of
type <classname>JFrame</classname> (or <classname>JDialog</classname>), then the
statement <code>window.pack()</code> will resize the window so that its size matches
the preferred size of its contents.  (In this case, of course, "<code>pack()</code>"
is equivalent to "<code>this.pack()</code>"; that is, it refers to the window that is
being created by the constructor.)  The <code>pack()</code> method is usually the best
way to set the size of a window.  Note that it will only work correctly if every
component in the window has a correct preferred size.  This is only a problem in
two cases:  when a panel is used as a drawing surface and when a panel is used as
a container with a <code>null</code> layout manager.  In both these cases there is no
way for the system to determine the correct preferred size automatically, and you should
set a preferred size by hand.  For example:</p>
   
<pre>panel.setPreferredSize( new Dimension(400, 250) );</pre>
   
<p>The last two lines in the constructor position the window so that it is exactly
centered on the screen. The line</p>
   
<pre>Dimension screensize = Toolkit.getDefaultToolkit().getScreenSize();</pre>
   
<np>determines the size of the screen.  The size of the screen is <code>screensize.width</code>
pixels in the horizontal direction and <code>screensize.height</code> pixels in the vertical
direction. The <code>setLocation()</code> method of the frame sets the position of the
upper left corner of the frame on the screen.  The expression "<code>screensize.width&nbsp;-&nbsp;getWidth()</code>"
is the amount of horizontal space left on the screen after subtracting the width of the window.
This is divided by 2 so that half of the empty space will be to the left of the window, leaving
the other half of the space to the right of the window.
Similarly, half of the extra vertical space is above the window, and half is below.</np>

<p>Note that the constructor has created the window and set its size and position, but that
at the end of the constructor, the window is not yet visible on the screen.  (More exactly,
the constructor has created the window <i>object</i>, but the visual representation of
that object on the screen has not yet been created.)  To show the window on the screen,
it will be necessary to call its instance method, <code>window.setVisible(true)</code>.</p>
   
<p>In addition to the constructor, the <classname>MosaicDraw</classname> class includes
a <code>main()</code> routine.  This makes it possible to run <classname>MosaicDraw</classname>
as a stand-alone application.  (The <code>main()</code> routine, as a <code>static</code> method,
has nothing to do with the function of a <classname>MosaicDraw</classname> object, and it
could (and perhaps should) be in a separate class.)  The <code>main()</code> routine
creates a <classname>MosaicDraw</classname> and makes it visible on the screen.  It
also calls</p>
   
<pre>window.setDefaultCloseOperation(JFrame.EXIT_ON_CLOSE);</pre>
   
<np>which means that the program will end when the user closes the window.  Note that this
is not done in the constructor because doing it there would make <classname>MosaicDraw</classname>
less flexible.  It is possible, for example, to write a program that lets the user
open multiple MosaicDraw windows.  In that case, we don't want to shut down the whole program just
because the user has closed <i>one</i> of the windows. 
There are other possible values for the default close operation of a window:</np>
   
<ul>
<li><code>JFrame.DO_NOTHING_ON_CLOSE</code> &mdash; the user's attempts to close the window by
clicking its close box will be ignored, except that it will generate a <classname>WindowEvent</classname>.
A program can listen for this event and take any action it wants when the user attempts to close
the window.</li>
<li><code>JFrame.HIDE_ON_CLOSE</code> &mdash;  when the user clicks its close box,
the window will be hidden just as if <code>window.setVisible(false)</code> were called.
The window can be made visible again by calling <code>window.setVisible(true)</code>.
This is the value that is used if you do not
specify another value by calling <code>setDefaultCloseOperation</code>.</li>
<li><code>JFrame.DISPOSE_ON_CLOSE</code> &mdash; the window is closed and any operating
system resources used by the window are released.  It is not possible to make the
window visible again.  (This is the proper way to permanently get rid of a window without
ending the program.
You can accomplish the same thing programmatically by calling the instance method
<code>window.dispose()</code>.)</li>
</ul>


</subsection>
   
<subsection title="Creating Jar Files" id="GUI1.8.4">
   
<p>As the final topic for this chapter, we look again at jar files.  Recall
that a jar file is a "java archive" that can contain a number of class files. When creating
a program that uses more than one class, it's usually a good idea to place all the classes that
are required by the program into a jar file.  If that is done, then a user will only need that
one file to run the program. In fact, it is possible to make a so-called <newword>executable
jar file</newword>.  A user can run an executable jar file in much the same way
as any other application, usually by double-clicking the icon of the jar file.
(The user's computer must have a correct version of Java installed, and the computer
must be configured correctly for this to work.  The configuration is usually done automatically when
Java is installed, at least on Windows and Mac OS.)</p>
   
<p>The question, then, is how to create a jar file.  The answer depends on what
programming environment you are using.  The two basic types of programming environment&mdash;command line
and IDE&mdash;were discussed in <localref href="basics.6"/>.  Any IDE (Integrated Programming Environment)
for Java should have a command for creating jar files.  In the Eclipse IDE, for example,
it can be done as follows:  In the Package Explorer pane, select the programming project (or just
all the individual source code files that you need).  Right-click on the selection, and
choose "Export" from the menu that pops up.  In the window that appears, select "JAR file"
and click "Next".  In the window that appears next, enter a name for the jar file in
the box labeled "JAR file".  (Click the "Browse" button next to this box to select the
file name using a file dialog box.)  The name of the file should end with ".jar".
If you are creating a regular jar file, not an executable
one, you can hit "Finish" at this point, and the jar file will be created.  To create an
executable file, hit the "Next" button <i>twice</i> to get to the "Jar Manifest
Specification" screen.  At the bottom of this screen is an input box labeled "Main class".
You have to enter the name of the class that contains the <code>main()</code> routine
that will be run when the jar file is executed.  If you hit the "Browse" button next to
the "Main class" box, you can select the class from a list of classes that contain
<code>main()</code> routines.  Once you've selected the main class, you can
click the "Finish" button to create the executable jar file.  (Note that newer versions of Eclipse
also have an option for exporting an executable Jar file in fewer steps.)</p>

<p>It is also possible to create jar files on the command line.  The Java Development Kit
includes a command-line program named <code>jar</code> that can be used to create jar files.
If all your classes are in the default package (like most of the examples in this book), then
the <code>jar</code> command is easy to use.  To create a non-executable jar file on the command line,
change to the directory that contains the class files that you want to include in the jar.
Then give the command</p>
   
<pre>jar  cf  JarFileName.jar  *.class</pre>
   
<np>where <code>JarFileName</code> can be any name that you want to use for the jar file.
The "<code>*</code>" in "<code>*.class</code>" is a wildcard that makes <code>*.class</code> match every class
file in the current directory.  This means that all the class files in the directory will be
included in the jar file.  If you want to include only certain class files, you
can name them individually, separated by spaces.  (Things get more complicated if your classes are not in the
default package.  In that case, the class files must be in subdirectories of the
directory in which you issue the <code>jar</code> command.  See <localref href="basics.6.6"/>.)</np>
   
<p>Making an executable jar file on the command line is  more complicated.
There has to be some way of specifying which class contains the <code>main()</code>
routine.  This is done by creating a <newword>manifest file</newword>.  The manifest
file can be a plain text file containing a single line of the form</p>

<pre>Main-Class: ClassName</pre>

<np>where <code>ClassName</code> should be replaced by the name of the class that contains
the <code>main()</code> routine.  For example, if the <code>main()</code> routine is in
the class <classname>MosaicDraw</classname>, then the manifest file should read
"<code>Main-Class: MosaicDraw</code>".  You can give the manifest file any name
you like.  Put it in the same directory where you will issue the <code>jar</code> command,
and use a command of the form</np>
   
<pre>jar  cmf  ManifestFileName  JarFileName.jar  *.class</pre>
   
<np>to create the jar file.  (The <code>jar</code> command is capable of performing a
variety of different operations.  The first parameter to the command, such as "<code>cf</code>"
or "<code>cmf</code>", tells it which operation to perform.)</np>
   
<p>By the way, if you have successfully created an executable jar file, you can run
it on the command line using the command "<code>java&nbsp;-jar</code>".  For example:</p>
   
<pre>java  -jar  JarFileName.jar</pre>

</subsection>

<endchapter/>

</section>
