<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >
<section id="recursion.2" title="Linked Data Structures">
   
<p><start><big>E</big>very useful object</start> contains instance variables.
When the type of an instance variable is given by a class or interface name,
the variable can hold a reference to another object. Such a reference is also
called a pointer, and we say that the variable <newword>points to</newword> 
the object. (Of course, any variable that can contain a reference to
an object can also contain the special value <code>null</code>, which points to
nowhere.) When one object contains an instance variable that points to another
object, we think of the objects as being "linked" by the pointer. Data
structures of great complexity can be constructed by linking objects
together.</p>
   
<subsection id="recursion.2.1" title="Recursive Linking">

<p>Something interesting happens when an object contains an instance variable
that can refer to another object of the same type. In that case, the definition
of the object's class is recursive. Such recursion arises naturally in many
cases. For example, consider a class designed to represent employees at a
company. Suppose that every employee except the boss has a supervisor, who is
another employee of the company. Then the <classname>Employee</classname> class would
naturally contain an instance variable of type <classname>Employee</classname> that points to
the employee's supervisor:</p>

<pre>
/**
 * An object of type Employee holds data about one employee.
 */
public class Employee {
       
   String name;          // Name of the employee.
   
   Employee supervisor;  // The employee's supervisor.

      .
      .  // (Other instance variables and methods.)
      .
      
} // end class Employee</pre>

<p>If <code>emp</code> is a variable of type <classname>Employee</classname>, then
<code>emp.supervisor</code> is another variable of type <classname>Employee</classname>. If
<code>emp</code> refers to the boss, then the value of <code>emp.supervisor</code>
should be <code>null</code> to indicate the fact that the boss has no supervisor.
If we wanted to print out the name of the employee's supervisor, for example,
we could use the following Java statement:</p>

<pre>if ( emp.supervisor == null) {
   System.out.println( emp.name + " is the boss and has no supervisor!" );
}
else {
   System.out.print( "The supervisor of " + emp.name + " is " );
   System.out.println( emp.supervisor.name );
}</pre>

<p>Now, suppose that we want to know how many levels of supervisors there are
between a given employee and the boss. We just have to follow the chain of
command through a series of <code>supervisor</code> links, and count how many steps
it takes to get to the boss:</p>

<pre>if ( emp.supervisor == null ) {
   System.out.println( emp.name + " is the boss!" );
}
else {
   Employee runner;  // For "running" up the chain of command.
   runner = emp.supervisor;
   if ( runner.supervisor == null) {
      System.out.println( emp.name  + " reports directly to the boss." );
   }
   else {
      int count = 0;
      while ( runner.supervisor != null ) {
         count++;  // Count the supervisor on this level.
         runner = runner.supervisor; // Move up to the next level.
      }
      System.out.println( "There are " + count
                             + " supervisors between " + emp.name
                             + " and the boss." );
   }
}</pre>

<np>As the <code>while</code> loop is executed, <code>runner</code> points in turn to
the original employee (<code>emp</code>), then to <code>emp's</code> supervisor, then to
the supervisor of <code>emp's</code> supervisor, and so on. The <code>count</code>
variable is incremented each time <code>runner</code> "visits" a new employee. The
loop ends when <code>runner.supervisor</code> is <code>null</code>, which indicates
that <code>runner</code> has reached the boss. At that point, <code>count</code> has
counted the number of steps between <code>emp</code> and the boss.</np>

<p>In this example, the <code>supervisor</code> variable is quite natural and
useful. In fact, data structures that are built by linking objects together are
so useful that they are a major topic of study in computer science. We'll be
looking at a few typical examples. In this section and the
<localref href="recursion.3">next</localref>, we'll be looking at <newword>linked lists</newword>. 
A linked list consists of a chain of objects of the same type,
linked together by pointers from one object to the next. This is much like the
chain of supervisors between <code>emp</code> and the boss in the above example.
It's also possible to have more complex situations, in which one object can contain
links to several other objects. We'll look at an example of this in <localref href="recursion.4"/>.</p>

<img src="linked-data-structures.png" alt="Some linked data structures" 
   width="432" height="340" tex="linked-data-structures.eps" texscale="0.75"/>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="recursion.2.2" title="Linked Lists">

<p>For most of the examples in the rest of this section, linked lists will be constructed out of
objects belonging to the class <classname>Node</classname> which is defined as follows:</p>

<pre>class Node {
   String item;
   Node next;
}</pre>

<np>The term <newword>node</newword> is often used to refer to one of
the objects in a linked data structure. Objects of type <classname>Node</classname> can be
chained together as shown in the top part of the above illustration. Each node holds
a <classname>String</classname> and a pointer to the next node in the list (if any).
The last node in such a list can always be identified by the fact that the instance variable
<code>next</code> in the last node holds the value <code>null</code> instead of a
pointer to another node.  The purpose of the chain of nodes is to represent a list
of strings.  The first string in the list is stored in the first node, the second
string is stored in the second node, and so on.  The pointers and the node objects
are used to build the structure, but the data that we want to represent
is the list of strings.  Of course, we could just as easily represent a list of integers or
a list of <classname>Buttons</classname> or a list of any other type of data
by changing the type of the <code>item</code> that is stored in each node.</np>


<p>Although the <classname>Nodes</classname> in this example are very simple, we can use them
to illustrate the common operations on linked lists. Typical operations include
deleting nodes from the list, inserting new nodes into the list, and searching
for a specified <classname>String</classname> among the <code>items</code> in the list. We will
look at subroutines to perform all of these operations, among others.</p>

<p>For a linked list to be used in a program, that program needs a variable
that refers to the first node in the list. It only needs a pointer to the first
node since all the other nodes in the list can be accessed by starting at the
first node and following links along the list from one node to the next.
In my examples, I will always use a variable named <code>head</code>, of
type <classname>Node</classname>, that points to the first node in the linked list. When the
list is empty, the value of <code>head</code> is null.</p>

<img src="list-with-head.png" alt="A variable pointing to the first node of a list" 
   width="459" height="113" tex="list-with-head.eps" texscale="0.75" />
   
</subsection>
   
<subsection id="recursion.2.3" title = "Basic Linked List Processing">
   
<p>It is very common to want to process all the items in a linked list in some way.  The common
pattern is to start at the head of the list, then move from each node to the next
by following the pointer in the node, stopping when the <code>null</code> that marks
the end of the list is reached.  If <code>head</code> is a variable of
type <classname>Node</classname> that points to the first node in the list, then
the general form of the code for processing all the items in a linked list is:</p>   
   
<pre>Node runner;    // A pointer that will be used to traverse the list.
runner = head;  // Start with runner pointing to the head of the list.
while ( runner != null ) {     // Continue until null is encountered.
   process( runner.item );     // Do something with the item in the current node.
   runner = runner.next;       // Move on to the next node in the list.
}</pre>
   
<np>Our only access to the list is
through the variable <code>head</code>, so we start by getting a copy of the value
in <code>head</code> with the assignment statement <code>runner&nbsp;=&nbsp;head</code>.
We need a <b>copy</b> of <code>head</code> because we are going to change the value 
of <code>runner</code>.
We can't change the value of <code>head</code>, or we would lose our only access to
the list! The variable <code>runner</code> will point to each node of the list in
turn.   When <code>runner</code> points to one of the nodes in the list,
<code>runner.next</code> is a pointer to the next node in the list, so the assignment
statement <code>runner&nbsp;= runner.next</code> moves the pointer along the  list
from each node to the next.  We know that we've reached the end of the list when
<code>runner</code> becomes equal to <code>null</code>.
Note that our list-processing code works even for an empty list, since for an empty list the value
of <code>head</code> is <code>null</code> and the body of the while loop is not executed
at all.  As an example, we can print all the strings in a list of <classname>Strings</classname>
by saying:</np>
   
<pre>Node runner = head;
while ( runner != null ) {
   System.out.println( runner.item );
   runner = runner.next;
}</pre>
  
<np>The <code>while</code> loop can, by the way, be rewritten as a <code>for</code> loop.
Remember that even though the loop control variable in a <code>for</code> loop is often
numerical, that is not a requirement.  Here is a <code>for</code> loop that is equivalent
to the above <code>while</code> loop:</np>
   
<pre>for ( Node runner = head; runner != null; runner = runner.next ) {
   System.out.println( runner.item );
}</pre>

<p>Similarly, we can traverse a list of integers to add up all the numbers in the list.
A linked list of integers can be constructed using the class</p>
   
<pre>public class IntNode {
   int item;       // One of the integers in the list.
   IntNode next;   // Pointer to the next node in the list.
}</pre>
   
<np>If <code>head</code> is a variable of type <classname>IntNode</classname> that points 
to a linked list of integers, we can find the sum of the integers in the list using:</np>
      
<pre>int sum = 0;
IntNode runner = head;
while ( runner != null ) {
   sum = sum + runner.item;   // Add current item to the sum.
   runner = runner.next;
}
System.out.println("The sum of the list of items is " + sum);</pre>
   
<p>It is also possible to use recursion to process a linked list.  Recursion is
rarely the natural way to process a list, since it's so easy to use a loop to
traverse the list.  However, understanding how to apply recursion to lists can
help with understanding the recursive processing of more complex data structures.
A non-empty linked list can be thought of as consisting of two parts: the
<newword>head</newword> of the list, which is just the first node in the list,
and the <newword>tail</newword> of the list, which consists of the remainder
of the list after the head.  Note that the tail is itself a linked list
and that it is shorter than the original list (by one node).  This is a natural
setup for recursion, where the problem of processing a list can be divided into
processing the head and recursively processing the tail.  The base case occurs
in the case of an empty list (or sometimes in the case of a list of length one).
For example, here is a recursive algorithm for adding up the numbers in a linked list of
integers:</p>
   
<pre>if the list is empty then
   return 0 (since there are no numbers to be added up)
otherwise
   let listsum = the number in the head node 
   let tailsum be the sum of the numbers in the tail list (recursively)
   add tailsum to listsum
   return listsum</pre>

<np>One remaining question is, how do we get the tail of a non-empty linked list?  If
<code>head</code> is a variable that points to the head node of the list,
then <code>head.next</code> is a variable that points to the second node
of the list&mdash;and that node is in fact the first node of the tail.  So, we
can view <code>head.next</code> as a pointer to the tail of the list.
One special case is when the original list consists of a single node.
In that case, the tail of the list is empty, and <code>head.next</code> is
<code>null</code>.  Since an empty list is represented by a null pointer,
<code>head.next</code> represents the tail of the list even in this special
case.  This allows us to write a recursive list-summing function in Java
as</np>   
 
<pre>/**
 *  Compute the sum of all the integers in a linked list of integers.
 *  @param head a pointer to the first node in the linked list
 */
public static int addItemsInList( IntNode head ) {
   if ( head == null ) {
         // Base case:  The list is empty,  so the sum is zero.
      return 0;
   }
   else {
         // Recursive case:  The list is non-empty.  Find the sum of
         // the tail list, and add that to the item in the head node.
         // (Note that this case could be written simply as
         //     return head.item + addItemsInList( head.next );)
      int listsum = head.item;
      int tailsum = addItemsInList( head.next );
      listsum = listsum + tailsum;
      return listsum;
   }
}</pre>
 
<p>I will finish by presenting a list-processing problem that is easy to solve with recursion,
but quite tricky to solve without it.  The problem is to print out all the strings in a
linked list of strings in the <b>reverse</b> of the order in which they occur in the
list.  Note that when we do this, the item in the head of a list is printed out after
all the items in the tail of the list.  This leads to the following recursive routine.
You should convince yourself that it works, and you should think about trying to do the
same thing without using recursion:</p>
       
<pre>public static void printReversed( Node head ) {
   if ( head == null ) {
         // Base case:  The list is empty, and there is nothing to print.
      return;
   }
   else {
         // Recursive case:  The list is non-empty.
      printReversed( head.next );  // Print strings from tail, in reverse order.
      System.out.println( head.item );  // Then print string from head node.
   }
}</pre>

<break/>   
   
<p>In the rest of this section, we'll look at a few more advanced operations on
a linked list of strings.  The subroutines that we consider are instance methods
in a class that I wrote named <classname>StringList</classname>.  An object of type <classname>StringList</classname> 
represents a linked list of
strings. The class has a private instance
variable named <code>head</code> of type <classname>Node</classname> that points
to the first node in the list, or is null if the list is empty.  Instance
methods in class <classname>StringList</classname> access <code>head</code>
as a global variable.  The source code for <classname>StringList</classname> is in
the file <sourceref href="StringList.java"/>, and it is used in a
sample program named <sourceref href="ListDemo.java"/>, so you can 
take a look at the code in context if you want.</p>
   
<p>One of the methods in the <classname>StringList</classname> class searches the list,
looking for a specified string.  If the string that we are looking for is <code>searchItem</code>,
then we have to compare <code>searchItem</code> to each
<code>item</code> in the list.   This is an example of basic list traversal and
processing. However, in this case, we can stop processing if we find the
item that we are looking for.</p>
   
<pre>/**
 * Searches the list for a specified item. 
 * @param searchItem the item that is to be searched for
 * @return true if searchItem is one of the items in the list or false if
 *    searchItem does not occur in the list.
 */
public boolean find(String searchItem) {

   Node runner;    // A pointer for traversing the list.

   runner = head;  // Start by looking at the head of the list.
                   //   (head is an instance variable! )
   
   while ( runner != null ) {
         // Go through the list looking at the string in each
         // node.  If the string is the one we are looking for,
         // return true, since the string has been found in the list.
      if ( runner.item.equals(searchItem) )
         return true;
      runner = runner.next;  // Move on to the next node.
   }

   // At this point, we have looked at all the items in the list
   // without finding searchItem.  Return false to indicate that
   // the item does not exist in the list.

   return false;

} // end find()</pre>
   

<p>It is possible that the list is empty, that is, that the value of
<code>head</code> is <code>null</code>. We should be careful that this case is handled
properly. In the above code, if <code>head</code> is <code>null</code>, then the body
of the <code>while</code> loop is never executed at all, so no nodes are processed
and the return value is <code>false</code>.  This is exactly what we want when the 
list is empty, since the <code>searchItem</code> can't occur in an empty list.</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="recursion.2.5" title="Inserting into a Linked List">

<p>The problem of inserting a new item into a linked list is more difficult, at least
in the case where the item is inserted into the middle of the list.  (In
fact, it's probably the most difficult operation on linked data structures that
you'll encounter in this chapter.)  In the <classname>StringList</classname> class, the
<code>items</code> in the nodes of the linked list are kept in increasing order.
When a new item is inserted into the list, it must be inserted at the correct
position according to this ordering. This means that, usually, we will have to
insert the new item somewhere in the middle of the list, between two existing
nodes. To do this, it's convenient to have two variables of type <classname>Node</classname>,
which refer to the existing nodes that will lie on either side of the new node.
In the following illustration, these variables are <code>previous</code> and
<code>runner</code>. Another variable, <code>newNode</code>, refers to the new node. In
order to do the insertion, the link from <code>previous</code> to <code>runner</code>
must be "broken," and new links from <code>previous</code> to <code>newNode</code> and
from <code>newNode</code> to <code>runner</code> must be added:</p>

<img src="insert-in-list.png" alt="inserting a node" width="433" height="289" 
   tex="insert-in-list.eps" texscale="0.8" />

<p>Once we have <code>previous</code> and <code>runner</code> pointing to the right nodes,
the command "<code>previous.next&nbsp;= newNode;</code>" can be used to make
<code>previous.next</code> point to the new node. 
And the command "<code>newNode.next&nbsp;= runner</code>" will set
<code>newNode.next</code> to point to the correct place.   However, before we can use
these commands, we need to set up <code>runner</code> and <code>previous</code> as
shown in the illustration. The idea is to start at the first node of the list,
and then move along the list past all the items that are less than the new
item. While doing this, we have to be aware of the danger of "falling off the
end of the list." That is, we can't continue if <code>runner</code> reaches the end
of the list and becomes <code>null</code>. If <code>insertItem</code> is the item that
is to be inserted, and if we assume that it does, in fact, belong somewhere in
the middle of the list, then the following code would correctly position
<code>previous</code> and <code>runner</code>:</p>

<pre>Node runner, previous;
previous = head;     // Start at the beginning of the list.  
runner = head.next;
while ( runner != null &amp;&amp; runner.item.compareTo(insertItem) &lt; 0 ) {
   previous = runner;  // "previous = previous.next" would also work
   runner = runner.next;
}</pre>

<np>(This uses the <code>compareTo()</code> instance method from the <classname>String</classname>
class to test whether the item in the node is less than the item that is being
inserted. See <localref href="basics.3.3"/>.)</np>

<p>This is fine, except that the assumption that the new node is inserted into
the middle of the list is not always valid. It might be that
<code>insertItem</code> is less than the first item of the list. In that case, the
new node must be inserted at the head of the list. This can be done with the
instructions</p>

<pre>newNode.next = head;   // Make newNode.next point to the old head.
head = newNode;        // Make newNode the new head of the list.</pre>

<np>It is also possible that the list is empty. In that case, <code>newNode</code>
will become the first and only node in the list. This can be accomplished
simply by setting <code>head = newNode</code>. The following <code>insert()</code>
method from the <classname>StringList</classname> class covers all of these
possibilities:</np>

<pre>/**
 * Insert a specified item into the list, keeping the list in order.
 * @param insertItem the item that is to be inserted.
 */
public void insert(String insertItem) {

   Node newNode;          // A Node to contain the new item.
   newNode = new Node();
   newNode.item = insertItem;  // (N.B.  newNode.next is null.)

   if ( head == null ) {
          // The new item is the first (and only) one in the list.
          // Set head to point to it.
      head = newNode;
   }
   else if ( head.item.compareTo(insertItem) >= 0 ) {
          // The new item is less than the first item in the list,
          // so it has to be inserted at the head of the list.
      newNode.next = head;
      head = newNode;
   }
   else {
          // The new item belongs somewhere after the first item
          // in the list.  Search for its proper position and insert it.
      Node runner;     // A node for traversing the list.
      Node previous;   // Always points to the node preceding runner.
      runner = head.next;   // Start by looking at the SECOND position.
      previous = head;
      while ( runner != null &amp;&amp; runner.item.compareTo(insertItem) &lt; 0 ) {
             // Move previous and runner along the list until runner
             // falls off the end or hits a list element that is
             // greater than or equal to insertItem.  When this 
             // loop ends, previous indicates the position where
             // insertItem must be inserted.
         previous = runner;
         runner = runner.next;
      }
      newNode.next = runner;     // Insert newNode after previous.
      previous.next = newNode;
   }

}  // end insert()</pre>

<p>If you were paying close attention to the above discussion, you might have
noticed that there is one special case which is not mentioned. What happens if
the new node has to be inserted at the <b>end</b> of the list? This will happen if all
the items in the list are less than the new item. In fact, this case is already
handled correctly by the subroutine, in the last part of the <code>if</code>
statement. If <code>insertItem</code> is greater than all the items in the list, then
the <code>while</code> loop will end when <code>runner</code> has traversed the entire
list and become <code>null</code>. However, when that happens, <code>previous</code>
will be left pointing to the last node in the list. Setting <code>previous.next&nbsp;= newNode</code> 
adds <code>newNode</code> onto the end of the list. Since
<code>runner</code> is <code>null</code>, the command <code>newNode.next = runner</code>
sets <code>newNode.next</code> to <code>null</code>, which is exactly what is
needed to mark the end of the list.</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="recursion.2.6" title="Deleting from a Linked List">

<p>The delete operation is similar to insert, although a little simpler. There
are still special cases to consider. When the first node in the list is to be
deleted, then the value of <code>head</code> has to be changed to point to what was
previously the second node in the list. Since <code>head.next</code> refers to the
second node in the list, this can be done by setting <code>head&nbsp;=&nbsp;head.next</code>.
(Once again, you should check that this works when <code>head.next</code> is
<code>null</code>, that is, when there is no second node in the list. In that case,
the list becomes empty.)</p>

<p>If the node that is being deleted is in the middle of the list, then we can
set up <code>previous</code> and <code>runner</code> with <code>runner</code> pointing to
the node that is to be deleted and with <code>previous</code> pointing to the node
that precedes that node in the list. Once that is done, the command
"<code>previous.next&nbsp;= runner.next</code>;" will delete the node. The deleted node
will be garbage collected.  I encourage you to draw a picture for yourself to illustrate
this operation.  Here is the complete code for the <code>delete()</code> method:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Delete a specified item from the list, if that item is present.
 * If multiple copies of the item are present in the list, only
 * the one that comes first in the list is deleted.
 * @param deleteItem the item to be deleted
 * @return true if the item was found and deleted, or false if the item
 *    was not in the list.
 */
public boolean delete(String deleteItem) {

   if ( head == null ) {
          // The list is empty, so it certainly doesn't contain deleteString.
      return false;
   }
   else if ( head.item.equals(deleteItem) ) {
           // The string is the first item of the list.  Remove it.
      head = head.next;
      return true;
   }
   else {
          // The string, if it occurs at all, is somewhere beyond the 
          // first element of the list.  Search the list.
      Node runner;     // A node for traversing the list.
      Node previous;   // Always points to the node preceding runner.
      runner = head.next;   // Start by looking at the SECOND list node.
      previous = head;
      while ( runner != null &amp;&amp; runner.item.compareTo(deleteItem) &lt; 0 ) {
             // Move previous and runner along the list until runner
             // falls off the end or hits a list element that is
             // greater than or equal to deleteItem.  When this 
             // loop ends, runner indicates the position where
             // deleteItem must be, if it is in the list.
         previous = runner;
         runner = runner.next;
      }
      if ( runner != null &amp;&amp; runner.item.equals(deleteItem) ) {
             // Runner points to the node that is to be deleted.
             // Remove it by changing the pointer in the previous node.
         previous.next = runner.next;
         return true;
      }
      else {
             // The item does not exist in the list.
         return false;
      }
   }

} // end delete()</pre>

</subsection>
   
</section>
