<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >
<section id="recursion.4" title="Binary Trees">

<p><start><big>W</big>e have seen</start> in the two previous sections how
objects can be linked into lists. When an object contains two pointers to
objects of the same type, structures can be created that are much more
complicated than linked lists. In this section, we'll look at one of the most
basic and useful structures of this type: <newword>binary trees</newword>. 
Each of the objects in a binary tree contains two pointers,
typically called <code>left</code> and <code>right</code>. In addition to these
pointers, of course, the nodes can contain other types of data. For example, a
binary tree of integers would be made up of objects of the following type:</p>

<pre>class TreeNode {
   int item;        // The data in this node.
   TreeNode left;   // Pointer to the left subtree.
   TreeNode right;  // Pointer to the right subtree.
}</pre>

<p>The <code>left</code> and
<code>right</code> pointers in a <code>TreeNode</code> can be <code>null</code> or can
point to other objects of type <code>TreeNode</code>. A node that points to another
node is said to be the <newword>parent</newword> of that node, and
the node it points to is called a <newword>child</newword>.  In a binary
tree, a child is either a "left child" or a "right child," and a node can
have a right child even if it has no left child.  In the
picture below, for example, node 3 is the parent of node 6, and nodes 4
and 5 are children of node 2. Not every linked structure made up of tree nodes
is a binary tree. A binary tree must have the following properties: There is
exactly one node in the tree which has no parent. This node is called the
<newword>root</newword> of the tree. Every other node in the tree has
exactly one parent. Finally, there can be no loops in a binary tree. That is,
it is not possible to follow a chain of pointers starting at some node and
arriving back at the same node.</p>

<img src="binary-tree.png" alt="TreeNodes linked to make a tree" 
   width="258" height="348" tex="binary-tree.eps" texscale="0.6"/> 

<p>A node that has no children is called a <newword>leaf</newword>. A
leaf node can be recognized by the fact that both the left and right pointers
in the node are <code>null</code>. In the standard picture of a binary tree, the
root node is shown at the top and the leaf nodes at the bottom&mdash;which doesn't
show much respect for the analogy to real trees. But at least you can see the
branching, tree-like structure that gives a binary tree its name.</p>
   
<subsection id="recursion.4.1" title="Tree Traversal">

<p>Consider any node in a binary tree. Look at that node together with all its
descendants (that is, its children, the children of its children, and so on).
This set of nodes forms a binary tree, which is called a 
<newword>subtree</newword> of the original tree. For example, in the picture,
nodes 2, 4, and 5 form a subtree. This subtree is called the 
<newword>left subtree</newword> of the root. Similarly, nodes 3 and 6 make up the
<newword>right subtree</newword> of the root. We can consider any
non-empty binary tree to be made up of a root node, a left subtree, and a right
subtree. Either or both of the subtrees can be empty. This is a recursive
definition, matching the recursive definition of the <classname>TreeNode</classname> class.
So it should not be a surprise that recursive subroutines are often used to
process trees.</p>

<p>Consider the problem of counting the nodes in a binary tree.  As an exercise,
you might try to come up with a non-recursive algorithm to do the counting,
but you shouldn't expect to find one easily.  The
heart of the problem is keeping track of which nodes remain to be counted. It's not
so easy to do this, and in fact it's not even possible without an auxiliary
data structure such as a stack or queue. With recursion, however, the algorithm
is almost trivial. Either the tree is empty or it consists of a root and two
subtrees. If the tree is empty, the number of nodes is zero. (This is the base
case of the recursion.) Otherwise, use recursion to count the nodes in each
subtree. Add the results from the subtrees together, and add one to count the
root. This gives the total number of nodes in the tree. Written out in
Java:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Count the nodes in the binary tree to which root points, and
 * return the answer.  If root is null, the answer is zero.
 */
static int countNodes( TreeNode root ) {
   if ( root == null )
      return 0;  // The tree is empty.  It contains no nodes.
   else {
      int count = 1;   // Start by counting the root.
      count += countNodes(root.left);  // Add the number of nodes
                                       //     in the left subtree.
      count += countNodes(root.right); // Add the number of nodes
                                       //    in the right subtree.
      return count;  // Return the total.
   }
} // end countNodes()</pre>

<p>Or, consider the problem of printing the items in a binary tree. If the tree
is empty, there is nothing to do. If the tree is non-empty, then it consists of
a root and two subtrees. Print the item in the root and use recursion to print
the items in the subtrees. Here is a subroutine that prints all the items on
one line of output:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Print all the items in the tree to which root points.
 * The item in the root is printed first, followed by the
 * items in the left subtree and then the items in the
 * right subtree.
 */
static void preorderPrint( TreeNode root ) {
   if ( root != null ) {  // (Otherwise, there's nothing to print.)
      System.out.print( root.item + " " );  // Print the root item.
      preorderPrint( root.left );   // Print items in left subtree.
      preorderPrint( root.right );  // Print items in right subtree.
   }
} // end preorderPrint()</pre>

<p>This routine is called "preorderPrint" because it uses a 
<newword>preorder traversal</newword> of the tree. In a preorder traversal, the
root node of the tree is processed first, then the left subtree is traversed,
then the right subtree. In a <newword>postorder traversal</newword>,
the left subtree is traversed, then the right subtree, and then the root node
is processed. And in an <newword>inorder traversal</newword>, the
left subtree is traversed first, then the root node is processed, then the
right subtree is traversed. Subroutines that use postorder and inorder
traversal to print the contents of a tree differ from <code>preorderPrint()</code> only in the placement of the
statement that outputs the root item:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Print all the items in the tree to which root points.
 * <newcode>The items in the left subtree are printed first, followed</newcode>
 * <newcode>by the items in the right subtree and then the item</newcode>
 * <newcode>in the root node.</newcode>
 */
static void postorderPrint( TreeNode root ) {
   if ( root != null ) {  // (Otherwise, there's nothing to print.)
      postorderPrint( root.left );   // Print items in left subtree.
      postorderPrint( root.right );  // Print items in right subtree.
      <newcode>System.out.print( root.item + " " );  // Print the root item.</newcode>
   }
} // end postorderPrint()
     
     
/**
 * Print all the items in the tree to which root points.
 * <newcode>The items in the left subtree are printed first, followed</newcode>
 * <newcode>by the item in the root node and then the items</newcode>
 * <newcode>in the right subtree.</newcode>
 */
static void inorderPrint( TreeNode root ) {
   if ( root != null ) {  // (Otherwise, there's nothing to print.)
      inorderPrint( root.left );   // Print items in left subtree.
      <newcode>System.out.print( root.item + " " );  // Print the root item.</newcode>
      inorderPrint( root.right );  // Print items in right subtree.
   }
} // end inorderPrint()</pre>

<p>Each of these subroutines can be applied to the binary tree shown in the
illustration at the beginning of this section. The order in which the items are
printed differs in each case:</p>

<pre>preorderPrint outputs:   1  2  4  5  3  6

postorderPrint outputs:  4  5  2  6  3  1

inorderPrint outputs:    4  2  5  1  3  6</pre>

<np>In <code>preorderPrint</code>, for example, the item at the root of the tree,
<code>1</code>, is output before anything else. But the preorder printing also
applies to each of the subtrees of the root. The root item of the left subtree,
<code>2</code>, is printed before the other items in that subtree, <code>4</code> and
<code>5</code>. As for the right subtree of the root, <code>3</code> is output before
<code>6</code>. A preorder traversal applies at all levels in the tree. The other
two traversal orders can be analyzed similarly.</np>

</subsection>

<subsection id="recursion.4.2" title="Binary Sort Trees">

<p>One of the examples in <localref href="recursion.2"/> was a linked list of
strings, in which the strings were kept in increasing order. While a linked
list works well for a small number of strings, it becomes inefficient for a
large number of items. When inserting an item into the list, searching for that
item's position requires looking at, on average, half the items in the list.
Finding an item in the list requires a similar amount of time. If the strings
are stored in a sorted array instead of in a linked list, then searching
becomes more efficient because binary search can be used.
However, inserting a new item into the array
is still inefficient since it means moving, on average, half of the items in
the array to make a space for the new item. A binary tree can be used to store
an ordered list in a way that makes both searching
and insertion efficient. A binary tree used in this way is called a
<newword>binary sort tree</newword> or <newword>BST</newword>.</p>

<p>A binary sort tree is a binary tree with the following property: For every
node in the tree, the item in that node is greater than or equal to every item in the left
subtree of that node, and it is less than or equal to all the items in the
right subtree of that node. Here for example is a binary sort tree containing
items of type <classname>String</classname>. (In this picture, I haven't bothered to draw all
the pointer variables. Non-null pointers are shown as arrows.)</p>

<img src="binary-sort-tree.png" alt="A binary sort tree" width="392"
   height="303" tex="binary-sort-tree.eps" texscale="0.6" />


<p>Binary sort trees have this useful property: An inorder traversal of the
tree will process the items in increasing order. In fact, this is really just
another way of expressing the definition. For example, if an inorder traversal
is used to print the items in the tree shown above, then the items will be in
alphabetical order. The definition of an inorder traversal guarantees that all
the items in the left subtree of "judy" are printed before "judy", and all the
items in the right subtree of "judy" are printed after "judy". But the binary
sort tree property guarantees that the items in the left subtree of "judy" are
precisely those that precede "judy" in alphabetical order, and all the items in
the right subtree follow "judy" in alphabetical order. So, we know that "judy"
is output in its proper alphabetical position. But the same argument applies to
the subtrees. "Bill" will be output after "alice" and before "fred" and its
descendents. "Fred" will be output after "dave" and before "jane" and "joe".
And so on.</p>

<p>Suppose that we want to search for a given item in a binary search tree.
Compare that item to the root item of the tree. If they are equal, we're done.
If the item we are looking for is less than the root item, then we need to
search the left subtree of the root&mdash;the right subtree can be eliminated
because it only contains items that are greater than or equal to the root.
Similarly, if the item we are looking for is greater than the item in the root,
then we only need to look in the right subtree. In either case, the same
procedure can then be applied to search the subtree. Inserting a new item is
similar: Start by searching the tree for the position where the new item
belongs. When that position is found, create a new node and attach it to the
tree at that position.</p>

<p>Searching and inserting are efficient operations on a binary search tree,
provided that the tree is close to being <newword>balanced</newword>.
A binary tree is balanced if for each node, the left subtree of that node
contains approximately the same number of nodes as the right subtree. In a
perfectly balanced tree, the two numbers differ by at most one. Not all binary
trees are balanced, but if the tree is created by inserting items in a random
order, there is a high
probability that the tree is approximately balanced. (If the order of insertion
is not random, however, it's quite possible for the tree to be very unbalanced.)
During a search of any
binary sort tree, every comparison eliminates one of two subtrees from further
consideration. If the tree is balanced, that means cutting the number of items
still under consideration in half. This is exactly the same as the binary
search algorithm, and the result is a similarly efficient algorithm.
</p>
   
<p>In terms of asymptotic analysis (<localref href="robustness.5"/>), searching, inserting,
and deleting in a binary search tree have average case run time &Theta;(log(n)).
The problem size, n, is the number of items in the tree, and the average is
taken over all the different orders in which the items could have been inserted into the tree.
As long as the actual insertion order is random, the actual run time can be expected
to be close to the average.  However, the worst case run time for binary
search tree operations is &Theta;(n), which is much worse than &Theta;(log(n)).
The worst case occurs for  particular insertion orders.  For example,
if the items are inserted into the tree in order of increasing size, then every
item that is inserted moves always to the right as it moves down the tree.
The result is a "tree" that looks more like a linked list, since it consists
of a linear string of nodes strung together by their <code>right</code> child
pointers.  Operations on such a tree have the same performance as operations
on a linked list.  Now, there are data structures that are similar to simple binary
sort trees, except that insertion and deletion of nodes are implemented in
a way that will always keep the tree balanced, or almost balanced.  For
these data structures, searching, inserting, and deleting have both average case 
and worst case run times that are &Theta;(log(n)).  Here, however, we will
look at only the simple versions of inserting and searching.</p>

<p>The sample program <sourceref href="SortTreeDemo.java"/> is a demonstration of
binary sort trees. The program includes subroutines that implement inorder
traversal, searching, and insertion. We'll look at the latter two subroutines
below. The <code>main()</code> routine tests the subroutines by letting you type in
strings to be inserted into the tree.</p>

<p>In <classname>SortTreeDemo</classname>, nodes in the binary tree are represented using the
following static nested class, including a simple constructor that makes creating nodes
easier:</p>

<pre>
/**
 * An object of type TreeNode represents one node in a binary tree of strings.
 */
private static class TreeNode {
   String item;      // The data in this node.
   TreeNode left;    // Pointer to left subtree.
   TreeNode right;   // Pointer to right subtree.
   TreeNode(String str) {
          // Constructor.  Make a node containing str.
          // Note that left and right pointers are null.
      item = str;
   }
}  // end class TreeNode</pre>

<np>A static member variable of type <classname>TreeNode</classname> points to the binary sort
tree that is used by the program:</np>

<pre>private static TreeNode root;  // Pointer to the root node in the tree.
                               // When the tree is empty, root is null.</pre>

<np>A recursive subroutine named <code>treeContains</code> is used to search for a
given item in the tree. This routine implements the search algorithm for binary
trees that was outlined above:</np>

<pre>/**
 * Return true if item is one of the items in the binary
 * sort tree to which root points.  Return false if not.
 */
static boolean treeContains( TreeNode root, String item ) {
   if ( root == null ) {
          // Tree is empty, so it certainly doesn't contain item.
      return false;
   }
   else if ( item.equals(root.item) ) {
          // Yes, the item has been found in the root node.
      return true;
   }
   else if ( item.compareTo(root.item) &lt; 0 ) {
          // If the item occurs, it must be in the left subtree.
      return treeContains( root.left, item );
   }
   else {
          // If the item occurs, it must be in the right subtree.
      return treeContains( root.right, item );
   }
}  // end treeContains()</pre>

<np>When this routine is called in the <code>main()</code> routine, the first
parameter is the static member variable <code>root</code>, which points to the root
of the entire binary sort tree.</np>

<p>It's worth noting that recursion is not really essential in this case. A
simple, non-recursive algorithm for searching a binary sort tree follows
the rule: Start at the root and move down the tree until you find the item or reach a null pointer.
Since the search follows a single path down the tree, it can be implemented as
a <code>while</code> loop. Here is a non-recursive version of the search routine:</p>

<pre>private static boolean treeContainsNR( TreeNode root, String item ) {
   TreeNode runner;  // For "running" down the tree.
   runner = root;    // Start at the root node.
   while (true) {
      if (runner == null) {
            // We've fallen off the tree without finding item.
         return false;  
      }
      else if ( item.equals(runner.item) ) {
            // We've found the item.
         return true;
      }
      else if ( item.compareTo(runner.item) &lt; 0 ) {
            // If the item occurs, it must be in the left subtree.
            // So, advance the runner down one level to the left.
         runner = runner.left;
      }
      else {
            // If the item occurs, it must be in the right subtree.
            // So, advance the runner down one level to the right.
         runner = runner.right;
      }
   }  // end while
} // end treeContainsNR();</pre>

<p>The subroutine for inserting a new item into the tree turns out to be more
similar to the non-recursive search routine than to the recursive. The
insertion routine has to handle the case where the tree is empty. In that case,
the value of <code>root</code> must be changed to point to a node that contains the
new item:</p>

<pre>root = new TreeNode( newItem ); </pre>

<np>But this means, effectively, that the root can't be passed as a parameter to
the subroutine, because it is impossible for a subroutine to change the value
stored in an actual parameter. (I should note that this is something that
<b>is</b> possible in other languages.) Recursion uses parameters in an
essential way. There are ugly ways to work around the problem, but the easiest thing
is just to use a non-recursive insertion routine that accesses the static
member variable <code>root</code> directly. One difference between inserting an
item and searching for an item is that we have to be careful not to fall off
the tree. That is, we have to stop searching just <b>before</b> <code>runner</code>
becomes <code>null</code>. When we get to an empty spot in the tree, that's where
we have to insert the new node:</np>

<pre>/**
 * Add the item to the binary sort tree to which the global variable 
 * "root" refers.  (Note that root can't be passed as  a parameter to 
 * this routine because the value of root might change, and a change 
 * in the value of a formal parameter does not change the actual parameter.)
 */
private static void treeInsert(String newItem) {
   if ( root == null ) {
          // The tree is empty.  Set root to point to a new node containing
          // the new item.  This becomes the only node in the tree.
      root = new TreeNode( newItem );
      return;
   }
   TreeNode runner;  // Runs down the tree to find a place for newItem.
   runner = root;   // Start at the root.
   while (true) {
      if ( newItem.compareTo(runner.item) &lt; 0 ) {
             // Since the new item is less than the item in runner,
             // it belongs in the left subtree of runner.  If there
             // is an open space at runner.left, add a new node there.
             // Otherwise, advance runner down one level to the left.
         if ( runner.left == null ) {
            runner.left = new TreeNode( newItem );
            return;  // New item has been added to the tree.
         }
         else
            runner = runner.left;
      }
      else {
             // Since the new item is greater than or equal to the item in
             // runner, it belongs in the right subtree of runner.  If there
             // is an open space at runner.right, add a new node there.
             // Otherwise, advance runner down one level to the right.
         if ( runner.right == null ) {
            runner.right = new TreeNode( newItem );
            return;  // New item has been added to the tree.
         }
         else
            runner = runner.right;
      }
   } // end while
}  // end treeInsert()</pre>

</subsection>

<subsection id="recursion.4.3" title="Expression Trees">

<p>Another application of trees is to store mathematical expressions such as
<code>15*(x+y)</code> or <code>sqrt(42)+7</code> in a convenient form. Let's stick for
the moment to expressions made up of numbers and the operators <code>+</code>, <code>-</code>,
<code>*</code>, and <code>/</code>. Consider the expression
<code>3*((7+1)/4)+(17-5)</code>. This expression is made up of two subexpressions,
<code>3*((7+1)/4)</code> and <code>(17-5)</code>, combined with the operator "<code>+</code>". When
the expression is represented as a binary tree, the root node holds the
operator <code>+</code>, while the subtrees of the root node represent the subexpressions
<code>3*((7+1)/4)</code> and <code>(17-5)</code>. Every node in the tree holds either a
number or an operator. A node that holds a number is a leaf node of the tree. A
node that holds an operator has two subtrees representing the operands to which
the operator applies. The tree is shown in the illustration below. I will refer
to a tree of this type as an <newword>expression tree</newword>.</p>

<p>Given an expression tree, it's easy to find the value of the expression that
it represents. Each node in the tree has an associated value. If the node is a
leaf node, then its value is simply the number that the node contains. If the
node contains an operator, then the associated value is computed by first
finding the values of its child nodes and then applying the operator to those
values. The process is shown by the upward-directed arrows in the illustration. The value
computed for the root node is the value of the expression as a whole. There are
other uses for expression trees. For example, a postorder traversal of the tree
will output the postfix form of the expression.</p>

<img src="expression-tree.png" alt="An expression tree" width="430" 
   height="429" tex="expression-tree.eps" texscale="0.6" />


<p>An expression tree contains two types of nodes: nodes that contain numbers
and nodes that contain operators. Furthermore, we might want to add other types
of nodes to make the trees more useful, such as nodes that contain variables.
If we want to work with expression trees in Java, how can we deal with this
variety of nodes? One way&mdash;which will be frowned upon by object-oriented
purists&mdash;is to include an instance variable in each node object to record
which type of node it is:</p>

<pre>enum NodeType { NUMBER, OPERATOR }   // Possible kinds of node.
   
class ExpNode {  // A node in an expression tree.

    NodeType kind;  // Which type of node is this?
    double number;  // The value in a node of type NUMBER.
    char op;        // The operator in a node of type OPERATOR.
    ExpNode left;   // Pointers to subtrees,
    ExpNode right;  //     in a node of type OPERATOR.
    
    ExpNode( double val ) {
          // Constructor for making a node of type NUMBER.
       kind = NodeType.NUMBER;
       number = val;
    }
 
    ExpNode( char op, ExpNode left, ExpNode right ) {
          // Constructor for making a node of type OPERATOR.
       kind = NodeType.OPERATOR;
       this.op = op;
       this.left = left;
       this.right = right;
    }
 
 } // end class ExpNode</pre>

<np>Given this definition, the following recursive subroutine will find the
value of an expression tree:</np>

<pre>static double getValue( ExpNode node ) {
       // Return the value of the expression represented by
       // the tree to which node refers.  Node must be non-null.
    if ( node.kind == NodeType.NUMBER ) {
          // The value of a NUMBER node is the number it holds.
       return node.number;
    }
    else {  // The kind must be OPERATOR.
            // Get the values of the operands and combine them
            //    using the operator.
       double leftVal = getValue( node.left );
       double rightVal = getValue( node.right );
       switch ( node.op ) {
          case '+':  return leftVal + rightVal;
          case '-':  return leftVal - rightVal;
          case '*':  return leftVal * rightVal;
          case '/':  return leftVal / rightVal;
          default:   return Double.NaN;  // Bad operator.
       }
    }
 } // end getValue()</pre>

<p>Although this approach works, a more object-oriented approach is to note
that since there are two types of nodes, there should be two classes to
represent them, perhaps named <classname>ConstNode</classname> and <classname>BinOpNode</classname>. To represent the
general idea of a node in an expression tree, we need another class,
<classname>ExpNode</classname>. Both <classname>ConstNode</classname> and <classname>BinOpNode</classname> will be
subclasses of <classname>ExpNode</classname>. Since any actual node will be either a
<code>ConstNode</code> or a <classname>BinOpNode</classname>, <classname>ExpNode</classname> should be an
abstract class. (See <localref href="OOP.5.5"/>.) Since one of the
things we want to do with nodes is find their values, each class should have an
instance method for finding the value:</p>

<pre>abstract class ExpNode {
       // Represents a node of any type in an expression tree.
       
    abstract double value();  // Return the value of this node.
    
} // end class ExpNode


class ConstNode extends ExpNode {
       // Represents a node that holds a number.
       
    double number;  // The number in the node.
    
    ConstNode( double val ) {
          // Constructor.  Create a node to hold val.
       number = val;
    }
 
    double value() {
          // The value is just the number that the node holds.
       return number;
    }
 
 } // end class ConstNode
 
 
 class BinOpNode extends ExpNode {
       // Represents a node that holds an operator.
  
    char op;        // The operator.
    ExpNode left;   // The left operand.
    ExpNode right;  // The right operand.
 
    BinOpNode( char op, ExpNode left, ExpNode right ) {
          // Constructor.  Create a node to hold the given data.
       this.op = op;
       this.left = left;
       this.right = right;
    }
 
    double value() {
          // To get the value, compute the value of the left and
          // right operands, and combine them with the operator.
        double leftVal = left.value();
        double rightVal = right.value();
        switch ( op ) {
            case '+':  return leftVal + rightVal;
            case '-':  return leftVal - rightVal;
            case '*':  return leftVal * rightVal;
            case '/':  return leftVal / rightVal;
            default:   return Double.NaN;  // Bad operator.
         }
    }
 
 } // end class BinOpNode</pre>

<p>Note that the left and right operands of a <classname>BinOpNode</classname> are of type
<classname>ExpNode</classname>, not <classname>BinOpNode</classname>. This allows the operand to be either
a <classname>ConstNode</classname> or another <classname>BinOpNode</classname>&mdash;or any other type of
<classname>ExpNode</classname> that we might eventually create. Since every <classname>ExpNode</classname>
has a <code>value()</code> method, we can call <code>left.value()</code> to compute the
value of the left operand. If <code>left</code> is in fact a <classname>ConstNode</classname>,
this will call the <code>value()</code> method in the <classname>ConstNode</classname> class. If
it is in fact a <classname>BinOpNode</classname>, then <code>left.value()</code> will call the
<code>value()</code> method in the <classname>BinOpNode</classname> class. Each node knows how to
compute its own value.</p>

<p>Although it might seem more complicated at first, the object-oriented
approach has some real advantages. For one thing, it doesn't waste memory. In the
original <classname>ExpNode</classname> class, only some of the instance variables in each
node were actually used, and we needed an extra instance variable to keep track
of the type of node. More important, though, is the fact that new types of
nodes can be added more cleanly, since it can be done by creating a new
subclass of <classname>ExpNode</classname> rather than by modifying an existing class.</p>

<p>We'll return to the topic of expression trees in the next section, where
we'll see how to create an expression tree to represent a given expression.</p>
   
</subsection>

</section>