<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE quiz SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd">

<quiz>

<question>
<ques><p>One of the components of a
computer is its <i>CPU.</i> What is a CPU and what role does it play in a
computer?</p></ques>
<ans><p>The CPU, or Central Processing
Unit, is the active part of the computer. Its function is to execute programs
that are coded in machine language and stored in the main memory (RAM) of the
computer. It does this by repeating the fetch-and-execute cycle over and over;
that is, it repeatedly fetches a machine language instruction from memory and
executes it.</p></ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>Explain what is meant by an
"asynchronous event." Give some examples.</p></ques>
<ans><p>An asynchronous event is one
that occurs at an unpredictable time outside the control of the program that
the CPU is running. It is not "synchronized" with the program. An example would
be when the user presses a key on the keyboard or clicks the mouse button.
(These events generate "interrupts" that cause the CPU to interrupt what it is
doing and to take some action to handle the asynchronous event. After handling
the event, the CPU returns to what it was doing before it was interrupted.)</p></ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>What is the difference
between a "compiler" and an "interpreter"?</p></ques>
<ans><p>Compilers and interpreters have
similar functions: They take a program written in some programming language and
translate it into machine language. A compiler does the translation all at
once. It produces a complete machine language program that can then be
executed. An interpreter, on the other hand, just translates one instruction at
a time, and then executes that instruction immediately. (Java uses a compiler
to translate java programs into Java Bytecode, which is a machine language for
the imaginary Java Virtual Machine. Java Bytecode programs are then executed by
an interpreter.)</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Explain the difference
between <i>high-level languages</i> and <i>machine language.</i></p></ques>
<ans><p>Programs written in the machine
language of a given type of computer can be directly executed by the CPU of
that type of computer. High-level language programs must be translated into
machine language before they can be executed. (Machine language instructions
are encoded as binary numbers that are meant to be used by a machine, not read
or written by people. High-level languages use a syntax that is closer to human
language.)</p></ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>If you have the source code
for a Java program, and you want to run that program, you will need both a
<i>compiler</i> and an <i>interpreter.</i> What does the Java compiler do, and
what does the Java interpreter do?</p></ques>
<ans><p>The Java compiler translates
Java programs into a language called Java bytecode. Although bytecode is
similar to machine language, it is not the machine language of any actual
computer. A Java interpreter is used to run the compiled Java bytecode program.
(Each type of computer needs its own Java bytecode interpreter, but all these
interpreters interpret the same bytecode language.)</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>What is a<i> subroutine?</i></p></ques>
<ans><p>A subroutine is a set of
instructions for performing some task that have been grouped together and given
a name. Later, when that task needs to be performed, it is only necessary to
call the subroutine by giving its name, rather than repeating the whole
sequence of instructions.</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Java is an object-oriented
programming language. What is an <i>object</i>?</p></ques>
<ans><p>An object consists of some data
together with a set of subroutines that manipulate that data. (An object is a
kind of "module," or self-contained entity that communicates with the rest of
the world through a well-defined interface. An object should represent some
coherent concept or real-world object.)</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>What is a <i>variable?</i>
(There are four different ideas associated with variables in Java. Try to
mention all four aspects in your answer. Hint: One of the aspects is the
variable's name.)</p></ques>
<ans><p>A variable is a <u>memory location</u> that has been given a <u>name</u> so that it can easily be
referred to in a program. The variable holds a <u>value</u>, which must be of
some specified <u>type</u>. The value can be changed during the course of the
execution of the program.</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Java is a
"platform-independent language." What does this mean?</p></ques>
<ans><p>A Java program can be compiled
once into a Java Bytecode program. The compiled program can then be run on any
computer that has an interpreter for the Java virtual machine. Other languages
have to be re-compiled for each platform on which they are going to run. The
point about Java is that it can be executed on many different types of
computers without being recompiled.</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>What is the "Internet"?
Give some examples of how it is used. (What kind of services does it
provide?)</p></ques>
<ans><p>The Internet is a network
connecting millions of computers around the world. Computers connected to the
Internet can communicate with each other. The Internet can be used for Email
(which lets a user of one computer send a message to a user on another computer), file sharing
(which is used to copy files between computers), and the World Wide Web (which
lets a user view "pages" of information published on computers around the
world).</p></ans>
</question>

</quiz>