<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="control.3" title="The while and do..while Statements" shorttitle="while and do..while">

<p><start><big>S</big>tatements in Java can</start> be either simple statements
or compound statements. Simple statements, such as assignment statements and
subroutine call statements, are the basic building blocks of a program.
Compound statements, such as <code>while</code> loops and <code>if</code> statements,
are used to organize simple statements into complex structures, which are
called control structures because they control the order in which the
statements are executed. The next five sections explore the details of
control structures that are available in Java, starting with the <code>while</code>
statement and the <code>do..while</code> statement in this section. At the same
time, we'll look at examples of programming with each control structure and
apply the techniques for designing algorithms that were introduced in the
<localref href="control.2">previous&nbsp;section</localref>.</p>


<subsection id="control.3.1" title="The while Statement">

<p>The <code>while</code> statement was already introduced in <localref href="control.1"/>. 
A <code>while</code> loop has the form</p>

<pre>while ( <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> )
   <bnf>statement</bnf></pre>

<np>The <bnf>statement</bnf> can, of course, be a block
statement consisting of several statements grouped together between a pair of
braces. This statement is called the <newword>body of the loop</newword>. 
The body of the loop is repeated as long as the <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> is true. This boolean expression is
called the <newword>continuation condition</newword>, or more simply
the <newword>test</newword>, of the loop. There are a few points that
might need some clarification. What happens if the condition is false in the
first place, before the body of the loop is executed even once? In that case,
the body of the loop is never executed at all. The body of a while loop can be
executed any number of times, including zero. What happens if the condition is
true, but it becomes false somewhere in the <b>middle</b> of the loop
body? Does the loop end as soon as this happens? It doesn't, because the
computer continues executing the body of the loop until it gets to the end.
Only then does it jump back to the beginning of the loop and test the
condition, and only then can the loop end.</np>

<p>Let's look at a typical problem that can be solved using a <code>while</code>
loop: finding the average of a set of positive integers entered by the user.
The average is the sum of the integers, divided by the number of integers. The
program will ask the user to enter one integer at a time. It will keep count of
the number of integers entered, and it will keep a running total of all the
numbers it has read so far. Here is a pseudocode algorithm for the program:</p>

<pre>Let sum = 0     // The sum of the integers entered by the user.
Let count = 0   // The number of integers entered by the user.
while there are more integers to process:
    Read an integer
    Add it to the sum
    Count it
Divide sum by count to get the average
Print out the average</pre>

<p>But how can we test whether there are more integers to process? A typical
solution is to tell the user to type in zero after all the data have been
entered. This will work because we are assuming that all the data are positive
numbers, so zero is not a legal data value. The zero is not itself part of the
data to be averaged. It's just there to mark the end of the real data. A data
value used in this way is sometimes called a <newword>sentinel value</newword>. 
So now the test in the while loop becomes "while the input
integer is not zero". But there is another problem! The first time the test is
evaluated, before the body of the loop has ever been executed, no integer has
yet been read. There is no "input integer" yet, so testing whether the input
integer is zero doesn't make sense. So, we have to do something
<b>before</b> the while loop to make sure that the test makes sense.
Setting things up so that the test in a <code>while</code> loop makes sense the
first time it is executed is called <newword>priming the loop</newword>. 
In this case, we can simply read the first integer before the
beginning of the loop. Here is a revised algorithm:</p>

<pre>Let sum = 0
Let count = 0
Read an integer
while the integer is not zero:
    Add the integer to the sum
    Count it
    Read an integer
Divide sum by count to get the average
Print out the average</pre>

<p>Notice that I've rearranged the body of the loop. Since an integer is read
before the loop, the loop has to begin by processing that integer. At the end
of the loop, the computer reads a new integer. The computer then jumps back to
the beginning of the loop and tests the integer that it has just read. Note
that when the computer finally reads the sentinel value, the loop ends before
the sentinel value is processed. It is not added to the sum, and it is not
counted. This is the way it's supposed to work. The sentinel is not part of the
data. The original algorithm, even if it could have been made to work without
priming, was incorrect since it would have summed and counted all the integers,
including the sentinel. (Since the sentinel is zero, the sum would still be
correct, but the count would be off by one. Such so-called <newword>off-by-one errors</newword> 
are very common. Counting turns out to be
harder than it looks!)</p>

<p>We can easily turn the algorithm into a complete program. Note that the
program cannot use the statement "<code>average&nbsp;=&nbsp;sum/count</code>;" to compute the
average. Since <code>sum</code> and <code>count</code> are both variables of type
<ptype>int</ptype>, the value of <code>sum/count</code> is an integer. The average should
be a real number. We've seen this problem before: we have to convert one of the
<ptype>int</ptype> values to a <ptype>double</ptype> to force the computer to compute the
quotient as a real number. This can be done by type-casting one of the
variables to type <ptype>double</ptype>. The type cast "(double)sum" converts the
value of <code>sum</code> to a real number, so in the program the average is
computed as "<code>average&nbsp;= ((double)sum)&nbsp;/&nbsp;count</code>;". Another solution in
this case would have been to declare <code>sum</code> to be a variable of type
<ptype>double</ptype> in the first place.</p>

<p>One other issue is addressed by the program: If the user enters zero as the
first input value, there are no data to process. We can test for this case by
checking whether <code>count</code> is still equal to zero after the <code>while</code>
loop. This might seem like a minor point, but a careful programmer should cover
all the bases.</p>


<p>Here is the full source code for the program (with comments added, of course!):</p>

<pre>import textio.TextIO;

/**
 * This program reads a sequence of positive integers input
 * by the user, and it will print out the average of those
 * integers.  The user is prompted to enter one integer at a
 * time.  The user must enter a 0 to mark the end of the
 * data.  (The zero is not counted as part of the data to
 * be averaged.)  The program does not check whether the
 * user's input is positive, so it will actually add up
 * both positive and negative input values.
 */
public class ComputeAverage {
        
   public static void main(String[] args) {
      
      int inputNumber;   // One of the integers input by the user.
      int sum;           // The sum of the positive integers.
      int count;         // The number of positive integers.
      double average;    // The average of the positive integers.
      
      /* Initialize the summation and counting variables. */
      
      sum = 0;
      count = 0;
      
      /* Read and process the user's input. */
      
      System.out.print("Enter your first positive integer: ");
      inputNumber = TextIO.getlnInt();
      
      while (inputNumber != 0) {
         sum += inputNumber;   // Add inputNumber to running sum.
         count++;              // Count the input by adding 1 to count.
         System.out.print("Enter your next positive integer, or 0 to end: ");
         inputNumber = TextIO.getlnInt();
      }
      
      /* Display the result. */
      
      if (count == 0) {
         System.out.println("You didn't enter any data!");
      }
      else {
         average = ((double)sum) / count;
         System.out.println();
         System.out.println("You entered " + count + " positive integers.");
         System.out.printf("Their average is %1.3f.\n", average);
      }
 
   } // end main()
   
} // end class ComputeAverage</pre>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="control.3.2" title="The do..while Statement">
   

<p>Sometimes it is more convenient to test the continuation condition at the
end of a loop, instead of at the beginning, as is done in the <code>while</code>
loop. The <code>do..while</code> statement is very similar to the <code>while</code>
statement, except that the word "while," along with the condition that it
tests, has been moved to the end. The word "do" is added to mark the beginning
of the loop. A <code>do..while</code> statement has the form</p>

<pre>do
    <bnf>statement</bnf>
while ( <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> );</pre>

<np>or, since, as usual, the <bnf>statement</bnf> can be a
block,</np>

<pre>do {
    <bnf>statements</bnf>
} while ( <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> );</pre>

<np>Note the semicolon, ';', at the very  end. This semicolon is part of the
statement, just as the semicolon at the end of an assignment statement or
declaration is part of the statement. Omitting it is a syntax error. (More
generally, <b>every</b> statement in Java ends either with a
semicolon or a right brace, '}'.)</np>

<p>To execute a <code>do</code> loop, the computer first executes the body of the
loop&mdash;that is, the statement or statements inside the loop&mdash;and then it
evaluates the boolean expression. If the value of the expression is
<code>true</code>, the computer returns to the beginning of the <code>do</code> loop and repeats
the process; if the value is <code>false</code>, it ends the loop and continues
with the next part of the program. Since the condition is not tested until the
end of the loop, the body of a <code>do</code> loop is always executed at least once.</p>

<p>For example, consider the following pseudocode for a game-playing program.
The <code>do</code> loop makes sense here instead of a <code>while</code> loop because
with the <code>do</code> loop, you know there will be at least one game. Also, the
test that is used at the end of the loop wouldn't even make sense at the
beginning:</p>

<pre>do {
   Play a Game
   Ask user if he wants to play another game
   Read the user's response
} while ( the user's response is yes );</pre>

<p>Let's convert this into proper Java code. Since I don't want to talk about
game playing at the moment, let's say that we have a class named
<code>Checkers</code>, and that the <code>Checkers</code> class contains a static
member subroutine named <code>playGame()</code> that plays one game of checkers
against the user. Then, the pseudocode "Play a game" can be expressed as the
subroutine call statement "<code>Checkers.playGame();</code>". We need a variable
to store the user's response. The <classname>TextIO</classname> class makes it convenient to
use a <ptype>boolean</ptype> variable to store the answer to a yes/no question. The
input function <code>TextIO.getlnBoolean()</code> allows the user to enter the
value as "yes" or "no" (among other acceptable responses). 
"Yes" is considered to be <code>true</code>, and "no" is
considered to be <code>false</code>. So, the algorithm can be coded as</p>

<pre>boolean wantsToContinue;  // True if user wants to play again.
do {
   Checkers.playGame();
   System.out.print("Do you want to play again? ");
   wantsToContinue = TextIO.getlnBoolean();
} while (wantsToContinue == true);</pre>

<np>When the value of the <ptype>boolean</ptype> variable is set to <code>false</code>, it
is a signal that the loop should end. When a <ptype>boolean</ptype> variable is used
in this way&mdash;as a signal that is set in one part of the program and tested in
another part&mdash;it is sometimes called a <newword>flag</newword> or
<newword>flag variable</newword> (in the sense of a signal flag).</np>

<p>By the way, a more-than-usually-pedantic programmer would sneer at the test
"<code>while (wantsToContinue == true)</code>". This test is exactly equivalent to
"<code>while (wantsToContinue)</code>". Testing whether "<code>wantsToContinue&nbsp;==&nbsp;true</code>" 
is true amounts to the same thing as testing whether
"<code>wantsToContinue</code>" is true. A little less offensive is an expression of
the form "<code>flag&nbsp;==&nbsp;false</code>", where <code>flag</code> is a boolean variable.
The value of "<code>flag&nbsp;==&nbsp;false</code>" is exactly the same as the value of
"<code>!flag</code>", where <code>!</code> is the boolean negation operator. So you can
write "<code>while&nbsp;(!flag)</code>" instead of "<code>while (flag&nbsp;==&nbsp;false)</code>", and
you can write "<code>if&nbsp;(!flag)</code>" instead of "<code>if&nbsp;(flag&nbsp;==&nbsp;false)</code>".</p>

<p>Although a <code>do..while</code> statement is sometimes more convenient than a
<code>while</code> statement, having two kinds of loops does not make the language
more powerful. Any problem that can be solved using <code>do..while</code> loops
can also be solved using only <code>while</code> statements, and vice versa. In
fact, if <bnf>doSomething</bnf> represents any block of
program code, then</p>

<pre>do {
    <bnf>doSomething</bnf>
} while ( <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> );</pre>

<np>has exactly the same effect as</np>

<pre><bnf>doSomething</bnf>
while ( <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> ) {
    <bnf>doSomething</bnf>
}</pre>

<np>Similarly,</np>

<pre>while ( <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> ) {
    <bnf>doSomething</bnf>
} </pre>

<np>can be replaced by</np>

<pre>if ( <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> ) {
   do {
       <bnf>doSomething</bnf>
   } while ( <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> );
}</pre>

<np>without changing the meaning of the program in any way.</np>


</subsection>
   
<subsection id="control.3.3" title="break and continue">

<p>The syntax of the <code>while</code> and <code>do..while</code> loops allows you to
test the continuation condition at either the beginning of a loop or at the
end. Sometimes, it is more natural to have the test in the middle of the loop,
or to have several tests at different places in the same loop. Java provides a
general method for breaking out of the middle of any loop. It's called the
<code>break</code> statement, which takes the form</p>

<pre>break;</pre>

<p>When the computer executes a <code>break</code> statement in a loop, it will
immediately jump out of the loop. It then continues on to whatever follows the
loop in the program. Consider for example:</p>

<pre>while (true) {  // looks like it will run forever!
   System.out.print("Enter a positive number: ");
   N = TextIO.getlnInt();
   if (N &gt; 0)   // the input value is OK, so jump out of loop
      break;
   System.out.println("Your answer must be &gt; 0.");
}
// continue here after break</pre>

<np>If the number entered by the user is greater than zero, the <code>break</code>
statement will be executed and the computer will jump out of the loop.
Otherwise, the computer will print out "Your answer must be &gt; 0." and will
jump back to the start of the loop to read another input value.</np>

<p>The first line of this loop, "<code>while&nbsp;(true)</code>" might look a bit
strange, but it's perfectly legitimate. The condition in a <code>while</code> loop
can be any boolean-valued expression. The computer evaluates this expression
and checks whether the value is <code>true</code> or <code>false</code>. The boolean
literal "<code>true</code>" is just a boolean expression that always evaluates to
true. So "<code>while&nbsp;(true)</code>" can be used to write an infinite loop, or one
that will be terminated by a <code>break</code> statement.</p>

<p>A <code>break</code> statement terminates the loop that immediately encloses the
<code>break</code> statement. It is possible to have <newword>nested</newword> loops, 
where one loop statement is contained inside
another. If you use a <code>break</code> statement inside a nested loop, it will
only break out of that loop, not out of the loop that contains the nested loop. 
There is something called a <newword>labeled break</newword> statement that allows you to
specify which loop you want to break. This is not very common, so I will go over it quickly.
Labels work like this:  You can put a <newword>label</newword> in
front of any loop.  A label consists of a simple identifier followed
by a colon.  For example, a <code>while</code> with a label might
look like "<code>mainloop:&nbsp;while&dots;</code>".  Inside
this loop you can use the labeled break statement "<code>break&nbsp;mainloop;</code>"
to break out of the labeled loop.  For example, here is a code segment that checks
whether two strings, <code>s1</code> and <code>s2</code>, have a character in common.
If a common character is found, the value of the flag variable <code>nothingInCommon</code>
is set to <code>false</code>, and a labeled break is used to end the processing
at that point:</p>

<pre>boolean nothingInCommon;
nothingInCommon = true;  // Assume s1 and s2 have no chars in common.
int i,j;  // Variables for iterating through the chars in s1 and s2.

i = 0;
bigloop: while (i &lt; s1.length()) {
   j = 0;
   while (j &lt; s2.length()) {
      if (s1.charAt(i) == s2.charAt(j)) { // s1 and s2 have a common char...
          nothingInCommon = false;  // so nothingInCommon is actually false.
          break bigloop;  // break out of BOTH loops
      }
      j++;  // Go on to the next char in s2.
   }
   i++;  //Go on to the next char in s1.
}</pre>

<break/>
   
<p>The <code>continue</code> statement is related to <code>break</code>, but less
commonly used. A <code>continue</code> statement tells the computer to skip the
rest of the current iteration of the loop. However, instead of jumping out of
the loop altogether, it jumps back to the beginning of the loop and continues
with the next iteration (including evaluating the loop's continuation condition to
see whether any further iterations are required).  As with <code>break</code>,
when a <code>continue</code> is in a nested loop, it will continue the loop
that directly contains it; a "labeled continue" can be used to continue
the containing loop instead.</p>

<p><code>break</code> and <code>continue</code> can be used in <code>while</code> loops and
<code>do..while</code> loops. They can also be used in <code>for</code> loops, which
are covered in the <localref href="control.4">next&nbsp;section</localref>. 
In <localref href="control.6"/>, we'll see that <code>break</code> can also be used to
break out of a <code>switch</code> statement.   A <code>break</code> can occur
inside an <code>if</code> statement, but only if the <code>if</code> statement
is nested inside a loop or inside a <code>switch</code> statement.
In that case, it does <b>not</b> mean
to break out of the <code>if</code>.  Instead, it breaks out of the loop or
<code>switch</code> statement that contains the <code>if</code> statement.
The same consideration applies to <code>continue</code> statements inside <code>ifs</code>.</p>

</subsection>
   
</section>