<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="control.6" title="The switch Statement">
   
<p><start><big>T</big>he second branching statement</start> in Java is the
<code>switch</code> statement, which is introduced in this section. The
<code>switch</code> statement is used far less often than the <code>if</code> statement, but it
is sometimes useful for expressing a certain type of multiway branch.</p>

   
<subsection id="control.6.1" title="The Basic switch Statement">

<p>A switch statement allows you to test the value of an expression and,
depending on that value, to jump directly to some location within the switch statement.
Only expressions of certain types can be used.  The value of the expression
can be one of the primitive integer types <ptype>int</ptype>,
<ptype>short</ptype>, or <ptype>byte</ptype>.
It can be the primitive <ptype>char</ptype> type.  
It can be <classname>String</classname>.
Or it can be an enum type (see <localref href="basics.3.4"/> for an introduction to enums).  
In particular, note that the expression <b>cannot</b> be a <ptype>double</ptype> or 
<ptype>float</ptype> value.  </p>

<p>The positions within a switch statement to which it
can jump are marked with <newword>case labels</newword> that take the form: 
"case&nbsp;<bnf>constant</bnf>:".  The <bnf>constant</bnf> here is a literal of
the same type as the expression in the <code>switch</code>.
A case label marks the position the
computer jumps to when the expression evaluates to the given <bnf>constant</bnf> value. 
You can also use the label "default:" in a <code>switch</code> statement; this provides a default jump point that
is used when the value of the expression is not listed in any case label.</p>

<p>A <code>switch</code> statement, as it is most often used, has the form:</p>

<pre>switch (<bnf>expression</bnf>) {
   case <bnf>constant-1</bnf>:
      <bnf>statements-1</bnf>
      break;
   case <bnf>constant-2</bnf>:
      <bnf>statements-2</bnf>
      break;
      .
      .   // (more cases)
      .
   case <bnf>constant-N</bnf>:
      <bnf>statements-N</bnf>
      break;
   default:  // optional default case
      <bnf>statements-(N+1)</bnf>
} // end of switch statement</pre>

<np>This has exactly the same effect as the following multiway <code>if</code> statement,
but the <code>switch</code> statement can be more efficient because the computer
can evaluate one expression and jump directly to the correct case, 
whereas in the <code>if</code> statement, the
computer must evaluate up to <code>N</code> expressions before it knows which set of
statements to execute:</np>

<pre>if (<bnf>expression</bnf> == <bnf>constant-1</bnf>) { // but use .equals for String!!
    <bnf>statements-1</bnf>
} 
else if (<bnf>expression</bnf> == <bnf>constant-2</bnf>) { 
    <bnf>statements-2</bnf>
} 
    .
    .
    .
else if (<bnf>expression</bnf> == <bnf>constant-N</bnf>) { 
    <bnf>statements-N</bnf>
} 
else {
    <bnf>statements-(N+1)</bnf>
}</pre>

<p>The <code>break</code> statements in the <code>switch</code> are not actually
required by the syntax of the <code>switch</code> statement. The effect of a
<code>break</code> is to make the computer jump past the end of the switch statement,
skipping over all the remaining cases.
If you leave out the break statement, the computer will just forge ahead after
completing one case and will execute the statements associated with the next
case label. This is rarely what you want, but it is legal. (I will note here&mdash;although 
you won't understand it until you get to the next chapter&mdash;that
inside a subroutine, the <code>break</code> statement is sometimes replaced by a
<code>return</code> statement, which terminates the subroutine as well as the switch.)</p>

<p>Note that you can leave out one of the groups of statements entirely
(including the <code>break</code>). You then have two case labels in a row,
containing two different constants. This just means that the computer will jump
to the same place and perform the same action for each of the two
constants.</p>

<p>Here is an example of a switch statement. This is not a useful example, but
it should be easy for you to follow. Note, by the way, that the constants in
the case labels don't have to be in any particular order, but they must
all be different:</p>

<pre>switch ( N ) {   // (Assume N is an integer variable.)
   case 1:
      System.out.println("The number is 1.");
      break;
   case 2:
   case 4:
   case 8:
      System.out.println("The number is 2, 4, or 8.");
      System.out.println("(That's a power of 2!)");
      break;
   case 3:
   case 6:
   case 9:
      System.out.println("The number is 3, 6, or 9.");
      System.out.println("(That's a multiple of 3!)");
      break;
   case 5:
      System.out.println("The number is 5.");
      break;
   default:
      System.out.println("The number is 7 or is outside the range 1 to 9.");
}</pre>

   
<p>The switch statement is pretty primitive as control structures go, and it's
easy to make mistakes when you use it. Java takes all its control structures
directly from the older programming languages C and C++. The switch statement
is certainly one place where the designers of Java should have introduced some
improvements.</p>

   
   
</subsection>

<subsection id="control.6.2" title="Menus and switch Statements">

<p>One application of <code>switch</code> statements is in processing menus. A menu
is a list of options. The user selects one of the options. The computer has to
respond to each possible choice in a different way. If the options are numbered
1, 2,&nbsp;&dots;, then the number of the chosen option can be used in a
<code>switch</code> statement to select the proper response.</p>

<p>In a command-line program, the menu can be presented as a numbered
list of options, and the user can choose an option by typing in its number.
Here is an example that could be used in a variation of the
<code>LengthConverter</code> example from the <localref href="control.5">previous
section</localref>:</p>

<pre>int optionNumber;   // Option number from menu, selected by user.
double measurement; // A numerical measurement, input by the user.
                    //    The unit of measurement depends on which
                    //    option the user has selected.
double inches;      // The same measurement, converted into inches.

/* Display menu and get user's selected option number. */

System.out.println("What unit of measurement does your input use?");
System.out.println();
System.out.println("         1.  inches");
System.out.println("         2.  feet");
System.out.println("         3.  yards");
System.out.println("         4.  miles");
System.out.println();
System.out.println("Enter the number of your choice: ");
optionNumber = TextIO.getlnInt();

/* Read user's measurement and convert to inches. */

switch ( optionNumber ) {
   case 1:
       System.out.println("Enter the number of inches: ");
       measurement = TextIO.getlnDouble();
       inches = measurement;
       break;          
   case 2:
       System.out.println("Enter the number of feet: ");
       measurement = TextIO.getlnDouble();
       inches = measurement * 12;
       break;          
   case 3:
       System.out.println("Enter the number of yards: ");
       measurement = TextIO.getlnDouble();
       inches = measurement * 36;
       break;          
   case 4:
       System.out.println("Enter the number of miles: ");
       measurement = TextIO.getlnDouble();
       inches = measurement * 12 * 5280;
       break;
   default:
       System.out.println("Error!  Illegal option number!  I quit!");
       System.exit(1);          
} // end switch

/* Now go on to convert inches to feet, yards, and miles... */</pre>

<np>This example could instead be written using a <classname>String</classname>
in the <code>switch</code> statement:</np>

<pre>String units;       // Unit of measurement, entered by user.
double measurement; // A numerical measurement, input by the user.
double inches;      // The same measurement, converted into inches.

/* Read the user's unit of measurement. */

System.out.println("What unit of measurement does your input use?");
System.out.print("Legal responses: inches, feet, yards, or miles : ");
units = TextIO.getln().toLowerCase();

/* Read user's measurement and convert to inches. */

System.out.print("Enter the number of " + units + ":  ");
measurement = TextIO.getlnDouble();

switch ( units ) {
   case "inches":
       inches = measurement;
       break;          
   case "feet":
       inches = measurement * 12;
       break;          
   case "yards":
       inches = measurement * 36;
       break;          
   case "miles":
       inches = measurement * 12 * 5280;
       break;
   default:
       System.out.println("Wait a minute!  Illegal unit of measure!  I quit!");
       System.exit(1);          
} // end switch</pre>

   
</subsection>

<subsection id="control.6.3" title="Enums in switch Statements">
   
<p>The type of the expression in a <code>switch</code> can be an enumerated
type.  In that case, the constants in the <code>case</code> labels must
be values from the enumerated type.  For example, suppose that the type of
the expression is the enumerated type <classname>Season</classname>
defined by</p>

<pre>enum Season { SPRING, SUMMER, FALL, WINTER }</pre>

<np>and that the expression in a <code>switch</code> statement is an expression
of type <classname>Season</classname>.  The constants in the case label must be chosen from among
the values <code>Season.SPRING</code>, <code>Season.SUMMER</code>, <code>Season.FALL</code>, or
<code>Season.WINTER</code>.  However, there is a quirk in the syntax:
when an enum  constant is used in a <code>case</code> label, only the simple name,
such as "<code>SPRING</code>" is used, not the full name, such as "<code>Season.SPRING</code>".
Of course, the computer already knows that the value in the <code>case</code> label
must belong to the enumerated type, since it can tell that from the type of expression
used, so there is really no need to specify the type name in the constant.  For example,
assuming that <code>currentSeason</code> is a variable of type <classname>Season</classname>,
then we could have the <code>switch</code> statement:</np>
  
<pre>switch ( currentSeason ) {
   case WINTER:    // ( NOT Season.WINTER ! )
      System.out.println("December, January, February");
      break;
   case SPRING:
      System.out.println("March, April, May");
      break;
   case SUMMER:
      System.out.println("June, July, August");
      break;
   case FALL:
      System.out.println("September, October, November");
      break;
}</pre>
</subsection>

<subsection id="control.6.4" title="Definite Assignment and switch Statements">
   
<p>As a somewhat more realistic example, the following <code>switch</code> statement
makes a random choice among three possible alternatives.  Recall that the
value of the expression <code>(int)(3*Math.random())</code> is one of the
integers 0, 1, or 2, selected at random with equal probability, so the
<code>switch</code> statement below will assign one of the values
<code>"Rock"</code>, <code>"Paper"</code>, <code>"Scissors"</code> to <code>computerMove</code>,
with probability 1/3 for each case:</p>

<pre>switch ( (int)(3*Math.random()) ) {
   case 0:
      computerMove = "Rock";
      break;
   case 1:
      computerMove = "Paper";
      break;
   case 2:
      computerMove = "Scissors";
      break;
}</pre>

<np>Now, this <code>switch</code> statement is perfectly OK, but suppose that we use it in the
following code segment:</np>
   
<pre><newcode>String computerMove;</newcode>
switch ( (int)(3*Math.random()) ) {
   case 0:
      computerMove = "Rock";
      break;
   case 1:
      computerMove = "Paper";
      break;
   case 2:
      computerMove = "Scissors";
      break;
}
<newcode>System.out.println("The computer's move is " + computerMove);</newcode>  // ERROR!</pre>

<np>Now there is a subtle error on the last line!  The problem here is due to
definite assignment, the idea that the Java compiler must be able to determine
that a variable has definitely been assigned a value before its value is used.
Definite assignment was introduced in <localref href="control.1.4"/>.
In this example, it's true that the three cases in the <code>switch</code>
cover all the possibilities, but the compiler is not smart enough to figure
that out; it just sees that there is an integer-valued expression in the <code>switch</code>
but not all possible integer values are covered by the given cases.
</np>

<p>A simple solution is to replace the final <code>case</code> in the <code>switch</code>
statement with <code>default</code>.  With a <code>default</code> case, all
possible values of the expression in the <code>switch</code> are certainly covered,
and the compiler knows that <code>computerMove</code> is definitely assigned
a value:</p>

<pre>String computerMove;
switch ( (int)(3*Math.random()) ) {
   case 0:
      computerMove = "Rock";
      break;
   case 1:
      computerMove = "Paper";
      break;
   <newcode>default</newcode>:
      computerMove = "Scissors";
      break;
}
System.out.println("The computer's move is " + computerMove);  // OK!</pre>


</subsection>

<subsection id="control.6.5" title="A New switch Statement Syntax">

<p>A new version of the <code>switch</code> statement has been added to the Java
language in Java&nbsp;14.  The new version uses <code>-&gt;</code> in place of a colon after
a <code>case</code>, and the code in a case is a single statement, possibly
a block statement consisting of several statements enclosed in braces.
No <code>break</code> statement is required, although one can be used to end a case
early.  This avoids the common error of having control accidently 
fall through from one case to the next because of an omitted <code>break</code>.
Furthermore, instead of allowing just one value per case label, a case
can take several values separated by commas.  Using the new syntax, the
first example in this section can be written as follows:
</p>


<pre>switch ( N ) {   // (Assume N is an integer variable.)
   case 1 -> System.out.println("The number is 1.");
   case 2, 4, 8 -> {
      System.out.println("The number is 2, 4, or 8.");
      System.out.println("(That's a power of 2!)");
   }
   case 3, 6, 9 -> {
      System.out.println("The number is 3, 6, or 9.");
      System.out.println("(That's a multiple of 3!)");
   }
   case 5 -> System.out.println("The number is 5.");
   default ->
      System.out.println("The number is 7 or is outside the range 1 to 9.");
}</pre>

<np>This seems to me to be a big improvement.  But the original <code>switch</code>
syntax is still available.</np>

<p>Along with the improved <code>switch</code>
statement, a new "<code>switch</code> expression" has been introduced.  Like any
expression, a <code>switch</code> expression computes and returns a single value.
The syntax is similar to a <code>switch</code> statement, but instead of a statement
in each <code>case</code>, there is an expression.  For example,</p>

<pre>String computerMove = switch ( (int)(3*Math.random()) ) {
    case 1 -> "Rock";
    case 2 -> "Paper";
    default -> "Scissors";
};</pre>

<np>A <code>switch</code> expression must always compute a value and therefore
will almost always have a <code>default</code> case.  The expression in a <code>case</code>
can be replaced by a block containing several statements; the value for that <code>case</code>
should then be specified by a <code>yield</code> statement (such as "<code>yield&nbsp;42;</code>")
rather than a <code>return</code> or <code>break</code> statement.</np>

</subsection>
   
</section>