<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossary SYSTEM "javanotes7.dtd" >
<glossary>
<gitem term="abstract class">A class that cannot be used to create objects, and that
exists only for the purpose of creating subclasses.  Abstract classes in Java are
defined using the modifier <code>abstract</code>.</gitem>
<gitem term="abstract data type (ADT)">A data type for which the possible values of the type
and the permissible operations on those values are specified, without specifying how
the values and operations are to be implemented.</gitem>
<gitem term="access specifier">A modifier used on a method definition or variable
specification that determines what classes can use that method or variable.
The access specifiers in Java are <code>public</code>, <code>protected</code>, and
<code>private</code>.  A method or variable that has no access specifier is said
to have "package" visibility.</gitem>
<gitem term="activation record">A data structure that contains all the information 
necessary to implement a subroutine call, including the values of parameters and local
variables of the subroutine and the return address to which the computer will return
when the subroutine ends.  Activation records are stored on a stack, which makes it
possible for several subroutine calls to be active at the same time.  This is particularly
important for recursion, where several calls to the same subroutine can be active
at the same time.</gitem>
<gitem term="actual parameter">A parameter in a subroutine call statement, whose value
will be passed to the subroutine when the call statement is executed.  Actual parameters
are also called "arguments".</gitem>
<gitem term="address">Each location in the computer's memory has an address, which is
a number that identifies that location.  Locations in memory are numbered sequentially.
In modern computers, each byte of memory has its own address.
Addresses are used when information is being stored into or retrieved from memory.</gitem>
<gitem term="algorithm">An unambiguous, step-by-step procedure for performing some task,
which is guaranteed to terminate after a finite number of steps.</gitem>
<gitem term="alpha color component">A component of a color that says how transparent or opaque
that color is.  The higher the alpha component, the more opaque the color.</gitem>
<gitem term="API">Application Programming Interface.  A specification of the interface
to a software package or "toolbox."  The API says what classes or subroutines are provided
in the toolbox and how to use them.</gitem>
<gitem term="applet">A type of Java program that is meant to run on a Web page in
a Web browser, as opposed to a stand-alone application.</gitem>
<gitem term="animation">An apparently moving picture created by rapidly showing a sequence of
still images, called frames, one after the other.  In Java, animations are often driven by <classname>Timer</classname>
objects; a new frame of the animation is shown each time the timer fires. </gitem>
<gitem term="antialiasing">Adjusting the color of pixels to reduce the "jagged" effect
that can occur when shapes and text are represented by pixels.  For antialiased drawing,
when the shape covers only part of a pixel, the color of the shape is blended with the
previous color of the pixel.  The degree of blending depends on how much of the pixel
is covered.</gitem>
<gitem term="array">A list of items, sequentially numbered.  Each item in the list can be
identified by its index, that is, its sequence number.  In Java, all the items in 
array must have the same type, called the base type of the array.  An array
is a random access data structure; that is, you can get directly at any item
in the array at any time.</gitem>
<gitem term="array type">A data type whose possible values are arrays.  If <classname>Type</classname>
is the name of a type, then <atype>Type[]</atype> is the array type for arrays that
have base type <classname>Type</classname>.</gitem>
<gitem term="assignment statement">A statement in a computer program that retrieves or 
computes a value and stores that value in a variable.  An assignment statement
in Java has the form: <bnf>variable-name</bnf> = <bnf>expression</bnf>;</gitem>
<gitem term="asynchronous event">An event that can occur at an unpredictable time, outside
the control of a computer program.  User input events, such as pressing a button on the
mouse, are asynchronous.</gitem>
<gitem term="ASCII">American Standard Code for Information Interchange.
A way of encoding characters using 7 bits for characters.  ASCII code
only supports 128 characters, with no accented letters, non-English alphabets, special symbols,
or ideograms for non-alphabetic languages such as Chinese.  Java uses the much larger and
more complete Unicode code for characters.</gitem>
<gitem term="base case">In a recursive algorithm, a simple case that is handled directly
rather than by applying the algorithm recursively.</gitem>
<gitem term="binary number">A number encoded as a sequence of zeros and ones.  A binary
number is represented in the "base&nbsp;2" in the same way that ordinary numbers are
represented in the "base&nbsp;10."</gitem>
<gitem term="binary tree">A linked data structure that is either empty or consists of a root
node that contains pointers to two smaller (possibly empty) binary trees.  The two smaller
binary trees are called the left subtree and the right subtree.</gitem>
<gitem term="bit">A single-digit binary number, which can be either 0 or 1.</gitem>
<gitem term="black box">A system or component of a system that can be used without understanding
what goes on inside the box.  A black box has an interface and an implementation.
A black box that is meant to be used as a component in a system is called a module.</gitem>
<gitem term="block">In Java programming, a sequence of statements enclosed between a pair
of braces, <code>{</code> and <code>}</code>.  Blocks are used to group several statements
into a single statement.  A block can also be empty, meaning that it contains no statements
at all and consists of just an empty pair of braces.</gitem>
<gitem term="blocking operation">An operation, such as reading data from a network connection,
is said to "block" if it has to wait for some event to occur.  A thread that performs a blocking
operation can be "blocked" until the required event occurs.  A thread cannot execute any
instructions while it is blocked.  Other threads in the same program, however, can continue
to run.</gitem>
<gitem term="blocking queue">A queue in which the dequeue operation will block if the
queue is empty, until an item is added to the queue.  If the blocking queue has a
limited capacity, the enqueue operation can also block, if the queue is full.</gitem>
<gitem term="bottom-up design">An approach to software design in which you start by designing
basic components of the system, then combine them into more complex components, and so on.</gitem>
<gitem term="BufferedImage">A class representing "off-screen canvases," that is, images
that are stored in the computer's memory and that can be used for drawing images off-screen.</gitem>
<gitem term="branch">A control structure that allows the computer to choose among
two or more different courses of action.  Java has two branch statements:  <i>if</i>
statements and <i>switch</i> statements.</gitem>
<gitem term="byte">A unit of memory that consists of eight bits.  One byte of memory can
hold an eight-bit binary number.</gitem>
<gitem term="bytecode">&leftquote;Java bytecode" is the usual name for the machine language of
the Java Virtual Machine.  Java programs are compiled into Java bytecode, which can
then be executed by the JVM.</gitem>
<gitem term="charset">A particular encoding of character data into binary form.  Examples
include UTF-8 and ISO-8859-1.</gitem>
<gitem term="checked exception">An exception in Java that must be handled, either by
a <code>try..catch</code> statement or by a <code>throws</code> clause on the method
that can throw he exception.  Failure to handle a checked exception in one way or
the other is a syntax error.</gitem>
<gitem term="class">The basic unit of programming in Java.  A class is a collection 
of static and non-static methods and variables.  Static members of a class are part of
the class itself; non-static, or "instance," members constitute a blueprint for
creating objects, which are then said to "belong" to the class.</gitem>
<gitem term="class variables and class methods">Alternative terms for "static variables" and
"static methods", which are part of the class itself rather than of objects.</gitem>
<gitem term="client/server">A model of network communication in which a "server" waits
at a known address on the network for connection requests that are sent to the server
by "clients."  This is the basic model for communication using the TCP/IP protocol.</gitem>
<gitem term="command-line interface">A way of interacting with the computer in which
the user types in commands to the computer and the computer responds to
each command.</gitem>
<gitem term="comment">In a computer program, text that is ignored by the computer.  Comments
are for human readers, to help them understand the program.</gitem>
<gitem term="compiler">A computer program that translates programs written in some
computer language (generally a high-level language) into programs written in machine
language.</gitem>
<gitem term="component">General term for a visual element of a GUI, such as a window,
button, or menu.  A component is represented in Java by an object belonging to a
subclass of the class <code>java.awt.Component</code>.</gitem>
<gitem term="constructor">A special kind of subroutine in a class whose purpose is
to construct objects belonging to that class.  A constructor is called using
the <code>new</code> operator, and is not considered to be a "method."</gitem>
<gitem term="container">A component, such as a <classname>JPanel</classname>, that
can contain other GUI components.  Containers have <code>add()</code> methods that
can be used to add components.</gitem>
<gitem term="contract of a method">The semantic component of the method's interface.
The contract specifies the responsibilities of the method and of the caller of the
method.  It says how to use the method correctly and specifies the task that the method
will perform when it is used correctly.  The contract of a method should be fully specified
by its Javadoc comment.</gitem>
<gitem term="control structure">A program structure such as an <i>if</i> statement
or a <i>while</i> loop that affects the flow of control in a program (that is, the
order in which the instructions in the program are executed).</gitem>
<gitem term="CPU">Central Processing Unit.  The CPU is the part of
the program that actually performs calculations and carries out programs.</gitem>
<gitem term="data structure">An organized collection of data, that can be treated
as a unit in a program.</gitem>
<gitem term="deadlock">A situation in which several threads hang indefinitely, 
for example because each of them is waiting for some resource that is locked by one of the
other threads.</gitem>
<gitem term="default method">A method in a Java 8 interface that has an implementation.
The default implementation is used in any class that implements the interface but
does not override the method.  Default methods are marked with the reserved word
<code>default</code>.  Not supported in Java&nbsp;7.</gitem>
<gitem term="default package">The unnamed package.  A class that does not declare itself
to be in a named package is considered to be in the default package.</gitem>
<gitem term="definite assignment">Occurs at a particular point in a program if
it is definitely true that a given variable must have been assigned a value
before that point in the program.  It is only legal to use the value of a local variable if
that variable has "definitely" been assigned a value before it is used.  For this to
be true, the compiler must be able to verify that <b>every</b> path through the program
from the declaration of the variable to its use must pass through a statement that
assigns a value to that variable.</gitem>
<gitem term="deprecated">Considered to be obsolete, but still available for backwards
compatibility.  A deprecated Java class or method is still part of the Java language,
but it is not advisable to use it in new code.  Deprecated items might be removed in
future versions of Java.</gitem>
<gitem term="dialog box">A window that is dependent on another window, called its parent.
Dialog boxes are usually popped up to get information from the user or to display a
message to the user.  Dialog boxes in the Swing API are represented by objects of type
<classname>JDialog</classname>.</gitem>
<gitem term="distributed computing">A kind of parallel processing in which several
computers, connected by a network, work together to solve a problem.</gitem>
<gitem term="dummy parameter">Identifier that is used in a subroutine definition
to stand for the value of an actual parameter that will be passed to the subroutine
when the subroutine is called.  Dummy parameters are also called "formal parameters"
(or sometimes just "parameters," when the term "argument" is used instead of actual
parameter).</gitem>
<gitem term="enum">Enumerated type.  A type that is defined by listing every possible
value of that type.  An enum type in Java is a class, and the possible values of the
type are objects.</gitem>
<gitem term="event">In GUI programming, something that happens outside the control
of the program, such as a mouse click, and that the program must respond to when
it occurs.</gitem>
<gitem term="exception">An error or exceptional condition that is outside the normal
flow of control of a program.  In Java, an exception can be represented by an object
of type <classname>Throwable</classname> that can be caught and handled in a 
<code>try..catch</code> statement.</gitem>
<gitem term="fetch-and-execute cycle">The process by which the CPU executes machine language
programs.  It fetches (that is, reads) an instruction from memory and carries out
(that is, executes) the instruction, and it repeats this over and over in a continuous
cycle.</gitem>
<gitem term="flag">A boolean value that is set to true to indicate that some condition
or event is true.  A single bit in a binary number can also be used as a flag.</gitem>
<gitem term="formal parameter">Another term for "dummy parameter."</gitem>
<gitem term="frame">One of the images that make up an animation.  Also used as
another name for activation record.</gitem>
<gitem term="function">A subroutine that returns a value.</gitem>
<gitem term="garbage collection">The automatic process of reclaiming memory that is
occupied by objects that can no longer be accessed.</gitem>
<gitem term="generic programming">Writing code that will work with various types
of data, rather than with just a single type of data.  The Java Collection Framework,
and classes that use similar techniques, are examples of generic programming in Java.</gitem>
<gitem term="getter">An instance method in a class that is used to read the value
of some property of that class.  Usually the property is just the value of some
instance variable.  By convention, a getter is named <code>getXyz()</code> where
<code>xyz</code> is the name of the property.</gitem>
<gitem term="global variable">Another name for member variable, emphasizing the fact
that a member variable in a class exists outside the methods of that class.</gitem>
<gitem term="graphics context">The data and methods necessary for
drawing to some particular destination.  A graphics context in Java is an object
belonging to the <classname>Graphics</classname> class.</gitem>
<gitem term="GUI">Graphical User Interface.  The modern way of interacting with a computer,
in which the computer displays interface components such as buttons and menus on a screen
and the user interacts with them&mdash;for example by clicking on them with a mouse.</gitem>
<gitem term="hash table">A data structure optimized for efficient search, insertion, and deletion
of objects.  A hash table consists of an array of locations, and the location in which
an object is stored is determined by that object's "hash code," an integer that can be
efficiently computed from the contents of the object.</gitem>
<gitem term="heap">The section of the computer's memory in which objects are stored.</gitem>
<gitem term="high level language">A programming language, such as Java, that is convenient
for human programmers but that has to be translated into machine language before it
can be executed.</gitem>
<gitem term="HSB">A color system in which colors are specified by three numbers (in Java, real
numbers in the range 0.0 to 1.0) giving the hue, saturation, and brightness.</gitem>
<gitem term="IDE">Integrated Development Environment.  A programming environment with
a graphical user interface that integrates tools for creating, compiling, and executing
programs.</gitem>
<gitem term="identifier">A sequence of characters that can be used as a name in a program.
Identifiers are used as names of variables, methods, and classes.</gitem>
<gitem term="index">The position number of one item in an array.</gitem>
<gitem term="implementation">The inside of a black box, such as the code
that defines a subroutine.</gitem>
<gitem term="immutable object">An immutable object cannot be modified after it is constructed,
because all of its instance variables are <code>final</code>.</gitem>
<gitem term="infinite loop">A loop that never ends, because its continuation condition
always evaluates to <code>true</code>.</gitem>
<gitem term="inheritence">The fact that one class can extend another.  It then inherits
the data and behavior of the class that it extends.</gitem>
<gitem term="instance of a class">An object that belongs to that class (or a subclass of that class).
An object belongs to a class in this sense when the class is used as a template for the object when
the object is created by a constructor defined in that class.</gitem>
<gitem term="instance method">A non-static method in a class and hence a method 
in any object that is an instance of that class.</gitem>
<gitem term="instance variable">A non-static variable in a class and hence a variable 
in any object that is an instance of that class.</gitem>
<gitem term="interface">As a general term, how to use a black box such as a subroutine.
Knowing the interface tells you nothing about what goes on inside the box.  "Interface"
is also a reserved word in Java; in this sense, an <code>interface</code> is a type
that specifies one or more abstract methods.  An object that implements the <code>interface</code>
must provide definitions for those methods.
</gitem>
<gitem term="interpreter">A computer program that executes program written in some
computer language by reading instructions from the program, one-by-one, and carrying each
one out (by translating it into equivalent machine language instructions).</gitem>
<gitem term="I/O">Input/Output, the way a computer program communicates with the
rest of the world, such as by displaying data to the user, getting information from the user,
reading and writing files, and sending and receiving data over a network.</gitem>
<gitem term="iterator">An object associated with a collection, such a list or a set,
that can be used to traverse that collection.  The iterator will visit each member of
the collection in turn.</gitem>
<gitem term="Java Collection Framework (JCF)">A set of standard classed that implement
generic data structures, including <classname>ArrayList</classname> and <classname>TreeSet</classname>,
for example.</gitem>
<gitem term="JavaFX">The new toolkit for GUI applications, which becomes the preferred approach
to GUI programming in Java&nbsp;8.  JavaFX is not covered in this book.</gitem>
<gitem term="JDK">Java Development Kit.  Basic software that supports both compiling
and running Java programs.  A JDK includes a command-line programming environment as 
well as a JRE.  You need a JDK if you want to compile Java source code, as well as
executing pre-compiled programs.</gitem>
<gitem term="JRE">Java Runtime Environment.  Basic software that supports running
standard Java programs that have already been compiled.  A JRE includes a Java
Virtual Machine and all the standard Java classes.</gitem>
<gitem term="just-in-time compiler">A kind of combination interpreter/compiler that
compiles parts of a program as it interprets them.  This allows subsequent executions
of the same parts of the program to be executed more quickly than they were the first
time.  This can result is greatly increased speed of execution.  Modern JVMs use 
a just-in-time compiler.</gitem>
<gitem term="JVM">Java Virtual Machine.  The imaginary computer whose machine language
is Java bytecode.  Also used to refer to computer programs that act as interpreters for
programs written in bytecode; to run Java programs on your computer, you need a JVM.</gitem>
<gitem term="layout manager">An object whose function is to lay out the components
in a container, that is, to set their sizes and locations.  Different types of layout
managers implement different policies for laying out components.</gitem>
<gitem term="linked data structure">A collection of data consisting of a number of objects
that are linked together by pointers which are stored in instance variables of the objects.
Examples include linked lists and binary trees.</gitem>
<gitem term="linked list">A linked data structure in which nodes are linked together by pointers
into a linear chain.</gitem>
<gitem term="listener">In GUI programming, an object that can be registered to be notified
when events of some given type occur.  The object is said to "listen" for the events.</gitem>
<gitem term="literal">A sequence of characters that is typed in a program to represent
a constant value.  For example, <code>'A'</code> is a literal that represents the
constant <ptype>char</ptype> value, A, when it appears in a Java program.</gitem>
<gitem term="location (in memory)">The computer's memory is made up of a sequence of
locations.  These locations are sequentially numbered, and the number that identifies
a particular location is called the address of that location.</gitem>
<gitem term="local variable">A variable declared within a method, for use only inside
that method.  A variable declared inside a block
is valid from the point where it is declared until the end of
block in which the declaration occurs.</gitem>
<gitem term="loop">A control structure that allows a sequence of instructions to
be executed repeatedly.  Java has three kinds of loops:  <i>for</i> loops, <i>while</i>
loops, and <i>do</i> loops</gitem>
<gitem term="loop control variable">A variable in a <i>for</i> loop whose value is modified
as the loop is executed and is checked to determine whether or not to end the loop.</gitem>
<gitem term="machine language">A programming language consisting of instructions that
can be executed directed by a computer.  Instructions in machine language are
encoded as binary numbers.  Each type of computer has its own machine
language.  Programs written in other languages must be translated into a computer's machine
language before they can be executed by that computer.</gitem>
<gitem term="main memory">Programs and data can be stored in a computer's main memory,
where they are available to the CPU.  Other forms of memory, such as a disk drive,
also store information, but only main memory is directly accessible to the CPU.
Programs and data from a disk drive have to be copied into main memory before they can be used
by the CPU.</gitem>
<gitem term="map">An associative array; a data structure that associates an object from some
collection to each object in some set.  In Java, maps are
represented by the generic interface <classname>Map&lt;T,S&gt;</classname></gitem>
<gitem term="member variable">A variable defined in a class but not inside a method,
 as opposed to a local variable, which is defined inside some method.</gitem>
<gitem term="memory">Memory in a computer is used to hold programs and data.</gitem>
<gitem term="method">Another term for <i>subroutine</i>, used in the context of
object-oriented programming.  A method is a subroutine that is contained in a class or in an object.</gitem>
<gitem term="module">A component of a larger system that interacts with
the rest of the system in a simple, well-defined, straightforward manner.</gitem>
<gitem term="multitasking">Performing multiple tasks at once, either by switching rapidly
back and forth from one task to another or by literally working on multiple tasks at
the same time.</gitem>
<gitem term="multiprocessing">Multitasking in which more than one processor is used,
so that multiple tasks can literally be worked on at the same time.</gitem>
<gitem term="mutual exclusion">Prevents two threads from accessing the same resource
at the same time.  In Java, this only applies to threads that access the resource
in <code>synchronized</code> methods or <code>synchronized</code> statements.
Mutual exclusion can prevent race conditions but introduces the possibility of deadlock.</gitem>
<gitem term="MVC pattern">The Model/View/Controller pattern, a strategy for dividing responsibility
in a GUI component.  The model is the data for the component.  The view is the visual presentation
of the component on the screen. The controller is responsible for reacting to events by 
changing the model.  According to the MVC pattern, these responsibilities should be handled
by different objects.</gitem>
<gitem term="NaN">Not a Number.  <code>Double.NaN</code> is a special value of type
<ptype>double</ptype> that represents an undefined or illegal value.</gitem>
<gitem term="node">Common term for one of the objects in a linked data structure.</gitem>
<gitem term="null">A special pointer value that means "not pointing to anything."</gitem>
<gitem term="numerical analysis">The field that studies algorithms that use approximations,
such as real numbers, and the errors that can result from such approximation.</gitem>
<gitem term="off-by-one error">A common type of error in which one too few or one
too many items are processed, often because counting is not being handled correctly
or because the processing stops too soon or continues too long for some other reason.</gitem>
<gitem term="object">An entity in a computer program that can have data (variables) and
behaviors (methods).  An object in Java must be created using some class as a template.
The class of an object determines what variables and methods it contains.</gitem>
<gitem term="object type">A type whose values are objects, as opposed to primitive types.
Classes and interfaces are object types.</gitem>
<gitem term="OOP">Object-Oriented Programming. An approach to the design and implementation
of computer programs in which classes and objects are created to represent concepts and
entities and their interactions.</gitem>
<gitem term="operating system">The basic software that is always running on a computer,
without which it would not be able to function.  Examples include Linux, Mac&nbsp;OS, and
Windows Vista.</gitem>
<gitem term="operator">A symbol such as "+", "&lt;=", or "++" that represents
an operation that can be applied to one or more values in an expression.</gitem>
<gitem term="overloading (of operators)">The fact that the same operator can be used with
different types of data.  For example, the "+" operator can be applied to both numbers
and strings.</gitem>
<gitem term="overloading (of method names)">The fact that several methods that
are defined in the same class can have the same name, as long as they have different signatures.</gitem>
<gitem term="overriding">Redefining in a subclass.  When a subclass provides a new definition
of a method that is inherited from a superclass, the new definition is said to override the 
original definition.</gitem>
<gitem term="package">In Java, a named collection of related classes and sub-packages, such as
<code>java.awt</code> and <code>javax.swing</code>.</gitem>
<gitem term="parallel processing">When several tasks are being performed simultaneously, either
by multiple processors or by one processor that switches back and forth among
the tasks.</gitem>
<gitem term="parameter">Used to provide information to a subroutine when that subroutine
is called.  Values of "actual parameters" in the subroutine call statement are
assigned to the "dummy parameters" in the subroutine definition before the code
in the subroutine is executed.</gitem>
<gitem term="parameterized type">A type such as <classname>ArrayList&lt;String&gt;</classname>
that includes one or more type parameters (<classname>String</classname> in the example).</gitem>
<gitem term="parsing">Determining the syntactical structure of a string in some language.
To parse a string is to determine whether the string is legal according to the grammar of
the language, and if so, how it can be created using the rules of the grammar.
</gitem>
<gitem term="partially full array">An array that is used to store varying numbers of items.
A partially full array can be represented as a normal array plus a counter to keep track
of how many items are actually stored.</gitem>
<gitem term="pixel">A "picture element" on the screen or in an image.  A picture consists of
rows and columns of pixels.  The color of each pixel can be individually set.</gitem>
<gitem term="polymorphism">The fact that the meaning of a call to an instance method
can depend on the actual type of the object that is used to make the call at run time.
That is, if <code>var</code> is a variable of object type, then the method that is called
by a statement such as <code>var.action()</code> depends on the type of the object to which
<code>var</code> refers when the statement is executed at run time, not on the type of
variable <code>var</code>.</gitem>
<gitem term="pointer">A value that represents an address in the computer's memory, and hence
can be thought of as "pointing" to the location that has that address.  A variable in Java can never hold
an object; it can only hold a pointer to the location where the object is stored.
A pointer is also called a "reference."</gitem>
<gitem term="pragmatics">Rules of thumb that describe what it means to write a
<i>good</i> program.  For example, style rules and guidelines about how to structure
a program are part of the pragmatics of a programming language.</gitem>
<gitem term="precedence">The precedence of operators determines the order in which
they are applied, when several operators occur in an expression, in the absence of parentheses.</gitem>
<gitem term="precondition">A condition that must be true at some point in the execution of a program,
in order for the program to proceed correctly from that point.  A precondition of a subroutine
is something that must be true when the subroutine is called, in order for the subroutine to
function properly.  Subroutine preconditions are often restrictions on the values of the actual
parameters that can be passed into the subroutine.</gitem>
<gitem term="priority queue">A data structure representing a collection of items where each item
has a "priority." A priority queue has operations <i>add</i> and <i>remove</i>.  Items
can be added in any order, but the <i>remove</i> operation always removes an item of
minimal priority.  (Some version of priority queue use maximum instead of minimum priority.)</gitem>
<gitem term="postcondition">A condition that is known to be true at some point in the execution
of a program, as a result of the computation that has come before that point.  A postcondition
of a subroutine is something that must be true after the subroutine finishes its execution.
A postcondition of a function often describe the return value of the function.</gitem>
<gitem term="primitive type">One of the eight basic built-in data types in Java, <ptype>double</ptype>,
<ptype>float</ptype>, <ptype>long</ptype>, <ptype>int</ptype>, <ptype>short</ptype>,
<ptype>byte</ptype>, <ptype>boolean</ptype>, and <ptype>char</ptype>.  A variable of
primitive type holds an actual value, as opposed to a pointer to that value.</gitem>
<gitem term="priority of a thread">An integer associated with a thread that can affect the
order in which threads are executed.  A thread with greater priority is executed in preference
to a thread with lower priority.</gitem>
<gitem term="producer/consumer">A classic pattern in parallel programming in which
one or more producers produce items that are consumed by one or more consumers,
and the producers and consumers are meant to run in parallel.  The problem is to get
items safely and efficiently from the producers to the consumers.  In Java, the
producer/consumer pattern is implemented by blocking queues.</gitem>
<gitem term="program">A set of instructions to be carried out by a computer, written
in an appropriate programming language.  Used as a
verb, it means to create such a set of instructions.</gitem>
<gitem term="programming language">A language that can be used to write programs for a
computer.  Programming languages range in complexity from machine language to high-level
languages such as Java.</gitem>
<gitem term="protocol">A specification of what constitutes legal communication in a give
context. A protocol specifies the format of legal messages, when they can be sent,
what kind of reply is expected, and so on.</gitem>
<gitem term="pseudocode">Informal specification of algorithms, expressed in language that
is closer to English than an actual programming language, and usually without filling in
every detail of the procedure.</gitem>
<gitem term="queue">A data structure consisting of a list of items,
where items can only be added at one end and removed at
the opposite end of the list.</gitem>
<gitem term="race condition">A source of possible errors in parallel programming, where
one thread can cause an error in another thread by changing some aspect of the state of 
the program that the second thread is depending on (such as the value of variable).</gitem>
<gitem term="RAM">Random Access Memory.  This term is often used as a synonym for the
main memory of a computer.  Technically, however, it means memory in which all 
locations are equally accessible at any given time.  The term also implies that
data can be written to the memory as well as read from it.</gitem>
<gitem term="recursion">Defining something in terms of itself.  In particular, a
recursive subroutine is one that calls itself, either directly, or indirectly through a
chain of other subroutines.  Recursive algorithms work by reducing a complex problem into
smaller problems which can be solved either directly or by applying the same algorithm "recursively."</gitem>
<gitem term="RGB">A color system in which colors are specified by three numbers (in Java, integers
in the range 0 to 255) giving the red, green, and blue components of the color.</gitem>
<gitem term="reference">Another term for "pointer."</gitem>
<gitem term="return type of a function">The type of value that is returned by that function.</gitem>
<gitem term="reserved word">A sequence of characters that looks like an identifier
but can't be used as an identifier because it has a special meaning in the language.
For example, <code>class</code>, <code>public</code>, and <code>if</code> are reserved
words in Java.</gitem>
<gitem term="resource">An image, sound, text, or other data file that is part of a program.
Resource files for Java programs are stored on the same class path where the compiled class
files for the program are stored.</gitem>
<gitem term="robust program">A program is robust if it is not only correct, but also is
capable of handling errors such as a non-existent file or a failed network connection
in a reasonable way.</gitem>
<gitem term="set">A collection of objects which contains no duplicates.  In Java, sets are
represented by the generic interface <classname>Set&lt;T&gt;</classname></gitem>
<gitem term="scope">The region in a program where the declaration of an identifier is
valid.</gitem>
<gitem term="semantics">Meaning.  The semantics rules of a language determine the
meaning of strings of symbols (such as sentences or statements) in that language.</gitem>
<gitem term="sentinel value">A special value that marks the end of a sequence of data
values, to indicate the end of the data.</gitem>
<gitem term="setter">An instance method in a class that is used to set the value
of some property of that class.  Usually the property is just the value of some
instance variable.  By convention, a setter is named <code>setXyz()</code> where
<code>xyz</code> is the name of the property.</gitem>
<gitem term="signature of a method">The name of the method, the number of formal
parameters in its definition, and the type of each formal parameter.  Method signatures
are the information needed by a compiler to tell which method is being called by
a given subroutine call statement.</gitem>
<gitem term="socket">An abstraction representing one end of a connection between 
two computers on a network.  A socket represents a logical connection between computer
programs, not a physical connection between computers.</gitem>
<gitem term="stack">A data structure consisting of a list of items where items can only be added and removed at
one end of the list, which is known as the "top" of the stack.
Adding an item to a stack is called "pushing," and removing
an item is called "popping."  The term stack also refers to the stack of activation records
that is used to implement subroutine calls.</gitem>
<gitem term="standard input">The standard source from which a program reads input data.  It is 
represented by the object <code>System.in</code>.  Usually, standard input comes from text typed
by the user, but standard input can be "redirected" to read from another source, such as a file,
instead.</gitem>
<gitem term="standard output">The standard destination to which a program writes output text.  It is 
represented by the object <code>System.out</code>.  Usually, standard output is displayed to
the user, but standard output can be "redirected" to write to another destination, such as a file,
instead.  There is also an object <code>System.err</code> that is meant for writing error messages.</gitem>
<gitem term="state machine">A model of computation where an abstract "machine" can be
in any of some finite set of different states.  The behavior of the machine depends on
its state, and the state can change in response to inputs or events.  The basic logical
structure of a GUI program can often be represented as a state machine.</gitem>
<gitem term="step-wise refinement">A technique for developing an algorithm by starting
with a general outline of the procedure, often expressed in pseudocode, and then
gradually filling in the details.</gitem>
<gitem term="stream">An abstraction representing a source of input data or a destination
for output data.  Java has four basic stream classes representing input and output
of character and binary data.  These classes form the foundation for Java's
input/output API.</gitem>
<gitem term="source code">Text written in a high-level programming language, which must
be translated into a machine language such as Java bytecode before it can be executed by
a computer.</gitem>
<gitem term="subclass">A class that extends another class, directly or indirectly, and
therefore inherits its data and behaviors.  The first class is said to be a subclass
of the second.</gitem>
<gitem term="subroutine">A sequence of program instructions that have been grouped together
and given a name.  The name can then be used to "call" the subroutine.  Subroutines are
also called <i>methods</i> in the context of object-oriented programming.</gitem>
<gitem term="subroutine call statement">A statement in a program that calls a subroutine.
When a subroutine call statement is executed, the computer executes the code that is
inside the subroutine.</gitem>
<gitem term="super">A special variable, automatically defined in any instance method,
that refers to the object that contains the method, but considered as belonging to
the superclass of the class in which the method definition occurs.
<code>super</code> gives access to members of the superclass that are hidden by
members of the same name in the subclass.</gitem>
<gitem term="syntax">Grammar.  The syntax rules of a language determine what strings of symbols 
are legal&mdash;that is, grammatical&mdash;in that language.</gitem>
<gitem term="TCP/IP">Protocols that are used for network communication on the Internet.</gitem>
<gitem term="this">A special variable, automatically defined in any instance method,
that refers to the object that contains the method.</gitem>
<gitem term="thread">An abstraction representing a sequence of instructions to be
executed one after the other.  It is possible for a computer to execute several threads
in parallel.</gitem>
<gitem term="thread pool">A collection of "worker threads" that are available to perform tasks.
As tasks become available, they are assigned to threads in the pool.  A thread
pool is often used with a blocking queue that holds the tasks.</gitem>
<gitem term="top-down design">An approach to software design in which you start with the
problems, as a whole, subdivide it into smaller problems, divide those into even smaller
problems, and so on, until you get to problems that can be solved directly.</gitem>
<gitem term="type">Specifies some specific kind of data values.  For example, the type
<ptype>int</ptype> specifies integer data values that can be represented as 32-bit binary numbers.  In Java,
a type can be a primitive type, a class names, or an interface name.  Type names are used to
specify the types of variables, of dummy parameters in subroutines, and of return values of subroutines.</gitem>
<gitem term="type cast">Forces the conversion of a value of one type into another type.
For example, in <code>(int)(6*Math.random())</code>, the <code>(int)</code> is a type-cast
operation that converts the <ptype>double</ptype> value <code>(6*Math.random())</code> into
an integer by discarding the fractional part of the real number.</gitem>
<gitem term="Unicode">A way of encoding characters as binary numbers.  The Unicode character
set includes characters used in many languages, not just English.  Unicode is the character
set that is used internally by Java.</gitem>
<gitem term="URL">Universal Resource Locator; an address for a resource on the Internet, such as a web page.</gitem>
<gitem term="variable">A named memory location (or sequence of locations)
that can be used to store data.  A variable is created in a program, and a name is assigned
to the variable, in a variable declaration
statement.  The name can then be used in that program to refer to the memory
location, or to the data stored in that memory location, depending on context.  
In Java, a variable has a <i>type</i>, which specifies what kind of data it can hold.</gitem>
<gitem term="wrapper class">A class such as <classname>Double</classname> or <classname>Integer</classname>
that makes it possible to "wrap" a primitive type value in an object belonging to the wrapper class.
This allows primitive type values to be used in contexts were objects are required, such as with
the Java Collection Framework.</gitem>
<gitem term="XML">eXtensible Markup Language.  A very common 
and well-supported standard syntax for creating text-based 
data-representation languages.</gitem>
</glossary>
