<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface SYSTEM "javanotes8.dtd">

<preface>
<p><start><big>I</big>ntroduction to Programming Using Java</start> is a free
introductory computer programming textbook that uses Java as the language of
instruction.  It is suitable for use in an introductory programming course
and for people who are trying to learn programming on their own. There are
no prerequisites beyond a general familiarity with the ideas of computers and
programs.  There is enough material for a full year of college-level
programming.  Chapters 1 through 7 can be used as a textbook in a one-semester
college-level course or in a year-long high school course.  The remaining
chapters can be covered in a second course.</p>

<p>The Eighth Edition of the book covers Java&nbsp;8, and it uses
JavaFX&nbsp;8 for GUI programming.  Although later
versions of Java have been released, I have no plans to cover them
in this textbook.  (However, all sample programs and exercise solutions
have been compiled using Java&nbsp;10 as well as Java&nbsp;8.)</p>
   
<p>The home web site for this book is
<a href="http://math.hws.edu/javanotes/">http://math.hws.edu/javanotes8/</a>.
The page at that address contains links for downloading a copy of
the web site and for downloading PDF versions of the book.
The web site&mdash;and the web site download&mdash;includes source code for the sample programs that are
discussed in the text, answers to end-of-chapter quizzes and a discussion
and solution for each end-of-chapter exercise.  Readers are encouraged
to download the source code for the examples and to read and run the
programs as they read the book.  Readers are also strongly encouraged
to read the exercise solutions if they want to get the most out of this book.</p>


<p>In style, this is a textbook rather than a tutorial. That is, it
concentrates on explaining concepts rather than giving step-by-step
how-to-do-it guides.
I have tried to use a conversational writing style that
might be closer to classroom lecture than to a typical textbook. This is
certainly not a Java reference book, and it is not a
comprehensive survey of all the features of Java. It is <b>not</b> written as
a quick introduction to Java for people who already know another programming
language. Instead, it is directed mainly towards people who are learning
programming for the first time, and it is as much about general programming
concepts as it is about Java in particular. I believe that <i>Introduction to
Programming using Java</i> is fully competitive with the conventionally
published, printed programming textbooks that are available on the market.
(Well, all right, I'll confess that I think it's better.)</p>

<p>There are several approaches to teaching Java. One approach uses
graphical user interface programming from the very beginning. Some people
believe that object oriented programming should also be emphasized from the
very beginning. This is <b>not</b> the approach that I take. The approach that I favor
starts with the more basic building blocks of programming and builds from
there. After an introductory chapter,
I cover procedural programming in Chapters 2, 3, and&nbsp;4.
Object-oriented programming is introduced in Chapter&nbsp;5. Chapter&nbsp;6
covers the closely related topic of event-oriented programming and
graphical user interfaces. Arrays are introduced in Chapter&nbsp;3 with a full treatment in Chapter&nbsp;7.
Chapter&nbsp;8 is a short chapter that marks a turning point in the book, moving beyond the
fundamental ideas of programming to cover more advanced topics.
Chapter&nbsp;8 is about writing robust, correct, and efficient programs.
Chapters&nbsp;9 and 10 cover recursion and data structures, including generic programming and the Java Collection
Framework.  Chapter&nbsp;11 is about files and networking.  Chapter&nbsp;12
covers threads and parallel processing.  Finally,
Chapter&nbsp;13 returns to the topic of graphical user interface programming
to cover some of JavaFX's more advanced capabilities.</p>

<break/>

<p>The biggest change from the seventh edition of this textbook is a switch from
Swing to JavaFX for GUI programming.  With just a few exceptions in code that
the user is not meant to read, all example code and exercises use JavaFX.
(Unfortunately, even as I was working on the new edition, the future of JavaFX
has become unclear as Oracle has announced that it will not be included as
part of the standard download of JDK&nbsp;11 and later; however, it will
still be available to be downloaded and installed separately.)
The eighth edition also incorporates some features that were introduced
in Java&nbsp;8: lambda expressions and the stream API.  Lambda expressions are
covered fairly early, as part of the material on subroutines in Chapter&nbsp;4.
They are used extensively with JavaFX in Chapter&nbsp;6 and Chapter&nbsp;13, as
well as with the stream API, which is introduced in Section&nbsp;10.6.
Aside from these major changes, there are small improvements throughout,
such as a short discussion of loop invariants and class invariants in
Section&nbsp;8.2, increased coverage of Java's higher level concurrency
support in Chapter&nbsp;12, and the consistent use of factory methods like
<code>Integer.valueOf(n)</code> in preference to constructors.</p>

<break/>
   

<p>The seventh edition of <i>Introduction to Programming using Java</i> is available on line at
<a href="http://math.hws.edu/javanotes/">http://math.hws.edu/javanotes/</a>.  (Once a final version
of the eighth edition is released, it will replace the seventh edition at that address.)
The first version of the book was written in 1996, and there have
been several editions since then.  All editions are archived (at least until my retirement) 
at the following Web addresses:</p>
   
<ul>
<li>First edition: <a href=
"http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes1/">http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes1/</a> (Covers Java 1.0.)</li>
<li>Second edition: <a href=
"http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes2/">http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes2/</a> (Covers Java 1.1.)</li>
<li>Third edition: <a href=
"http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes3/">http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes3/</a> (Covers Java 1.1.)</li>
<li>Fourth edition: <a href=
"http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes4/">http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes4/</a> (Covers Java 1.4.)</li>
<li>Fifth edition: <a href=
"http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes5/">http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes5/</a> (Covers Java 5.0.)</li>
<li>Sixth edition: <a href=
"http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes6/">http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes6/</a> (Covers Java 5.0, with a bit of 6.0.)</li>
<li>Seventh edition: <a href=
"http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes7/">http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes7/</a> (Covers Java 7.)</li>
<li>Eighth edition: <a href=
"http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes8/">http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/javanotes8/</a> (Covers Java 8.)</li>
</ul>
   

<p><i>Introduction to Programming using Java</i> is <b>free</b>, but it is not in the
public domain. Version&nbsp;8 is published under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License. 
To view a copy of this license, visit 
<a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</a>.
For example, you can:</p>

<ul>
<li>Post an unmodified copy of the on-line version on your own Web site (including
the parts that list the author and state the license under which it is distributed!).
</li>

<li>Give away unmodified copies of this book or sell them at cost of production, as long as they
meet the requirements of the license.</li>

<li>Make modified copies of the complete book or parts of it
and post them on the web or otherwise distribute them non-commercially, provided that attribution
to the author is given, the modifications are clearly noted, and the modified copies
are distributed under the same license as the original.  This includes translations
to other languages.</li>

</ul>

<p>For uses of the book in ways not covered by the license, permission of the
author is required.</p>

<p>While it is not actually required by the license, I do appreciate hearing
from people who are using or distributing my work.</p>
   
<break/>
   

<p><b>A technical note on production:</b> The on-line and PDF versions of this
book are created from a single source, which is written largely in XML. 
To produce the
PDF version, the XML is processed into a form that can be used by the TeX
typesetting program.  In addition to
XML files, the source includes DTDs, XSLT transformations, Java source code files,
image files, a TeX macro file, and a couple of scripts that are used in processing.
The scripts work on Linux and on Mac&nbsp;OS.
</p>

<!-- 
<p><b>I have made the complete source files available for download at
the following address:</b></p>

<p align="center"><a href="http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/downloads/javanotes8-full-source.zip">http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs124/downloads/javanotes8-full-source.zip</a></p>
-->

<p>I will make the complete source files available on request, and will post a link to
them on the book's web site once the final version of the eighth edition is released.</p>

<p>These files were not originally meant for publication, and therefore are not very
cleanly written.  Furthermore, it requires a fair amount of expertise to use them.
However, I have had several requests for the sources and have made
them available on an "as-is" basis.  For more information about the sources and
how they are used see the <tex>README file</tex><web><a href="README-full-source.txt">README&nbsp;file</a></web> from
the source download.</p>
   
<break/> 

<np>Professor David J. Eck<br />
Department of Mathematics and Computer Science<br />
Hobart and William Smith Colleges<br />
300 Pulteney Street<br />
Geneva, New York 14456, USA<br />
Email: <a href="mailto:eck@hws.edu">eck@hws.edu</a><br />
WWW: <a href="http://math.hws.edu/eck/">http://math.hws.edu/eck/</a><br /><br />
</np>



  
   
</preface>