<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE intro SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<intro>
<p><start><big>I</big>n the classic programming model,</start> there
is a single central processing unit that reads instructions from 
memory and carries them out, one after the other.  The purpose of a
program is to provide the list of instructions for the processor to execute.
This is the only type of programming that we have considered so
far.</p>
<p>However, this model of programming has limitations.  Modern
computers have multiple processors, making it possible for them
to perform several tasks at the same time.  To use the full 
potential of all those processors, you will need to write
programs that can do <newword>parallel processing</newword>.
For Java programmers, that means learning about
<newword>threads</newword>.  A single thread is similar
to the programs that you have been writing up until now,
but more than one thread can be running at the same time,
"in parallel." What makes things more interesting&mdash;and more 
difficult&mdash;than single-threaded programming is the fact
that the threads in a parallel program are rarely completely
independent of one another.  They usually need to cooperate
and communicate.  Learning to manage and control cooperation
among threads is the main hurdle that you will face in this
chapter.</p>
<p>There are several reasons to use parallel programming.  One
is simply to do computations more quickly by setting several 
processors to work on them simultaneously.  Just as important,
however, is to use threads to deal with "blocking" operations,
where a process can't proceed until some event occurs.  In the
<localref href="IO">previous chapter</localref>, for example, we saw how
programs can block while waiting for data to arrive over
a network connection.  Threads make it possible for one part of a program
to continue to do useful work even while another part is 
blocked, waiting for some event to occur.  In this context,
threads are a vital programming tool even for a computer that
has only a single processing unit.</p>
<p>As Java has developed, new features have been added to the
language that make it possible to do parallel programming
without using threads directly.  We have already seen one
of these: parallel streams in the stream API from 
<localref href="generics.6"/>.  We will encounter several
more in this chapter.  But to use these higher level language
features safely and efficiently, you still need to know
something about the hazards and benefits of threads.</p>
</intro>
