<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE quiz SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<quiz>

<question>
<ques><p>Write a complete subclass of <classname>Thread</classname> to represent
a thread that writes out the numbers from 1 to 10.  Then write some code that
would create and start a thread belonging to that class.</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>The class that defines the thread:</p>
<pre>public class CountingThread extends Thread {
   public static run() {
      for (int i = 1; i &lt;= 10; i++)
         System.out.println(i);
   }
}</pre>
<p>Code to create an object of type <classname>CountingThread</classname> and start the thread:</p>
<pre>CountingThread counter;     // Declare a variable to represent a thread.
counter = new CountingThread();  // Create the thread object.
counter.start();                 // Start the thread running.</pre>
<p>(Note that it's possible to create a new thread and start it with one statement:</p>
<pre>new CountingThread().start();</pre>
<np>Because of the precedence of the <code>new</code> operator, this is equivalent to
<code>(new&nbsp;CountingThread()).start()</code>, and the effect is to create a new
object of type <classname>CountingThread</classname> and then to call the
<code>start()</code> method in that object.)</np>
</ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Suppose that <code>thrd</code> is an object of type <classname>Thread</classname>.
Explain the difference between calling <code>thrd.start()</code> and calling <code>thrd.run()</code>.</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>Calling <code>thrd.start()</code> creates a new thread of control and returns immediately after doing so;
then the thread's <code>run()</code> method is called in the new thread of control.  The code in the <code>run()</code> method is
executed at the same time, in parallel, with the code that follows the call to <code>thrd.start()</code>.</p>
<p>The statement <code>thrd.run()</code> calls the run method in the usual way: The <code>run()</code> method is
executed in the same thread of control as the method that called <code>run()</code>.  Only  after
the <code>run()</code> method returns will the code that follows <code>thrd.run()</code> be executed.</p>
</ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>What is a <i>race condition</i>?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>A race condition is a problem that can occur in a multithreaded program.
Suppose that a thread takes a sequence of actions in which one action can depend on
the result of a previous action.  A race condition occurs if it's possible for another thread
to change or invalidate the result of the previous action, before the first thread completes the
sequence.  For example, there is a race condition in the simple assignment statement
<code>count&nbsp;=&nbsp;count+1</code> because it is executed as a sequence of steps.
The old value of <code>count</code> is read, one is added to that value, and the new value is stored
back into <code>count</code>.  A race condition occurs if it is possible for another thread to
increment the value of <code>count</code> between the time when the first thread reads the old value
and the time when it stores the new value.  In this case, the race condition can result in an
incorrect value for <code>count</code>&mdash;<code>count</code> might be increased by one
when it was supposed to be increased by two.  Another example occurs in the if statement</p>
<pre>if ( ! list.isEmpty() )
    return list.removeFirst();</pre>
<np>There is a race condition if it is possible for another thread to empty the list
between the time when the first thread tests whether the list is empty and the
time when the first thread tries to remove an element from the list.  In this case,
the race condition can result in an exception when the first thread tries to remove
an item from an empty list.</np>
</ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>How does synchronization prevent race conditions, and what does it mean to say
that synchronization only provides <i>mutual</i> exclusion?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>Synchronization makes it possible for a thread to complete a sequence of actions
without interference from another thread.  Two threads cannot be synchronized on the
same object at the same time.  While one thread is executing a synchronized block of
code, it's impossible for another thread to be executing the same block of code, or
any other block of code that is synchronized on the same object.  For example, if
a thread executes</p>
<pre>synchronized(list) {
   if ( ! list.isEmpty() )
      return list.removeFirst();
}</pre>
<np>then, assuming that all code that manipulates <code>list</code> is properly
synchronized, it can be sure that no other thread will be able to empty the list
between the time when the first thread tests whether the list is empty and the
time when it removes the first element from the list.</np>
<p>Synchronization provides only <i>mutual</i> exclusion because it only protects
a thread from other threads that are <i>also synchronized</i> on the same object.  In the example,
the code has exclusive access to <code>list</code> only if all the code
segments that manipulate <code>list</code> are synchronized. There is no
protection against a thread that executes the statement <code>list.clear()</code> without 
synchronization.</p>
</ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Suppose that a program uses a single thread that takes 4 seconds to run.
Now suppose that the program creates two threads and divides the same work between the
two threads.  What can be said about the expected execution time of the program
that uses two threads?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>The execution time will depend on whether the program is being run on a
computer that has more than one processor.  If so, the execution time could be
as little as 2 seconds, since each of two processors can do half of the 4-seconds
worth of work.  If the computer has only one processor, however, the two-threaded
program will still take 4 seconds, since all the work will have to be done
by the single processor.  (Even on a multiprocessor computer, it might take longer
than 2 seconds, if the work is not divided evenly between the two threads.)</p>
</ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>What is an <classname>ArrayBlockingQueue</classname>  and how does it
solve the producer/consumer problem?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>An <classname>ArrayBlockingQueue</classname> is a queue in which the operations
of adding and removing items can block.  Adding an item will block if the queue is full;
removing an item will block if the queue is empty.  (Furthermore, operations on the
queue are properly synchronized for use in a multithreaded program.)</p>
<p>The producer/consumer problem is the problem of safely and efficiently 
getting items that are produced by one group of threads to a second group of
threads that consume the items.  If the items are sent through a blocking queue,
then the threads in the second group will block when there are no items
available for them to consume, and threads in the first group will block if
they are producing items faster than they can be consumed.  (Furthermore, the
synchronization guarantees that no item will be lost or consumed twice.)</p>
<p>In an application in which only the consuming threads should block, a
<classname>LinkedBlockingQueue</classname>, which has unlimited capacity,
can be used.</p>
</ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>What is a <i>thread pool</i>?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>Thread pools are used when a large number of tasks are to be performed,
as an alternative to creating a new thread to execute each task.  A thread pool
is a relatively small collection of threads that are available for performing
tasks.  When a task becomes available, instead of creating a new thread for
the task, the task is assigned to one of the threads from the pool.  When
the task is complete, the thread goes back into the pool so that more
tasks can be assigned to it.</p>
<p>Typically, tasks are placed into a queue as they become available.  Each thread
in the pool runs in an infinite loop in which it repeatedly takes a task from the queue
and executes it.  (Blocking queues work well for this application.)</p>
</ans>
</question>

  

   
<question>
<ques><p>Network server programs are
often <i>multithreaded.</i> Explain what this means and why it is true.</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>A multi-threaded server uses threads to handle the client connections that it accepts. A server program
is generally designed to process connection requests from many clients. It runs
in an infinite loop in which it accepts a connection request and processes it.
If the processing takes a significant amount of time, it's not a good idea to
make the other clients wait while the current client is processed. The solution
is for the server to make a new thread to handle each client connection, or to 
use a thread pool of threads that can handle the client connections. The
server can continue to accept more client connections even while the first
client is being serviced.</p>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Why does a multithreaded network server program often use 
many times more threads than the number of available processors?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>Network operations can <i>block</i>, which means that a thread
that handles communication with a client will often spend most of its
time sleeping.  In order to keep all the processors busy, the number
of <b>active</b> threads should be comparable to the number of processors.
If at any given time, the number of active threads is only a fraction of
the total number of threads, then the total number of threads should
be several times the number of processors.</p>
</ans>
</question>
   

   
<question>
<ques><p>Consider the <classname>ThreadSafeCounter</classname> example from
<localref href="threads.1.3"/>:</p>
<pre>public class ThreadSafeCounter {
   
   private int count = 0;  // The value of the counter.
   
   synchronized public void increment() {
      count = count + 1;
   }
   
   synchronized public int getValue() {
      return count;
   }
   
}</pre>
<p>The <code>increment()</code> method is synchronized so that the caller of the method can
complete the three steps of the operation "Get value of count," "Add 1 to value,"
"Store new value in count" without being interrupted by another thread. 
But <code>getValue()</code> consists of a single,
simple step.  Why is <code>getValue()</code> synchronized?  (This is a deep and
tricky question.)</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>The <code>getValue()</code> method has to be synchronized because of the
caching of local data that was discussed in <localref href="threads.1.4"/>.
If <code>getValue()</code> were not synchronized, it is possible that a thread
that calls <code>getValue()</code> would see an old, cached value of <code>count</code>
rather than the most current value.  Synchronization ensures that the most
current value of <code>count</code> will be seen.  If <code>count</code> were
declared to be a <code>volatile</code> variable, then <code>getValue()</code> would
not have to be synchronized.  However, <code>increment()</code> would still need
to be synchronized to prevent the race condition.</p>
</ans>
</question>

   

</quiz>