<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE quiz SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<quiz>

<question>
<ques><p>Object-oriented programming
uses <i>classes</i> and <i>objects</i>. What are classes and what are objects?
What is the relationship between classes and objects?</p></ques>
<ans><p>When used in object-oriented
programming, a class is a factory for creating objects. (We are talking here
about the non-static part of the class.) An object is a collection of data and
behaviors that represent some entity (real or abstract). A class defines the
structure and behaviors of all entities of a given type. An object is one
particular "instance" of that type of entity. For example, if <i>Dog</i> is a
class, then a particular dog named <i>Lassie</i> would be an object of type <i>Dog</i>.</p></ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>Explain carefully what
<i>null</i> means in Java, and why this special value is necessary.</p></ques>
<ans><p>When a variable is of object
type (that is, declared with a class or interface as its type rather than one of Java's
primitive types), the value stored in the variable is not an object. Objects
exist in a part of memory called the heap, and the variable holds a
<i>pointer</i> or <i>reference</i> to the object. Null is a special value that
can be stored in a variable to indicate that it does not actually point to any
object.</p></ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>What is a
<i>constructor?</i> What is the purpose of a constructor in a class?</p></ques>
<ans><p>A constructor is a special kind
of subroutine in a class. It has the same name as the name of the class, and it
has no return type, not even <code>void.</code> A constructor is called with the
<code>new</code> operator in order to create a new object. Its main purpose is to
initialize the newly created object, but in fact, it can do anything that the
programmer wants it to do.</p></ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Suppose that
<code>Kumquat</code> is the name of a class and that <code>fruit</code> is a variable
of type <code>Kumquat.</code> What is the meaning of the statement "<code>fruit = new
Kumquat();</code>"? That is, what does the computer do when it executes this
statement? (Try to give a complete answer. The computer does several
things.)</p></ques>
<ans><p>This statement creates a new
object belonging to the class <code>Kumquat</code>, and it stores a reference to
that object in the variable <code>fruit.</code> More specifically, when the
computer executes this statement, it allocates memory to hold a new object of
type <code>Kumquat</code>. It calls a constructor, which can initialize the
instance variables of the object as well as perform other tasks. A reference to
the new object is returned as the value of the expression "<code>new
Kumquat()</code>". Finally, the assignment statement stores the reference in the
variable, <code>fruit</code>. So, <code>fruit</code> can now be used to access the new
object.</p></ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>What is meant by the terms
<i>instance variable</i> and <i>instance method</i>?</p></ques>
<ans><p>Instance variables and instance
methods are non-static variables and methods in a class; that is, their
definitions in the class are <b>not</b> marked with the "static" modifier.
This means that they
do not belong to the class itself. Instead, they specify what variables and
methods are in an object that belongs to that class. That is, the class
contains the source code that defines instance variables and instance methods,
but actual instance variables and instance methods are contained in objects,
at least logically.
(Such objects are called "instances" of the class.) Thus, instance variables
and instance methods are the data and the behaviors of objects.</p></ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>Explain what is meant by the
terms <i>subclass</i> and <i>superclass.</i></p></ques>
<ans><p>In object oriented programming,
one class can inherit all the properties and behaviors from another class. It
can then add to and modify what it inherits. The class that inherits is called
a subclass, and the class that it inherits from is said to be its superclass.
In Java, the fact that <code>ClassA</code> is a subclass of <code>ClassB</code> is
indicated in the definition of <code>ClassA</code> as follows:</p>
<pre>class ClassA extends ClassB {...}</pre>
</ans>
</question>

   
<question>
<ques><p>Modify the following class so that the two instance variables are <code>private</code>
and there is a getter method and a setter method for each instance variable:</p>
<pre>public class Player {
   String name;
   int score;
}</pre>
</ques>
<ans><p>To make a variable private, just add the word "private" in front of each
declaration.  We need two methods for each variable.  One of them returns the value
of the variable.  The other provides a new value for the variable.
The names for these methods should follow the usual naming convention for
getter and setter methods.  (Note that my setter methods use the special
variable <code>this</code> so that I can use the same name for the parameter
of the method as is used for the instance variable. This is a very common pattern.)</p>
<pre>public class Player {
   private String name;
   private int score;
   public String getName() {
      return name;
   }
   public void setName(String name) {
      this.name = name;  // ("this.name" refers to the instance variable)
   }
   public int getScore() {
      return score;
   }
   public void setScore(int score) {
      this.score = score;
   }
}</pre>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Explain why the class <classname>Player</classname> that is defined in the previous
question has an instance method named <code>toString()</code>, even though no definition
of this method appears in the definition of the class.</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>If a class is not declared to <code>extend</code> any class, then it automatically
extends the class <classname>Object</classname>, which is one of the built-in classes of
Java.  So in this case, <classname>Player</classname> is a direct subclass of
<classname>Object</classname>.  The <classname>Object</classname> class defines
a <code>toString()</code> method, and the <classname>Player</classname> class inherits
this <code>toString()</code> method from <classname>Object</classname>.  The methods and
member variables in a class include not just those defined in the class but also those
inherited from its superclass.  (However, the inherited <code>toString()</code> method
will not produce a useful string representation of a <classname>Player</classname>;
to get that, you would have to override <code>toString()</code> in the
<classname>Player</classname> class.)</p>
</ans>
</question>
   


<question>
<ques><p>Explain the term
<i>polymorphism.</i></p>
</ques>
<ans><p>Polymorphism refers to the fact
that different objects can respond to the same method in different ways,
depending on the actual type of the object. This can occur because a method can
be overridden in a subclass. In that case, objects belonging to the subclass
will respond to the method differently from objects belonging to the
superclass.</p>

<p>(Note: If B is a subclass of A, then a variable of type A can refer to
either an object of type A or an object of type B. Let's say that <code>var</code>
is such a variable and that <code>action()</code> is a method in class A that is
redefined in class B. Consider the statement "var.action()". Does this execute
the method from class A or the method from class B? The answer is that there is
no way to tell! The answer depends on what type of object <code>var</code> refers
to, a class A object or a class B object. The method executed by
<code>var.action()</code> depends on the actual type of the object that
<code>var</code> refers to <b>at run time</b>, not on the type of the variable <code>var</code>. This is
the real meaning of polymorphism.)</p></ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Java uses "garbage
collection" for memory management. Explain what is meant here by garbage
collection. What is the alternative to garbage collection?</p></ques>
<ans><p>The purpose of garbage
collection is to identify objects that can no longer be used, and to dispose of
such objects and reclaim the memory space that they occupy. If garbage
collection is not used, then the programmer must be responsible for keeping
track of which objects are still in use and disposing of objects when they are
no longer needed. If the programmer makes a mistake, then there is a "memory
leak," which might gradually fill up memory with useless objects until the
program crashes for lack of memory.</p></ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>What is an <i>abstract class</i>, and how can you recognize an abstract class in Java?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>An abstract class is one that cannot be used to create objects.  It exists only as a basis
for making subclasses, and it expresses all the properties and behaviors that those subclasses
have in common.  In Java, a class can be marked with the modifier <code>abstract</code> to make
it abstract.  For example,</p>
<pre><newcode>abstract</newcode> public class Vehicle { ...</pre>
<np>It will then be a syntax error to try to call a "<code>new Vehicle</code>" constructor.
(Note: Only a class that has been marked as <code>abstract</code> can contain abstract instance methods.)</np>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>What is <code>this</code>?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>"<code>this</code>" is a special variable in Java, which does not have to be declared.  
Java makes it available automatically in instance methods and constructors.
It holds a reference to the object that is being constructed
or that contains the instance method that is being executed (or, in terms of messages, the
object that received the message that is being processed).  It provides a way to refer to
"this object."  If <code>x</code> is an instance variable, it can also be referred to as
<code>this.x</code> within the same class.  If <code>doSomething()</code> is an instance method, 
it can also be called as <code>this.doSomething()</code> within the same class.  (Personally,
I would be happier with Java if it required the use of "this" instead of using it implicitly.)</p>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>For this problem, you should
write a very simple but complete class. The class represents a counter that
counts 0, 1, 2, 3, 4,&nbsp;&dots;. The name of the class should be <code>Counter</code>. It
has one <code>private</code> instance variable representing the value of the
counter. It has two instance methods: <code>increment()</code> adds one to the
counter value, and <code>getValue()</code> returns the current counter value. Write
a complete definition for the class, <code>Counter</code>.</p></ques>
<ans><p>Here is a possible answer. (Note
that the initialization of the instance variable, value, to zero is not really
necessary, since it would be initialized to zero anyway if no explicit
initialization were provided.)</p>

<pre>
/**
 * An object of this class represents a counter that counts up from zero.
 */
public class Counter {

   private int value = 0;  // Current value of the counter.

   /**
    * Add one to the value of the counter.
    */
   public void increment() {  
      value++;
   }

   /**
    * Returns the current value of the counter.
    */
   public int getValue() {    
      return value;
   }

} // end of class Counter</pre>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>This problem uses the
<code>Counter</code> class from the previous question. The following program segment is meant
to simulate tossing a coin 100 times. It should use two <code>Counter</code>
objects, <code>headCount</code> and <code>tailCount</code>, to count the number of
heads and the number of tails. Fill in the blanks so that it will do so:</p>

<pre>Counter headCount, tailCount;
tailCount = new Counter();
headCount = new Counter();
for ( int flip = 0;  flip &lt; 100;  flip++ ) {
   if (Math.random() &lt; 0.5)    // There's a 50/50 chance that this is true.
   
       ______________________ ;   // Count a "head".
       
   else
   
       ______________________ ;   // Count a "tail".
}

System.out.println("There were " + ___________________ + " heads.");

System.out.println("There were " + ___________________ + " tails.");</pre>
</ques>
<ans><p>The variable <code>headCount</code>
is a variable of type <code>Counter</code>, so the only thing that you can do with
it is call the instance methods <code>headCount.increment()</code> and
<code>headCount.getValue()</code>. Call <code>headCount.increment()</code> to add one
to the counter. Call <code>headCount.getValue()</code> to discover the current
value of the counter. Note that you can't get at the value of the counter
directly, since the variable that holds the value is a <code>private</code>
instance variable in the <code>Counter</code> object. Similarly for
<code>tailCount</code>. Here is the program with calls to these instance methods
filled in:</p>

<pre>Counter headCount, tailCount;
tailCount = new Counter();
headCount = new Counter();
for ( int flip = 0;  flip &lt; 100;  flip++ ) {
   if (Math.random() &lt; 0.5)    // There's a 50/50 chance that this is true.
       <newcode>headCount.increment()</newcode> ;   // Count a "head", using headCount
   else
       <newcode>tailCount.increment()</newcode> ;   // Count a "tail", using tailCount
}
System.out.println(("There were " + <newcode>headCount.getValue()</newcode> + " heads.");
System.out.println(("There were " + <newcode>tailCount.getValue()</newcode> + " tails.");</pre>
</ans>
</question>

</quiz>