<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes7.dtd" >

<section id="OOP.1" title="Objects, Instance Methods, and Instance Variables" shorttitle="Objects and Instance Methods">

<p><start><big>O</big>bject-oriented programming</start> (OOP) represents an
attempt to make programs more closely model the way people think about and deal
with the world. In the older styles of programming, a programmer who is faced
with some problem must identify a computing task that needs to be performed in
order to solve the problem. Programming then consists of finding a sequence of
instructions that will accomplish that task. But at the heart of
object-oriented programming, instead of tasks we find objects&mdash;entities that
have behaviors, that hold information, and that can interact with one another.
Programming consists of designing a set of objects that somehow model the
problem at hand. Software objects in the program can represent real or abstract
entities in the problem domain. This is supposed to make the design of the
program more natural and hence easier to get right and easier to
understand.</p>

<p>To some extent, OOP is just a change in point of view. We can think of an
object in standard programming terms as nothing more than a set of variables
together with some subroutines for manipulating those variables. In fact, it is
possible to use object-oriented techniques in any programming language.
However, there is a big difference between a language that makes OOP possible
and one that actively supports it. An object-oriented programming language such
as Java includes a number of features that make it very different from a
standard language. In order to make effective use of those features, you have
to "orient" your thinking correctly.</p>

<p>As I have mentioned before, in the context of object-oriented programming,
subroutines are often referred to as <newword>methods</newword>.  Now that
we are starting to use objects, I will be using the term "method" more often
than "subroutine."</p>

<subsection id="OOP.1.1" title="Objects, Classes, and Instances">

<p>Objects are closely related to classes. We have already been working with
classes for several chapters, and we have seen that a class can contain
variables and methods (that is, subroutines). If an object is also a collection of variables and
methods, how do they differ from classes? And why does it require a
different type of thinking to understand and use them effectively? In the one
section where we worked with objects rather than classes, 
<localref href="control.8"/>, it didn't seem to make much difference: We
just left the word "<code>static</code>" out of the subroutine definitions!</p>

<p>I have said that classes "describe" objects, or more exactly that the
non-static portions of classes describe objects. But it's probably not very
clear what this means. The more usual terminology is to say that objects
<newword>belong to</newword> classes, but this might not be much
clearer. (There is a real shortage of English words to properly distinguish all
the concepts involved. An object certainly doesn't "belong" to a class in the
same way that a member variable "belongs" to a class.) From the point of view
of programming, it is more exact to say that classes are used to create
objects. A class is a kind of factory&mdash;or blueprint&mdash;for constructing objects. The non-static
parts of the class specify, or describe, what variables and methods the
objects will contain. This is part of the explanation of how objects differ
from classes: Objects are created and destroyed as the program runs, and there
can be many objects with the same structure, if they are created using the same
class.</p>

<p>Consider a simple class whose job is to group together a few static member
variables. For example, the following class could be used to store information
about the person who is using the program:</p>

<pre>class UserData {
    static String name;
    static int age;
}</pre>

<np>In a program that uses this class, there is only one copy of each of the
variables <code>UserData.name</code> and <code>UserData.age</code>.  When the class is
loaded into the computer, there is a section of memory devoted to the class, and
that section of memory includes space for the values of the variables <code>name</code>
and <code>age.</code>  We can picture the class in memory as looking like this:</np>

<img src="class-userdata.png" width="165" height="128" alt="the UserData class in memory, with space for name and age"
       tex="class-userdata.eps" texscale="0.75"/>

<p>An important point is that the static member variables are part of the representation 
of the class in memory.  
Their full names, <code>UserData.name</code> and <code>UserData.age</code>,
use the name of the class, since they are part of the class. 
When we use class <classname>UserData</classname> to represent the user of the program,
there can only be <b>one</b> user, since we only have memory space to store data about one user. Note that
the class, <code>UserData</code>, and the variables it contains exist as long as the
program runs. (That is essentially what it means to be "static.")
Now, consider a similar class that includes some non-static variables:</p>

<pre>class PlayerData {
   static int playerCount;
   String name;
   int age;
}</pre>

<np>I've also included a static variable in the <classname>PlayerData</classname> class.
Here, the static variable <code>playerCount</code> is stored as part of the representation of the class in memory.
Its full name is <code>PlayerData.playerCount</code>, and there is only one of it, which exists
as long as the program runs.  However, the other two variables in the class definition are non-static.
There is no such variable as <code>PlayerData.name</code> or
<code>PlayerData.age</code>, since non-static variables do not become part of the
class itself.  But the <classname>PlayerData</classname> class can
be used to create objects.   There can be many objects created using the class, and each 
one will have its <b>own</b> variables called <code>name</code> and <code>age</code>.  
This is what it means for the non-static parts of the class to be a template for objects: 
Every object gets its own copy of the non-static part of the class.  We can visualize
the situation in the computer's memory after several object have been created like this:</np>


<img src="instance-of-PlayerData.png" width="573" height="358" alt="the PlayerData class and three objects in memory"
     tex="instance-of-PlayerData.eps" texscale="0.75"/>

<np>Note that the static variable <code>playerCount</code> is part of the class, and there
is only one copy.  On the other hand, every object contains a <code>name</code> and an 
<code>age</code>.  An object that is created from a class is called an <newword>instance</newword> of
that class, and as the picture shows every object "knows" which class was used to create it.
I've shown class <classname>PlayerData</classname> as containing something called a
"constructor;" the constructor is a subroutine that creates objects.</np>

<p>Now there can
be many "players" because we can make new objects to represent new players on
demand.  A program might use the <classname>PlayerData</classname> class to store information about multiple
players in a game. Each player has a name and an age. When a player joins the
game, a new <code>PlayerData</code> object can be created to represent that player.
If a player leaves the game, the <code>PlayerData</code> object that represents
that player can be destroyed. A system of objects in the program is being used
to <newword>dynamically</newword> model what is happening in the game.
You can't do this with static variables!  "Dynamic" is the opposite of "static."</p>

<break/>

<p>An object that is created using a class is said to be an <newword>instance</newword> 
of that class.  We will sometimes say that the object <newword>belongs</newword> to the class.
The variables that the object contains
are called <newword>instance variables</newword>. The methods (that is, subroutines)
that the object contains are called <newword>instance methods</newword>. 
For example, if the
<code>PlayerData</code> class, as defined above, is used to create an object, then
that object is an instance of the <code>PlayerData</code> class, and <code>name</code>
and <code>age</code> are instance variables in the object.</p>

<p>My examples here don't include any methods, but methods work similarly to variables.
Static methods are part of the class; non-static, or instance, methods become part of
objects created from the class.  It's not literally true that each object contains
its own copy of the actual compiled code for an instance method. But logically an instance
method is part of the object, and I will continue to say that the object "contains"
the instance method.</p>

<p>Note that you should distinguish between
the <b>source code</b> for the class, and the <b>class itself</b> (in memory).  The
source code determines both the class and the objects that are created from
that class.  The "static" definitions in the source code specify the things
that are part of the class itself (in the computer's memory), whereas the non-static definitions in the
source code specify things that will become part of every instance object
that is created from the class.   By the way, static member
variables and static member subroutines in a class are sometimes called
<newword>class variables</newword> and <newword>class methods</newword>, 
since they belong to the class itself, rather than to instances
of that class.</p>

<p>As you can see, the static and the non-static portions of a class are very
different things and serve very different purposes. Many classes contain only
static members, or only non-static, and we will see only a few examples of
classes that contain a mixture of the two.  </p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="OOP.1.2" title="Fundamentals of Objects">
   
<p>So far, I've been talking mostly in generalities, and I haven't given you
much of an idea about what you have to put in a program if you want to work with objects.
Let's look at a specific example to see how it works. Consider this extremely
simplified version of a <code>Student</code> class, which could be used to store
information about students taking a course:</p>

<pre>public class Student {

   public String name;  // Student's name.
   public double test1, test2, test3;   // Grades on three tests.
   
   public double getAverage() {  // compute average test grade
      return (test1 + test2 + test3) / 3;
   }
   
}  // end of class Student</pre>

<p>None of the members of this class are declared to be <code>static</code>, so the
class exists only for creating objects. This class definition says that any
object that is an instance of the <code>Student</code> class will include instance
variables named <code>name</code>, <code>test1</code>, <code>test2</code>, and
<code>test3</code>, and it will include an instance method named
<code>getAverage()</code>. The names and tests in different objects will generally
have different values. When called for a particular student, the method
<code>getAverage()</code> will compute an average using <b>that
student's</b> test grades. Different students can have different averages.
(Again, this is what it means to say that an instance method belongs to an
individual object, not to the class.)</p>

<p>In Java, a class is a <b>type</b>, similar to the built-in types
such as <ptype>int</ptype> and <ptype>boolean</ptype>. So, a class name can be used to
specify the type of a variable in a declaration statement, or the type of a formal
parameter, or the return type of a function. For example, a program could
define a variable named <code>std</code> of type <code>Student</code> with the
statement</p>

<pre>Student std;</pre>

<np>However, declaring a variable does <b>not</b> create an object!
This is an important point, which is related to this Very Important Fact:</np>

<centered><p><b>In Java, no variable can ever hold an object.<br/>
A variable can only hold a reference to an object.</b></p></centered>

<p>You should think of objects as floating around independently in the
computer's memory. In fact, there is a special portion of memory called the
<newword>heap</newword> where objects live. Instead of holding an
object itself, a variable holds the information necessary to find the object in
memory. This information is called a <newword>reference</newword> or
<newword>pointer</newword> to the object. In effect, a reference to
an object is the address of the memory location where the object is stored.
When you use a variable of object type, the computer uses the reference in the
variable to find the actual object.</p>

<p>In a program, objects are created using an operator called <code>new</code>, which
creates an object and returns a reference to that object.  (In fact, the <code>new</code> operator
calls a special subroutine called a "constructor" in the class.)
For example, assuming that <code>std</code> is a variable of type <code>Student</code>, declared as above,
the assignment statement</p>

<pre>std = new Student();</pre>

<np>would create a new object which is an instance of the class
<code>Student</code>, and it would store a reference to that object in the variable
<code>std</code>. The value of the variable is a reference, or pointer, to the object.
The object itself is somewhere in the heap.
It is not quite true, then, to say that the object is the "value
of the variable <code>std</code>" (though sometimes it is hard to avoid using this
terminology). It is certainly <b>not at all true</b> to say that the
object is "stored in the variable <code>std</code>." The proper terminology is that
"the variable <code>std</code> <newword>refers to</newword> or <newword>points to</newword>
the object," and I will try to stick to that terminology as much as possible.
If I ever say something like "std <b>is</b> an object," you should read it as
meaning "std is a variable that refers to an object."</np>

<p>So, suppose that the variable <code>std</code> refers to an object that is an instance of
class <code>Student</code>. That object contains instance variables <code>name</code>,
<code>test1</code>, <code>test2</code>, and <code>test3</code>. These instance variables
can be referred to as <code>std.name</code>, <code>std.test1</code>,
<code>std.test2</code>, and <code>std.test3</code>. This follows the usual naming
convention that when <code>B</code> is part of <code>A</code>, then the full name of
<code>B</code> is <code>A.B</code>. For example, a program might include the lines</p>

<pre>System.out.println("Hello, "  +  std.name  +  ".  Your test grades are:");
System.out.println(std.test1);
System.out.println(std.test2);
System.out.println(std.test3);</pre>

<np>This would output the name and test grades from the object to which
<code>std</code> refers. Similarly, <code>std</code> can be used to call the
<code>getAverage()</code> instance method in the object by saying
<code>std.getAverage()</code>. To print out the student's average, you could
say:</np>

<pre>System.out.println( "Your average is "  +  std.getAverage() );</pre>

<p>More generally, you could use <code>std.name</code> any place where a variable
of type <classname>String</classname> is legal. You can use it in expressions. You can assign
a value to it. You can even use it to call subroutines from the <classname>String</classname>
class. For example, <code>std.name.length()</code> is the number of characters in
the student's name.</p>

<p>It is possible for a variable like <code>std</code>, whose type is given by a
class, to refer to no object at all. We say in this case that <code>std</code>
holds a <newword>null pointer</newword> or <newword>null reference</newword>. The null pointer is
written in Java as "<code>null</code>". You can store a null reference in the
variable <code>std</code> by saying</p>

<pre>std = null;</pre>

<np><code>null</code> is an actual value that is stored in the variable, not a pointer
to something else.  It is <b>not</b> correct to say that the variable "points to null";
in fact, the variable <b>is</b> null.  For example,
you can test whether the value of <code>std</code> is null by testing</np>

<pre>if (std == null) . . .</pre>

<p>If the value of a variable is <code>null</code>, then it is, of course, illegal
to refer to instance variables or instance methods through that variable&mdash;since
there <b>is</b> no object, and hence no instance variables to refer to!  For
example, if the value of the variable <code>std</code> is <code>null</code>, then it
would be illegal to refer to <code>std.test1</code>. If your program attempts to
use a null pointer illegally in this way, the result is an error called a
<newword>null pointer exception</newword>.  When this happens while the program
is running, an exception of type <classname>NullPointerException</classname>
is thrown.
</p>

<p>Let's look at a sequence of statements that work with objects:</p>

<pre>Student std, std1,       // Declare four variables of
          std2, std3;    //   type Student.

std = new Student();     // Create a new object belonging
                         //   to the class Student, and
                         //   store a reference to that
                         //   object in the variable std.

std1 = new Student();    // Create a second Student object
                         //   and store a reference to
                         //   it in the variable std1.

std2 = std1;             // Copy the reference value in std1
                         //   into the variable std2.

std3 = null;             // Store a null reference in the
                         //   variable std3.
                         
std.name = "John Smith";  // Set values of some instance variables.
std1.name = "Mary Jones";

     // (Other instance variables have default
     //    initial values of zero.)</pre>

<np>After the computer executes these statements, the situation in the
computer's memory looks like this:</np>

<img height="425" width="537" alt="Objects and variables created by the above code" 
        src="objects-in-heap.png" tex="objects-in-heap.eps" texscale="0.75"/>


<np>In this picture, when a variable
contains a reference to an object, the value of that variable is shown as an
arrow pointing to the object.   Note, by the way, that the <classname>Strings</classname>
are objects!  The variable <code>std3</code>, with a value of
<code>null</code>, doesn't point anywhere. The arrows from <code>std1</code> and
<code>std2</code> both point to the same object. This illustrates a Very Important
Point:</np>

<centered><p><b>When one object variable is assigned<br/>
to another, only a reference is copied.<br/>
The object referred to is not copied.</b></p></centered>

<np>When the assignment "<code>std2 = std1</code>;" was executed, no new object was
created. Instead, <code>std2</code> was set to refer to the very same object that
<code>std1</code> refers to.   This is to be expected, since the assignment
statement just copies the value that is stored in <code>std1</code> into 
<code>std2</code>, and that value is a pointer, not an object.
But this has some consequences that might be surprising.
For example, <code>std1.name</code> and <code>std2.name</code> are two different names for the
same variable, namely the instance variable in the object that both
<code>std1</code> and <code>std2</code> refer to. After the string <code>"Mary
Jones"</code> is assigned to the variable <code><b>std1</b>.name</code>, it is also
true that the value of <code><b>std2</b>.name</code> is <code>"Mary Jones"</code>.
There is a potential for a lot of confusion here, but you can help protect
yourself from it if you keep telling yourself, "The object is not in the
variable. The variable just holds a pointer to the object."</np>

<p>You can test objects for equality and inequality using the operators <code>==</code> and
<code>!=</code>, but here again, the semantics are different from what you are used to. When
you make a test "<code>if&nbsp;(std1&nbsp;==&nbsp;std2)</code>", you are testing whether the
values stored in <code>std1</code> and <code>std2</code> are the same. But the values that you are comparing
are references to objects; they are not objects. So, you are testing whether
<code>std1</code> and <code>std2</code> refer to the same object, that is, whether they
point to the same location in memory. This is fine, if it's what you want to do.
But sometimes, what you want to check is whether the instance variables in the
objects have the same values. To do that, you would need to ask whether 
"<code>std1.test1 == std2.test1 &amp;&amp; std1.test2 == std2.test2 &amp;&amp;
std1.test3 == std2.test3 &amp;&amp; std1.name.equals(std2.name)</code>".</p>

<p>I've remarked previously that <classname>Strings</classname> are objects, and I've shown
the strings <code>"Mary Jones"</code> and <code>"John Smith"</code> as objects in the
above illustration.  (Strings are special objects, treated by Java in a special way, and I
haven't attempted to show the actual internal structure of the <classname>String</classname> objects.)
Since strings are objects, a variable of type <classname>String</classname> can only hold a
reference to a string, not the string itself.  This
explains why using the <code>==</code> operator to test strings for equality is not
a good idea. Suppose that <code>greeting</code> is a variable of type
<classname>String</classname>, and that it refers to the string <code>"Hello"</code>. Then
would the test <code>greeting&nbsp;==&nbsp;"Hello"</code> be true? Well, maybe, maybe not.
The variable <code>greeting</code> and the <classname>String</classname> literal <code>"Hello"</code>
each refer to a string that contains the characters H-e-l-l-o. But the strings
could still be different objects, that just happen to contain the same
characters; in that case, <code>greeting&nbsp;==&nbsp;"Hello"</code> would be false.
The function <code>greeting.equals("Hello")</code> tests whether
<code>greeting</code> and <code>"Hello"</code> contain the same characters, which is
almost certainly the question you want to ask. The expression 
<code>greeting&nbsp;==&nbsp;"Hello"</code> tests whether <code>greeting</code> 
and <code>"Hello"</code> contain the same characters <b>stored in the same memory location</b>.
(Of course, a <classname>String</classname> variable such as <code>greeting</code>
can also contain the special value <code>null</code>, and it <b>would</b> make
sense to use the <code>==</code> operator to test whether "<code>greeting&nbsp;==&nbsp;null</code>".)
</p>

<break/>

<p>The fact that variables hold references to objects, not objects themselves,
has a couple of other consequences that you should be aware of. They follow
logically, if you just keep in mind the basic fact that the object is not
stored in the variable. The object is somewhere else; the variable points to it.</p>

<p>Suppose that a variable that refers to an object is declared to be
<code>final</code>. This means that the value stored in the variable can never be
changed, once the variable has been initialized. The value stored in the
variable is a reference to the object. So the variable will continue to refer
to the same object as long as the variable exists. However, this does not
prevent the data <b>in the object</b> from changing. The variable is
<code>final</code>, not the object. It's perfectly legal to say</p>

<pre>final Student stu = new Student();

stu.name = "John Doe";  // Change data in the object;
                        // The value stored in stu is not changed!
                        // It still refers to the same object.</pre>

<p>Next, suppose that <code>obj</code> is a variable that refers to an object.
Let's consider what happens when <code>obj</code> is passed as an actual parameter
to a subroutine. The value of <code>obj</code> is assigned to a formal parameter in
the subroutine, and the subroutine is executed. The subroutine has no power to
change the value stored in the variable, <code>obj</code>. It only has a copy of
that value. However, the value is a reference to an object. Since the
subroutine has a reference to the object, it can change the data stored <b>in</b> the
object. After the subroutine ends, <code>obj</code> still points to the same
object, but the data stored <b>in the object</b> might have changed.
Suppose <code>x</code> is a variable of type <ptype>int</ptype> and <code>stu</code> is a
variable of type <code>Student</code>. Compare:</p>

<pre>void dontChange(int z) {                void change(Student s) {
    z = 42;                                  s.name = "Fred";
}                                       }

<newcode>The lines:                              The lines:</newcode>

   x = 17;                                 stu.name = "Jane";
   dontChange(x);                          change(stu);
   System.out.println(x);                  System.out.println(stu.name);
 
<newcode>output the value 17.                    output the value "Fred".
 
The value of x is <b>not</b>                   The value of stu is not
changed by the subroutine,              changed, but stu.name <b>is</b> changed.
which is equivalent to                  This is equivalent to</newcode>

   z = x;                                  s = stu;
   z = 42;                                 s.name = "Fred";</pre>
   
</subsection>
   
<subsection id="OOP.1.3" title="Getters and Setters">

<p>When writing new classes, it's a good idea to pay attention to the issue
of access control.  Recall that making a member of a class <code>public</code>
makes it accessible from anywhere, including from other classes.  On the
other hand, a <code>private</code> member can only be used in the class
where it is defined.</p>
   
<p>In the opinion of many programmers, almost all member variables should
be declared <code>private</code>.  This gives you complete control over what
can be done with the variable.  Even if the variable itself is private,
you can allow other classes to find out what its value is by providing
a <code>public</code> <newword>accessor method</newword> that returns the
value of the variable.  For example, if your class contains a <code>private</code>
member variable, <code>title</code>, of type <classname>String</classname>, you
can provide a method</p>

<pre>public String getTitle() {
    return title;
}</pre>

   
<np>that returns the value of <code>title</code>.  By convention, the name of
an accessor method for a variable is obtained by capitalizing the name of variable and
adding "get" in front of the name.  So, for the variable <code>title</code>, we get
an accessor method named "get" <code>+</code> "Title", or <code>getTitle()</code>.
Because of this naming convention, accessor methods are more often referred to
as <newword>getter methods</newword>.  A getter method provides "read access" to
a variable.  (Sometimes for <ptype>boolean</ptype> variables, "is" is used in place
of "get".  For example, a getter for a <ptype>boolean</ptype> member variable named
<code>done</code> might be called <code>isDone()</code>.)</np>
   
<p>You might also want to allow "write access" to a <code>private</code> variable.
That is, you might want to make it possible for other classes to specify a new value
for the variable.  This is done with a <newword>setter method</newword>.  (If you don't
like simple, Anglo-Saxon words, you can use the fancier term <newword>mutator method</newword>.)
The name of a setter method should consist of "set" followed by a capitalized copy of
the variable's name, and it should have a parameter with the same type as the
variable.  A setter method for the variable <code>title</code> could be written</p>
   
<pre>public void setTitle( String newTitle ) {
   title = newTitle;
}</pre>
   
<p>It is actually very common to provide both a getter and a setter method for
a private member variable.  Since this allows other classes both to see and to
change the value of the variable, you might wonder why not just make the
variable <code>public</code>?  The reason is that getters and setters are not
restricted to simply reading and writing the variable's value.  In fact,
they can take any action at all.  For example, a getter method might keep
track of the number of times that the variable has been accessed:</p>

<pre>public String getTitle() {
    titleAccessCount++;  // Increment member variable titleAccessCount.
    return title;
}</pre>

<np>and a setter method might check that the value that is being
assigned to the variable is legal:</np>
   
<pre>public void setTitle( String newTitle ) {
   if ( newTitle == null )   // Don't allow null strings as titles!
      title = "(Untitled)";  // Use an appropriate default value instead.
   else
      title = newTitle;
}</pre>
   
<np>Even if you can't think of any extra chores to do in a getter or setter
method, you might change your mind in the future when you redesign and
improve your class.  If you've used a getter and setter from the beginning,
you can make the modification to your class without affecting any of the
classes that use your class.  The <code>private</code> member variable
is not part of the public interface of your class; only the <code>public</code>
getter and setter methods are, and you are free to change their implementations
without changing the public interface of your class.
If you <b>haven't</b> used get and set from
the beginning, you'll have to contact everyone who uses your class and
tell them, "Sorry people, you'll have to track down every use that you've
made of this variable and change your code to use my new get and set
methods instead."</np>
   
<p>A couple of final notes:  Some advanced aspects of Java rely on the
naming convention for getter and setter methods, so it's a good idea to
follow the convention rigorously.  And though I've been talking about using
getter and setter methods for a variable, you can define get and set
methods even if there is no variable.  A getter and/or setter method defines
a <newword>property</newword> of the class, that might or might not correspond
to a variable.  For example, if a class includes a <code>public</code> <code>void</code>
instance method with signature <code>setValue(double)</code>, then the class
has a "property" named <code>value</code> of type <ptype>double</ptype>, and
it has this property whether or not the class has a member variable
named <code>value</code>.
</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="OOP.1.4" title="Arrays and Objects">

<p>As I noted in <localref href="control.7a.1"/>, arrays are objects.  Like <classname>Strings</classname>
they are special objects, with their own unique syntax.  An array type such as
<atype>int[]</atype> or <atype>String[]</atype> is actually a class, and arrays
are created using a special version of the <code>new</code> operator.
As in the case for other object variables,  an array variable can never
hold an actual array&mdash;only a reference to an array object.  The array object 
itself exists in the heap.  It is possible for an array variable to hold the value
<code>null</code>, which means there is no actual array.</p>

<p>For example, suppose that <code>list</code> is a variable of type <atype>int[]</atype>.
If the value of <code>list</code> is <code>null</code>, then any attempt to access
<code>list.length</code> or an array element <code>list[i]</code> would be an error
and would cause an exception of type <classname>NullPointerException</classname>.  If
<code>newlist</code> is another variable of type <atype>int[]</atype>, then the
assignment statement</p>

<pre>newlist = list;</pre>

<np>only copies the reference value in <code>list</code> into <code>newlist</code>.
If <code>list</code> is <code>null</code>, the result is that <code>newlist</code> will also be <code>null</code>.
If <code>list</code> points to an array, the assignment statement does <b>not</b> make a copy of the
array.  It just sets <code>newlist</code> to refer to the same array as <code>list</code>.  For
example, the output of the following code segment</np>

<pre>list = new int[3];
list[1] = 17;
newlist = list; // newlist points to the same array as list!
newlist[1] = 42;
System.out.println( list[1] );</pre>

<np>would be 42, not 17, since <code>list[1]</code> and <code>newlist[1]</code> are just different names
for the same element in the array.  All this is very natural, once you understand that
arrays are objects and array variables hold pointers to arrays.</np>

<p>This fact also comes into play when an array is passed as a parameter to a subroutine.
The value that is copied into the subroutine is a pointer to the array.  The array is
not copied.  Since the subroutine has a reference to the original array, any changes that
it makes to elements of the array are being made to the original and will persist after
the subroutine returns.</p>

<break/>

<p>Arrays are objects.  They can also hold objects.
The base type of an array can be a class.  We have already seen this when we used
arrays of type <atype>String[]</atype>, but any class can be used as the base type.
For example, suppose <classname>Student</classname> is the class defined earlier in
this section.  Then we can have arrays of type <atype>Student[]</atype>.  For an array
of type <atype>Student[]</atype>, each element of the array is a variable of type
<classname>Student</classname>.  To store information about 30 students,
we could use an array</p>

<pre>Student[] classlist;  // Declare a variable of type Student[].
classlist = new Student[30];  // The variable now points to an array.</pre>

<np>The array has 30 elements, <code>classlist[0]</code>, <code>classlist[1]</code>, 
&dots; <code>classlist[29]</code>.  When the array is created, it is filled with the
default initial value, which for an object type is <code>null</code>.  So, although
we have 30 array elements of type <classname>Student</classname>, we don't yet have
any actual <classname>Student</classname> objects!  All we have is 30 nulls.
If we want student objects, we have to create them:</np>

<pre>Student[] classlist;
classlist = new Student[30];
for ( int i = 0; i &lt; 30; i++ ) {
    classlist[i] = new Student();
}</pre>

<np>Once we have done this, each <code>classlist[i]</code> points to an object of type
<classname>Student</classname>.  If we want to talk about the name of student number 3,
we can use <code>classlist[3].name</code>.  The average for student number <code>i</code>
can be computed by calling <code>classlist[i].getAverage()</code>.  You can do anything
with <code>classlist[i]</code> that you could do with any other variable of type
<classname>Student</classname>.</np>

</subsection>

</section>