<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes7.dtd" >

<section id="OOP.3" title="Programming with Objects">


<p><start><big>T</big>here are several ways</start> in which object-oriented
concepts can be applied to the process of designing and writing programs. The
broadest of these is <newword>object-oriented analysis and design</newword> 
which applies an object-oriented methodology to the earliest
stages of program development, during which the overall design of a program is
created. Here, the idea is to identify things in the problem domain that can be
modeled as objects. On another level, object-oriented programming encourages
programmers to produce <newword>generalized software components</newword> 
that can be used in a wide variety of programming projects.</p>
   
   
<p>Of course, for the most part, you will experience "generalized software
components" by using the standard classes that come along with Java.  We begin
this section by looking at some built-in classes that are used for creating
objects.  At the end of the section, we will get back to generalities.</p>

<subsection id="OOP.3.1" title="Some Built-in Classes">

<p>Although the focus of object-oriented programming is generally on the design
and implementation of new classes, it's important not to forget that the
designers of Java have already provided a large number of reusable classes.
Some of these classes are meant to be extended to produce new classes, while
others can be used directly to create useful objects. A true mastery of Java
requires familiarity with a large number of built-in classes&mdash;something that
takes a lot of time and experience to develop. Let's take a moment to look at a 
few built-in classes that you might find useful.</p>

<p>A string can be built up from smaller pieces using the <code>+</code> operator,
but this is not always efficient. If <code>str</code> is a <classname>String</classname> and
<code>ch</code> is a character, then executing the command
"<code>str&nbsp;= str&nbsp;+&nbsp;ch;</code>" involves creating a whole new
string that is a copy of <code>str</code>, with the value of <code>ch</code> appended
onto the end. Copying the string takes some time. Building up a long string
letter by letter would require a surprising amount of processing. The class
<classname>StringBuilder</classname> makes it possible to be efficient about
building up a long string from a number of smaller pieces.  To do this,
you must make an object belonging to the <classname>StringBuilder</classname>
class.  For example:</p>
   
<pre>StringBuilder builder = new StringBuilder();</pre>
   
<np>(This statement both declares the variable <code>builder</code> and initializes
it to refer to a newly created <classname>StringBuilder</classname> object.  Combining
declaration with initialization was covered in <localref href="subroutines.7.1"/> and works
for objects just as it does for primitive types.)</np> 
   
 <p>Like a <classname>String</classname>, a <classname>StringBuilder</classname> 
contains a sequence of characters.
However, it is possible to add new characters onto the end of a
<code>StringBuilder</code> without continually making copies of the data that it already
contains. If
<code>x</code> is a value of any type and <code>builder</code> is the variable
defined above, then the command <code>builder.append(x)</code>
will add <code>x</code>, converted into a string representation, onto the end of
the data that was already in the builder.  This can be done more efficiently than
copying the data every time something is appended. A&nbsp;long
string can be built up in a <classname>StringBuilder</classname> using a sequence of
<code>append()</code> commands. When the string is complete, the function
<code>builder.toString()</code> will return a copy of the string in the builder as an
ordinary value of type <classname>String</classname>. The <classname>StringBuilder</classname>
class is in the standard package <code>java.lang</code>, so you can use its simple name without
importing it.</p>

<p>A number of useful classes are collected in the package <code>java.util</code>.
For example, this package contains classes for working with collections of
objects.  We
will study such collection classes extensively in <localref href="generics"/>.
Another class in this package, <code>java.util.Date</code>, is
used to represent times. When a <code>Date</code> object is constructed without
parameters, the result represents the current date and time, so an easy way to
display this information is:</p>

<pre>System.out.println( new Date() );</pre>

<np>Of course, since it is in the package <code>java.util</code>,
in order to use the <code>Date</code> class in your program, you must make it
available by importing it with one of the statements
"<code>import&nbsp;java.util.Date;</code>" or "<code>import&nbsp;java.util.*;</code>"
at the beginning of your program. (See <localref href="subroutines.5.3"/>
for a discussion of packages and <code>import</code>.)</np>

<p>I will also mention the class <code>java.util.Random</code>. An object
belonging to this class is a <i>source</i> of random numbers (or, more precisely
pseudorandom numbers).  The standard
function <code>Math.random()</code> uses one of these objects behind the scenes to
generate its random numbers. An object of type <code>Random</code> can generate
random integers, as well as random real numbers. If <code>randGen</code> is created
with the command:</p>

<pre>Random randGen = new Random();</pre>

<np>and if <code>N</code> is a positive integer, then <code>randGen.nextInt(N)</code>
generates a random integer in the range from <code>0</code> to <code>N-1</code>. For
example, this makes it a little easier to roll a pair of dice. Instead of
saying "<code>die1&nbsp;= (int)(6*Math.random())+1;</code>", one can say
"<code>die1&nbsp;= randGen.nextInt(6)+1;</code>". (Since you also have to
import the class <code>java.util.Random</code> and create the <code>Random</code>
object, you might not agree that it is actually easier.)  An object of
type <code>Random</code> can also be used to generate so-called
Gaussian distributed random real numbers.</np>

<p>Many of Java's standard classes are used in GUI programming. You will encounter
a number of them in the <localref href="GUI1"/>.  Here, I will mention only
the class <classname>Color</classname>,
from the package <code>java.awt</code>, so that I can use it in the next example.
A <classname>Color</classname> object represents a 
color that can be used for drawing.  In <localref href="control.8"/>, you encountered
color constants such as <code>Color.RED</code>.  These constants are final, static member
variables in the <classname>Color</classname> class, and their values are objects of type
<classname>Color</classname>.  It is also possible to create new color objects.  Class
<classname>Color</classname> has several constructors.  One of them, which is called
as <code>new&nbsp;Color(r,g,b)</code>, takes three integer parameters to specify the
red, green, and blue components of the color.  The parameters must be in the range 0
to 255.  Another constructor, <code>new&nbsp;Color(r,g,b,t)</code>, adds a fourth
integer parameter, which must also be in the range 0 to 255.  The fourth parameter
determines how transparent or opaque the color is.  When you draw with a transparent
color, the background shows through the color to some extent.  A larger value of
the parameter <code>t</code> gives a color that is less transparent and more opaque.
(If you know hexadecimal color codes, there is a constructor for you.  It takes one
parameter of type <ptype>int</ptype> that encodes all the color components.
For example, <code>new&nbsp;Color(0x8B5413)</code> creates a brown color.)</p>

<p>A <classname>Color</classname> object has only a few instance methods that you
are likely to use.  Mainly, there are functions like <code>getRed()</code> to
get the individual color components of the color.  There are no "setter" methods
to change the color components.  In fact, a <classname>Color</classname> is
an <newword>immutable</newword> object, meaning that all of its instance variables
are <code>final</code> and cannot be changed after the object is created.
<classname>Strings</classname> are another example of immutable objects, and we
will make some of our own later in this section.</p>
   
<p>The main point of all this, again, is that many problems have already been solved,
and the solutions are available in Java's standard classes. If you are faced
with a task that looks like it should be fairly common, it might be worth
looking through a Java reference to see whether someone has already written a
class that you can use.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="OOP.3.3" title='The class &leftquote;Object"'>

<p>We have already seen that one of the major features of object-oriented programming
is the ability to create subclasses of a class.   The subclass inherits all the properties
or behaviors of the class, but can modify and add to what it inherits.  In <localref href="OOP.5"/>,
you'll learn how to create subclasses.   What you don't
know yet is that <b>every</b> class in Java (with just one exception) is a subclass
of some other class.  If you create a class and don't explicitly make it a subclass of
some other class, then it automatically becomes a subclass of the special class
named <classname>Object</classname>.  (<classname>Object</classname> is the one class
that is not a subclass of any other class.)</p>

<p>Class <classname>Object</classname> defines several instance methods that are inherited by
every other class.  These methods can be used with any object whatsoever. I will mention
just one of them here.  You will encounter more of them later in the book.</p>
   
<p>The instance method <code>toString()</code> in class <classname>Object</classname> returns
a value of type <classname>String</classname> that is supposed to be a string representation
of the object.  You've already used this method implicitly,  any time you've printed out an object or
concatenated an object onto a string.  When you use an object in a context that requires a
string, the object is automatically converted to type <classname>String</classname> 
by calling its <code>toString()</code> method.</p>

<p>The version of <code>toString</code> that is defined in <classname>Object</classname> just returns
the name of the class that the object belongs to, concatenated with a code number called the
<newword>hash code</newword> of the object; this is not very useful. When you create a class,
you can write a new <code>toString()</code> method for it, which will replace the inherited
version.  For example, we might add the following method to any of the <classname>PairOfDice</classname>
classes from the previous section:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Return a String representation of a pair of dice, where die1
 * and die2 are instance variables containing the numbers that are
 * showing on the two dice.
 */
public String toString() {
   if (die1 == die2)
      return "double " + die1;
   else
      return die1 + " and " + die2;
}</pre>
   
<np>If <code>dice</code> refers to a <classname>PairOfDice</classname> object, then
<code>dice.toString()</code> will return strings such as "3&nbsp;and&nbsp;6",
"5&nbsp;and&nbsp;1", and "double&nbsp;2", depending on the numbers showing on the dice.
This method would be used automatically to convert <code>dice</code> to type
<classname>String</classname> in a statement such as</np>
   
<pre>System.out.println( "The dice came up " + dice );</pre>
   
<np>so this statement might output, "The dice came up 5 and&nbsp;1" or "The
dice came up double 2".  You'll see another example of a <code>toString()</code>
method in the <localref href="OOP.4">next section</localref>.</np>
   
</subsection>

   
<subsection id="OOP.3.2" title="Writing and Using a Class">

<p>As an example, we will write an animation program, based on the same
animation framework that was used in <localref href="control.8.3"/>.  The animation
shows a number of semi-transparent disk that grow in size as the
animation plays.  The disks have random colors and locations.  When a disk gets too
big, or sometimes just at random, the disk disappears and is replaced with a
new disk at a random location.  Here is a screenshot from the program:
</p>

<img src="growing-circles.png" width="300" height="240" alt="100 translucent filled circles"
      tex="growing-circles.eps" texscale="0.6"/>
      
<np>A disk in this program can be represented as an object.  A disk has properties&mdash;color,
location, and size&mdash;that can be instance variables in the object.  As for instance
methods, we need to think about what we might want to do with a disk.  An obvious candidate
is that we need to be able to draw it, so we can include an instance method
<code>draw(g)</code>, where <code>g</code> is a graphics context that will be used to
do the drawing.  The class can also include one or more constructors.  A constructor
initializes the object.  It's not always clear what data should be provided as parameters
to the constructors.  In this case, as an example,
the constructor's parameters specify the location and size for
the circle, but the constructor makes up a color using random values for the red, green,
and blue components.  Here's the complete class:</np>

<pre>import java.awt.Color;  // import some standard GUI classes
import java.awt.Graphics;

/**
 * A simple class that holds the size, color, and location of a colored disk,
 * with a method for drawing the filled circle in a graphics context.  The 
 * circle is drawn as a filled oval, with a black outline.
 */
public class CircleInfo {
    
    public int radius;    // The radius of the circle.
    public int x,y;       // The location of the center of the circle.
    public Color color;   // The color of the circle.
    
    /**
     * Create a CircleInfo with a given location and radius and with a
     * randomly selected, semi-transparent color.
     * @param centerX   The x coordinate of the center.
     * @param centerY   The y coordinate of the center.
     * @param rad       The radius of the circle.
     */
    public CircleInfo( int centerX, int centerY, int rad ) {
        x = centerX;
        y = centerY;
        radius = rad;
        int red = (int)(255*Math.random());
        int green = (int)(255*Math.random());
        int blue = (int)(255*Math.random());
        color = new Color(red,green,blue, 100);
    }
    
    /**
     * Draw the disk in graphics context g, with a black outline.
     */
    public void draw( Graphics g ) {
        g.setColor( color );
        g.fillOval( x - radius, y - radius, 2*radius, 2*radius );
        g.setColor( Color.BLACK );
        g.drawOval( x - radius, y - radius, 2*radius, 2*radius );
    }
}</pre>

<np>It would probably be better style to write getters and setters for the
instance variables, but to keep things simple, I made them public.</np>

<p>The main program for my animation is a class <classname>GrowingCircleAnimation</classname>.
The program uses 100 disks, each one represented by an object of type
<classname>CircleInfo</classname>.  To make that manageable, the program uses
an array of objects.  The array variable is a member variable in the class:
</p>

<pre>private CircleInfo[] circleData; // holds the data for all 100 circles</pre>

<np>Note that it is not <code>static</code>.  GUI programming generally uses objects
rather than static variables and methods.  Basically, this is because we can imagine
having several <classname>GrowingCircleAnimations</classname> going on at the same time,
each with its own array of disks.  Each animation would be represented by an object,
and each object will need to have its own <code>circleData</code> instance variable.  If
<code>circleData</code> were static, there would only be one array and all the
animations would show exactly the same thing.</np>

<p>The array must be created and filled with data.  The array is created using
<code>new&nbsp;CircleInfo[100]</code>, and then 100 objects of type <classname>CircleInfo</classname>
are created to fill the array.  The new objects are created with random locations and sizes.
In the program, this is done before drawing the first frame of the animation.  Here is the
code, where <code>width</code> and <code>height</code> are the size of the
drawing area:</p>

<pre>circleData = new CircleInfo[100];  // create the array

for (int i = 0; i &lt; circleData.length; i++) { // create the objects
    circleData[i] = new CircleInfo( 
                            (int)(width*Math.random()),
                            (int)(height*Math.random()),
                            (int)(100*Math.random()) );
}</pre>

<np>In each frame, the radius of the disk is increased and the disk is drawn using
the code</np>

<pre>circleData[i].radius++;
circleData[i].draw(g);</pre>

<np>These statements look complicated, so let's unpack them.  Now,
<code>circleData[i]</code> is an element of the array <code>circleData</code>.
That means that it is a variable of type <classname>CircleInfo</classname>.  This variable
refers to an object of type <classname>CircleInfo</classname>, which contains a public
instance variable named <code>radius</code>.  This means that <code>circleData[i].radius</code> is the
full name for that variable.  Since it is a variable of type <ptype>int</ptype>, we
can use the <code>++</code> operator to increment its value.  So the effect
of <code>circleData[i].radius++</code> is to increase the radius of the circle by one.
The second line of code is similar, but in that statement, <code>circleData[i].draw</code>
is an instance method in the <classname>CircleInfo</classname> object.  The statement
<code>circleData[i].draw(g)</code> calls that instance method with parameter&nbsp;<code>g</code>.
</np>

<p>The source code example <sourceref href="GrowingCircleAnimation.java"/> contains the
full source code for the program, if you are interested.  Since the program uses
class <classname>CircleInfo</classname>, you will also need a copy of <sourceref href="CircleInfo.java"/>
in order to compile and run the program.
</p>

</subsection>
   
   

<subsection id="OOP.3.4" title="Object-oriented Analysis and Design">

<p>Every programmer builds up a stock of techniques and expertise expressed as
snippets of code that can be reused in new programs using the tried-and-true
method of cut-and-paste: The old code is physically copied into the new program
and then edited to customize it as necessary. The problem is that the editing
is error-prone and time-consuming, and the whole enterprise is dependent on the
programmer's ability to pull out that particular piece of code from last year's
project that looks like it might be made to fit. (On the level of a corporation
that wants to save money by not reinventing the wheel for each new project,
just keeping track of all the old wheels becomes a major task.)</p>

<p>Well-designed classes are software components that can be reused without
editing. A well-designed class is not carefully crafted to do a particular job
in a particular program. Instead, it is crafted to model some particular type
of object or a single coherent concept. Since objects and concepts can recur in
many problems, a well-designed class is likely to be reusable without
modification in a variety of projects.</p>

<p>Furthermore, in an object-oriented programming language, it is possible to
make <newword>subclasses</newword> of an existing class. This makes
classes even more reusable. If a class needs to be customized, a subclass can
be created, and additions or modifications can be made in the subclass without
making any changes to the original class. This can be done even if the
programmer doesn't have access to the source code of the class and doesn't know
any details of its internal, hidden implementation.</p>

<break/>
   
<p>The <classname>PairOfDice</classname> class in the <localref href="OOP.2">previous section</localref>
is already an example of a generalized software component, although one that
could certainly be improved. The class represents a single, coherent concept,
"a pair of dice." The instance variables hold the data relevant to the state of
the dice, that is, the number showing on each of the dice. The instance method
represents the behavior of a pair of dice, that is, the ability to be rolled.
This class would be reusable in many different programming projects.</p>

<p>On the other hand, the <classname>Student</classname> class from the previous section is
not very reusable. It seems to be crafted to represent students in a particular
course where the grade will be based on three tests. If there are more tests or
quizzes or papers, it's useless. If there are two people in the class who have
the same name, we are in trouble (one reason why numerical student ID's are
often used). Admittedly, it's much more difficult to develop a general-purpose
student class than a general-purpose pair-of-dice class. But this particular
<classname>Student</classname> class is good mostly as an example in a programming
textbook.</p>

<break/>

<p>A large programming project goes through a number of stages, starting with
<newword>specification</newword> of the problem to be solved,
followed by <newword>analysis</newword> of the problem and
<newword>design</newword> of a program to solve it. Then comes
<newword>coding</newword>, in which the program's design is expressed
in some actual programming language. This is followed by <newword>testing</newword> 
and <newword>debugging</newword> of the
program. After that comes a long period of <newword>maintenance</newword>, 
which means fixing any new problems that are
found in the program and modifying it to adapt it to changing requirements.
Together, these stages form what is called the <newword>software life cycle</newword>. 
(In the real world, the ideal of consecutive stages is
seldom if ever achieved. During the analysis stage, it might turn out that the
specifications are incomplete or inconsistent. A problem found during testing
requires at least a brief return to the coding stage. If the problem is serious
enough, it might even require a new design. Maintenance usually involves
redoing some of the work from previous stages&dots;.)</p>

<p>Large, complex programming projects are only likely to succeed if a careful,
systematic approach is adopted during all stages of the software life cycle.
The systematic approach to programming, using accepted principles of good
design, is called <newword>software engineering</newword>. The
software engineer tries to efficiently construct programs that verifiably meet
their specifications and that are easy to modify if necessary. There is a wide
range of "methodologies" that can be applied to help in the systematic design
of programs. (Most of these methodologies seem to involve drawing little boxes
to represent program components, with labeled arrows to represent relationships
among the boxes.)</p>

<p>We have been discussing object orientation in programming languages, which
is relevant to the coding stage of program development. But there are also
object-oriented methodologies for analysis and design. The question in this
stage of the software life cycle is, How can one discover or invent the overall
structure of a program? As an example of a rather simple object-oriented
approach to analysis and design, consider this advice: Write down a description
of the problem. Underline all the nouns in that description. The nouns should
be considered as candidates for becoming classes or objects in the program
design. Similarly, underline all the verbs. These are candidates for methods.
This is your starting point. Further analysis might uncover the need for more
classes and methods, and it might reveal that subclassing can be used to take
advantage of similarities among classes.</p>

<p>This is perhaps a bit simple-minded, but the idea is clear and the general
approach can be effective: Analyze the problem to discover the concepts that
are involved, and create classes to represent those concepts. The design should
arise from the problem itself, and you should end up with a program whose
structure reflects the structure of the problem in a natural way.</p>
   
</subsection>


</section>