<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="OOP.5" title="Inheritance, Polymorphism, and Abstract Classes" shorttitle="Inheritance and Polymorphism">
   
<p><start><big>A</big> class represents a set of objects</start> which share the
same structure and behaviors. The class determines the structure of objects by
specifying variables that are contained in each instance of the class, and it
determines behavior by providing the instance methods that express the behavior
of the objects. This is a powerful idea. However, something like this can be
done in most programming languages. The central new idea in object-oriented
programming&mdash;the idea that really distinguishes it from traditional
programming&mdash;is to allow classes to express the similarities among objects
that share <b>some</b>, but not all, of their structure and behavior.
Such similarities can be expressed using <newword>inheritance</newword> 
and <newword>polymorphism</newword>.</p>

   
<subsection id="OOP.5.1" title="Extending Existing Classes">
<p>Any programmer should know what is meant by
subclass, inheritance, and polymorphism. However, it will probably be a while
before you actually do anything with inheritance except for extending classes
that already exist.  In the first part of this section, we look at how that
is done.</p>

<p>In day-to-day programming, especially for programmers who are just beginning
to work with objects, subclassing is used mainly in one situation: There is an
existing class that can be adapted with a few changes or additions. This is
much more common than designing groups of classes and subclasses from scratch.
The existing class can be <newword>extended</newword> to make a
subclass. The syntax for this is</p>

<pre>public class <bnf>subclass-name</bnf> extends <bnf>existing-class-name</bnf> {
   .
   .   // Changes and additions.
   .
}</pre>


<p>As an example, suppose you want to write a program that plays the card game,
Blackjack. You can use the <classname>Card</classname>, 
<classname>Hand</classname>, and <classname>Deck</classname>
classes developed in <localref href="OOP.4"/>. However, a hand in the
game of Blackjack is a little different from a hand of cards in general, since
it must be possible to compute the "value" of a Blackjack hand according to the
rules of the game. The rules are as follows: The value of a hand is obtained by
adding up the values of the cards in the hand. The value of a numeric card such
as a three or a ten is its numerical value. The value of a Jack, Queen, or King
is 10. The value of an Ace can be either 1 or 11. An Ace should be counted as
11 unless doing so would put the total value of the hand over 21. Note that
this means that the second, third, or fourth Ace in the hand will always be
counted as 1.</p>

<p>One way to handle this is to extend the existing <classname>Hand</classname> class by
adding a method that computes the Blackjack value of the hand. Here's the
definition of such a class:</p>

<pre>public class BlackjackHand <newcode>extends Hand</newcode> {

    /**
     * Computes and returns the value of this hand in the game
     * of Blackjack.
     */
    public int getBlackjackValue() {

        int val;      // The value computed for the hand.
        boolean ace;  // This will be set to true if the
                      //   hand contains an ace.
        int cards;    // Number of cards in the hand.

        val = 0;
        ace = false;
        cards = getCardCount();  // (method defined in class Hand.)

        for ( int i = 0;  i &lt; cards;  i++ ) {
                // Add the value of the i-th card in the hand.
            Card card;    // The i-th card; 
            int cardVal;  // The blackjack value of the i-th card.
            card = getCard(i);
            cardVal = card.getValue();  // The normal value, 1 to 13.
            if (cardVal &gt; 10) {
                cardVal = 10;   // For a Jack, Queen, or King.
            }
            if (cardVal == 1) {
                ace = true;     // There is at least one ace.
            }
            val = val + cardVal;
         }

         // Now, val is the value of the hand, counting any ace as 1.
         // If there is an ace, and if changing its value from 1 to 
         // 11 would leave the score less than or equal to 21,
         // then do so by adding the extra 10 points to val. 

         if ( ace == true  &amp;&amp;  val + 10 &lt;= 21 )
             val = val + 10;

         return val;

    }  // end getBlackjackValue()

} // end class BlackjackHand</pre>

<np>Since <classname>BlackjackHand</classname> is a subclass of <classname>Hand</classname>, an object of
type <classname>BlackjackHand</classname> contains all the instance variables and instance
methods defined in <classname>Hand</classname>, plus the new instance method named
<code>getBlackjackValue()</code>. For example, if <code>bjh</code> is a variable of
type <code>BlackjackHand</code>, then the following are all legal:
<code>bjh.getCardCount()</code>, <code>bjh.removeCard(0)</code>, and
<code>bjh.getBlackjackValue()</code>.  The first two methods are defined in <classname>Hand</classname>,
but are inherited by <classname>BlackjackHand</classname>.</np>

<p>Variables and methods from the <classname>Hand</classname> class  are
inherited by <classname>BlackjackHand</classname>, and they can be used 
in the definition of <classname>BlackjackHand</classname> just as if they
were actually defined in that class&mdash;except for any that are
declared to be <code>private</code>, which prevents access even by subclasses. The statement "<code>cards&nbsp;=
getCardCount();</code>" in the above definition of <code>getBlackjackValue()</code>
calls the instance method <code>getCardCount()</code>, which was defined in
<classname>Hand</classname>.</p>

<p>Extending existing classes is an easy way to build on previous work. We'll
see that many standard classes have been written specifically to be used as the
basis for making subclasses.</p>
   
<break/>
   
<p>Access modifiers such as <code>public</code> and <code>private</code> are used
to control access to members of a class.  There is one more access modifier,
<newword>protected</newword>, that comes into the picture when subclasses are taken
into consideration.  When <code>protected</code> is applied as an access modifier
to a method or member variable in a class,
that member can be used in subclasses&mdash;direct or indirect&mdash;of the class in which
it is defined, but it cannot be used in non-subclasses.  (There is an exception: A <code>protected</code> member
can also be accessed by any class in the same package as the class that contains the protected member.
Recall that using no access modifier makes a member accessible to classes in the same package, and nowhere
else.  Using the <code>protected</code> modifier is strictly more liberal than using no modifier
at all:  It allows access from classes in the same package and from <b>subclasses</b> that are not
in the same package.)</p>
   
<p>When you declare a method or member variable to be <code>protected</code>, you are saying
that it is part of the implementation of the class, rather than part of the public interface of
the class.  However, you are allowing subclasses to use and modify that part of the implementation.</p>
   
<p>For example, consider a <classname>PairOfDice</classname> class that has instance
variables <code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code>
to represent the numbers appearing on the two dice.  We could make those variables
<code>private</code> to make it impossible to change their values from outside the
class, while still allowing read access through getter methods.  However, if we think
it possible that <classname>PairOfDice</classname> will be used to create subclasses,
we might want to make it possible for subclasses to change the numbers on the dice.
For example, a <classname>GraphicalDice</classname> subclass that draws the dice might
want to change the numbers at other times besides when the dice are rolled.
In that case, we could make <code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code>
<code>protected</code>, which would allow the
subclass to change their values without making them public to the rest of the world.
(An even better idea would be to define <code>protected</code> setter methods for
the variables.  A setter method could, for example, ensure that the value that is
being assigned to the variable is in the legal range 1 through&nbsp;6.)</p>
   
</subsection>
   
<subsection id="OOP.5.2" title="Inheritance and Class Hierarchy">
   
<p>The term <newword>inheritance</newword> refers to the fact that
one class can inherit part or all of its structure and behavior from another
class.  The class that does the inheriting is said to be a <newword>subclass</newword> 
of the class from which it inherits. If class B is a
subclass of class A, we also say that class A is a <newword>superclass</newword> of 
class B. (Sometimes the terms <newword>derived class</newword> and <newword>base class</newword> are
used instead of subclass and superclass; this is the common terminology in&nbsp;C++.) 
A subclass can add to the structure
and behavior that it inherits. It can also replace or modify inherited behavior
(though not inherited structure). The relationship between subclass and
superclass is sometimes shown by a diagram in which the subclass is shown
below, and connected to, its superclass, as shown on the left below:</p>


<img src="subclass-superclass.png" width="552" height="223" 
    alt="two class hierarchy diagrams" tex="subclass-superclass.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<p>In Java, to create a class named "B" as a subclass of a class named "A", 
you would write</p>

<pre>class B extends A {
    .
    .  // additions to, and modifications of,
    .  // stuff inherited from class A
    .
}</pre>
   

<p>Several classes
can be declared as subclasses of the same superclass. The subclasses, which
might be referred to as "sibling classes," share some structures and behaviors&mdash;namely, 
the ones they inherit from their common superclass. The superclass
expresses these shared structures and behaviors. In the diagram shown
on the right above,
classes B, C, and D are sibling classes. Inheritance can also extend over
several "generations" of classes. This is shown in the diagram, where class E
is a subclass of class D which is itself a subclass of class A. In this case,
class E is considered to be a subclass of class A, even though it is not a
direct subclass.  This whole set of classes forms a small
<newword>class hierarchy</newword>.</p>

<imageclear/>

</subsection>

<subsection id="OOP.5.3" title="Example: Vehicles">

<p>Let's look at
an example. Suppose that a program has to deal with motor vehicles, including
cars, trucks, and motorcycles. (This might be a program used by a Department of
Motor Vehicles to keep track of registrations.) The program could use a class
named <classname>Vehicle</classname> to represent all types of vehicles.  Since cars, trucks,
and motorcycles are types of vehicles, they would be represented by subclasses
of the <classname>Vehicle</classname> class, as shown in this class hierarchy diagram:</p>

<img width="290" height="123" src="vehicle-hierarchy.png" tex="vehicle-hierarchy.eps" texscale="0.6"/> 
   
<np>The <classname>Vehicle</classname>
class would include instance variables such as <code>registrationNumber</code> and
<code>owner</code> and instance methods such as <code>transferOwnership()</code>. These
are variables and methods common to all vehicles. The three subclasses of
<classname>Vehicle</classname>&mdash;<classname>Car</classname>, 
<classname>Truck</classname>, and <classname>Motorcycle</classname>&mdash;could
then be used to hold variables and methods specific to particular types
of vehicles. The <classname>Car</classname> class might add an instance variable
<code>numberOfDoors</code>, the <classname>Truck</classname> class might have
<code>numberOfAxles</code>, and the <classname>Motorcycle</classname> class could have a boolean
variable <code>hasSidecar</code>. (Well, it <u>could</u> in theory at least, even
if it might give a chuckle to the people at the Department of Motor Vehicles.)
The declarations of these classes in a Java program would look, in outline, like
this (although they are likely to be  defined
in separate files and declared as <code>public</code> classes):</np>

<pre>class Vehicle {
   int registrationNumber;
   Person owner;  // (Assuming that a Person class has been defined!)
   void transferOwnership(Person newOwner) {
       . . .
   }
   . . .
}

class Car extends Vehicle {
   int numberOfDoors;
   . . .
}

class Truck extends Vehicle {
   int numberOfAxles;
   . . .
}

class Motorcycle extends Vehicle {
   boolean hasSidecar;
   . . .
}</pre>

<p>Suppose that <code>myCar</code> is a variable of type <classname>Car</classname> that has been
declared and initialized with the statement</p>

<pre>Car myCar = new Car();</pre>

<np>Given this declaration, a program could refer to
<code>myCar.numberOfDoors</code>, since <code>numberOfDoors</code> is an instance
variable in the class <code>Car</code>. But since class <classname>Car</classname> extends class
<classname>Vehicle</classname>, a car also has all the structure and behavior of a vehicle.
This means that <code>myCar.registrationNumber</code>, <code>myCar.owner</code>, and
<code>myCar.transferOwnership()</code> also exist.</np>

<p>Now, in the real world, cars, trucks, and motorcycles are in fact vehicles.
The same is true in a program. That is, an object of type <classname>Car</classname> or
<classname>Truck</classname> or <classname>Motorcycle</classname> is automatically an object of type
<classname>Vehicle</classname> too. This brings us to the following Important Fact:</p>

<centered><p><b>A variable that can hold a reference<br/>
to an object of class A can also hold a reference<br/>
to an object belonging to any subclass of A.</b></p>
</centered>

<np>The practical effect of this in our example is that an object of type
<classname>Car</classname> can be assigned to a variable of type <classname>Vehicle</classname>. That is,
it would be legal to say</np>

<pre>Vehicle myVehicle = myCar;</pre>

<np>or even</np>

<pre>Vehicle myVehicle = new Car();</pre>

<np>After either of these statements, the variable <code>myVehicle</code> holds a
reference to a <classname>Vehicle</classname> object that happens to be an instance of the
subclass, <classname>Car</classname>. The object "remembers" that it is in fact a
<classname>Car</classname>, and not <b>just</b> a <classname>Vehicle</classname>. Information about the
actual class of an object is stored as part of that object. It is even possible
to test whether a given object belongs to a given class, using the
<code>instanceof</code> operator. The test:</np>

<pre>if (myVehicle instanceof Car) ...</pre>

<np>determines whether the object referred to by <code>myVehicle</code> is in fact a
car.</np>

<p>On the other hand, the assignment statement</p>

<pre>myCar = myVehicle;  // ERROR!</pre>

<np>would be illegal because <code>myVehicle</code> could potentially refer to other
types of vehicles that are not cars. This is similar to a problem we saw
previously in <localref href="basics.5.6"/>: The computer will not
allow you to assign an <ptype>int</ptype> value to a variable of type <ptype>short</ptype>,
because not every <ptype>int</ptype> is a <ptype>short</ptype>. Similarly, it will not
allow you to assign a value of type <classname>Vehicle</classname> to a variable of type
<classname>Car</classname> because not every vehicle is a car. As in the case of
<ptype>ints</ptype> and <ptype>shorts</ptype>, the solution here is to use type-casting.
If, for some reason, you happen to know that <code>myVehicle</code> does in fact
refer to a <classname>Car</classname>, you can use the type cast <code>(Car)myVehicle</code> to
tell the computer to treat <code>myVehicle</code> as if it were actually of type
<classname>Car</classname>. So, you could say</np>

<pre>myCar = (Car)myVehicle;</pre>

<np>and you could even refer to <code>((Car)myVehicle).numberOfDoors</code>. 
(The parentheses are necessary because of precedence.  The "<code>.</code>"
has higher precedence than the type-cast, so
<code>(Car)myVehicle.numberOfDoors</code> would be read as <code>(Car)(myVehicle.numberOfDoors)</code>,
an attempt to type-cast the <ptype>int</ptype>
<code>myVehicle.numberOfDoors</code> into a <classname>Vehicle</classname>,
which is impossible.)
</np>

<p>As an
example of how this could be used in a program, suppose that you want to print
out relevant data about the <classname>Vehicle</classname> referred to by
<code>myVehicle</code>.  If it's a <classname>Car</classname>, you will want
to print out the car's <code>numberOfDoors</code>, but you can't
say <code>myVehicle.numberOfDoors</code>, since there is no <code>numberOfDoors</code>
in the <classname>Vehicle</classname> class.  But you could say:</p>

<pre>System.out.println("Vehicle Data:");
System.out.println("Registration number:  " 
                              + myVehicle.registrationNumber);
if (myVehicle instanceof Car) {
   System.out.println("Type of vehicle:  Car");
   Car c;
   c = (Car)myVehicle;  // Type-cast to get access to numberOfDoors!
   System.out.println("Number of doors:  " + c.numberOfDoors);
}
else if (myVehicle instanceof Truck) {
   System.out.println("Type of vehicle:  Truck");
   Truck t;
   t = (Truck)myVehicle;  // Type-cast to get access to numberOfAxles!
   System.out.println("Number of axles:  " + t.numberOfAxles);
}
else if (myVehicle instanceof Motorcycle) {
   System.out.println("Type of vehicle:  Motorcycle");
   Motorcycle m;
   m = (Motorcycle)myVehicle;  // Type-cast to get access to hasSidecar!
   System.out.println("Has a sidecar:    " + m.hasSidecar);
}</pre>

<p>Note that for object types, when the computer executes a program, it checks
whether type-casts are valid. So, for example, if <code>myVehicle</code> refers to
an object of type <classname>Truck</classname>, then the type cast <code>(Car)myVehicle</code>
would be an error.  When this happens, an exception of type
<classname>ClassCastException</classname> is thrown.  This check is done at run time,
not compile time, because the actual type of the object referred to by <code>myVehicle</code>
is not known when the program is compiled.  The code above avoids <classname>ClassCastExceptions</classname>
by using <code>instanceof</code> to test the type of the variable before doing a type cast.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="OOP.5.4" title="Polymorphism">


<p>As another example, consider a program that deals with shapes drawn on the
screen. Let's say that the shapes include rectangles, ovals, and roundrects of
various colors.  (A "roundrect" is just a rectangle with rounded corners.)</p>

<img width="494" height="164" alt="(illustration showing various shapes)"
   src="various-shapes.png" tex="various-shapes.eps" texscale="0.6" bordered="true"/>

<p>Three classes, <classname>Rectangle</classname>, <classname>Oval</classname>, 
and <classname>RoundRect</classname>,
could be used to represent the three types of shapes. These three classes would
have a common superclass, <classname>Shape</classname>, to represent features that all three
shapes have in common. The <classname>Shape</classname> class could include instance
variables to represent the color, position, and size of a shape, and it could
include instance methods for changing the values of those properties.
Changing the color, for example, might involve changing the value of an
instance variable, and then redrawing the shape in its new color:</p>

<pre>class Shape {

    Color color; // (must be imported from package java.awt)
                   
    void setColor(Color newColor) {
          // Method to change the color of the shape.
       color = newColor; // change value of instance variable
       redraw(); // redraw shape, which will appear in new color
    }
    
    void redraw() {
          // method for drawing the shape
       ? ? ?  // what commands should go here?
    }

    . . .          // more instance variables and methods
 
} // end of class Shape</pre>

<p>Now, you might see a problem here with the method <code>redraw()</code>. The
problem is that each different type of shape is drawn differently. The method
<code>setColor()</code> can be called for any type of shape. How does the computer
know which shape to draw when it executes the <code>redraw()</code>? Informally, we
can answer the question like this: The computer executes <code>redraw()</code> by
asking the shape to redraw <b>itself</b>. Every shape object knows
what it has to do to redraw itself.</p>

<p>In practice, this means that each of the specific shape classes has its own
<code>redraw()</code> method:</p>

<pre>class Rectangle extends Shape {
   void redraw() {
      . . .  // commands for drawing a rectangle
   }
   . . . // possibly, more methods and variables
}

class Oval extends Shape {
   void redraw() {
      . . .  // commands for drawing an oval
   }
   . . . // possibly, more methods and variables
}

class RoundRect extends Shape {
   void redraw() {
      . . .  // commands for drawing a rounded rectangle
   }
   . . . // possibly, more methods and variables
}</pre>

<p>Suppose that <code>someShape</code> is a variable of type <classname>Shape</classname>.   
Then it could refer to
an object of any of the types <classname>Rectangle</classname>, <classname>Oval</classname>, or
<classname>RoundRect</classname>. As a program executes, and the value of <code>someShape</code>
changes, it could even refer to objects of different types at different times!
Whenever the statement</p>

<pre>someShape.redraw();</pre>

<np>is executed, the redraw method that is actually called is the one
appropriate for the type of object to which <code>someShape</code> actually refers.
There may be no way of telling, from looking at the text of the program, what
shape this statement will draw, since it depends on the value that
<code>someShape</code> happens to have when the program is executed. Even more is
true. Suppose the statement is in a loop and gets executed many times. If the
value of <code>someShape</code> changes as the loop is executed, it is possible that
the very same statement "<code>someShape.redraw();</code>" will call different
methods and draw different kinds of shape as it is executed several times. We say that
the <code>redraw()</code> method is <newword>polymorphic</newword>. A
method is polymorphic if the action performed by the method depends on the
actual type of the object to which the method is applied at run time. Polymorphism is one
of the major distinguishing features of object-oriented programming.  This can be
seen most vividly, perhaps, if we have an array of shapes.  Suppose that
<code>shapelist</code> is a variable of type <atype>Shape[]</atype>,
and that the array has already been created and filled with data.  Some of
the elements in the array might be <classname>Rectangles</classname>,
some might be <classname>Ovals</classname>, and some might be <classname>RoundRects</classname>.
We can draw all the shapes in the array by saying</np>

<pre>for (int i = 0; i &lt; shapelist.length; i++ ) {
    Shape shape = shapelist[i];
    shape.redraw();
}</pre>

<np>As the computer goes through this loop, the statement <code>shape.redraw()</code>
will sometimes draw a rectangle, sometimes an oval, and sometimes a roundrect,
depending on the type of object to which array element number <code>i</code> refers.</np>

<p>Perhaps this becomes more understandable if we change our terminology a bit:
In object-oriented programming, calling a method is often referred to as
sending a <newword>message</newword> to an object. The object
responds to the message by executing the appropriate method. The statement
"<code>someShape.redraw();</code>" is a message to the object referred to by
<code>someShape</code>. Since that object knows what type of object it is, it knows
how it should respond to the message. From this point of view, the computer
always executes "<code>someShape.redraw();</code>" in the same way: by sending a
message. The response to the message depends, naturally, on who receives it.
From this point of view, objects are active entities that send and receive
messages, and polymorphism is a natural, even necessary, part of this view.
Polymorphism just means that different objects can respond to the same message
in different ways.</p>

<p> One of the
most beautiful things about polymorphism is that it lets code that you write do
things that you didn't even conceive of, at the time you wrote it. Suppose that
I decide to add beveled rectangles to the types of shapes my program can deal
with.  A beveled rectangle has a triangle cut off each corner:</p>
   
<img width="185" height="220" src="beveled-rects.png" tex="beveled-rects.eps" alt="some examples of beveled rects"
              texscale="0.6" bordered="yes"/>

   
<p>To implement beveled rectangles, I can write a new subclass, <classname>BeveledRect</classname>, of
class <classname>Shape</classname> and give it its own <code>redraw()</code> method.
Automatically, code that I wrote previously&mdash;such as the statement
<code>someShape.redraw()</code>&mdash;can now suddenly start drawing beveled
rectangles, even though the beveled rectangle class didn't exist when I wrote
the statement!</p>

<break/>

<p>In the statement "<code>someShape.redraw();</code>", the <code>redraw</code> message
is sent to the object <code>someShape</code>. Look back at the method in the
<classname>Shape</classname> class for changing the color of a shape:</p>

<pre>void setColor(Color newColor) {
   color = newColor; // change value of instance variable
   redraw(); // redraw shape, which will appear in new color
}</pre>

<np>A <code>redraw</code> message is sent here, but which object is it sent to?
Well, the <code>setColor</code> method is itself a message that was sent to some
object. The answer is that the <code>redraw</code> message is sent to that <b>same
object</b>, the one that received the <code>setColor</code> message. If that object is
a rectangle, then it contains a <code>redraw()</code> method for drawing rectangles,
and that is the one that is executed.  If the object is an oval, then 
the <code>redraw()</code> method from the <classname>Oval</classname> class is executed. This is what you
should expect, but it means that the "<code>redraw();</code>" statement in the
<code>setColor()</code> method does <b>not</b> necessarily call the
<code>redraw()</code> method in the <classname>Shape</classname> class! The <code>redraw()</code>
method that is executed could be in any subclass of <classname>Shape</classname>.
This is just another case of polymorphism.</np>


</subsection>

<subsection id="OOP.5.5" title="Abstract Classes">

<p>Whenever a <classname>Rectangle</classname>, <classname>Oval</classname>, 
or <classname>RoundRect</classname> object
has to draw itself, it is the <code>redraw()</code> method in the appropriate class
that is executed. This leaves open the question, What does the
<code>redraw()</code> method in the <classname>Shape</classname> class do? How should it be
defined?</p>

<p>The answer may be surprising: We should leave it blank! The fact is that the
class <classname>Shape</classname> represents the abstract idea of a shape, and there is no
way to draw such a thing. Only particular, concrete shapes like rectangles and
ovals can be drawn. So, why should there even be a <code>redraw()</code> method in
the <classname>Shape</classname> class? Well, it has to be there, or it would be illegal to
call it in the <code>setColor()</code> method of the <classname>Shape</classname> class, and it
would be illegal to write "<code>someShape.redraw()</code>;". The compiler would
complain that <code>someShape</code> is a variable of type <classname>Shape</classname> and
there's no <code>redraw()</code> method in the <classname>Shape</classname> class.</p>

<p>Nevertheless the version of <code>redraw()</code> in the <classname>Shape</classname> class itself
will never actually be called. In fact, if you think about it, there can never be any
reason to construct an actual object of type <classname>Shape</classname>! You can have
<b>variables</b> of type <classname>Shape</classname>, but the objects they refer
to will always belong to one of the subclasses of <classname>Shape</classname>. We say that
<classname>Shape</classname> is an <newword>abstract class</newword>. An abstract
class is one that is not used to construct objects, but only as a basis for
making subclasses. An abstract class exists <b>only</b> to express
the common properties of all its subclasses.  A class that is not abstract
is said to be <newword>concrete</newword>.  You can create objects belonging to
a concrete class, but not to an abstract class.  A variable whose type is given
by an abstract class can only refer to objects that belong to concrete subclasses
of the abstract class.</p>

<p>Similarly, we say that the <code>redraw()</code> method in class <classname>Shape</classname>
is an <newword>abstract method</newword>, since it is never meant to
be called. In fact, there is nothing for it to do&mdash;any actual redrawing is
done by <code>redraw()</code> methods in the subclasses of <classname>Shape</classname>. The
<code>redraw()</code> method in <classname>Shape</classname> has to be there. But it is there
only to tell the computer that <b>all</b> <code>Shapes</code> understand the
<code>redraw</code> message. As an abstract method, it exists merely to specify the
common interface of all the actual, concrete versions of <code>redraw()</code> in
the subclasses. There is no reason for the abstract
<code>redraw()</code> in class <classname>Shape</classname> to contain any code at all.</p>

<p><classname>Shape</classname> and its <code>redraw()</code> method are semantically abstract.
You can also tell the computer, syntactically, that they are abstract by adding
the modifier "<code>abstract</code>" to their definitions. For an abstract method,
the block of code that gives the implementation of an ordinary method is
replaced by a semicolon. An implementation must then be provided for the abstract
method in any concrete subclass of the abstract class. Here's what the
<classname>Shape</classname> class would look like as an abstract class:</p>

<pre>public abstract class Shape {

    Color color;   // color of shape. 
                              
    void setColor(Color newColor) {
          // method to change the color of the shape
       color = newColor; // change value of instance variable
       redraw(); // redraw shape, which will appear in new color
    }
    
    abstract void redraw();
          // abstract method&mdash;must be defined in 
          // concrete subclasses

    . . .  // more instance variables and methods

} // end of class Shape</pre>

<p>Once you have declared the class to be <code>abstract</code>, it becomes illegal to try to create actual objects
of type <classname>Shape</classname>, and the computer will report a syntax error if you try to do
so.</p>

<p>Note, by the way, that the <classname>Vehicle</classname> class discussed above would probably
also be an abstract class.  There is no way to own a vehicle as such&mdash;the actual vehicle has
to be a car or a truck or a motorcycle, or some other "concrete" type of vehicle.</p>

<break/>   

<p>Recall from <localref href="OOP.3.3"/> that a class that is not explicitly declared to be a subclass
of some other class is automatically made a subclass of the standard class <classname>Object</classname>.
That is, a class declaration with no "<code>extends</code>" part such as</p>

<pre>public class myClass { . . .</pre>

<np>is exactly equivalent to</np>

<pre>public class myClass extends Object { . . .</pre>

<p>This means that class <classname>Object</classname> is at the top of a huge class hierarchy that
includes every other class.  (Semantically, <classname>Object</classname> is an abstract class, in fact
the most abstract class of all.  Curiously, however, it is not declared to be <code>abstract</code>
syntactically, which means that you can create objects of type <classname>Object</classname>.  
However, there is not much that you can do with them.)</p>

<p>Since every class is a subclass of <classname>Object</classname>, a variable of type
<classname>Object</classname> can refer to any object whatsoever, of any type.  
Similarly, an array of
type <atype>Object[]</atype> can hold objects of any type. </p>

<break/>

<p>The sample source code file <sourceref href="ShapeDraw.java"/> uses an abstract
<classname>Shape</classname> class and an array of type <atype>Shape[]</atype>
to hold a list of shapes. 
You might want to look at this file, even though you won't be able to
understand all of it at this time. Even the definitions of the shape classes
are somewhat different from those that I have described in this section. (For example,
the <code>draw()</code> method has a parameter of type
<classname>GraphicsContext</classname>. This parameter is required because drawing in 
Java requires a graphics context.) I'll return to similar examples in later chapters when you know more
about GUI programming. However, it would still be worthwhile to look at the definition
of the <classname>Shape</classname> class and its subclasses in the source code.
You might also check how an array is used to hold the list of shapes.  Here is a scaled-down screenshot
from the program:</p>
 
 <img src="shapedraw-screenshot.png" width="500" height="415" alt="screenshot from ShapeDraw, showing several shapes in its drawing area"
           tex="shapedraw-screenshot.eps" texscale="0.5"/>
   
<p>If you run the <code>ShapeDraw</code> program, 
you can click one of the buttons along the bottom to add a shape to the picture.
The new shape will appear in the upper left corner of the drawing area. The color
of the shape is given by the "pop-up menu" of colors below the drawing area. Once a shape is
on the screen, you can drag it around with the mouse. A shape will maintain the
same front-to-back order with respect to other shapes on the screen, even while
you are dragging it. However, you can move a shape out in front of all the
other shapes if you hold down the shift key as you click on it.</p>
   
<p>In the program, the only time when the actual class of a shape is used is
when that shape is added to the screen. Once the shape has been created, it is
manipulated entirely as an abstract shape. The routine that implements
dragging, for example, works with variables of type <classname>Shape</classname> and
makes no reference to any of its subclasses. As the
shape is being dragged, the dragging routine just calls the
shape's draw method each time the shape has to be drawn, so it doesn't
have to know how to draw the shape or even what type of shape it is. The object
is responsible for drawing itself. If I wanted to add a new type of shape to
the program, I would define a new subclass of <classname>Shape</classname>, add another
button, and program the button to add the correct type of shape
to the screen. No other changes in the programming would be necessary.</p>

</subsection>

</section>
