<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="GUI1.6" title="Complete Programs">

<p><start><big>I</big>n this chapter, we have</start> covered many of the
basic aspects of GUI programming.  There is still a lot more to learn,
and we will return to the topic in <localref href="GUI2"/>.  But you
already know enough to write some interesting programs.  In this
section, we look at two complete programs that use what you have
learned about GUI programming in this chapter, as well as what you
learned about programming in general in earlier chapters.  Along
the way, we will also encounter a few new ideas.</p>


<subsection id="GUI1.6.1" title="A Little Card Game">
   

<p>The first program that we will consider is a GUI version 
of the command-line card game <sourceref chapter="5" href="HighLow.java"/>
from <localref href="OOP.4.3"/>.  In the new version,
<sourceref href="HighLowGUI.java"/>, you look at a playing card and try to
predict whether the next card will be higher or lower in value. (Aces have the
lowest value in this game.)  In this GUI version of the program, 
you click on a button to make your
prediction. If you predict wrong, you lose. If you make three correct
predictions, you win.  After completing a game, you can click "New Game"
to start another game. Here is
what the program looks like in the middle of a game:</p>

<img src="high-low-gui.png" width="334" height="205" alt="GUI version of the HighLow card game"
      tex="high-low-gui.eps" texscale="0.6"/>


<np>The complete source code for the program can be found in the file
<sourceref href="HighLowGUI.java"/>.  I encourage you to compile and run it.
Note that the program also requires <sourceref href="Card.java"/>, <sourceref href="Deck.java"/>, 
and <sourceref href="Hand.java"/>, from <localref href="OOP.4"/>,
since they define classes that are used in the program. And it requires
the file of card images, <sourceref href="cards.png"/>, that was used
in <sourceref href="RandomCards.java"/> from <localref href="GUI1.2.4"/>.</np>
   
<p>The layout of the program should be easy to guess:
<code>HighLowGUI</code> uses a <classname>BorderPane</classname> as the root
of the scene graph.  The center position is occupied by a <classname>Canvas</classname>
on which the cards and a message are drawn.  The bottom position contains an
<classname>HBox</classname> that in turn contains three <classname>Buttons</classname>.
In order to make the buttons fill the <classname>HBox</classname>, I set them
all to have the same width, as discussed in <localref href="GUI1.5.3"/>.
You can see all this in the <code>start()</code> method from the program:</p>
   
<pre>public void start(Stage stage) {

    cardImages = new Image("cards.png");     // Load card images.
    board = new Canvas(4*99 + 20, 123 + 80); // Space for 4 cards.
    
    Button higher = new Button("Higher");    // Create the buttons, and
    higher.setOnAction( e -> doHigher() );   //    install event handlers.
    Button lower = new Button("Lower");
    lower.setOnAction( e -> doLower() );
    Button newGame = new Button("New Game");
    newGame.setOnAction( e -> doNewGame() );

    HBox buttonBar = new HBox( higher, lower, newGame );
            
    higher.setPrefWidth(board.getWidth()/3.0);  // Make each button fill
    lower.setPrefWidth(board.getWidth()/3.0);   //     1/3 of the width.
    newGame.setPrefWidth(board.getWidth()/3.0);
            
    BorderPane root = new BorderPane();  // Create the scene graph root node.
    root.setCenter(board);
    root.setBottom(buttonBar);

    doNewGame();  // set up for the first game

    Scene scene = new Scene(root);  // Finish setting up the scene and stage.
    stage.setScene(scene);
    stage.setTitle("High/Low Game");
    stage.setResizable(false);
    stage.show();
    
}  // end start()</pre>
   
   
<p>Note that the event handlers call methods such as
<code>doNewGame()</code> that are defined elsewhere in the program.
The programming of those methods
is a nice example of thinking in terms of a state machine.  (See <localref href="GUI1.3.6"/>.)
It is important to think in terms of the states that the game can be in, how the
state can change, and how the response to events can depend on the state. The
approach that produced the original, text-oriented game in 
<localref href="OOP.4.3"/> is not appropriate here. Trying to think about
the game in terms of a process that goes step-by-step from beginning to end is
more likely to confuse you than to help you.</p>

<p>The state of the game includes the cards and the message. The cards are
stored in an object of type <classname>Hand</classname>. 
The message is a <classname>String</classname>.
These values are stored in instance variables. There is also another, less
obvious aspect of the state: Sometimes a game is in progress, and the user is
supposed to make a prediction about the next card. Sometimes we are between
games, and the user is supposed to click the "New Game" button. It's a good
idea to keep track of this basic difference in state. The program uses a
boolean instance variable named <code>gameInProgress</code> for this purpose.</p>

<p>The state of the game can change whenever the user clicks on a button. The
program has three methods to respond to button clicks:
<code>doHigher()</code>, <code>doLower()</code>, and <code>newGame()</code>. 
It's in these three event-handling methods that the action of the game takes place.</p>

<p>We don't want to let the user start a new game if a game is currently in
progress. That would be cheating. So, the response in the <code>newGame()</code>
method is different depending on whether the state variable
<code>gameInProgress</code> is true or false. If a game is in progress, the
<code>message</code> instance variable should be set to be an error message. If a
game is not in progress, then all the state variables should be set to
appropriate values for the beginning of a new game. In any case, the board must
be redrawn so that the user can see that the state has changed. The complete
<code>newGame()</code> method is as follows:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Called by the start() method, and called by an event handler if
 * the user clicks the "New Game" button.  Start a new game.
 */
private void doNewGame() {
    if (gameInProgress) {
            // If the current game is not over, it is an error to try
            // to start a new game.
        message = "You still have to finish this game!";
        drawBoard();
        return;
    }
    deck = new Deck();   // Create the deck and hand to use for this game.
    hand = new Hand();
    deck.shuffle();
    hand.addCard( deck.dealCard() );  // Deal the first card into the hand.
    message = "Is the next card higher or lower?";
    gameInProgress = true;
    drawBoard();
} // end doNewGame()</pre>

<p>The <code>doHigher()</code> and <code>doLower()</code> methods are almost identical
to each other (and could probably have been combined into one method with a
parameter, if I were more clever). Let's look at the <code>doHigher()</code>
routine. This is called when the user clicks the "Higher" button. This only
makes sense if a game is in progress, so the first thing <code>doHigher()</code>
should do is check the value of the state variable <code>gameInProgress</code>. If
the value is <code>false</code>, then <code>doHigher()</code> should just set up an
error message. If a game is in progress, a new card should be added to the hand
and the user's prediction should be tested. The user might win or lose at this
time. If so, the value of the state variable <code>gameInProgress</code> must be
set to <code>false</code> because the game is over. In any case, the board is
redrawn to show the new state. Here is the <code>doHigher()</code> method:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Called by an event handler when user clicks "Higher" button.
 * Check the user's prediction.  Game ends if user guessed
 * wrong or if the user has made three correct predictions.
 */
private void doHigher() {
    if (gameInProgress == false) {
            // If the game has ended, it was an error to click "Higher",
            // So set up an error message and abort processing.
        message = "Click \"New Game\" to start a new game!";
        drawBoard();
        return;
    }
    hand.addCard( deck.dealCard() );     // Deal a card to the hand.
    int cardCt = hand.getCardCount();
    Card thisCard = hand.getCard( cardCt - 1 );  // Card just dealt.
    Card prevCard = hand.getCard( cardCt - 2 );  // The previous card.
    if ( thisCard.getValue() &lt; prevCard.getValue() ) {
        gameInProgress = false;
        message = "Too bad! You lose.";
    }
    else if ( thisCard.getValue() == prevCard.getValue() ) {
        gameInProgress = false;
        message = "Too bad!  You lose on ties.";
    }
    else if ( cardCt == 4) {
        gameInProgress = false;
        message = "You win!  You made three correct guesses.";
    }
    else {
        message = "Got it right!  Try for " + cardCt + ".";
    }
    drawBoard();
} // end doHigher()</pre>

<p>The <code>drawBoard()</code> method, which is responsible for drawing the content
of the canvas, uses the values in the state variables to decide what to show. It displays the
string stored in the <code>message</code> variable. It draws each of the cards in
the <code>hand</code>. There is one little tricky bit: If a game is in progress, it
draws an extra face-down card, which is not in the hand, to represent the next
card in the deck.  The technique for drawing the individual cards was
explained in <localref href="GUI1.2"/>.  See the <sourceref href="HighLowGUI.java">source code</sourceref>
for the method definition.</p>

</subsection>

   
<subsection title="Menus and Menubars" id="GUI1.6.2">

<p>Our second example program, "MosaicDraw," is a kind of drawing program.  
The source code for the program is in the file <sourceref href="MosaicDraw.java"/>.
The program also requires <sourceref href="MosaicCanvas.java"/>.  Here is a half-size
screenshot showing a sample drawing made with the program:</p>
   
<img src="mosaic-draw.png" width="300" height="328" alt="a face drawn with MosaicDraw"
      tex="mosaic-draw.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<p>As the user clicks-and-drags the
mouse in the large drawing area of this program, it leaves a trail of little colored
squares. There is some random variation in the color of the squares.  (This is meant
to make the picture look a little more like a real mosaic, which is a picture made out of 
small colored stones in which there would be some natural color variation.)  The program has
one feature that we have not encountered before:
There is a menu bar above the drawing area.  The "Control" menu contains
commands for filling and clearing the drawing area, along with a few options that affect
the appearance of the picture.  The "Color" menu lets the user select the color that will
be used when the user draws.  The "Tools" menu affects the behavior of the mouse.
Using the default "Draw" tool, the mouse leaves a trail of single squares.  Using the
"Draw&nbsp;3x3" tool, the mouse leaves a swatch of colored squares that is three squares wide.
There are also "Erase" tools, which let the user set squares back to their default
black color.</p>
   
<p>The drawing area of the program is a panel that belongs to the <classname>MosaicCanvas</classname>
class, a subclass of <classname>Canvas</classname> that is defined in <sourceref href="MosaicCanvas.java"/>.
<classname>MosaicCanvas</classname> is a highly reusable class for representing mosaics of colored
rectangles.  It was also used behind the scenes in the sample program in <localref href="subroutines.6.3"/>.
The <classname>MosaicCanvas</classname> class
does not directly support drawing on the mosaic, but it does support setting
the color of each individual square.  The MosaicDraw program installs mouse handlers on
the canvas.  The handlers respond to <code>MousePressed</code> and <code>MouseDragged</code> events on the
canvas by applying the currently selected tool to the canvas at the square
that contains the mouse position.  This is a nice example of
applying event listeners to an object to do something that was not programmed into the object
itself.</p>
   
<p>I urge you to study <sourceref href="MosaicDraw.java"/>.  I will not be discussing all aspects
of the code here, but you should be able to understand it all after reading this section. As for
<sourceref href="MosaicCanvas.java"/>, it uses some techniques that you would not understand at this
point, but I encourage you to at least read the comments in that file to learn about the API
for <classname>MosaicCanvas</classname>.</p>

<break/>
  
<p>MosaicDraw is the first example that we have seen that uses a menu bar.  Fortunately,
menus are very easy to use in JavaFX.  The items in a menu are represented by objects belonging
to class <classname>MenuItem</classname> or to one of its subclasses.
(<classname>MenuItem</classname> and other menu-related classes are in package <code>javafx.scene.control</code>.)
Menu items are used in almost exactly the
same way as buttons.  In particular, a <classname>MenuItem</classname> can be created using
a constructor that specifies the text of the menu item, such as:</p>
   
<pre>MenuItem fillCommand = new MenuItem("Fill");</pre>

<np>Menu items, like buttons, can have a graphic as well as text, and there is a second
constructor that allows you to specify both text and graphic.
When the user selects a <classname>MenuItem</classname> from a menu, an <classname>ActionEvent</classname>
is generated.  Just as for a button, you can add an action event listener to the menu item using its
<code>setOnAction(handler)</code> method.  A menu item has a <code>setDisable(disabled)</code> method
that can be used to enable and disable the item.  And it has a <code>setText()</code> method for
changing the text that is displayed in the item.</np>
   
<p>The main difference between a menu item and a button, of course, is that a menu
item is meant to appear in a menu.  (Actually, a menu item is a <classname>Node</classname>
that can appear anywhere in a scene graph, but the usual place for it is in a menu.)
A menu in JavaFX is
represented by the class <classname>Menu</classname>.  (In fact, <classname>Menu</classname>
is actually a subclass of <classname>MenuItem</classname>, which means that you can
add a menu as an item in another menu.  The menu that you add becomes a submenu of the
menu that you add it to.)  A <classname>Menu</classname> has a name,
which is specified in the constructor.  It has an instance method <code>getItems()</code>
that returns a list of menu items contained in the menu.  To add items to the
menu, you need to add them to that list:</p>

<pre>Menu sampleMenu = new Menu("Sample");
sampleMenu.getItems().add( menuItem );  // Add one menu item to the menu.
sampleMenu.getItems().addAll( item1, item2, item3 );  // Add multiple items.</pre>
  
<np>Once a menu has been created, it can be added to a menu bar.  A menu bar is represented
by the class <classname>MenuBar</classname>.  A menu bar is just a container for menus.
It does not have a name.  The <classname>MenuBar</classname> constructor can be called
with no parameters, or it can have a parameter list containing <classname>Menus</classname>
to be added to the menu bar.  The instance method <code>getMenus()</code>
returns a list of menus, with methods <code>add()</code> and <code>addAll()</code>
for adding menus to the menu bar.  For example,
the <code>MosaicDraw</code> program uses three menus, <code>controlMenu</code>, <code>colorMenu</code>,
and <code>toolMenu</code>.  We could create a menu bar and add the menus to it with
the statements:</np>
   
<pre>MenuBar menuBar = new MenuBar();
menuBar.getMenus().addAll(controlMenu, colorMenu, toolMenu);</pre>

<np>Or we could list the menus in the menu bar constructor:</np>

<pre>MenuBar menuBar = new MenuBar(controlMenu, colorMenu, toolMenu);</pre>

<p>The final step in using menus is to add the menu bar to the program's
scene graph.  The menu bar could actually appear anywhere, but typically,
it should be at the top of the window.  A program that has a menu bar
will usually use a <classname>BorderPane</classname> as the root of
its scene graph, and it will add the menu bar as the top component
in that root pane.  The rest of the GUI for the program can be placed
in the other four positions of the border pane.</p>
     
<p>So using menus generally follows the same pattern:  Create a menu bar.  Create menus
and add them to the menu bar.  Create menu items and add them to the menus (and set up
listening to handle action events from the menu items).  Place the menu bar at the
top of a <classname>BorderPane</classname>, which is the root of the scene graph.</p>
   
<break/>
   
<p>There are other kinds of menu items, defined by subclasses of <classname>MenuItem</classname>,
that can be added to menus.  A very simple example is <classname>SeparatorMenuItem</classname>,
which appears in a menu as a line between other menu items.  You can see an example
in the "Control" menu of <classname>MosaicDraw</classname>. To add a separator to
a <classname>Menu</classname>, <code>menu</code>, you just need to say</p>

<pre>menu.getItems().add( new SeparatorMenuItem() );</pre>

<np>Much more interesting are the subclasses <classname>CheckMenuItem</classname>
and <classname>RadioMenuItem</classname>.</np>

<p>A <classname>CheckMenuItem</classname> represents a menu item that can be in one 
of two states, selected or not selected. The state is changed when the user
selects the item from the menu that contains it.
A <classname>CheckMenuItem</classname> has the same functionality and is used in
the same way as a <classname>CheckBox</classname> (see <localref href="GUI1.4.3"/>).
Three <classname>CheckMenuItems</classname> are used in the "Control" menu
of the MosaicDraw program.  One is used to turn the random color variation of
the squares on and off.  Another turns a symmetry feature on and off; when symmetry is
turned on, the user's drawing is reflected horizontally and vertically to produce
a symmetric pattern.  And the third <classname>CheckMenuItem</classname> shows and hides
"grouting" in the mosaic (grouting consists of gray lines drawn around each
of the little squares in the mosaic).  The <classname>CheckMenuItem</classname> that corresponds to the
"Use Randomness" option in the "Control" menu could be set up with the statements:</p>
       
<pre>useRandomness = new CheckMenuItem("Use Randomness");
useRandomness.setSelected(true);  // Randomness is initially turned on.
controlMenu.getMenus().add(useRandomness);   // Add menu item to the menu.</pre>

<np>No <classname>ActionEvent</classname> handler is added to <code>useRandomness</code>;
the program simply checks its state by calling <code>useRandomness.isSelected()</code>
whenever it is coloring a square, to decide whether to
add some random variation to the color.  On the other hand, when the user selects the
"Use&nbsp;Grouting" check box from the menu, the canvas must immediately be redrawn to
reflect the new state.  A handler is added to the <classname>CheckMenuItem</classname>
to take care of that by calling an appropriate method:</np>

<pre>useGrouting.setOnAction( e -> doUseGrouting(useGrouting.isSelected()) );</pre>

<break/>
   
<p>The "Color" and "Tools" menus contain items of type <classname>RadioMenuItem</classname>,
which are used in the same way as the <classname>RadioButtons</classname> that were
discussed in <localref href="GUI1.4.3"/>:  A <classname>RadioMenuItem</classname>,
like a check box, can be either selected or unselected, but when several 
<classname>RadioMenuItems</classname> are added to a <classname>ToggleGroup</classname>,
then at most one of the group members can be selected.  In the program, the user
selects the tool that they want to use from the "Tools" menu.  Only one
tool can be selected at a time, so it makes sense to use <classname>RadioMenuItems</classname>
to represent the available tools, and to put all of those items into the same
<classname>ToggleGroup</classname>.  The currently selected option in the "Tools" menu will be
marked as selected; when the user chooses a new tool, the mark is moved.  This gives the
user some visible feedback about which tool is currently selected for use.
Furthermore, the <classname>ToggleGroup</classname> has an observable property
representing the currently selected option (see <localref href="GUI1.3.7"/>).  The program
adds a listener to that property with an event handler that will be
called whenever the user selects a new tool.  Here is the code that creates the
"Tools" menu:</p>

<pre>Menu toolMenu = new Menu("Tools");
ToggleGroup toolGroup = new ToggleGroup();
toolGroup.selectedToggleProperty().addListener( 
                 e -> doToolChoice(toolGroup.getSelectedToggle()) );
addRadioMenuItem(toolMenu,"Draw",toolGroup, true);
addRadioMenuItem(toolMenu,"Erase",toolGroup, false);
addRadioMenuItem(toolMenu,"Draw 3x3",toolGroup, false);
addRadioMenuItem(toolMenu,"Erase 3x3",toolGroup, false);</pre>

<np>The <code>addRadioMenuItem</code> method that is used in this code
is a utility method that is defined elsewhere in the program:</np>

<pre>/**
 * Utility method to create a radio menu item, add it 
 * to a ToggleGroup, and add it to a menu.
 */
private void addRadioMenuItem(Menu menu, String command, 
                                   ToggleGroup group, boolean selected) {
    RadioMenuItem menuItem = new RadioMenuItem(command);
    menuItem.setToggleGroup(group);
    menu.getItems().add(menuItem);
    if (selected) {
        menuItem.setSelected(true);
    }
}</pre>

<p>The complete code for creating the menu bar in <code>MosaicDraw</code> can
be found in a method <code>createMenuBar()</code>.  Again, I encourage you
to study the <sourceref href="MosaicDraw.java">source code</sourceref>.</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection title="Scene and Stage" id="GUI1.6.3">
   
<p>Before ending this brief introduction to GUI programming,
we look at two fundamental classes in a little more detail:
<classname>Scene</classname>, from package <code>javafx.scene</code>,
and <classname>Stage</classname>, from package <code>javafx.stage</code>.</p>

<p>A <classname>Scene</classname> represents the content area of a window
(that is, not including the window's border and title bar),
and it serves as a holder for the root of the scene graph.
The <classname>Scene</classname> class has several constructors, but they
all require the root of the scene graph as one of the parameters, and the
root cannot be <code>null</code>.  Perhaps the most common constructor is
the one that has only the root as parameter: <code>new&nbsp;Scene(root)</code>.</p>

<p>A scene has a width and a height, which can be specified as parameters to the
constructor: <code>new Scene(root,width,height)</code>.  In the typical case
where the <code>root</code> is a <classname>Pane</classname>, the size of the
pane will be set to match the size of the scene, and the pane will lay out
its contents based on that size.  If the size of the scene is not specified in the constructor,
then the size of the scene will be set to the preferred size of the pane.
It is not possible for a program to set the width or
height of a <classname>Scene</classname> after it has been created, but if the size of the stage that 
contains a scene is changed, then the size of the scene is automatically changed 
to match the new size of the stage's content area, and the root node of the
scene (if it is a <classname>Pane</classname>) will be resized as well.</p>

<p>A <classname>Scene</classname> can have a background fill <classname>color</classname> (actually
a <classname>Paint</classname>), which can be specified in the constructor.  Generally, the scene's 
background is not seen, since it is covered by the background of the root node.  The default
style sets the background of the root to be light gray.  However, you can set the background color
of the root to be transparent if you want to see the scene background instead.</p>

<break/>

<p>A <classname>Stage</classname>, from package <code>javafx.stage</code>, represents a
window on the computer's screen.  Any JavaFX <classname>Application</classname> has at
least one stage, called the primary stage, which is created by the system and passed 
as a parameter to the application's <code>start()</code> method.  Although we have not seen any
examples so far in this textbook, many programs
use more than one window.  It is possible for a program to create new <classname>Stage</classname>
objects; we will see how to do that in <localref href="GUI2"/>.</p>

<p>A stage contains a scene, which fills its content area.  The scene is installed in the stage by calling the
instance method <code>stage.setScene(scene)</code>.  It is possible to show a stage
that does not contain a scene, but its content area will just be a blank rectangle.</p>

<p>In addition to a content area, a stage has a title bar above the content.  The title bar
contains a title for the window and some "decorations"&mdash;little controls that the
user can click to do things like close and maximize the window.  The title bar is provided
by the operating system, not by Java, and its style is set by the operating system.
The instance method <code>stage.setTitle(string)</code> sets the text that is shown in
the title bar.  The title can be changed at any time.</p>

<p>By default a stage is resizable.  That is, the size of the window can be changed by the
user, by dragging its borders or corners.  To prevent the user from changing the
window size, you can call <code>stage.setResizable(false)</code>.  However, a program
can change the size of a stage with the instance methods <code>stage.setWidth(w)</code>
and <code>stage.setHeight(h)</code>, and this can be done even if the stage has
been made non-resizable.  Usually, the initial size of a stage is determined by the
size of the scene that it contains, but it is also possible to set the initial size before
showing the window using <code>setWidth()</code> and <code>setHeight()</code>.</p>

<p>By default, when a stage is resizable, the user can make the window arbitrarily small
and arbitrarily large.  It is possible to put limits on the resizability of a window
with the instance methods <code>stage.setMinWidth(w)</code>, <code>stage.setMaxWidth(w)</code>,
<code>stage.setMinHeight(h)</code>, and <code>stage.setMaxHeight(h)</code>.  The size
limits apply only to what the user can do by dragging the borders or corners of the window.
</p>

<p>It is also possible to change the position of a stage on the screen, using the
instance methods <code>stage.setX(x)</code> and <code>stage.setY(y)</code>.
The x and y coordinates specify the position of the top left corner of the window,
in the coordinate system of the screen.  Typically, you would do this before showing
the stage.</p>

<p>Finally, for now, remember that a stage is not visible on the screen until you
show it by calling the instance method <code>stage.show()</code>.  Showing the
primary stage is typically the last thing that you do in a application's
<code>start()</code> method.</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection title="Creating Jar Files" id="GUI1.6.4">
   
<p>Java classes and resource files are often distributed in jar ("java archive") files.
For a program that consists of multiple files, it can make sense to pack them
into a single jar file.  As the last topic for this chapter, we look at how to do that.
The program can be run directly from the jar file, without unpacking it.  However, for
JavaFX programs, the user will still need access to the JavaFX SDK.
A jar file can be "executable," meaning that it specifies the class that
contains the <code>main()</code> routine that will be run when the jar file is
executed.  If you have an executable jar file that does not require JavaFX or
other external resources, you can run it on the command line using a command
of the form:</p>

<pre>java  -jar  JarFileName.jar</pre>

<np>and you might even be able to run the jar file by double-clicking its icon in 
a file browser window.  If an executable jar file requires JavaFX, you will need 
to add the same options to the <code>java</code> command that were discussed in 
<localref href="basics.6.7"/>.  For example,</np>

<pre>java -p /opt/jfx17/lib --add-modules=ALL-MODULE-PATH JarFileName.jar</pre>

   
<p>The question, then, is how to create a jar file.  The answer depends on what
programming environment you are using.  The two basic types of programming environment&mdash;command line
and IDE&mdash;were discussed in <localref href="basics.6"/>.  Any IDE (Integrated Development Environment)
for Java should have a command for creating jar files.  In the Eclipse IDE, for example,
it can be done as follows:  In the Package Explorer pane, select the programming project (or just
all the individual source and resource files that you want to include).  Right-click on the selection, and
choose "Export" from the menu that pops up.  In the window that appears, select "JAR file"
and click "Next".  In the window that appears next, enter a full path name for the jar file in
the box labeled "JAR file".  (Click the "Browse" button next to this box to select the
file name using a file dialog box.)  The name of the file should end with ".jar".
If you are creating a regular jar file, not an executable
one, you can hit "Finish" at this point, and the jar file will be created.  To create an
executable file, hit the "Next" button <i>twice</i> to get to the "Jar Manifest
Specification" screen.  At the bottom of this screen is an input box labeled "Main class".
You have to enter the name of the class that contains the <code>main()</code> routine
that will be run when the jar file is executed.  If you hit the "Browse" button next to
the "Main class" box, you can select the class from a list of classes that contain
<code>main()</code> routines.  Once you've selected the main class, you can
click the "Finish" button to create the executable jar file.</p>

<p>It is also possible to create jar files on the command line.  The Java Development Kit
includes a command-line program named <code>jar</code> that can be used to create jar files.
If all your classes are in the default package (like most of the examples in this book), then
the <code>jar</code> command is easy to use.  To create a non-executable jar file on the command line,
change to the directory that contains the class files that you want to include in the jar.
Then give the command</p>
   
<pre>jar  -c  -f  JarFileName.jar  *.class</pre>
   
<np>where <code>JarFileName</code> can be any name that you want to use for the jar file.
The <code>-c</code> option is used to create a jar file.  The <code>-f</code> is followed by
the name of the jar file that is to be created.
The "<code>*</code>" in "<code>*.class</code>" is a wildcard that makes <code>*.class</code> match every class
file in the current directory.  This means that all the class files in the directory will be
included in the jar file.  If you want to include only certain class files, you
can name them individually, separated by spaces. You can also list the class file names separately.
If the program uses resource files, such as images, they should
also be listed in the command.  (Things get more complicated if your classes and resources are not in the
default package.  In that case, the files must be in subdirectories of the
directory in which you issue the <code>jar</code> command, and you have to include the path to
the file in the name.  For example: <code>textio/TextIO.class</code> on MacOS and Linux,
or <code>textio\TextIO.class</code> on Windows.)</np>
   
<p>Making an executable jar file on the command line is  only a little more complicated.
There has to be some way of specifying which class contains the <code>main()</code>
routine.  This can be done by adding the <code>-e</code> option to the command,
with a value giving the full name of the class that is to be executed when the
jar file is run.  For example, if the name of the class is <classname>MyMainClass</classname>,
then the jar file could be created with:</p>
   
<pre>jar  -c  -f  JarFileName.jar  -e  MyMainClass  *.class</pre>
   
<np>For a program defined in two packages, <code>grapher.ui</code> and <code>grapher.util</code>,
with a main class defined in the file <code>Main.java</code> in package <code>grapher.ui</code>,
the command would become</np>

<pre>jar -c -f Grapher.jar -e grapher.ui.Main grapher/ui/*.class grapher/util/*.class</pre>

<np>except that on Windows, the slashes would be replaced by backslashes.</np>
   
<p>(The options <code>-c</code>, <code>-f</code>, and <code>-e</code> are abbreviations
for the longer forms <code>--create</code>, <code>--file</code>, and <code>--main-class</code>,
and you can use the longer forms, if you prefer clarity to brevity.)</p>
   
</subsection>

<subsection title="jpackage" id="GUI1.6.5">

<p>You can collect the class files and resource files for a program into a jar file,
and you can give that jar file to someone who would like to use your
program.  However, that person will still need to have Java installed on their
computer&mdash;something that is really not very likely these days, unless that person
is a Java developer.  A possible solution is to bundle a Java virtual machine
along with your program.  The Java Development Kit includes the <code>jpackage</code>
command to make that possible.</p>

<p>The <code>jpackage</code> command can create an installer that will install your
program along with as much Java support as is needed to run it.  It has some
significant limitations.  It can only make an installer for the type of computer
and operating system that you are using; for example, it is not possible to use <code>jpackage</code>
on Linux to make an installer for Windows.  And the files that it makes are very
large, since they have to include large parts of a Java execution environment.
So <code>jpackage</code> is really meant for packaging large, serious applications.
But if you want to try it, here is a basic example, using only a few of the
options that are available for <code>jpackage</code>.  For the example, 
I&nbsp;made an installer for the network poker game from <localref href="threads.5.4"/>.
This might also help you understand how to work with packages in general.</p>

<p>To apply <code>jpackage</code> to a program that uses JavaFX, you have to make
Java packages available to the <code>jpackage</code> command.  For this purpose,
you can't use the JavaFX SDK.  Instead, you need the JavaFX "jmods".  See
<localref href="basics.6.7"/> for a discussion of the JavaFX SDK. For <code>jpackage</code>,
you will need to download the jmods for your operating system from
<a href="https://gluonhq.com/products/javafx/">https://gluonhq.com/products/javafx/</a>.
For my computer, I extracted the downloaded file into <code>/opt/javafx-jmods-17.0.2</code>.
(The jmods are required because they include specific operating system support that is not in
the SDK jar files.)</p>

<p>To use <code>jpackage</code>, you need a jar file that contains the classes and resource files for your
program.  The poker game uses classes from the packages <code>netgame.common</code> and
<code>netgame.fivecarddraw</code>, plus a resource image file <code>cards.png</code>
in <code>netgame.fivecarddraw</code>.  To make the jar file, I first compiled
the Java files for the program.  Since the poker game uses JavaFX, I included the
necessary options in the <code>javac</code> command.  
I used the following command in the directory that contained
the <sourceref chapter="12" href="netgame"/> directory, <i>typed all on one line</i>:</p>

<pre>javac  --module-path  /opt/jfx17/lib  --add-modules=ALL-MODULE-PATH
                    netgame/common/*.java  netgame/fivecarddraw/*.java</pre>

<np>I then created a jar file, <code>Poker.jar</code>, with this command,
<i>typed all on one line</i>:</np>

<pre>jar -c -f Poker.jar  netgame/common/*.class  netgame/fivecarddraw/*.class
                netgame/fivecarddraw/cards.png</pre>
                
<np>It is important to include the image resource file along with the class files.
(Note that on Windows, the slashes, "/", would be replaced by backslashes, "\".)</np>

<p>I moved <code>Poker.jar</code> to a new directory.  Working in that new directory,
I used the following very long <code>jpackage</code> command, again <i>typed all on one line</i>:</p>

<pre>jpackage  --input  <b>.</b>  --main-jar  Poker.jar
            --main-class  netgame.fivecarddraw.Main  --name  NetPoker 
            --module-path /opt/javafx-jmods-17.0.2
            --add-modules  javafx.base,javafx.controls,javafx.graphics</pre>
             
<np>The value for the <code>--input</code> option is a period, which represents the current working
directory; it could be replaced by a path to the directory that contains <code>Poker.jar</code>.
The value for the <code>--main-class</code> option is the full name of the class that
contains the main program; this option is not needed if the jar file is executable.
The value of the <code>--name</code> option is used to name the installer and
to name the executable file that it will install.  The <code>--module-path</code>
refers to the directory that contains the JavaFX jmods.  And the added modules
are just those JavaFX modules that are needed for this program.</np>

<p>When used on my computer, running Linux Mint, this produced a file named
<code>netpoker_1.0-1_amd64.deb</code> that I could
then install in the usual way. It installed the poker executable
as <code>/opt/netpoker/bin/NetPoker</code>.</p>

<p>On MacOS 10.15, using the JDK from adoptium.net (see <localref href="basics.6.1"/>),
I found that <code>jpackage</code> was installed as part of the
JDK, but it was not made available on the command-line.  I was able to define it
myself as an alias: </p>

<pre>alias jpackage=
     "/Library/Java/JavaVirtualMachines/temurin-17.jdk/Contents/Home/bin/jpackage"</pre>

<np>Again, type this all on one line.  With that done, I used the same commands
as given above, with appropriate directory names for the JavaFX SDK and jmods.
The result was a .dmg file containing a program, <code>netpoker.app</code>,
that could be run by double-clicking. (The jpackage command might be properly set up
in newer versions of MacOS.)</np>

<p>The <code>jpackage</code> command should also work on Windows, but it requires
something called the "WiX toolset" in addition to the JDK.  I have not tried it.</p>


</subsection>

<endchapter/>

</section>