<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="basics.2" title="Variables and the Primitive Types" shorttitle="Variables and Types">

<p><start><big>N</big>ames are fundamental to programming</start>. In programs,
names are used to refer to many different sorts of things. In order to use
those things, a programmer must understand the rules for giving names to them
and the rules for using the names to work with them. That is, the
programmer must understand the syntax and the semantics of names.</p>

<p>According to the syntax rules of Java, the most basic names are <newword>identifiers</newword>.
Identifiers can be used to name classes, variables, and subroutines.
An identifier is a sequence of one or more
characters. It must begin with a letter or underscore and must consist entirely of letters,
digits, and underscores. ("Underscore" refers to the character '_'.) For example, here are some legal
identifiers:</p>

<pre>N   n   rate  x15   quite_a_long_name   HelloWorld</pre>

<np>No spaces are allowed in identifiers; <code>HelloWorld</code> is a legal identifier,
but "Hello World" is not.
Upper case and lower case letters are considered to be different, so that
<code>HelloWorld</code>, <code>helloworld</code>, <code>HELLOWORLD</code>, and
<code>hElloWorLD</code> are all distinct names. Certain words are reserved for
special uses in Java, and cannot be used as identifiers.
These <newword>reserved words</newword> include: <code>class</code>,
<code>public</code>, <code>static</code>, <code>if</code>, <code>else</code>, <code>while</code>,
and several dozen other words.  (Remember that reserved words are
<b>not</b> identifiers, since they can't be used as names for things.)</np>

<p>Java is actually pretty liberal about what counts as a letter or a digit.
Java uses the <newword>Unicode</newword> character set, which
includes thousands of characters from many different languages and different
alphabets, and many of these characters count as letters or digits. However, I
will be sticking to what can be typed on a regular English keyboard.</p>
   
<p>The pragmatics of naming includes style guidelines about how to choose
names for things.  For example, it is customary for names of classes to begin with
upper case letters, while names of variables and of subroutines begin with
lower case letters; you can avoid a lot of confusion by following this standard
convention in your own programs.  Most Java programmers do not use underscores in names,
although some do use them at the beginning of the names of certain kinds
of variables.  When a name  is made up of several words, such
as <code>HelloWorld</code> or <code>interestRate</code>, it is customary
to capitalize each word, except possibly the first; this is sometimes
referred to as <newword>camel case</newword>, since the
upper case letters in the middle of a name are supposed to look something
like the humps on a camel's back.</p>

<p>Finally, I'll note that in addition to simple identifiers, things in Java
can have <newword>compound names</newword>
which consist of several simple names separated by periods.  (Compound names
are also called <newword>qualified names</newword>.) You've already
seen an example: <code>System.out.println</code>. The idea here is that things in
Java can contain other things. A compound name is a kind of path to an item
through one or more levels of containment. The name <code>System.out.println</code>
indicates that something called "System" contains something called "out" which
in turn contains something called "println".</p>

<subsection id="basics.2.1" title="Variables">

<p>Programs manipulate data that are stored in memory. In machine language,
data can only be referred to by giving the numerical address of the location in
memory where the data is stored. In a high-level language such as Java, names are
used instead of numbers to refer to data. It is the job of the computer to keep
track of where in memory the data is actually stored; the programmer only has
to remember the name. A name used in this way&mdash;to refer to data stored in
memory&mdash;is called a <newword>variable</newword>.</p>

<p>Variables are actually rather subtle. Properly speaking, a variable is not a
name for the data itself but for a location in memory that can hold data. You
should think of a variable as a container or box where you can store data that
you will need to use later. The variable refers directly to the box and only
indirectly to the data in the box. Since the data in the box can change, a
variable can refer to different data values at different times during the
execution of the program, but it always refers to the same box. Confusion can
arise, especially for beginning programmers, because when a variable is used in
a program in certain ways, it refers to the container, but when it is used in
other ways, it refers to the data in the container. You'll see examples of both
cases below.</p>

<p>In Java, the <b>only</b> way to get data into a variable&mdash;that
is, into the box that the variable names&mdash;is with an <newword>assignment statement</newword>. 
An assignment statement takes the
form:</p>

<pre><bnf>variable</bnf> = <bnf>expression</bnf>;</pre>

<np>where <bnf>expression</bnf> represents anything that
refers to or computes a data value. When the computer comes to an assignment
statement in the course of executing a program, it evaluates the expression and
puts the resulting data value into the variable. For example, consider the
simple assignment statement</np>

<pre>rate = 0.07;</pre>

<np>The <bnf>variable</bnf> in this assignment statement is
<code>rate</code>, and the <bnf>expression</bnf> is the number
0.07. The computer executes this assignment statement by putting the number
0.07 in the variable <code>rate</code>, replacing whatever was there before. Now,
consider the following more complicated assignment statement, which might come
later in the same program:</np>

<pre>interest = rate * principal;</pre>

<np>Here, the value of the expression "<code>rate * principal</code>" is being
assigned to the variable <code>interest</code>. In the expression, the <code>*</code>
is a "multiplication operator" that tells the computer to multiply
<code>rate</code> times <code>principal</code>. The names <code>rate</code> and
<code>principal</code> are themselves variables, and it is really the
<b>values</b> stored in those variables that are to be multiplied. We
see that when a variable is used in an expression, it is the value stored in
the variable that matters; in this case, the variable seems to refer to the
data in the box, rather than to the box itself. When the computer executes this
assignment statement, it takes the <b>value</b> of <code>rate</code>,
multiplies it by the <b>value</b> of <code>principal</code>, and stores
the answer in the <b>box</b> referred to by <code>interest</code>.
When a variable is used on the left-hand side of an assignment statement,
it refers to the box that is named by the variable.</np>

<p>(Note, by the way, that an assignment statement is a command that is
executed by the computer at a certain time. It is not a statement of fact. For
example, suppose a program includes the statement "<code>rate = 0.07;</code>". If
the statement "<code>interest = rate * principal;</code>" is executed later in the
program, can we say that the <code>principal</code> is multiplied by 0.07? No! The
value of <code>rate</code> might have been changed in the meantime by another
statement. The meaning of an assignment statement is completely different from
the meaning of an equation in mathematics, even though both use the symbol&nbsp;"=".)</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="basics.2.2" title="Types">

<p>A variable in Java is designed to hold only one particular type of data; it
can legally hold that type of data and no other. The compiler will consider it
to be a syntax error if you try to violate this rule by assigning a value of the
wrong type to a variable. We say that Java is a
<newword>strongly typed</newword> language because it enforces this
rule.</p>

<p>There are eight so-called <newword>primitive types</newword> built
into Java. The primitive types are named <ptype>byte</ptype>, <ptype>short</ptype>,
<ptype>int</ptype>, <ptype>long</ptype>, <ptype>float</ptype>, <ptype>double</ptype>, <ptype>char</ptype>,
and <ptype>boolean</ptype>. The first four types hold integers (whole numbers such as
17, -38477, and 0). The four integer types are distinguished by the ranges of
integers they can hold. The <ptype>float</ptype> and <ptype>double</ptype> types hold real
numbers (such as 3.6 and -145.99). Again, the two real types are distinguished
by their range and accuracy. A variable of type <ptype>char</ptype> holds a single
character from the Unicode character set. And a variable of type
<ptype>boolean</ptype> holds one of the two logical values <code>true</code> or
<code>false</code>.</p>

<p>Any data value stored in the computer's memory must be represented as a
binary number, that is as a string of zeros and ones. A single zero or one is
called a <newword>bit</newword>. A string of eight bits is called a
<newword>byte</newword>. Memory is usually measured in terms of
bytes. Not surprisingly, the <ptype>byte</ptype> data type refers to a single byte of
memory. A variable of type <ptype>byte</ptype> holds a string of eight bits, which
can represent any of the integers between -128 and 127, inclusive. (There are
256 integers in that range; eight bits can represent 256&mdash;two raised to the
power eight&mdash;different values.) As for the other integer types,</p>

<ul>
<li><ptype>short</ptype> corresponds to two bytes (16 bits). Variables of type
<ptype>short</ptype> have values in the range -32768 to 32767.</li>

<li><ptype>int</ptype> corresponds to four bytes (32 bits). Variables of type
<ptype>int</ptype> have values in the range -2147483648 to 2147483647.</li>

<li><ptype>long</ptype> corresponds to eight bytes (64 bits). Variables of type
<ptype>long</ptype> have values in the range -9223372036854775808 to
9223372036854775807.</li>
</ul>

<p>You don't have to remember these numbers, but they do give you some idea of
the size of integers that you can work with. Usually, for representing integer
data you should just stick to
the <ptype>int</ptype> data type, which is good enough for most purposes.</p>

<p>The <ptype>float</ptype> data type is represented in four bytes of memory, using a
standard method for encoding real numbers. The maximum value for a
<ptype>float</ptype> is about 10 raised to the power 38. A <ptype>float</ptype> can have
about 7 significant digits. (So that 32.3989231134 and 32.3989234399 would both
have to be rounded off to about 32.398923 in order to be stored in a variable
of type <ptype>float</ptype>.) A <ptype>double</ptype> takes up 8 bytes, can range up to
about 10 to the power 308, and has about 15 significant digits. Ordinarily, you
should stick to the <ptype>double</ptype> type for real values.</p>

<p>A variable of type <ptype>char</ptype> occupies two bytes in memory. The value of
a <ptype>char</ptype> variable is a single character such as A, *, x, or a space
character. The value can also be a special character such a tab or a carriage
return or one of the many Unicode characters that come from different
languages.  Values of type <ptype>char</ptype> are closely related to integer
values, since a character is actually stored as a 16-bit integer code number.  In
fact, we will see that <ptype>chars</ptype> in Java can actually be used like integers in
certain situations.</p>

<p>It is important to remember that a primitive type value is represented using only
a certain, finite number of bits.  So, an <ptype>int</ptype> can't be an arbitrary integer;
it can only be an integer in a certain finite range of values.  Similarly, <ptype>float</ptype>
and <ptype>double</ptype> variables can only take on certain values.  They are not true
real numbers in the mathematical sense.  For example, the mathematical constant &pi; can only
be approximated by a value of type <ptype>float</ptype> or <ptype>double</ptype>, since
it would require an infinite number of decimal places to represent it exactly.  For that
matter, many simple numbers such as 1/3 can only be approximated by <ptype>floats</ptype> and
<ptype>doubles</ptype>.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="basics.2.3" title="Literals">

<p>A data value is stored in the computer as a sequence of bits.  In the computer's
memory, it doesn't look anything like a value written on this page.  You need a
way to include constant values in the programs that you write.  In a program, you represent constant values
as <newword>literals</newword>.  A literal is something that you can type in a program to
represent a value.  It is a kind of name for a constant value.</p>

<p>For example, to type a value of type <ptype>char</ptype> in a program, you must surround it with
a pair of single quote marks, such as <code>'A'</code>, <code>'*'</code>, or <code>'x'</code>.
The character and the quote marks make up a literal of type <ptype>char</ptype>.
Without the quotes, <code>A</code> would be an
identifier and <code>*</code> would be a multiplication operator. The quotes are <b>not</b> part of
the value and are not stored in the variable; they are just a convention for
naming a particular character constant in a program.  If you want to store the character A in
a variable <code>ch</code> of type <ptype>char</ptype>, you could do so with the assignment
statement</p>

<pre>ch = 'A';</pre>

<np>Certain special characters have special literals
that use a backslash, <code>\</code>, as an "escape character." In particular, a tab is
represented as <code>'\t'</code>, a carriage return as <code>'\r'</code>, a linefeed as
<code>'\n'</code>, the single quote character as <code>'\''</code>, and the backslash
itself as <code>'\\'</code>. Note that even though you type two characters between
the quotes in <code>'\t'</code>, the value represented by this literal is a single
tab character.</np>

<p>Numeric literals are a little more complicated than you might expect. Of
course, there are the obvious literals such as 317 and 17.42. But there are
other possibilities for expressing numbers in a Java program. First of all,
real numbers can be represented in an exponential form such as 1.3e12 or
12.3737e-108. The "e12" and "e-108" represent powers of 10, so that 1.3e12
means 1.3 times 10<sup>12</sup> and 12.3737e-108 means 12.3737 times
10<sup>-108</sup>. This format can be used to express very large and very small numbers.
Any numeric literal that contains a decimal point or exponential is a literal
of type <ptype>double</ptype>. To make a literal of type <ptype>float</ptype>, you have to
append an "F" or "f" to the end of the number. For example, "1.2F" stands for
1.2 considered as a value of type <ptype>float</ptype>. (Occasionally, you need to
know this because the rules of Java say that you can't assign a value of type
<ptype>double</ptype> to a variable of type <ptype>float</ptype>, so you might be
confronted with a ridiculous-seeming error message if you try to do something
like "<code>x&nbsp;=&nbsp;1.2;</code>" if <code>x</code> is a variable of type
<ptype>float</ptype>. You have to say "<code>x&nbsp;=&nbsp;1.2F;"</code>.
This is one reason why I advise sticking to type <ptype>double</ptype> for real
numbers.)</p>

<p>Even for integer literals, there are some complications. Ordinary integers
such as 177777 and -32 are literals of type <ptype>byte</ptype>, <ptype>short</ptype>, or
<ptype>int</ptype>, depending on their size. You can make a literal of type
<ptype>long</ptype> by adding "L" as a suffix. For example: 17L or 728476874368L. As
another complication, Java allows binary, octal (base-8), and hexadecimal (base-16)
literals. I don't want to cover number bases in detail, but in case
you run into them in other people's programs, it's worth knowing a few things:
Octal numbers use only the digits 0 through 7.  In Java, a numeric literal
that begins with a 0 is interpreted as an octal number; for example, the octal
literal 045 represents the number 37, not the number 45.  Octal numbers are rarely
used, but you need to be aware of what happens when you start a number with a zero.
Hexadecimal numbers use 16 digits, the usual digits 0 through 9 and the letters
A, B, C, D, E, and F.  Upper case and lower case letters can be used
interchangeably in this context.  The letters represent the numbers 10 through 15.
In Java, a hexadecimal literal begins with <code>0x</code> or <code>0X</code>,
as in <code>0x45</code> or <code>0xFF7A</code>.  Finally, binary literals
start with <code>0b</code> or <code>0B</code> and contain only the digits
0 and&nbsp;1; for example: 0b10110.</p>

<p>As a final complication, numeric
literals can include the underscore character&nbsp;("<code>_</code>"), which
can be used to separate groups of digits.  For example, the integer constant
for two billion could be written 2_000_000_000, which is a good deal easier to decipher
than 2000000000.  There is no rule about how many digits have to be in each group.
Underscores can be especially useful in long binary numbers; for example,
<code>0b1010_1100_1011</code>.</p>

<p>I will note that hexadecimal numbers can also be used to represent
arbitrary Unicode characters.  A Unicode literal consists of <code>\u</code> followed
by four hexadecimal digits.  For example, the character literal <code>'\u00E9'</code>
represents the Unicode character that is an "e" with an acute accent.
</p>

<p>For the type <ptype>boolean</ptype>, there are precisely two literals:
<code>true</code> and <code>false</code>. These literals are typed just as I've written
them here, without quotes, but they represent constant values, not variables. Boolean
values occur most often as the values of conditional expressions. For
example,</p>

<pre>rate &gt; 0.05</pre>
   
<np>is a boolean-valued expression that evaluates to <code>true</code> if the value
of the variable <code>rate</code> is greater than 0.05, and to <code>false</code> if
the value of <code>rate</code> is less than or equal to 0.05. As you'll see in <localref href="control"/>, 
boolean-valued expressions are used
extensively in control structures. Of course, boolean values can also be
assigned to variables of type <ptype>boolean</ptype>.  For example, if <code>test</code> is 
a variable of type <ptype>boolean</ptype>, then both of the following assignment statements
are legal:</np>

<pre>test = true;
test = rate &gt; 0.05;</pre>


</subsection>

<subsection id="basics.2.4" title="Strings and String Literals">

<p>Java has other types in addition to the primitive types, but all the other
types represent objects rather than "primitive" data values. 
For the most part,
we are not concerned with objects for the time being. However, there is one
predefined object type that is very important: the type <classname>String</classname>. 
(<classname>String</classname> is a type, but not a primitive type; it is in fact the
name of a class, and we will return to that aspect of strings in the 
<localref href="basics.3">next&nbsp;section</localref>.  The fact that <classname>String</classname> is
a class explains why the name begins with an upper case "S" rather than lower case.)</p>


<p>A value of type <classname>String</classname> is a sequence of characters. You've already seen a string
literal: <code>"Hello World!"</code>. The double quotes are part of the literal; they have
to be typed in the program. However, they are not part of the actual <classname>String</classname>
value, which consists of just the characters between the quotes.   A string can contain
any number of characters, even zero.  A string with no characters is called the
<newword>empty string</newword> and is represented by the literal <code>""</code>, a pair
of double quote marks with nothing between them.  Remember the difference between single
quotes and double quotes!  Single quotes are used for <ptype>char</ptype> literals and
double quotes for <classname>String</classname> literals!  There is a big difference between
the <classname>String</classname> <code>"A"</code> and the <ptype>char</ptype> <code>'A'</code>.</p>

<p>Within a string literal, special characters can be represented using the backslash notation.
Within this context, the double quote is itself a special character. For
example, to represent the string <b>value</b></p>

<pre>I said, "Are you listening!"</pre>

<np>with a linefeed at the end, you would have to type the string <b>literal</b>:</np>

<pre>"I said, \"Are you listening!\"\n"</pre>

<p>You can also use <code>\t</code>, <code>\r</code>, <code>\\</code>, 
and Unicode sequences such as <code>\u00E9</code> to
represent other special characters in string literals.</p>

</subsection>


<subsection id="basics.2.5" title="Variables in Programs">

<p>A variable can be used in a program only if it has first been <newword>declared</newword>. 
A <newword>variable declaration statement</newword> is used to declare one or more variables and to give them
names. When the computer executes a variable declaration, it sets aside memory
for the variable and associates the variable's name with that memory. A simple
variable declaration takes the form:</p>

<pre><bnf>type-name</bnf>  <bnf>variable-name-or-names</bnf>;</pre>
   
<np>The <bnf>variable-name-or-names</bnf> can be a single
variable name or a list of variable names separated by commas. (We'll see later
that variable declaration statements can actually be somewhat more complicated
than this.) Good programming style is to declare only one variable in a
declaration statement, unless the variables are closely related in some way.
For example:</np>

<pre>int numberOfStudents;
String name;
double x, y;        
boolean isFinished;
char firstInitial, middleInitial, lastInitial;</pre>
   
<p>It is also good style to include a comment with each variable declaration to
explain its purpose in the program, or to give other information that might
be useful to a human reader.  For example:</p>
   
<pre>double principal;    // Amount of money invested.
double interestRate; // Rate as a decimal, not percentage.</pre>

<p>In this chapter, we will only use variables declared inside the
<code>main()</code> subroutine of a program. Variables declared inside a subroutine
are called <newword>local variables</newword> for that subroutine.
They exist only inside the subroutine, while it is running, and are completely
inaccessible from outside. Variable declarations can occur anywhere inside the
subroutine, as long as each variable is declared before it is used in any
way. Some people like to declare all the variables at the beginning of
the subroutine. Others like to wait to declare a variable until it is needed.
My preference: Declare important variables at the beginning of the subroutine,
and use a comment to explain the purpose of each variable. Declare "utility
variables" which are not important to the overall logic of the subroutine at
the point in the subroutine where they are first used. Here is a simple program
using some variables and assignment statements:</p>

<pre>/**
 * This class implements a simple program that
 * will compute the amount of interest that is
 * earned on $17,000 invested at an interest
 * rate of 0.027 for one year.  The interest and
 * the value of the investment after one year are
 * printed to standard output.
 */
 
public class Interest {
   
   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
       /* Declare the variables. */
   
       double principal;     // The value of the investment.
       double rate;          // The annual interest rate.
       double interest;      // Interest earned in one year.
       
       /* Do the computations. */
       
       principal = 17000;
       rate = 0.027;
       interest = principal * rate;   // Compute the interest.
       
       principal = principal + interest;
             // Compute value of investment after one year, with interest.
             // (Note: The new value replaces the old value of principal.)
             
       /* Output the results. */
             
       System.out.print("The interest earned is $");
       System.out.println(interest);
       System.out.print("The value of the investment after one year is $");
       System.out.println(principal);
                      
   } // end of main()
      
} // end of class Interest</pre>


<p>This program uses several subroutine call statements to display information
to the user of the program. Two different subroutines are used:
<code>System.out.print</code> and <code>System.out.println</code>. The difference
between these is that <code>System.out.println</code> adds a linefeed after
the end of the information that it displays, while <code>System.out.print</code>
does not. Thus, the value of <code>interest</code>, which is displayed by the
subroutine call "<code>System.out.println(interest);</code>", follows on the same
line as the string displayed by the previous <code>System.out.print</code> statement. Note that the value
to be displayed by <code>System.out.print</code> or <code>System.out.println</code> is
provided in parentheses after the subroutine name. This value is called a
<newword>parameter</newword> to the subroutine. A parameter provides
a subroutine with information it needs to perform its task. In a subroutine
call statement, any parameters are listed in parentheses after the subroutine
name. Not all subroutines have parameters. If there are no parameters in a
subroutine call statement, the subroutine name must be followed by an empty
pair of parentheses.</p>
   
<p>
All the sample programs for this textbook are available in separate source code files in
the on-line version of this text at <fx><a href="http://math.hws.edu/javanotes/source">http://math.hws.edu/javanotes/source</a>.</fx>
<swing><a href="http://math.hws.edu/javanotes-swing/source">http://math.hws.edu/javanotes-swing/source</a>.</swing>  They
are also included in the downloadable archive of the web site, in a folder named <code>source</code>.
The source code for the <code>Interest</code> program, for example, 
can be found in the file <sourceref href="Interest.java"/> in subfolder named <code>chapter2</code> inside the <code>source</code>
folder.
</p>

   
</subsection>
   
</section>