<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="basics.5" title="Details of Expressions">

<p><start><big>T</big>his section takes a closer look</start> at expressions.
Recall that an expression is a piece of program code that represents or
computes a value. An expression can be a literal, a variable, a function call,
or several of these things combined with operators such as <code>+</code>
and&nbsp;<code>&gt;</code>. The value of an expression can be assigned to a variable, used
as a parameter in a  subroutine call, or combined with other values into a
more complicated expression. (The value can even, in some cases, be ignored, if
that's what you want to do; this is more common than you might think.)
Expressions are an essential part of programming. So far, this book has
dealt only informally with expressions. This section tells you the more-or-less
complete story (leaving out some of the less commonly used operators).</p>

<p>The basic building blocks of expressions are literals (such as <code>674</code>,
<code>3.14</code>, <code>true</code>, <code>'X'</code>, and <code>"Hello"</code>), variables, and function calls.
Recall that a function is a subroutine that returns a value. You've already
seen some examples of functions, such as the input routines from the <classname>TextIO</classname>
class and the mathematical functions from the <classname>Math</classname> class.
</p>
   
<p>The <classname>Math</classname> class also contains a couple of mathematical constants
that are useful in mathematical expressions:  <code>Math.PI</code> represents
&pi; (the ratio of the circumference of a circle to its
diameter), and <code>Math.E</code> represents <i>e</i> (the base of the natural
logarithms).  These "constants" are actually member variables in 
<classname>Math</classname> of type <ptype>double</ptype>.  They are only
approximations for the mathematical constants, which would require an infinite
number of digits to specify exactly.  The standard class <classname>Integer</classname>
contains a couple of constants related to the <ptype>int</ptype> data type:
<code>Integer.MAX_VALUE</code> is the largest possible <ptype>int</ptype>,
2147483647, and <code>Integer.MIN_VALUE</code> is the smallest <ptype>int</ptype>,
-2147483648.  Similarly, the class <classname>Double</classname> contains some
constants related to type <ptype>double</ptype>.  <code>Double.MAX_VALUE</code>
is the largest value of type <ptype>double</ptype>, and <code>Double.MIN_VALUE</code>
is the smallest <b>positive</b> value.  It also has constants to represent infinite
values, <code>Double.POSITIVE_INFINITY</code> and <code>Double.NEGATIVE_INFINITY</code>,
and the special value <code>Double.NaN</code> to represent an undefined value.  For
example, the value of <code>Math.sqrt(-1)</code> is <code>Double.NaN</code>.
</p>

<p>Literals, variables, and function calls are simple expressions. More complex
expressions can be built up by using <newword>operators</newword> to
combine simpler expressions. Operators include <code>+</code> for adding two
numbers, <code>&gt;</code> for comparing two values, and so on. When several
operators appear in an expression, there is a question of <newword>precedence</newword>, 
which determines how the operators are grouped for
evaluation. For example, in the expression "<code>A&nbsp;+&nbsp;B&nbsp;*&nbsp;C</code>", <code>B*C</code>
is computed first and then the result is added to <code>A</code>. We say that
multiplication (<code>*</code>) has <newword>higher precedence</newword>
than addition (<code>+</code>). If the default precedence is not what you want, you
can use parentheses to explicitly specify the grouping you want. For example,
you could use "<code>(A&nbsp;+&nbsp;B)&nbsp;*&nbsp;C</code>" if you want to add <code>A</code> to
<code>B</code> first and then multiply the result by <code>C</code>.</p>

<p>The rest of this section gives details of operators in Java. The number of
operators in Java is quite large.  I will not cover them all here, but most of
the important ones are here.</p>

 
<subsection id="basics.5.1" title="Arithmetic Operators">

<p>Arithmetic operators include addition, subtraction, multiplication, and
division. They are indicated by <code>+</code>, <code>-</code>, <code>*</code>, and
<code>/</code>. These operations can be used on values of any numeric type:
<ptype>byte</ptype>, <ptype>short</ptype>, <ptype>int</ptype>, <ptype>long</ptype>, <ptype>float</ptype>, or
<ptype>double</ptype>.  They can also be used with values of type <ptype>char</ptype>, which
are treated as integers in this context;
a <ptype>char</ptype> is converted into its Unicode code number when it is used with an
arithmetic operator.  When the computer actually calculates one of these operations,
the two values that it combines must be of the same type. If your program tells
the computer to combine two values of different types, the computer will
convert one of the values from one type to another. For example, to compute
37.4&nbsp;+&nbsp;10, the computer will convert the integer 10 to a real number 10.0 and
will then compute 37.4&nbsp;+&nbsp;10.0.  This is called a <newword>type conversion</newword>.
Ordinarily, you don't have to worry about type conversion in expressions,
because the computer does it automatically.</p>

<p>When two numerical values are combined (after doing type conversion on one
of them, if necessary), the answer will be of the same type. If you multiply
two <ptype>ints</ptype>, you get an <ptype>int</ptype>; if you multiply two
<ptype>doubles</ptype>, you get a <ptype>double</ptype>. This is what you would expect, but
you have to be very careful when you use the division operator <code>/</code>. When
you divide two integers, the answer will always be an integer; if the quotient
has a fractional part, it is discarded. For example, the value of <code>7/2</code>
is <code>3</code>, not <code>3.5</code>. If <code>N</code> is an integer variable, then
<code>N/100</code> is an integer, and <code>1/N</code> is equal to zero for any
<code>N</code> greater than one! This fact is a common source of programming
errors. You can force the computer to compute a real number as the answer by
making one of the operands real: For example, when the computer evaluates
<code>1.0/N</code>, it first converts <code>N</code> to a real number in order to match
the type of <code>1.0</code>, so you get a real number as the answer.
</p>

<p>Java also has an operator for computing the remainder when one number is
divided by another. This operator is indicated by <code>%</code>. If <code>A</code> and
<code>B</code> are integers, then <code>A&nbsp;%&nbsp;B</code> represents the remainder when
<code>A</code> is divided by <code>B</code>. 
(However, for negative operands, <code>%</code> is not quite the
same as the usual mathematical "modulus" operator, since if <code>A</code> 
is negative, then the value of <code>A&nbsp;%&nbsp;B</code> will be negative.)
For example, <code>7&nbsp;%&nbsp;2</code> is <code>1</code>,
while <code>34577&nbsp;%&nbsp;100</code> is <code>77</code>, and <code>50&nbsp;%&nbsp;8</code> is <code>2</code>. A
common use of <code>%</code> is to test whether a given integer is even or odd:
<code>N</code> is even if and only if <code>N&nbsp;%&nbsp;2</code> is zero.  (If <code>N</code> is odd, then
<code>N&nbsp;%&nbsp;2</code> is plus or minus <code>1</code>, depending on whether <code>N</code>
is positive or negative.)  More generally, you can check whether an integer <code>N</code> is
evenly divisible by an integer <code>M</code> by checking whether
<code>N&nbsp;%&nbsp;M</code> is zero.</p>

<p>The <code>%</code> operator also works with real numbers.
In general, <code>A&nbsp;%&nbsp;B</code> is what is left over after you remove as many copies of <code>B</code>
as possible from <code>A</code>.  For example, <code>7.52&nbsp;%&nbsp;0.5</code> is 0.02.</p>

<p>Finally, you might need the <newword>unary minus</newword>
operator, which takes the negative of a number. For example, <code>-X</code> has
the same value as <code>(-1)*X</code>. For completeness, Java also has a unary plus
operator, as in <code>+X</code>, even though it doesn't really do anything.</p>

<p>By the way, recall that the <code>+</code> operator can also be used to concatenate
a value of any type onto a <classname>String</classname>.  When you use <code>+</code> to combine
a string with a value of some other type, it is another example of
type conversion, since any type can be automatically converted into type
<classname>String</classname>.</p>
   
</subsection>

<subsection id="basics.5.2" title="Increment and Decrement">

<p>You'll find that adding <code>1</code> to a variable is an extremely common
operation in programming. Subtracting <code>1</code> from a variable is also pretty
common. You might perform the operation of adding <code>1</code> to a variable with
assignment statements such as:</p>

<pre>counter  =  counter + 1;
goalsScored  =  goalsScored + 1;</pre>

<np>The effect of the assignment statement <code>x = x + 1</code> is to take the old
value of the variable <code>x</code>, compute the result of adding <code>1</code> to
that value, and store the answer as the new value of <code>x</code>. The same
operation can be accomplished by writing <code>x++</code> (or, if you prefer,
<code>++x</code>). This actually changes the value of <code>x</code>, so that it has
the same effect as writing "<code>x&nbsp;=&nbsp;x&nbsp;+&nbsp;1</code>". The two statements above could
be written</np>

<pre>counter++;
goalsScored++;</pre>

<np>Similarly, you could write <code>x--</code> (or <code>--x</code>) to subtract
<code>1</code> from <code>x</code>. That is, <code>x--</code> performs the same computation
as <code>x&nbsp;=&nbsp;x&nbsp;-&nbsp;1</code>. Adding <code>1</code> to a variable is called 
<newword>incrementing</newword> that variable, and subtracting <code>1</code> is
called <newword>decrementing</newword>. The operators <code>++</code> and
<code>--</code> are called the increment operator and the decrement operator,
respectively. These operators can be used on variables belonging to any of the
numerical types and also on variables of type <ptype>char</ptype>. 
(If <code>ch</code> is <code>'A'</code> then <code>ch++</code> changes the value
of <code>ch</code> to&nbsp;<code>'B'</code>.)</np>

<p>Usually, the operators <code>++</code> or <code>--</code> are used in statements
like "<code>x++</code>;" or "<code>x--</code>;". These statements are commands to
change the value of <code>x</code>. However, it is also legal to use <code>x++</code>,
<code>++x</code>, <code>x--</code>, or <code>--x</code> as expressions, or as parts of
larger expressions. That is, you can write things like:</p>

<pre>y = x++;
y = ++x;
TextIO.putln(--x);
z = (++x) * (y--);</pre>

<np>The statement "<code>y = x++</code>;" has the effects of adding <code>1</code> to
the value of <code>x</code> and, in addition, assigning some value to <code>y</code>.
The value assigned to <code>y</code> is 
defined to be the <b>old</b> value of <code>x</code>, before the
<code>1</code> is added. Thus, if the value of <code>x</code> is <code>6</code>, the
statement "<code>y = x++</code>;" will change the value of <code>x</code> to
<code>7</code>, but it will change the value of <code>y</code> to <code>6</code>, because the
value assigned to <code>y</code> is the <b>old</b> value of <code>x</code>. On the
other hand, the value of <code>++x</code> is defined to be the <b>new</b>
value of <code>x</code>, after the <code>1</code> is added. So if <code>x</code> is
<code>6</code>, then the statement "<code>y = ++x</code>;" changes the values of both
<code>x</code> and <code>y</code> to <code>7</code>. The decrement operator, <code>--</code>,
works in a similar way.</np>

<p>Note in particular that the statement <code>x = x++;</code> <b>does not change the value of x</b>!
This is because the value that is being assigned to x is the old value of x, the one that it had
before the statement was executed.  The net result is that x is incremented but then immediately
changed back to its previous value!  You also need to remember that <code>x++</code> is <b>not</b>
the same as <code>x&nbsp;+&nbsp;1</code>.  The expression <code>x++</code> changes the value of x;
the expression <code>x&nbsp;+&nbsp;1</code> does not.</p>

<p>This can be confusing, and I have seen many bugs in student programs resulting from the confusion.
My advice is: Don't be confused. Use <code>++</code> and
<code>--</code> only as stand-alone statements, not as expressions. I will follow
this advice in almost all examples in these notes.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="basics.5.3" title="Relational Operators">

<p>Java has boolean variables and boolean-valued expressions that can be used
to express conditions that can be either <code>true</code> or <code>false</code>. One
way to form a boolean-valued expression is to compare two values using a
<newword>relational operator</newword>. Relational operators are used
to test whether two values are equal, whether one value is greater than
another, and so forth. The relational operators in Java are: <code>==</code>,
<code>!=</code>, <code>&lt;</code>, <code>&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;=</code>, and <code>&gt;=</code>.
The meanings of these operators are:</p>

<pre>A == B       Is A "equal to" B?
A != B       Is A "not equal to" B?
A &lt; B        Is A "less than" B?
A &gt; B        Is A "greater than" B?
A &lt;= B       Is A "less than or equal to" B?
A &gt;= B       Is A "greater than or equal to" B?</pre>

<np>These operators can be used to compare values of any of the numeric types.
They can also be used to compare values of type <ptype>char</ptype>. For characters,
<code>&lt;</code> and <code>&gt;</code> are defined according the numeric Unicode
values of the characters. (This might not always be what you want. It is not
the same as alphabetical order because all the upper case letters come before
all the lower case letters.)</np>

<p>When using boolean expressions, you should remember that as far as the
computer is concerned, there is nothing special about boolean values. In the
next chapter, you will see how to use them in loop and branch statements. But
you can also assign boolean-valued expressions to boolean variables, just as
you can assign numeric values to numeric variables.  And functions can return
boolean values.</p>

<p>By the way, the operators <code>==</code> and <code>!=</code> can be used to compare boolean values too.
This is occasionally useful. For example, can you figure out what this
does:</p>

<pre>boolean sameSign;
sameSign = ((x &gt; 0) == (y &gt; 0));</pre>

<p>One thing that you <b>cannot</b> do with the relational operators
<code>&lt;</code>, <code>&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;=</code>, and <code>&gt;=</code> is to use them
to compare values of type <classname>String</classname>. You can legally use <code>==</code> and
<code>!=</code> to compare <code>Strings</code>, but because of peculiarities in the
way objects behave, they might not give the results you want. (The <code>==</code>
operator checks whether two objects are stored in the same memory location,
rather than whether they contain the same value. Occasionally, for some
objects, you do want to make such a check&mdash;but rarely for strings. I'll get
back to this in a later chapter.) Instead, you should compare strings using subroutines such as
<code>equals()</code>  and <code>compareTo()</code>, which
were described in <localref href="basics.3.3"/>.</p>

<p>Another place where <code>==</code> and <code>!=</code> don't always work as you would expect
is with <code>Double.NaN</code>, the constant that represents an undefined value of
type <ptype>double</ptype>.  The value of <code>x&nbsp;==&nbsp;Double.NaN</code>
is defined to be <code>false</code> for any <code>x</code>,
and <code>x&nbsp;!=&nbsp;Double.NaN</code> is defined to be <code>true</code> in
all cases.  Those values hold even when <code>x</code> is <code>Double.NaN</code>!  To test whether
a real value <code>x</code> is the undefined value <code>Double.NaN</code>,
use the <ptype>boolean</ptype>-valued function <code>Double.isNaN(x)</code>.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="basics.5.4" title="Boolean Operators">

<p>In English, complicated conditions can be formed using the words "and",
"or", and "not." For example, "If there is a test <b>and</b> you did <b>not</b>
study for it&dots;". "And", "or", and "not" are <newword>boolean operators</newword>, and they exist
in Java as well as in English.</p>

<p>In Java, the boolean operator "and" is represented by <code>&amp;&amp;</code>.
The <code>&amp;&amp;</code> operator is used to combine two boolean values. The
result is also a boolean value. The result is <code>true</code> if <b>both</b> of
the combined values are <code>true</code>, and the result is <code>false</code> if
<b>either</b> of the combined values is <code>false</code>. For example, 
"<code>(x&nbsp;==&nbsp;0) &amp;&amp; (y&nbsp;==&nbsp;0)</code>"
is <code>true</code> if and only if both <code>x</code> is
equal to 0 and <code>y</code> is equal to&nbsp;0.</p>

<p>The boolean operator "or" is represented by <code>||</code>. (That's supposed to
be two of the vertical line characters,&nbsp;<code>|</code>.) The expression 
"<code>A&nbsp;||&nbsp;B</code>" is <code>true</code> if either <code>A</code> is <code>true</code> or <code>B</code> is
<code>true</code>, or if both are true. "<code>A&nbsp;||&nbsp;B</code>" is <code>false</code> only if
both <code>A</code> and <code>B</code> are false.</p>

<p>The operators <code>&amp;&amp;</code> and <code>||</code> are said to be
<newword>short-circuited</newword> versions of the boolean operators.
This means that the second operand of <code>&amp;&amp;</code> or <code>||</code> is not
necessarily evaluated. Consider the test</p>

<pre>(x != 0) &amp;&amp; (y/x &gt; 1)</pre>

<np>Suppose that the value of <code>x</code> is in fact zero. In that case, the
division <code>y/x</code> is undefined mathematically.
However, the computer will never perform the division, since when the computer
evaluates <code>(x&nbsp;!=&nbsp;0)</code>, it finds that the result is <code>false</code>, and so
it knows that (<code>(x&nbsp;!=&nbsp;0)&nbsp;&amp;&amp;</code>&nbsp;<b>anything</b>) has to
be false. Therefore, it doesn't bother to evaluate the second operand.
The evaluation has been short-circuited and the division by zero
is avoided.  (This may seem like a technicality, and it is. But at
times, it will make your programming life a little easier.)</np>

<p>The boolean operator "not" is a unary operator. In Java, it is indicated by
<code>!</code> and is written in front of its single operand. For example, if
<code>test</code> is a boolean variable, then</p>

<pre>test = ! test;</pre>

<np>will reverse the value of test, changing it from <code>true</code> to
<code>false</code>, or from <code>false</code> to <code>true</code>.</np>

</subsection>

<subsection id="basics.5.5" title="Conditional Operator">

<p>Any good programming language has some nifty little features that aren't
really necessary but that let you feel cool when you use them. Java has the
conditional operator. It's a ternary operator&mdash;that is, it has three operands&mdash;and
it comes in two pieces, ? and :, that have to be used together. It takes
the form</p>

<pre><bnf>boolean-expression</bnf> ? <bnf>expression1</bnf> : <bnf>expression2</bnf></pre>

<np>The computer tests the value of <bnf>boolean-expression</bnf>. If the value is <code>true</code>, it
evaluates <bnf>expression1</bnf>; otherwise, it evaluates
<bnf>expression2</bnf>. The two expressions must be of the same type.  For example:</np>

<pre>next = (N % 2 == 0) ? (N/2) : (3*N+1);</pre>

<np>will assign the value <code>N/2</code> to <code>next</code> if <code>N</code> is even
(that is, if <code>N&nbsp;%&nbsp;2&nbsp;==&nbsp;0</code> is <code>true</code>), and it will assign the
value <code>(3*N+1)</code> to <code>next</code> if <code>N</code> is odd.  (The parentheses
in this example are not required, but they do make the expression easier to read.)</np>

</subsection>

<subsection id="basics.5.6" title="Assignment Operators and Type Conversion">

<p>You are already familiar with the assignment statement, which uses the
symbol "=" to assign the value of an expression to a variable. In fact, = is
really an operator in the sense that an assignment can itself be used as an
expression or as part of a more complex expression. The value of an assignment
such as <code>A=B</code> is the same as the value that is assigned to <code>A</code>.
So, if you want to assign the value of <code>B</code> to <code>A</code> and test at the
same time whether that value is zero, you could say:</p>

<pre>if ( (A=B) == 0 )...</pre>

<np>Usually, I would say, <b>don't do things like that</b>!</np>

<p>In general, the type of the expression on the right-hand side of an
assignment statement must be the same as the type of the variable on the
left-hand side. However, in some cases, the computer will automatically convert
the value computed by the expression to match the type of the variable.
Consider the list of numeric types: <ptype>byte</ptype>, <ptype>short</ptype>,
<ptype>int</ptype>, <ptype>long</ptype>, <ptype>float</ptype>, <ptype>double</ptype>. A value of a type
that occurs earlier in this list can be converted automatically to a value that
occurs later. For example:</p>

<pre>int A;
double X;
short B;
A = 17;
X = A;    // OK; A is converted to a double
B = A;    // illegal; no automatic conversion
          //       from int to short</pre>

<np>The idea is that conversion should only be done automatically when it can be
done without changing the semantics of the value. Any <ptype>int</ptype> can be
converted to a <ptype>double</ptype> with the same numeric value. However, there are
<ptype>int</ptype> values that lie outside the legal range of <ptype>shorts</ptype>. There
is simply no way to represent the <ptype>int</ptype> 100000 as a <ptype>short</ptype>, for
example, since the largest value of type <ptype>short</ptype> is 32767.</np>

<p>In some cases, you might want to force a conversion that wouldn't be done
automatically. For this, you can use what is called a <newword>type cast</newword>. 
A type cast is indicated by putting a type name, in
parentheses, in front of the value you want to convert. For example,</p>

<pre>int A;
short B;
A = 17;
B = (short)A;  // OK; A is explicitly type cast
               //      to a value of type short</pre>

<np>You can do type casts from any numeric type to any other numeric type.
However, you should note that you might change the numeric value of a number by
type-casting it. For example, <code>(short)100000</code> is -31072. (The -31072 is
obtained by taking the 4-byte <ptype>int</ptype> 100000 and throwing away two of
those bytes to obtain a <ptype>short</ptype>&mdash;you've lost the real information that
was in those two bytes.)</np>

<p>When you type-cast a real number to an integer, the fractional part is
discarded.  For example, <code>(int)7.9453</code> is <code>7</code>.
As another example of type casts, consider the problem of getting a random
integer between 1 and 6. The function <code>Math.random()</code> gives a real
number between 0.0 and 0.9999&dots;, and so <code>6*Math.random()</code> is between
0.0 and 5.999&dots;. The type-cast operator, <code>(int)</code>, can be used to
convert this to an integer: <code>(int)(6*Math.random())</code>. Thus,
<code>(int)(6*Math.random())</code> is one of the integers 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5. To
get a number between 1 and 6, we can add 1: "<code>(int)(6*Math.random())&nbsp;+&nbsp;1</code>".
(The parentheses around <code>6*Math.random()</code> are necessary because of precedence
rules; without the parentheses, the type cast operator would apply only to the <code>6</code>.)</p>

<p>The type <ptype>char</ptype> is almost an integer type.  You can assign <ptype>char</ptype>
values to <ptype>int</ptype> variables, and you can assign integer constants in the
range 0 to 65535 to <ptype>char</ptype> variables.  You can also use explicit type-casts between 
<ptype>char</ptype> and the numeric types.  For example, <code>(char)97</code> is <code>'a'</code>, 
<code>(int)'+'</code> is <code>43</code>, and (char)('A'&nbsp;+&nbsp;2) is&nbsp;'C'.</p>

<break/>

<p>Type conversion between <classname>String</classname> and other types cannot be done
with type-casts.  One way to convert a value of any type into a string is to concatenate
it with an empty string.  For example, <code>""&nbsp;+&nbsp;42</code> is the string <code>"42"</code>.
But a better way is to use the function <code>String.valueOf(x)</code>, a static member function
in the <classname>String</classname> class.  <code>String.valueOf(x)</code> returns the value of
<code>x</code>, converted into a string.  For example, <code>String.valueOf(42)</code> is
the string <code>"42"</code>, and if <code>ch</code> is a <ptype>char</ptype> variable, then
<code>String.valueOf(ch)</code> is a string of length one containing the single character that
is the value of <code>ch</code>.</p>

<p>It is also possible to convert certain strings into values of other types.  For example,
the string <code>"10"</code> should be convertible into the
<ptype>int</ptype> value 10, and  the string <code>"17.42e-2"</code> into
the <ptype>double</ptype> value 0.1742.  In Java, these conversions
are handled by built-in functions.</p>
   
<p>The standard class <classname>Integer</classname> contains
a static member function for converting from <classname>String</classname> 
to <ptype>int</ptype>. In particular, if <code>str</code> is any expression of type <classname>String</classname>,
then  <code>Integer.parseInt(str)</code> is a function call that attempts to convert the
value of <code>str</code> into a value of type <ptype>int</ptype>.  For example,
the value of <code>Integer.parseInt("10")</code> is the <ptype>int</ptype> value 10.
If the parameter to <code>Integer.parseInt</code> does not represent a legal <ptype>int</ptype>
value, then an error occurs.
</p>
   
<p>Similarly, the standard class <classname>Double</classname> includes
a function <code>Double.parseDouble</code>.  If <code>str</code> is a <classname>String</classname>,
then the function call <code>Double.parseDouble(str)</code> tries to convert <code>str</code>
into a value of type <ptype>double</ptype>.  An error occurs if <code>str</code> does not
represent a legal <ptype>double</ptype> value.</p>

<break/>

<p>Getting back to assignment statements, 
Java has several variations on the assignment operator, which exist to save
typing. For example, "<code>A&nbsp;+=&nbsp;B</code>" is defined 
to be the same as "<code>A&nbsp;=&nbsp;A&nbsp;+&nbsp;B</code>". 
Many of Java's operators give rise to
similar assignment operators. For example:</p>

<pre>x -= y;     // same as:   x = x - y;
x *= y;     // same as:   x = x * y;
x /= y;     // same as:   x = x / y;
x %= y;     // same as:   x = x % y;</pre>

<np>The combined assignment operator <code>+=</code> even works with strings. Recall that when the <code>+</code>
operator is used with a string as one of the operands, it represents
concatenation. Since <code>str += x</code> is equivalent to <code>str&nbsp;=&nbsp;str&nbsp;+&nbsp;x</code>,
when <code>+=</code> is used with a string on the left-hand side, it appends the
value on the right-hand side onto the string. For example, if <code>str</code> has
the value "tire", then the statement <code>str&nbsp;+=&nbsp;'d';</code> changes the value of
<code>str</code> to "tired".</np>

</subsection>
  
<subsection id="basics.5.7" title="Precedence Rules">

<p>If you use several operators in one expression, and if you don't use
parentheses to explicitly indicate the order of evaluation, then you have to
worry about the precedence rules that determine the order of evaluation.
(Advice: don't confuse yourself or the reader of your program; use parentheses
liberally.)</p>

<p>Here is a listing of the operators discussed in this section, listed in
order from highest precedence (evaluated first) to lowest precedence (evaluated
last):</p>

<pre>Unary operators:              ++, --, !, unary -, unary +, type-cast
Multiplication and division:  *,  /,  %
Addition and subtraction:     +,  -
Relational operators:         &lt;,  &gt;,  &lt;=,  &gt;=
Equality and inequality:      ==,  !=
Boolean and:                  &amp;&amp;
Boolean or:                   ||
Conditional operator:         ?:
Assignment operators:         =,  +=,  -=,  *=,  /=,  %=</pre>

<np>Operators on the same line have the same precedence. When operators of the same precedence are strung
together in the absence of parentheses, unary operators and assignment operators are evaluated right-to-left,
while the remaining operators are evaluated left-to-right. For example,
<code>A*B/C</code> means <code>(A*B)/C</code>, while <code>A=B=C</code> means
<code>A=(B=C)</code>. (Can you see how the expression <code>A=B=C</code> might be
useful, given that the value of <code>B=C</code> as an expression is the same as
the value that is assigned to <code>B</code>?)</np>
   
</subsection>

   
</section>