<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE quiz SYSTEM "../javanotes7.dtd" >

<quiz>

<question>
<ques><p>Programs written for a
graphical user interface have to deal with "events." Explain what is meant by
the term <i>event.</i> Give at least two different examples of events, and
discuss how a program might respond to those events.</p></ques>
<ans><p> An event is anything that can
occur asynchronously, not under the control of the program, to which the
program might want to respond. GUI programs are said to be "event-driven"
because for the most part, such programs simply wait for events and respond to
them when they occur. In many (but not all) cases, an event is the result of a
user action, such as when the user clicks the mouse button, types a character,
or clicks a button. The program might respond to a mouse-click on a canvas by
drawing a shape, to a typed character by adding the character to an input box,
or to a click on a button by clearing a drawing. More generally, a programmer
can set up any desired response to an event by writing an event-handling
routine for that event.</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Explain carefully what the
<code>repaint()</code> method does.</p></ques>
<ans><p>The <code>repaint()</code> method of a component is
called to notify the system that the component
needs to be redrawn. It does not itself do any drawing, and
does not itself call <code>paintComponent()</code>, but
sometime shortly after you call it, the system will call 
the component's <code>paintComponent()</code> routine.
You should call <code>repaint()</code> for a component when you have made some change to
the state of a program that requires the appearance of that component to change. </p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Java has a standard class
called <classname>JPanel</classname>. Discuss <b>two</b> ways in which JPanels can be
used.</p></ques>
<ans><p>A JPanel can be used as a <i>container</i> for other components or
as a <i>drawing surface</i>.   A JPanel is a type of component.
That is, it is a visible element of a GUI. By itself, a JPanel is simply a
blank rectangular region on the screen. However, a JPanel is a "container",
which means that other components can be added to it and will then appear on
the screen inside the JPanel. A JPanel can also be used as a drawing surface.
In order to do this, it is necessary to create a subclass of <classname>JPanel</classname>
and define a <code>paintComponent()</code> method in that subclass. An object
belonging to that subclass can then be added to another panel or other container.
The <code>paintComponent()</code> method defines how that object will draw itself
on the screen.</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Draw the picture that will
be produced by the following <code>paintComponent()</code> method:</p>
<pre>public static void paintComponent(Graphics g) {
    super.paintComponent(g);
    for (int i=10; i &lt;= 210; i = i + 50)
       for (int j = 10; j &lt;= 210; j = j + 50)
          g.drawLine(i,10,j,60);
}</pre></ques>
<ans><p>The outer loop is executed for
values of <code>i</code> equal to 10, 60, 110, 160, and 210. For <b>each</b> of
these values, the inner loop is executed for <code>j</code> equal to 10, 60, 110,
160, and 210. The <code>drawLine</code> command is therefore executed 25 times&mdash;and
so, 25 different lines are drawn. These lines connect the five points
(10,10), (60,10), (110,10), (160,10), and (210,10) to the five points (10,60),
(60,60), (110,60), (160,60), and (210,60) in all possible pairings. Here is the
picture:</p>
<img width="220" height="70" src="crisscross.png" alt="(25 criss-crossed lines)"/></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Suppose you would like a
panel that displays a green square inside a red circle, as illustrated. Write
a <code>paintComponent()</code> method for the panel class that will draw the image.</p>
<img src="square-in-circle.png" width="100" height="100" alt="(Picture of Circle in Square)"
   tex="square-in-circle.eps" texscale="0.8"/></ques>
<ans><p>(The size of the square and
circle are not specified in the problem, so any size would be acceptable, as
long as the square is in the middle of the circle. Notice that the drawing
commands are <code>fillOval</code> and <code>fillRect</code>. There are no special
routines for drawing circles or squares.  If your circle looks more jagged around
the edges than the one in the picture, it's because my solution turns on
antialiasing!)</p>
<pre>public void paintComponent(Graphics g) {

   super.paintComponent(g);
   
   Graphics2D g2 = (Graphics2D)g;  // turn on antialiasing
   g2.setRenderingHint(RenderingHints.KEY_ANTIALIASING, 
                                RenderingHints.VALUE_ANTIALIAS_ON);  
   
   g.setColor(Color.RED);      // draw the shapes
   g.fillOval(10,10,80,80);
   g.setColor(Color.GREEN);
   g.fillRect(30,30,40,40);

}</pre></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Java has a standard class
called <classname>MouseEvent</classname>. What is the purpose of this class? What does an
object of type <classname>MouseEvent</classname> do?</p></ques>
<ans><p>When an event occurs, the system
packages information about the event into an object. That object is passed as a
parameter to the event-handling routine. Different types of events are
represented by different classes of objects. An object of type
<classname>MouseEvent</classname> represents a mouse or mouse motion event. It contains
information about the location of the mouse cursor and any modifier keys that
the user is holding down. This information can be obtained by calling the
instance methods of the object. For example, if <code>evt</code> is a
<classname>MouseEvent</classname> object, then <code>evt.getX()</code> is the
<code>x</code>-coordinate of the mouse cursor, and <code>evt.isShiftDown()</code> is a
boolean value that tells you whether the user was holding down the Shift
key.</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>One of the main classes in
Swing is the <classname>JComponent</classname> class. What is meant by a component? What are
some examples?</p></ques>
<ans><p>A <classname>JComponent</classname> represents
a visual component of the computer's graphical user interface. A
<classname>JComponent</classname> is not completely independent. It must be added to a
"container," such as a panel. Examples of <classname>JComponents</classname> are
<classname>JButtons</classname>, <classname>JTextFields</classname>, and <classname>JPanels</classname>.</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p> What is the function of a
<classname>LayoutManager</classname> in Java?</p></ques>
<ans><p>A <classname>LayoutManager</classname>
implements some policy for laying out all the visual components that have been
added to a container, such as a <classname>JPanel</classname>. 
That is, it sets the sizes and positions of the components.
Different types of layout managers have different rules about how components
are to be arranged. Some standard layout manager classes are
<classname>BorderLayout</classname> and <classname>GridLayout</classname>.</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Consider the illustration of nested panels from the beginning of <localref href="GUI1.7"/>.
What type of layout manager is being used for each of the three panels
in that picture?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>The outer panel, shown in pink, seems to be using a <classname>GridLayout</classname>
with two rows and one column.  A <classname>GridLayout</classname> is most likely
since the two components in the main panel&mdash;the other two panels, shown in light cyan&mdash;are
exactly the same size.  Similarly, the bottom subpanel seems to
be using a <classname>GridLayout</classname> with one row and three columns.
The top subpanel could be using a <classname>BorderLayout</classname>.
The components on the left and right ends of the subpanel would be in the
<code>WEST</code> and <code>EAST</code> positions of the <classname>BorderLayout</classname>.
Each of these components would then be shown at its own preferred width, which would
explain how their widths could be different.  The third component, in the center
of the subpanel, would then be in the <code>CENTER</code> position.</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Explain how <classname>Timers</classname>
are used to do animation.</p></ques>
<ans><p>Displaying an animation requires
showing a sequence of frames. The frames are shown one after the other, with a
short delay between each frame and the next. A <classname>Timer</classname> can generate a
sequence of <classname>ActionEvents</classname>. When a timer is used to do animation, each
event triggers the display of another frame. The <classname>ActionListener</classname> that
processes events from the timer just needs to be programmed to display a new frame
each time its <classname>actionPerformed()</classname> method is called.  Usually,
the <code>actionPerformed()</code> method just changes the values of some state variables and
calls <code>repaint()</code> to make the effect of the changes visible on the screen.</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>What is a <classname>JCheckBox</classname>
and how is it used?</p></ques>
<ans><p>A <classname>JCheckBox</classname> is a
component that has two possible states, "selected" and "not selected". The user can
change the state by clicking on the <classname>JCheckBox</classname>. If <code>box</code> is a
variable of type <classname>JCheckBox</classname>, then a program can set the state of the box 
to "selected" by
calling <code>box.setSelected(true)</code> and can unselect the box by calling
<code>box.setSelected(false)</code>. The current state can be determined by calling
<code>box.isSelected()</code>, which is a boolean-valued function. A
<classname>JCheckBox</classname> generates an event of type <code>ActionEvent</code> when it
changes state. A program can listen for these events if it wants to take some
action at the time the state changes. Often, however, it's enough for a program
simply to look at the state of the <classname>JCheckBox</classname> when it needs it.</p></ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>How is the <i>preferred size</i> of a component set, and how is it used?</p></ques>
<ans><p>Standard components such as <classname>JButton</classname> and <classname>JLabel</classname>
are responsible for computing their own preferred size, and the preferred size of a container
is usually computed by the layout manager for that container, but it is possible to set the
preferred size of a component, <code>comp</code>, by calling the method <code>comp.setPreferredSize(dim)</code>,
where <code>dim</code> is an object of type <classname>Dimension</classname>.  When a <classname>JPanel</classname>
is used as a drawing surface, it is usually necessary to set its preferred size in this way,
since otherwise its preferred size will be zero.</p>
<p>A layout uses the preferred sizes of all the components in a container when it decides how to
lay out those components.  It also uses the components' preferred sizes when computing the
preferred size of the container.  (Note that the preferred size is only preferred; it is not
necessarily the size at which the component will appear on screen.  The actual size can depend
on which layout manager is used, the position of the component in the layout, the size of the
container, and the preferred sizes of other components in the container.)</p></ans>
</question>
   
</quiz>