<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="GUI1.1" title="The Basic GUI Application">
   
<p><start><big>T</big>he command-line programs</start> that you have
learned how to program would seem very alien to most computer users.
The style of interaction where the user and the computer take turns
typing strings of text seems like something out of the early days
of computing, although it was only in the mid 1980s that home computers
with graphical user interfaces started to become available.  Today,
most people interact with their computers exclusively through a GUI.
A GUI program offers a much richer type of user interface, where the user uses a mouse
and keyboard to interact with GUI components such as windows, menus, buttons,
check boxes, text input boxes, scroll bars, and so on.</p>

<p>A GUI program still has a <code>main()</code> subroutine, but in general, that main
routine just creates one or more GUI components and displays them
on the computer screen. Once the GUI
components have been created, they follow their <b>own</b> programming&mdash;programming
that tells them how to draw themselves on the screen and how to respond to events
such as being clicked on by the user.</p>

<p>A GUI program doesn't have to be immensely complex.  We can, for example,
write a very simple GUI "Hello World" program that says "Hello" to the user,
but does it by opening a window where the greeting is displayed:</p>
   
<pre>import javax.swing.JOptionPane;

public class HelloWorldGUI1 {
   
   public static void main(String[] args) {
      JOptionPane.showMessageDialog( null, "Hello World!" );
   }

}</pre>   
   
<p>When this program is run, a window appears on the screen that contains the
message "Hello World!".   The window also contains an "OK" button for the user 
to click after reading the message.  When the user clicks this button, the 
window closes and the program ends.  This program can be placed
in a file named <sourceref href="HelloWorldGUI1.java"/>, compiled, and run
using the <code>java</code> command on the command line
just like any other Java program.</p>
   
<p>Now, this program is already doing some pretty fancy stuff.  It creates a window,
it draws the contents of that window, and it handles the event that is generated
when the user clicks the button.  The reason the program was so easy to write is that all
the work is done by <code>showMessageDialog()</code>, a <code>static</code> method in the
built-in class <classname>JOptionPane</classname>.  (Note that the source code 
"imports" the class <code>javax.swing.JOptionPane</code> to make it possible
to refer to the <classname>JOptionPane</classname> class using its simple name.
See <localref href="subroutines.5.3"/> for information about importing classes from
Java's standard packages.)</p>
   
<p>If you want to display a message to the user in a GUI program, this is a good way to
do it:  Just use a standard class that already knows how to do the work!  And in fact,
<classname>JOptionPane</classname> is regularly used for just this purpose 
(but as part of a larger program, usually).
Of course, if you want to do anything serious in a GUI program, there is a lot more to learn.  To give you
an idea of the types of things that are involved, we'll look at a short GUI program that
does the same things as the previous program&mdash;open a window containing a message
and an OK button, and respond to a click on the button by ending the program&mdash;but
does it all by hand instead of by using the built-in <classname>JOptionPane</classname> class.
Mind you, this is <b>not</b> a good way to write the program, but it will
illustrate some important aspects of GUI programming in Java.</p>
   
<p>Here is the source code for the program.  You are not expected to understand it yet.
I will explain how it works below, but it will take the rest of the chapter before you
will really understand completely.  In this section, you will just get a brief overview
of GUI programming.</p>
   
<pre>import java.awt.*;
import java.awt.event.*;
import javax.swing.*;

public class HelloWorldGUI2 {
   
   private static class HelloWorldDisplay extends JPanel {
      public void paintComponent(Graphics g) {
         super.paintComponent(g);
         g.drawString( "Hello World!", 20, 30 );
      }
   }
   
   private static class ButtonHandler implements ActionListener {
      public void actionPerformed(ActionEvent e) {
         System.exit(0);
      }
   }
   
   public static void main(String[] args) {
      
      HelloWorldDisplay displayPanel = new HelloWorldDisplay();
      JButton okButton = new JButton("OK");
      ButtonHandler listener = new ButtonHandler();
      okButton.addActionListener(listener);

      JPanel content = new JPanel();
      content.setLayout(new BorderLayout());
      content.add(displayPanel, BorderLayout.CENTER);
      content.add(okButton, BorderLayout.SOUTH);

      JFrame window = new JFrame("GUI Test");
      window.setContentPane(content);
      window.setSize(250,100);
      window.setLocation(100,100);
      window.setVisible(true);

   }
   
}</pre>   

<subsection id="GUI1.1.1" title="JFrame and JPanel">
   
<p>In a Java GUI program, each GUI component in the interface is represented by an object in the program.
One of the most fundamental types of component is the <newword>window</newword>.  Windows have
many behaviors.  They can be opened and closed.  They can be resized.  They have "titles" that
are displayed in the title bar above the window.  And most important, they can contain other
GUI components such as buttons and menus.</p>
   
<p>Java, of course, has a built-in class to represent windows.  There are actually several
different types of window, but the most common type is represented by the <classname>JFrame</classname>
class (which is included in the package <code>javax.swing</code>).
A <classname>JFrame</classname> is an independent window that can, for example, act as the main window
of an application.  One of the most important things to understand is that a <classname>JFrame</classname>
object comes with many of the behaviors of windows already programmed in.  In particular, it
comes with the basic properties shared by all windows, such as a titlebar and the ability to be opened and
closed.  Since a <classname>JFrame</classname> comes with these behaviors, you don't have to
program them yourself!  This is, of course, one of the central ideas of object-oriented programming.
What a <classname>JFrame</classname> doesn't come with, of course, is <newword>content</newword>, the 
stuff that is contained in the window.  If you don't add any other content to a <classname>JFrame</classname>,
it will just display a blank area&mdash;or, if you don't set its size, it will be so tiny that it will
be hard to find on the screen.  You can add content either by creating a <classname>JFrame</classname>
object and then adding the content to it or by creating a subclass of <classname>JFrame</classname> and
adding the content in the constructor of that subclass.</p>
   
<p>The main program above declares a variable, <code>window</code>, of type <classname>JFrame</classname>
and sets it to refer to a new window object with the statement:</p>
  
<pre>JFrame window = new JFrame("GUI Test");</pre>
   
<np>The parameter (the string "GUI test") in the constructor specifies the title that will be displayed in 
the titlebar of the window.  This line creates the window object, but the window itself is
not yet visible on the screen.  Before making the window visible, some of its properties are set
with these statements:</np>
   
<pre>window.setContentPane(content);
window.setSize(250,100);
window.setLocation(100,100);</pre>
   
<np>The first line here sets the content of the window. (The content itself was created earlier
in the main program.)  The second line says that the window will be 250 pixels wide and 100 pixels
high.  The third line says that the upper left corner of the window will be 100 pixels over from
the left edge of the screen and 100 pixels down from the top.  Once all this has been set
up, the window is actually made visible on the screen with the command:</np>
   
<pre>window.setVisible(true);</pre>
   
<np>It might look as if the program ends at that point, and, in fact, the <code>main()</code> routine
does end.  However, the window is still on the screen and the program as a whole does not end
until the user clicks the OK button.  Once the window was opened, a new thread was created
to manage the graphical user interface, and that thread continues to run even after
<code>main()</code> has finished.</np>

<break/>
   
<p>The content that is displayed in a <classname>JFrame</classname> is called its
<newword>content pane</newword>.  (In addition to its content pane, a <classname>JFrame</classname> can also have
a menu bar, which is a separate thing that I will talk about <localref href="GUI1.8">later</localref>.)  
A basic <classname>JFrame</classname>
already has a blank content pane; you can either add things to that pane or you can replace the
basic content pane entirely.  In my sample program, the line
<code>window.setContentPane(content)</code> replaces the original blank content pane with
a different component.  (Remember that a "component" is just a visual element of a graphical user interface.)
In this case, the new content is a component of type <classname>JPanel</classname>.</p>

<p><classname>JPanel</classname> is another of the fundamental classes in Swing.  The basic <classname>JPanel</classname>
is, again, just a blank rectangle.  There are two ways to make a useful <classname>JPanel</classname>:
The first is to <b>add other components</b> to the panel; the second is to <b>draw something</b> in
the panel.  Both of these techniques are illustrated in the sample program. In fact, you will find two <classname>JPanels</classname>
in the program:  <code>content</code>, which is used to contain other components, and <code>displayPanel</code>, which
is used as a drawing surface.</p>
   
<p>Let's look more closely at <code>displayPanel</code>.  This variable is of type <classname>HelloWorldDisplay</classname>,
which is a static nested class inside the <classname>HelloWorldGUI2</classname> class.  (Nested classes were introduced
in <localref href="OOP.8"/>.)  This class defines just one instance method, <code>paintComponent()</code>, which
overrides a method of the same name in the <classname>JPanel</classname> class:</p>
   
<pre>private static class HelloWorldDisplay extends JPanel {
   public void paintComponent(Graphics g) {
      super.paintComponent(g);
      g.drawString( "Hello World!", 20, 30 );
   }
}</pre>

<np>The <code>paintComponent()</code> method is called by the system when a component needs to be painted
on the screen.  In the <classname>JPanel</classname> class, the <code>paintComponent</code> method simply
fills the panel with the panel's background color.  The <code>paintComponent()</code> method in
<classname>HelloWorldDisplay</classname> begins by calling <code>super.paintComponent(g)</code>.  This
calls the version of <code>paintComponent()</code> that is defined in the superclass, <classname>JPanel</classname>;
that is, it fills the panel with the background color.  (See <localref href="OOP.6.2"/> for a discussion of the
special variable <code>super</code>.)  Then it calls <code>g.drawString()</code> to paint
the string "Hello World!" onto the panel.  The net result is that whenever a <classname>HelloWorldDisplay</classname>
is shown on the screen, it displays the string "Hello World!".</np>
   
<p>We will often use <classname>JPanels</classname> in this way, as drawing surfaces.  Usually, when we do this,
we will define a class that is a subclass of <classname>JPanel</classname> and we will write a <code>paintComponent</code>
method in that class to draw the desired content in the panel.  The subclass of <classname>JPanel</classname>
can be defined either as a separate class in its own file or as a nested class.  In simple cases, I will
tend to use a nested class for the convenience.</p>
   
</subsection>
   
<subsection id="GUI1.1.2" title="Components and Layout">
   
<p>Another way of using a <classname>JPanel</classname> is as a <newword>container</newword>
to hold other components.  Java has many classes that define GUI components.  Except for top-level
components like windows, components must be <newword>added</newword> to a container before
they can appear on the screen.  In the sample program,
the variable named <code>content</code> refers to a <classname>JPanel</classname> that is
used as a container. Two other components are added to that container.  This is done in the
statements:</p>
   
<pre>content.add(displayPanel, BorderLayout.CENTER);
content.add(okButton, BorderLayout.SOUTH);</pre>

<np>Here, <code>content</code> refers to an object of type <classname>JPanel</classname>;
later in the program, this panel becomes the content pane of the window.
The first component that is added to <code>content</code> is 
<code>displayPanel</code> which, as discussed above, displays
the message, "Hello World!".  The second is <code>okButton</code> which represents the button that
the user clicks to close the window.  The variable
<code>okButton</code> is of type <classname>JButton</classname>, the Java class that represents 
push buttons.</np>

<p>The "BorderLayout" stuff in these statements has to do with
how the two components are arranged in the container.  When components
are added to a container, there has to be some way of deciding how those components are arranged
inside the container.  This is called "laying out" the components in the container, and the
most common technique for laying out components is to use a <newword>layout manager</newword>.
A layout manager is an object that implements some policy for how to arrange the components
in a container; different types of layout manager implement different policies.  One type of
layout manager is defined by the <classname>BorderLayout</classname> class.  In the program, the
statement</p>
   
<pre>content.setLayout(new BorderLayout());</pre>
   
<np>creates a new <classname>BorderLayout</classname> object and tells the <code>content</code>
panel to use the new object as its layout manager.  Essentially, this line determines how
components that are added to the content panel will be arranged inside the panel.  We will
cover layout managers in much more detail later, but for now all you need to know is
that adding <code>okButton</code> in the <code>BorderLayout.SOUTH</code> position puts
the button at the bottom of the panel, and putting <code>displayPanel</code> in the
<code>BorderLayout.CENTER</code> position makes it fill any space that is not taken
up by the button.</np>
   
<p>This example shows a general technique for setting up a GUI:  Create a container and
assign a layout manager to it, create components and add them to the container, and
use the container as the content pane of a window. A container is itself a
component, so it is possible that some of the components that are added to the top-level
container are themselves containers, with their own layout managers and components.
This makes it possible to build up complex user interfaces in a hierarchical fashion,
with containers inside containers inside containers&dots;</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="GUI1.1.3" title="Events and Listeners">
   
<p>The structure of containers and components sets up the physical appearance of a
GUI, but it doesn't say anything about how the GUI <b>behaves</b>.  That is, what
can the user do to the GUI and how will it respond?  GUIs are largely
<newword>event-driven</newword>; that is, the program waits for events that are generated
by the user's actions (or by some other cause).  When an event occurs, the program
responds by executing an <newword>event-handling method</newword>.  In order to
program the behavior of a GUI, you have to write event-handling methods to respond
to the events that you are interested in.</p>
   
<p>The most common technique for handling events in Java is to use <newword>event
listeners</newword>.  A listener is an object that includes one or more event-handling
methods.  When an event is detected by another object, such as a button or menu,
the listener object is notified and it responds by running the appropriate event-handling
method.  An event is detected or generated by an object.  Another object, the listener,
has the responsibility of responding to the event.  The event itself is actually represented
by a third object, which carries information about the type of event, when it occurred,
and so on.  This division of responsibilities makes it easier to organize large programs.</p>

<img src="event-handling.png" width="557" height="168" 
      alt="illustration of event being generated and sent to listener"
      bordered="true" tex="event-handling.eps" texscale="0.75"/>
   
<p>As an example, consider the OK button in the sample program.  When the user
clicks the button, an event is generated.  This event is represented by an object belonging
to the class <classname>ActionEvent</classname>.  The event that is generated is associated
with the button; we say that the button is the <newword>source</newword> of the event.
The listener object in this case is an object belonging to the class <classname>ButtonHandler</classname>,
which is defined as a nested class inside <classname>HelloWorldGUI2</classname>:</p>

<pre>private static class ButtonHandler implements ActionListener {
   public void actionPerformed(ActionEvent e) {
      System.exit(0);
   }
}</pre>
   
<p>This class implements the <classname>ActionListener</classname> interface&mdash;a requirement for
listener objects that handle events from buttons.  (Interfaces were introduced in 
<localref href="OOP.7"/>.)  The event-handling method is named <code>actionPerformed</code>,
as specified by the <classname>ActionListener</classname> interface.  This method contains the
code that is executed when the user clicks the button; in this case, the code is simply a call
to <code>System.exit()</code>, which will terminate the program.</p>
   
<p>There is one more ingredient that is necessary to get the event from the button to the
listener object:  The listener object must <newword>register</newword> itself with the button
as an event listener.  This is done with the statement:</p>

<pre>okButton.addActionListener(listener);</pre>
   
<np>This statement tells <code>okButton</code> that when the user clicks the button, the
ActionEvent that is generated should be sent to <code>listener</code>.  Without this statement,
the button has no way of knowing that there is something that would like to listen for events
from the button.</np>
   
<p>This example shows a general technique for programming the behavior of a GUI:
Write classes that include event-handling methods.  Create objects that belong to these
classes and register them as listeners with the objects that will actually detect or
generate the events.  When an event occurs, the listener is notified, and the code that you
wrote in one of its event-handling methods is executed.  At first, this might seem like
a very roundabout and complicated way to get things done, but as you gain experience
with it, you will find that it is very flexible and that it goes together very well with
object oriented programming.</p>

<p>This section has introduced some of the fundamentals of GUI programming.  We will
spend the rest of the chapter exploring them in more detail.</p>

</subsection>


<subsection id="GUI1.1.4" title="Some Java GUI History">

<p>The original GUI toolkit for Java was the AWT, the "Abstract Windowing Toolkit." It provided
a common interface to the GUI components already built into various operating systems.  At the
very beginning, it used a simpler event model that did not require listener objects, but that model
was abandoned in favor of listeners very quickly in Java&nbsp;1.1.</p>

<p>When Java was first introduced, one of the important applications was
<newword>applets</newword>.  An applet is a GUI program that can run on a web page
in a web browser.  Applets were covered in previous versions of this textbook,
but they have become much less widely used and have been dropped from this
seventh edition of the book.</p>

<p>The <newcode>Swing</newcode> GUI toolkit was introduced in Java 1.2
as an improved alternative to the AWT, with a larger variety of
sophisticated components and a more logical structure.  Although Swing uses some aspects of
the AWT, most of its components are written in Java rather than being based on operating system
components.  Swing has been the standard toolkit for writing GUI programs in Java for over
ten years, and it is the toolkit that I cover in this book.</p>

<p>More recently, however, another GUI toolkit called <newword>JavaFX</newword> has been
introduced.  It uses many of the same core ideas as Swing, including components, layout, and
events, but uses a different structure for its applications and a different set of classes.
With Java&nbsp;8, JavaFX becomes the preferred approach to writing GUI applications.
However, I do not cover JavaFX in this book.  JavaFX is compatible with Swing and can use
Swing components, and Swing will continue to be supported in Java.  (Indeed, the AWT is
still supported!)  And as I've said, JavaFX is built on the same core ideas as Swing.</p>

</subsection>
   
</section>