<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="GUI1.2" title="Some Basic Classes">

<p>In this section, we will look at some basic classes,
including classes representing colors, fonts, and images.
We will see how these classes are used in the <classname>GraphicsContext</classname>
API, which you already encountered in a preliminary way in <localref href="control.8"/>,
but they are also useful in other parts of JavaFX.  There is also a brief
introduction to <newword>CSS style sheets</newword>, which can be used to control
many aspects of the visual appearance of GUI components.</p>

<subsection id="GUI1.2.1" title="Color and Paint">
   
<p>Computer color uses an <newword>RGB color system</newword>.
That is, a color on a computer screen is specified by three numbers, called
<newword>color components</newword>, giving the level of red, green, and
blue in the color.  A color is represented by an object of type <classname>Color</classname>,
from package <code>javafx.scene.paint</code>.  In JavaFX, each color component
is a <ptype>double</ptype> value in the range 0.0 to 1.0.  A <classname>Color</classname>
object also has a fourth component in the range 0.0 to 1.0, referred as the <newword>alpha color component</newword>,
which is generally used to represent the transparency or opaqueness of the color
when it is used for drawing.  When a fully opaque color (alpha component equal to 1.0) is
used for drawing, the drawing color completely replaces the current color of the
drawing surface.  When a fully transparent color (alpha component equal to 0.0) is used
for drawing, it has no effect at all.  When the alpha component is between 0.0 and
1.0, the drawing color is combined with the current color to give the new color of
the drawing surface, as if the original contents of the drawing surface were being 
viewed through colored, translucent glass.  A <classname>Color</classname> object
can be constructed by giving its red, green, blue, and alpha components; for example,</p>

<pre>Color myColor = new Color( r, g, b, a );</pre>

<np>where r, g, b, and a are in the range 0.0 to 1.0.
However, the <classname>Color</classname> class also has a number of
static methods for making color objects.  Static methods whose job
is to create objects are sometimes called <newword>factory methods</newword>.
So instead of using the
constructor, you could also say</np>

<pre>Color myColor = Color.color( r, g, b, a );</pre>

<np>and in the common case of a fully opaque color, with <i>a</i> equal to 1.0,
you can use</np>

<pre>Color myColor = Color.color( r, g, b );</pre>

<np>These static factory methods are preferable to the constructor because they
have the option of reusing color objects.  For example,
two calls to <code>Color.color(0.2,0.3,1.0)</code> might return the same
<classname>Color</classname> object.  This is OK because 
color objects are immutable; that is, there is no way to change a color
after it has been constructed.  So there is really no reason to use
two different objects to represent the same color.</np>

<p>Your computer screen probably uses "32-bit color," which means that the
color of each pixel is actually represented using just 8 bits for each of the four
color components.  Eight bits can represent the 256 integers in the range 0 to 255,
so computer colors have traditionally been specified using
integer color components in the range 0 to 255.  The <classname>Color</classname>
class has the following static method for making colors in this way:
</p>

<pre>Color.rgb( r, g, b )</pre>

<np>where r, g, and b are integers in the range 0 to 255.  There is also
<code>Color.rgb(r,g,b,a)</code> where r, g, and b are <ptype>ints</ptype> in the
range 0 to 255, and a is a <ptype>double</ptype> in the range 0.0 to 1.0.</np>

<p>An alternative to RGB is the <newword>HSB color system</newword>.
In the HSB system, a color is specified by three numbers called the
<newword>hue</newword>, the <newword>saturation</newword>,
and the <newword>brightness</newword>. The hue is the basic color,
ranging from red through orange through all the other colors of the rainbow.
The brightness is pretty much what it sounds like. A fully saturated color is a
pure color tone. Decreasing the saturation is like mixing white or gray paint
into the pure color. In JavaFX, the hue is given by a <ptype>double</ptype>
value in the range 0.0 to 360.0, while saturation and brightness are
<ptype>double</ptype> values in the range 0.0 to 1.0.  (The hue value is
given in degrees, were the colors are seen as laid out along a circle, with
both 0.0 and 360.0 representing pure red.) The
<classname>Color</classname> class has static methods
<code>Color.hsb(h,s,b)</code> and <code>Color.hsb(h,s,b,a)</code>
for making HSB colors. For example, to make a color with a random hue that is as bright and as
saturated as possible, you could use:</p>

<pre>Color randomColor = Color.hsb( 360*Math.random(), 1.0, 1.0 );</pre>

<p>The RGB system and the HSB system are just different ways of describing the
same set of colors. It is possible to translate between one system and the
other. The best way to understand the color systems is to experiment with them.
The sample program <sourceref href="SimpleColorChooser.java"/> lets you do that.
You won't understand the source code at this time, but you can run it to play
with color selection or to find RGB or HSB values for the color that want.</p>

<p>The <classname>Color</classname> class also contains a large number of
constants representing colors, such as <code>Color.RED</code>, <code>Color.BLACK</code>,
<code>Color.LIGHTGRAY</code>, and <code>Color.GOLDENROD</code>.  It might be worth mentioning that
<code>Color.GREEN</code> is the fairly dark green color given by <code>Color.rgb(0,128,0)</code>;
the constant representing <code>Color.rgb(0,255,0)</code> is <code>Color.LIME</code>.
There is also <code>Color.TRANSPARENT</code>, which represents a fully transparent
color, with all RGBA color components equal to zero.</p>

<p>Given a <classname>Color</classname>, <code>c</code>, you can find out the
values of the various color components by calling functions such as
<code>c.getRed()</code>, <code>c.getHue()</code>, and <code>c.getOpacity()</code>.
These methods return <ptype>double</ptype> values in the range 0.0 to 1.0, except
for <code>c.getHue()</code>, which returns a <ptype>double</ptype> in the range
0.0 to 360.0.</p>

<break/>

<p><classname>Color</classname> is a subclass of another class,
<classname>Paint</classname>, which represents the more general idea of
"something that can be used to fill and to stroke shapes."  In addition
to colors, there are image paints and gradient paints.  I will not use these
more general paints in this chapter, but they will be covered in
<localref href="GUI2.2.2"/>.  For now, you should just know that when a
method has a parameter of type <classname>Paint</classname>, you
can use a <classname>Color</classname>.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection title="Fonts" id="GUI1.2.2">

<p>A <newword>font</newword> represents a particular size and style
of text. The same character will appear different in different fonts. In JavaFX,
a font is represented by an object of type <classname>Font</classname>,
from the package <code>javafx.scene.text</code>.  Although the <classname>Font</classname>
defines a couple of constructors, the best way to make a font object is with
one of the static factory methods from that class.</p>

<p>A font has a name, which is a string that specifies a font family such as "Times New Roman."
A given family can have variations such as a bold or an italic version of the font.
And a font has a size, which is specified in "points," where a point should really be 1/72 inch
but might in practice be equal to the size of a pixel.  The most general function for
making fonts can specify all of these options:
</p>

<pre>Font myFont = Font.font( family, weight, posture, size );</pre>

<np>If the system can't match the requested font properties exactly, it will return the
font that it thinks best matches the parameters.
Here, <code>family</code> is a <classname>String</classname> that should specify a font family
that is available to the program.  Unfortunately, there is no set of fonts that
is required to be available.  "Times New Roman," "Arial," and "Verdana" are
likely to work.  (These are fonts that were created by Microsoft and released for free
use; they are installed on many systems.)  You can pass <code>null</code> as the <code>familyName</code>
to use the default font family.</np>

<p>Font "weight" is given as an enumerated type value from the <code>enum</code>
<classname>FontWeight</classname>.  It will usually be either <code>FontWeight.BOLD</code>
or <code>FontWeight.NORMAL</code>, although there are a few other values such as
<code>FontWeight.EXTRA_BOLD</code>.  Similarly, font "posture" is one of the
constants <code>FontPosture.ITALIC</code> or <code>FontPosture.REGULAR</code>.
Both <classname>FontWeight</classname> and <classname>FontPosture</classname>
are from package <code>javafx.scene.text</code>.</p>

<p>The <classname>Font</classname> class has several other static functions for making
fonts, which specify only a subset of the four properties family, weight, posture, and
size.  These include: <code>Font.font(size)</code>, <code>Font.font(family)</code>,
<code>Font.font(family,weight,size)</code>, and a few others.  The missing properties
will have default values, which can depend on the computer where the program is running.
The static function <code>Font.getDefault()</code> returns a font that has default
values for all the properties.  You can call <code>Font.getDefault().getSize()</code>
to find the default point size.  (It's 13.0 on my computer, but might be different
on yours.)  Here are a few examples of making fonts:</p>

<pre>Font font1 = Font.font(40);
Font font2 = Font.font("Times New Roman", FontWeight.BOLD, 24);
Font font3 = Font.font(null, FontWeight.BOLD, FontPosture.ITALIC, 14);</pre>

</subsection>


<subsection title="Image" id="GUI1.2.3">

<p>The term "image" refers to something like a photograph or drawing&mdash;anything
that can be represented by a rectangular grid of colored pixels.  Images are often
stored in files.  JavaFX makes it easy to load an image from a file so that
it can be displayed by a program.  An image is represented by
an object of type <classname>Image</classname>, from package
<code>javafx.scene.image</code>.  The constructor</p>

<pre>new Image( path )</pre>

<np>is used to load an image from an image file.  The <code>path</code> parameter
is a string that specifies the location of the file.  The location can be very
general, such as an image on the Internet or on the user's computer, but for
now I'm interested in images from <newword>resource files</newword>.
A resource is something that is part of a program but is not code.  Resources
can include things like sounds, data files, and fonts, as well as images.
The system can load resources for a program from the same places where
it looks for the program's .class files.  For a resource file in the
program's top-level directory, the path to the file is simply the name
of the file.  If the file is in a subdirectory of the main directory, then
the path includes the subdirectory name.  For example, the path
"images/cards.png" refers to a file named "cards.png" inside a subdirectory
named "images," and "resources/sounds/beep.aiff" refers to a file named
"beep.aiff" inside a directory named "sounds" that is in turn inside a
directory named "resources."</np>

<p>There are many kinds of image files, which store the image data in
a variety of formats.  For JavaFX <classname>Image</classname> objects,
you can use image files whose names end with .gif, .jpeg (or .jpg), .png,
and .bmp.  So, for example, if "cards.png" is a file in the top-level program directory,
you can create the image object</p>

<pre>Image cards = new Image( "cards.png" );</pre>

<np>The image can then be displayed in a <classname>GraphicsContext</classname>,
as we will soon see.  There will be other uses for images later in this chapter.</np>


</subsection>



<subsection title="Canvas and GraphicsContext" id="GUI1.2.4">

<p>The screen of a computer is a grid of little squares called <newword>pixels</newword>.
The color of each pixel can be set individually, and
drawing on the screen just means setting the colors of individual pixels.
Every visible GUI component is drawn by coloring pixels, and every component
has a coordinate system that maps (x,y) coordinates to points within the
component.  Most components draw themselves, but there is one JavaFX component
on which you can draw anything you want by calling the appropriate methods.
Such "drawing surface" components are of type <classname>Canvas</classname>,
in package <code>javafx.scene.canvas</code>.  A <classname>Canvas</classname>
is a <classname>Node</classname> and so can be part of a scene graph.
(However, it is not a <classname>Parent</classname>, so it cannot act as
a container for other nodes and it cannot be the root of a scene graph.
This means that even when a canvas is the only thing that you want to show
in a window, it must still be placed into a container that will serve as 
the root of the scene graph.)</p>

<p>A <classname>Canvas</classname> appears on the screen as 
a rectangle made up of pixels. A position in the
rectangle is specified by a pair of coordinates, <code>(x,y)</code>. The
upper left corner has coordinates <code>(0,0)</code>. The <code>x</code> coordinate
increases from left to right, and the <code>y</code> coordinate increases from top
to bottom. The illustration shows a 20-pixel by 12-pixel canvas (with
very large pixels). A small line, rectangle, and oval are shown as they would
be drawn by coloring individual pixels:</p>

<img height="212" width="420" alt="pixel coordinate system" src="pixel-coordinates.png" 
   tex="pixel-coordinates.eps" texscale="0.75" bordered="true"/>
   
<np>Note that, properly speaking, the
coordinates don't belong to the pixels but to the grid lines between them,
and coordinates can, in fact, be numbers of type <ptype>double</ptype>
and can refer to points inside a pixel.  For example, the center of the
top left pixel in a canvas has coordinates (0.5,0.5).  In fact, all drawing
is done using coordinates of type <ptype>double</ptype>.</np>

<p>The width and height of a <classname>Canvas</classname> can be specified in the constructor that
used to create the canvas object.  For example, to create a tiny 20-by-12 canvas:</p>

<pre>Canvas canvas = new Canvas(20,12)</pre>

<np>You can query the size of a canvas by calling <code>canvas.getWidth()</code> and
<code>canvas.getHeight()</code>, which return values of type <ptype>double</ptype>.
Canvasses are usually meant to be non-resizable, but the size can be changed if necessary
by calling <code>canvas.setWidth(w)</code> and <code>canvas.setHeight(h)</code>.</np>

<p>When a canvas is first created, it is filled with "transparent black," that is, with a color
that has all RGBA components set to zero.  This makes the canvas transparent:  You will see
whatever lies behind the canvas in the scene.</p>

<p>In order to draw on a canvas, you need an object of type <classname>GraphicsContext</classname>.
Every <classname>Canvas</classname> has an associated <classname>GraphicsContext</classname>;
different <classname>GraphicsContexts</classname> draw on different <classname>Canvases</classname>.
You can get the graphics context for a <classname>Canvas</classname>, <code>canvas</code>,
by calling <code>canvas.getGraphicsContext2D()</code>.  For any given <classname>Canvas</classname>,
this method will always return the same <classname>GraphicsContext</classname> object.
<localref href="control.8"/> discussed some of the things that can be done with a graphics context.
In particular, you learned that a shape can be stroked and, if it has an interior, it can also be filled.
Methods in <classname>GraphicsContext</classname>, <code>g</code>, that can be used for drawing
include the following, where all numeric parameters are of type <ptype>double</ptype>:</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>g.strokeRect(x,y,w,h)</codedef> and <codedef>g.fillRect(x,y,w,h)</codedef> &mdash;
Draw a rectangle with top left corner at <code>(x,y)</code>, with width <code>w</code> and
with height&nbsp;<code>h</code>.  If <code>w</code> or <code>h</code> is less than or
equal to zero, nothing is drawn.
</li>
<li><codedef>g.clearRect(x,y,w,h)</codedef> &mdash; Fill the same rectangle with a fully transparent
color, so that whatever lies behind the rectangle will be visible through the canvas.  Note that 
this is <b>not</b> the same as calling <code>g.fillRect(x,y,w,h)</code> with a transparent fill
color; doing that has no effect at all on the contents of the rectangle.
</li>
<li><codedef>g.strokeOval(x,y,w,h)</codedef> and <codedef>g.fillOval(x,y,w,h)</codedef> &mdash;
Draw an oval that just fits inside the rectangle with top left corner at <code>(x,y)</code>, with width <code>w</code> and
with height&nbsp;<code>h</code>.
</li>
<li><codedef>g.strokeRoundRect(x,y,w,h,rh,rv)</codedef> and <codedef>g.fillRoundRect(x,y,w,h,rh,rv)</codedef> &mdash;
Draw a rectangle with rounded corners. The rectangle has top left corner at <code>(x,y)</code>, with width <code>w</code> and
with height&nbsp;<code>h</code>.  A quarter oval is cut off each corner, where the horizontal radius of the
oval is <code>rh</code> and its vertical radius is <code>rv</code>.
</li>
<li><codedef>g.strokeText(str,x,y)</codedef> and <codedef>g.fillText(str,x,y)</codedef> &mdash;
Draw the text of the <classname>String</classname> <code>str</code>.  The point <code>(x,y)</code>
is the left end of the baseline of the text. (A string is drawn on top of its baseline, with descenders
such as the tail of a "y" extending below the baseline.)  The string can contain multiple lines
separated by newline ('\n') characters; <code>(x,y)</code> then gives the baseline of the
first line of the string.  Note that stroking text means drawing just the outlines of the characters.
</li>
<li><codedef>g.strokePolygon(xcoords,ycoords,n)</codedef> and <codedef>g.fillPolygon(xcoords,ycoords,n)</codedef> &mdash;
Draw a polygon, consisting of line segments connecting a sequence of points.  The number of points is given
by the third parameter, <code>n</code>.  The first two parameters are arrays of type
<atype>double[]</atype> containing the coordinates of the points.  An extra line segment is automatically
added to connect the last point back to the first.  That is, the
polygon connects the points <code>(xcoords[0],ycoords[0])</code>, <code>(xcoords[1],ycoords[1])</code>, &dots;,
<code>(xcoords[n-1],ycoords[n-1])</code>, <code>(xcoords[0],ycoords[0])</code>.
</li>
<li><codedef>g.strokeLine(x1,y1,x2,y2)</codedef> &mdash; Draws a line from <code>(x1,y1)</code>
to <code>(x2,y2)</code>.  (It's no use trying to fill a line, since it has no interior.)</li>
</ul>

<p>The <classname>GraphicsContext</classname> object, <code>g</code> has a number of properties that affect
drawing.  When anything is drawn using <code>g</code>, the current values of the relevant
properties are used.  This means that changing the value of a property does not affect anything
that has already been drawn; the change only applies to things drawn in the future.  Each property
has a setter method and a getter method.  One of the properties is the <classname>Paint</classname> 
that is used for filling (which in
this chapter will always be a <classname>Color</classname>); this property can be set by calling
<code>g.setFill(paint)</code>, and you can get its current value by calling <code>g.getFill()</code>.
Similarly, the <classname>Paint</classname> that is used for stroking can be set and get using
<code>g.setStroke(paint)</code> and <code>g.getStroke()</code>, and the width of strokes can be
set and get using <code>g.getLineWidth(w)</code> and <code>g.getLineWidth()</code>, where
<code>w</code> is of type <ptype>double</ptype>.  And you can get and set the font that will be used
for drawing text with <code>g.setFont(font)</code> and <code>g.getFont()</code>.
</p>

<p>Note that stroking a shape is like dragging the <b>center</b> of a pen along the outline of the shape.
The size of the pen is given by the linewidth property.  The stroke that is drawn extends on both sides
of the actual path of the pen by an amount equal to half of the linewidth.  For example, if you
draw a horizontal line of width&nbsp;1 with endpoints (100,100) and (300,100), half of the stroke lies
above the geometric line and half lies below it.  The computer might show this by blending the color
of the stroke color with the current color.  If you want the stroke to 
nicely cover complete pixels, you should actually use (100.5,100.5) and (300.5,100.5) as the coordinates
of the endpoints of the line.  (Whenever you draw something, you might find that for pixels that are only
partially covered, the drawing color is blended with the current color instead of replacing it.  This is
done to decrease the jagged appearance of shapes that are made out of whole pixels, like the line and
oval in the above illustration.  This is known as <newword>antialiasing</newword>.)
</p>

<p>It is also possible to draw an image onto a canvas, where the image is represented by an
object of type <classname>Image</classname>.  There are several methods for drawing
images:</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>g.drawImage(image,x,y)</codedef> &mdash; Draws the <code>image</code> with its
upper left corner at <code>(x,y)</code>, using the actual size of the image.
</li>
<li><codedef>g.drawImage(image,x,y,w,h)</codedef> &mdash; Draws the <code>image</code> in the
rectangle with upper left corner at <code>(x,y)</code>, with width <code>w</code>, and
with height&nbsp;<code>h</code>.  The image is stetched or shrunk to fit that rectangle if 
necessary.
</li>
<li><codedef>g.drawImage(image, sx,sy,sw,sh, dx,dy,dh,dw)</codedef> &mdash; Draws the contents
of a specified "source" rectangle in the image to a specified "destination" rectangle on the
canvas.  This method lets you draw just part of an image.  The source rectangle has
upper left corner at <code>(sx,sy)</code>, width <code>sw</code>, and height&nbsp;<code>sh</code>.
The last four parameters specify the destination rectangle in a similar way.
</li>
</ul>

<break/>

<p>It's time for a couple of actual examples.  First, an example that draws some text using 
a variety of fonts.  
The program draws multiple copies of the string "Hello JavaFX" using random fonts and 
locations.  The text is filled with random colors and stroked with a thin black stroke:
</p>

<img src="randomStrings.png" width="400" height="293" tex="randomStrings.eps" texscale="0.5" alt="RandomStrings program"/>

<np>The program uses five fonts, which are created in the <code>start()</code> method using several
different static factory methods from the <classname>Font</classname> class:</np>

<pre>font1 = Font.font("Times New Roman", FontWeight.BOLD, 20);
font2 = Font.font("Arial", FontWeight.BOLD, FontPosture.ITALIC, 28);
font3 = Font.font("Verdana", 32);
font4 = Font.font(40);
font5 = Font.font("Times New Roman",FontWeight.BOLD,FontPosture.ITALIC,60);
</pre>

<np>The program defines a <code>draw()</code> method that completely
redraws the content of a canvas.  It is called when the canvas is first
created, and it is also called when the user clicks the "Redraw" button.
The method first fills the canvas with a white background, which erases
the previous contents of the canvas.  It then fills and strokes 25 copies
of "Hello JavaFX", using a random fill color, a random position for the
text, and a randomly selected font for each copy:</np>

<pre>private void draw() {

    GraphicsContext g = canvas.getGraphicsContext2D();
    
    double width = canvas.getWidth();
    double height = canvas.getHeight();
    
    g.setFill( Color.WHITE );  // fill with white background
    g.fillRect(0, 0, width, height);

    for (int i = 0; i &lt; 25; i++) {

        // Draw one string.  First, set the font to be one of the five
        // available fonts, at random.  

        int fontNum = (int)(5*Math.random()) + 1;
        switch (fontNum) {
        case 1:
            g.setFont(font1);
            break;
        case 2:
            g.setFont(font2);
            break;
        case 3:
            g.setFont(font3);
            break;
        case 4:
            g.setFont(font4);
            break;
        case 5:
            g.setFont(font5);
            break;
        } // end switch

        // Set the color to a bright, saturated color, with random hue.

        double hue = 360*Math.random();
        g.setFill( Color.hsb(hue, 1.0, 1.0) );

        // Select the position of the string, at random.

        double x,y;
        x = -50 + Math.random()*(width+40);
        y = Math.random()*(height+20);

        // Draw the message.

        g.fillText("Hello JavaFX",x,y);
        
        // Also stroke the outline of the strings with black.
        
        g.setStroke(Color.BLACK);
        g.strokeText("Hello JavaFX",x,y);

    } // end for

} // end draw()
</pre>

<np>You can find the full source code for the program in <sourceref href="RandomStrings.java"/>.</np>

<p>The second sample program is similar, but instead of drawing random strings, it draws five
playing cards dealt at random from a deck:</p>

<img src="randomCards.png" width="519" height="232" tex="randomCards.eps" texscale="0.5" alt="RandomCards program"/>

<np>The deck and cards are represented using the
<classname>Deck</classname> and <classname>Card</classname> classes from
<localref href="OOP.4"/>. The card images come from the file <sourceref href="cards.png"/>,
which is a resource file for the program.  The file contains a single image that contains
images of all the cards, arranged in rows and columns.  Here it is, shown at reduced size:</np>

<img src="cards.png" alt="deck of cards" width="513" height="307" 
   tex="cards.eps" texscale="0.33"/>

<np>(This image is from the Gnome desktop project, <a href="http://www.gnome.org">http://www.gnome.org</a>.)
The image file is loaded into the program in the <code>start()</code> method simply by saying</np>

<pre>cardImages = new Image("cards.png");</pre>

<np>where <code>cardImages</code> is an instance variable of type <classname>Image</classname>.
Suppose that we want to draw the card
from row number R and column number C in a <classname>GraphicsContext</classname> <code>g</code>
(where both rows and columns are numbered starting at zero).
Each card in the image is 79 pixels by 123 pixels, so the card that we want has its top
left corner at (79*C,123*R).  If we want to place the card on the canvas with its
top left corner at (x,y), we can use the third <code>drawImage()</code> method given above,
which specifies a source rectangle in the image and a destination rectangle on the canvas:
</np>

<pre>g.drawImage( cardImages, 79*C,123*R,79,123, x,y,79,123 );</pre>

<np>In the program, the card that we want to draw is given by a variable <code>card</code>
of type <classname>Card</classname>.  The row and column in the image are determined by
the suit and value of the card, which are given by <code>card.getSuit()</code> and
<classname>card.getValue()</classname>.  The values returned by these functions have to be
manipulated a little to get the correct row and column numbers, and the position of the
card on the canvas is calculated to leave a 20-pixel gap between one card and the next.
Here is the <classname>draw()</classname>
method from the program, which deals five random cards from a deck and draws them:</np>

<pre>private void draw() {
    
    GraphicsContext g = canvas.getGraphicsContext2D();
    
    Deck deck = new Deck();
    deck.shuffle();
    
    double sx,sy;  // top left corner of source rect for card in cardImages
    double dx,dy;  // corner of destination rect for card in the canvas
    
    for (int i = 0; i &lt; 5; i++) {
        Card card = deck.dealCard();
        System.out.println(card); // for testing
        sx = 79 * (card.getValue()-1);
        sy = 123 * (3 - card.getSuit());
        dx = 20 + (79+20) * i;
        dy = 20;
        g.drawImage( cardImages, sx,sy,79,123, dx,dy,79,123 );
    }
    
} // end draw()</pre>

<np>For the complete program, see <sourceref href="RandomCards.java"/>.</np>

</subsection>

<subsection title="A Bit of CSS" id="GUI1.2.5">

<p>JavaFX makes it possible to control the style&mdash;that is, the visual
appearance&mdash;of components in a GUI using <newword>CSS</newword> (Cascading Style Sheets).
CSS is one of several languages that are used to make web pages.  It can
control things like colors, fonts, and borders of elements of a web page.
It has been adapted to play a similar role in other contexts, such as
JavaFX.  I do not intend to cover CSS in any detail, and anything that
can be done with CSS can also be done with Java code.  However, there
are some things that are just easier to do with CSS; I will cover
a few of them in this short section and will use them in my programs.
For people who already know CSS, a guide to its use in JavaFX is
available as I write this at</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/javafx/api/javafx/scene/doc-files/cssref.html">https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/javafx/api/javafx/scene/doc-files/cssref.html</a></p>

<p>A CSS <newword>style rule</newword> consists of a property and a value for that property.
For example, CSS can be used to place a border around many kinds of GUI component.
A border has properties with names such as <code>-fx-border-color</code>
and <code>-fx-border-width</code>.  (All JavaFX CSS properties have names
that begine with "-fx-" to distinguish them from regular CSS properties.)
A value for <code>-fx-border-color</code> can be a color name such as
<code>red</code> or <code>lightblue</code>, among other formats.
One color format that I will use takes the form <code>#RRGGBB</code>,
where R, G, and B stand for hexadecimal digits.  A two-digit hexadecimal
number can represent numbers from 0 to 255.  The RR, GG, and BB in
<code>#RRGGBB</code> represent the red, green, and blue components of
a color, each in the range 0 to 255.  For example, <code>#FF0000</code>
represents pure red, and <code>#004444</code> represents a dard blue-green.</p>

<p>For the border width, the value can be a single size, such
as <code>3px</code> or <code>0.2cm</code>. The syntax is a number followed
by a unit of measure, with no space between them.  Here, "px" stands for
"pixels," and <code>3px</code> means 3 pixels.  When a width is given
by a single size, the size applies to all four sides of the border.
Alternative, four sizes can be given, separated by spaces, specifying
the border width on the top, right, bottom, and left, in that order.
For example, a thick, blue border could be specified as</p>

<pre>-fx-border-color: blue; -fx-border-width: 5px</pre>

<np>and for a dark red border that is thicker on the top  than
on the other sides, you can use</np>

<pre>-fx-border-color: #550000; -fx-border-width: 3px 1px 1px 1px</pre>

<np>When several CSS rules are used together, they should be separated
by semicolons.</np>

<p>The background color of a component can be set using 
<code>-fx-background-color</code> as the property name.  The value
is the same sort of color specification that would be used
with <code>-fx-border-color</code>.</p>

<p>And the CSS property <code>-fx-padding</code>
represents space that is left between the content of a component
and its edge (or border if there is one).  Like border width,
padding can be specified as either a single size or a list of
four sizes.  For example: <code>-fx-padding:&nbsp;8px</code>.</p>

<p>You can apply a style to a component using its <code>setStyle()</code>
method, whose parameter is a <classname>String</classname> containing
one or more CSS style rules.  For example, suppose <code>message</code>
is a <classname>Label</classname>.  By default, labels have no
padding or border.  They can be added with a command such as</p>

<pre>message.setStyle(
   "-fx-padding: 5px; -fx-border-color: black; -fx-border-width: 1px" );</pre>
   
<p>You can set the font for a component that displays text using the
<code>-fx-font</code> property.  The value for this property
specifies the size and font family for the font, and can optionally
be modified by a weight ("bold"), or by a style ("italic"), or both.
Some examples:</p>

<pre>-fx-font: 30pt "Times New Roman";
-fx-font: bold italic 18pt serif;
-fx-font: bold 42pt monospace;</pre>

<np>Note that if the font family name contains spaces, it must be enclosed
in quotes. The font families in the last two examples, "serif" and
"monospace", are so-called generic family names that specify a certain
style of font.  Other generic names include "sans-serif", "cursive",
and "fantasy".  The characters in a serif font has short lines as decorations
such as at the top and bottom of an upper case "I".  A "sans-serif" font
lacks these decorations.  The characters in a "monospace" font all have the
same width.  Monospace fonts are good for drawing characters that are meant
to line up in columns.</np>

<p>Many other properties can be set using CSS, but I will not cover them
here.  I will use CSS only for borders, padding, background colors, and fonts.</p>

<break/>

<p>Setting the style for many components can be tedious.  A <newword>CSS style sheet</newword>
can be used to apply style to all components of a given type as well as to individual components
and sets of components.  A style sheet is a file, usually with a name ending with .css.
I will not discuss the syntax, but 
here is a style sheet that will apply some style rules to all <classname>Labels</classname>
and <classname>Buttons</classname>:</p>

<pre>Button {
   -fx-font: bold 16pt "Times New Roman";
   -fx-text-fill: darkblue;
}

Label {
   -fx-font: 15pt sans-serif;
   -fx-padding: 7px;
   -fx-border-color: darkred;
   -fx-border-width: 2px;
   -fx-text-fill: darkred;
   -fx-background-color: pink;
}</pre>

<np>A style sheet file, just like an image file, can be a resource for a program.  That is,
it can be stored in the same place as the .class files for the program.  Suppose that
a style sheet named "mystyle.css" is in the program's top-level directory.  You can
then apply the style to all components in a scene with the statement</np>

<pre>scene.getStylesheets().add("mystyle.css");</pre>

<np>A <classname>Scene</classname> can have several style sheets, and style sheets
can also be added to individual containers.</np>

</subsection>

</section>

