<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="GUI1.3" title="Graphics and Painting">

<p><start><big>E</big>verything you see on a computer screen</start> has to be
drawn there, even the text. The Java API includes a range of classes and
methods that are devoted to drawing. In this section, I'll look at some of the
most basic of these.  Some of this material was already covered in preliminary
form in <localref href="control.8"/>.</p>

<p>The physical structure of a GUI is built of components. The term <newword>component</newword>
refers to a visual element in a GUI, including buttons, menus, text-input boxes, scroll bars,
check boxes, and so on. In Java,
GUI components are represented by objects belonging to subclasses of the class
<code>java.awt.Component</code>. Most components in the Swing GUI toolkit&mdash;although not
top-level components like JFrame&mdash;belong to subclasses of the class
<code>javax.swing.JComponent</code>, which is itself a subclass of <code>java.awt.Component</code>.
Every component is responsible for drawing
itself. If you want to use a standard component, you only have to
add it to your program. You don't have to worry about painting it on the screen.
That will happen automatically, since it already knows how to draw itself.</p>

<p>Sometimes, however, you do want to draw on a component. You will have to do
this whenever you want to display something that is not included among the
standard, pre-defined component classes. When you want to do this, you have to
define your own component class and provide a method in that class for drawing
the component.  I will always use a subclass of <classname>JPanel</classname>
when I need a drawing surface of this kind, as I did for the
<classname>HelloWorldDisplay</classname> class in the example
<sourceref href="HelloWorldGUI2.java"/> in the 
<localref href="GUI1.1">previous section</localref>.
A JPanel, like any JComponent, draws its content in the method</p>

<pre>public void paintComponent(Graphics g)</pre>

<np>To create a drawing surface, you should define a subclass of <code>JPanel</code>
and provide a custom <code>paintComponent()</code> method. Create an object
belonging to this class and use it in your program. When the time comes
for your component to be drawn on the screen, the system will call its
<code>paintComponent()</code> to do the drawing. That is, the code that you put
into the <code>paintComponent()</code> method will be executed whenever the
panel needs to be drawn on the screen; by writing this method, you determine
the picture that will be displayed in the panel.  Note that you are not likely to
call a <code>paintComponent()</code> method any more than you are likely to call
a <code>main()</code> routine.  The <i>system</i> calls the method.  You <i>write</i>
the method to say what will happen when the system calls it.</np>

<p>Note that the <code>paintComponent()</code> method has a parameter of type
<classname>Graphics</classname>. The <classname>Graphics</classname> object will be provided by the system
when it calls your method. You need this object to do the actual drawing. To do
any drawing at all in Java, you need a <newword>graphics context</newword>.
A graphics context is an object belonging to the class
<code>java.awt.Graphics</code>.  Instance methods are provided in this class for
drawing shapes, text, and images. Any given <classname>Graphics</classname> object can draw
to only one location. In this chapter, that location will always be a GUI
component belonging to some subclass of <code>JPanel</code>. The
<classname>Graphics</classname> class is an abstract class, which means that it is impossible
to create a graphics context directly, with a constructor. There are actually
two ways to get a graphics context for drawing on a component: First of all, of
course, when the <code>paintComponent()</code> method of a component is called by
the system, the parameter to that method is a graphics context for drawing on
the component. Second, every component has an instance method called
<code>getGraphics()</code>. This method is a function that returns a graphics
context that can be used for drawing on the component outside its
<code>paintComponent()</code> method. The official line is that you should
<b>not</b> do this, and I will almost always avoid it. But I have
found it convenient to use <code>getGraphics()</code> in a few examples.
(Note that if <code>g</code> is a graphics context created with <code>getGraphics()</code>,
it is good form to call <code>g.dispose()</code> when finished using it.  This
releases any operating system resources that might be held by&nbsp;<code>g</code>.)</p>
   
<p>The <code>paintComponent()</code> method in the <classname>JPanel</classname>
class simply fills the panel with the panel's background color.  When defining a
subclass of <classname>JPanel</classname> for use as a drawing surface, you will
usually want to fill the panel with the background color before drawing
other content onto the panel (although it is not necessary to do this if the drawing
commands in the method cover the background of the component completely).
This is traditionally done with a call to
<code>super.paintComponent(g)</code>, so most <code>paintComponent()</code>
methods that you write will have the form:</p>
   
<pre>public void paintComponent(g) {
   super.paintComponent(g);
   . . . // Draw the content of the component.
}</pre>
   


<break/>

<p>In general, a component should do all drawing operations in its
<code>paintComponent()</code> method. What happens if, in the middle of some other
method, you realize that the content of the component needs to be changed? You
should <b>not</b> call <code>paintComponent()</code> directly to make the
change. Instead, you have
to inform the system that the component needs to be redrawn, and let the system
do its job by calling <code>paintComponent()</code>. You do this by calling the
component's <code>repaint()</code> method. The method</p>

<pre>public void repaint();</pre>

<np>is defined in the <code>Component</code> class, and so can be used with any
component. You should call <code>repaint()</code> to inform the system that the
component needs to be redrawn. It is important to understand that the 
<code>repaint()</code> method returns
immediately, without doing any painting itself. The system will call the
component's <code>paintComponent()</code> method <i>later</i>, as soon as it gets
a chance to do so, after processing other pending events if there are any.
It is even possible that many calls to <code>repaint()</code> will all be handled
by one call to <code>paintComponent()</code>, if the calls to <code>repaint()</code>
occur in a very short timespan.</np>

<p>Note that the system can also call <code>paintComponent()</code> for other
reasons. It is called when the component first appears on the screen. It will
also be called if the size of the component changes, which can happen when
the user resizes the window that contains the component.  This means that
<code>paintComponent()</code> should be capable of redrawing the content
of the component on demand.  As you will see, however, some of our early examples 
will not be able to do this correctly.</p>

<p>This means that, to work properly, the <code>paintComponent()</code> method must
be smart enough to correctly redraw the component at any time. To make this
possible, a program should store data in its instance variables
about the state of the component. These variables should contain all the information
necessary to redraw the component completely. The <code>paintComponent()</code>
method should use the data in these variables to decide what to draw. When the
program wants to change the content of the component, it should not simply draw
the new content. It should change the values of the relevant variables and call
<code>repaint()</code>. When the system calls <code>paintComponent()</code>, that
method will use the new values of the variables and will draw the component
with the desired modifications. This might seem a roundabout way of doing
things. Why not just draw the modifications directly? There are at least two
reasons. First of all, it really does turn out to be easier to get things right
if all drawing is done in one method. Second, even if you could directly
draw the modifications, you would still have to save enough information about
the modifications to enable <code>paintComponent()</code>
to <b>redraw</b> the component correctly on demand.</p>

<p>You will see how all this works in practice as we work through examples in
the rest of this chapter. For now, we will spend the rest of this section
looking at how to get some actual drawing done.</p>

<subsection id="GUI1.3.1" title="Coordinates">

<p>The screen of a computer is a grid of little squares called <newword>pixels</newword>.
The color of each pixel can be set individually, and
drawing on the screen just means setting the colors of individual pixels.</p>

<img height="212" width="420" alt="pixel coordinate system" src="pixel-coordinates.png" 
   tex="pixel-coordinates.eps" texscale="0.75" bordered="true"/>

<p>A graphics context draws in a rectangle made up of pixels. A position in the
rectangle is specified by a pair of integer coordinates, <code>(x,y)</code>. The
upper left corner has coordinates <code>(0,0)</code>. The <code>x</code> coordinate
increases from left to right, and the <code>y</code> coordinate increases from top
to bottom. The illustration shows a 20-pixel by 12-pixel component (with
very large pixels). A small line, rectangle, and oval are shown as they would
be drawn by coloring individual pixels. (Note that, properly speaking, the
coordinates don't belong to the pixels but to the grid lines between them.)</p>

<p>For any component, you can find out the size of the rectangle that it
occupies by calling the instance methods <code>getWidth()</code> and
<code>getHeight()</code>, which return the number of pixels in the
horizontal and vertical directions, respectively.  In general, it's not
a good idea to assume that you know the size of a component, since the
size is often set by a layout manager and can even change if the component
is in a window and that window is resized by the user.   This means that it's good
form to check the size of a component before doing any drawing on that
component. For example, you can use a <code>paintComponent()</code> method that
looks like:</p>

<pre>public void paintComponent(Graphics g) {
   super.paintComponent(g);
   int width =  getWidth();   // Find out the width of this component.
   int height = getHeight();  // Find out its height.
   . . .   // Draw the content of the component.
}</pre>

<p>Of course, your drawing commands will have to take the size into account.
That is, they will have to use <code>(x,y)</code> coordinates that are calculated
based on the actual height and width of the component.  (However, if you are
sure that you know the size, using constants for the width and height can
make the drawing easier.)</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="GUI1.3.2" title="Colors">
   
<p>You will probably want to use some color when you draw.
Java is designed to work with the <newword>RGB color system</newword>.
An RGB color is specified by three numbers that give the level
of red, green, and blue, respectively, in the color. A color in Java is an
object of the class, <code>java.awt.Color</code>. You can construct a new color by
specifying its red, blue, and green components. For example,</p>

<pre>Color myColor = new Color(r,g,b);</pre>

<np>There are two constructors that you can call in this way. In the one that I
almost always use, <code>r</code>, <code>g</code>, and <code>b</code> are integers in the
range 0 to 255. In the other, they are numbers of type <ptype>float</ptype> in the
range 0.0F to 1.0F. (Recall that a literal of type <ptype>float</ptype> is
written with an "F" to distinguish it from a <ptype>double</ptype> number.) Often,
you can avoid constructing new colors altogether, since the <classname>Color</classname>
class defines several named constants representing common colors: <code>Color.WHITE</code>,
<code>Color.BLACK</code>, <code>Color.RED</code>, <code>Color.GREEN</code>,
<code>Color.BLUE</code>, <code>Color.CYAN</code>, <code>Color.MAGENTA</code>,
<code>Color.YELLOW</code>, <code>Color.PINK</code>, <code>Color.ORANGE</code>,
<code>Color.LIGHT_GRAY</code>, <code>Color.GRAY</code>, and <code>Color.DARK_GRAY</code>.
(There are older, alternative names for these constants that use lower case rather than
upper case constants, such as <code>Color.red</code> instead of <code>Color.RED</code>,
but the upper case versions are preferred because they follow the convention that
constant names should be upper case.)</np>

<p>An alternative to RGB is the <newword>HSB color system</newword>.
In the HSB system, a color is specified by three numbers called the
<newword>hue</newword>, the <newword>saturation</newword>,
and the <newword>brightness</newword>. The hue is the basic color,
ranging from red through orange through all the other colors of the rainbow.
The brightness is pretty much what it sounds like. A fully saturated color is a
pure color tone. Decreasing the saturation is like mixing white or gray paint
into the pure color. In Java, the hue, saturation and brightness are always
specified by values of type <ptype>float</ptype> in the range from 0.0F to 1.0F. The
<classname>Color</classname> class has a <code>static</code> member function named
<code>getHSBColor</code> for creating HSB colors. To create the color with HSB
values given by <code>h</code>, <code>s</code>, and <code>b</code>, you can say:</p>

<pre>Color myColor = Color.getHSBColor(h,s,b);</pre>

<np>For example, to make a color with a random hue that is as bright and as
saturated as possible, you could use:</np>

<pre>Color randomColor = Color.getHSBColor( (float)Math.random(), 1.0F, 1.0F );</pre>

<np>The type cast is necessary because the value returned by
<code>Math.random()</code> is of type <ptype>double</ptype>, and
<code>Color.getHSBColor()</code> requires values of type <ptype>float</ptype>. (By the
way, you might ask why RGB colors are created using a constructor while HSB
colors are created using a static member function. The problem is that we would
need two different constructors, both of them with three parameters of type
<ptype>float</ptype>. Unfortunately, this is impossible. You can have two
constructors only if the number of parameters or the parameter types differ.)</np>

<p>The RGB system and the HSB system are just different ways of describing the
same set of colors. It is possible to translate between one system and the
other. The best way to understand the color systems is to experiment with them.
(The sample program <sourceref href="SimpleColorChooser.java"/> lets you do that.
You won't understand the source code at this time, but you can run it to play
with color selection or to find the RGB or HSB values for the color that want.)</p>

<break/>

<p>One of the properties of a <classname>Graphics</classname> object is the current
drawing color, which is used for all drawing of shapes and text. If <code>g</code>
is a graphics context, you can change the current drawing color for <code>g</code>
using the method <code>g.setColor(c)</code>, where <code>c</code> is a <classname>Color</classname>.
For example, if you want to draw in green, you would just say
<code>g.setColor(Color.GREEN)</code> before doing the drawing. The graphics context
continues to use the color until you explicitly change it with another
<code>setColor()</code> command. If you want to know what the current drawing color
is, you can call the function <code>g.getColor()</code>, which returns an object of
type <classname>Color</classname>. This can be useful if you want to change to another
drawing color temporarily and then restore the previous drawing color.</p>

<p>Every component has an associated <newword>foreground color</newword> and 
<newword>background color</newword>. Generally, the
component is filled with the background color before anything else is drawn
(although some components are "transparent," meaning that the background color
is ignored). When a new graphics context is created for a component, the
current drawing color is set to the foreground color. Note that the foreground
color and background color are properties of the component, not of a graphics
context.</p>

<p>The foreground and background colors of a component can be set by calling instance methods
<code>component.setForeground(color)</code> and <code>component.setBackground(color)</code>, which are defined in
the <classname>Component</classname> class and therefore are available for use with any
component.  This can be useful even for standard components, if you want them
to use colors that are different from the defaults.</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="GUI1.3.3" title="Fonts">
   
<p>A <newword>font</newword> represents a particular size and style
of text. The same character will appear different in different fonts. In Java,
a font is characterized by a font name, a style, and a size. The available font
names are system dependent, but you can always use the following four strings
as font names: "Serif", "SansSerif", "Monospaced", and "Dialog".  (A "serif" is a
little decoration on a character, such as a short horizontal line at the bottom
of the letter&nbsp;i. "SansSerif" means "without serifs." "Monospaced" means that
all the characters in the font have the same width. The "Dialog" font is the
one that is typically used in dialog boxes.)</p>

<p>The style of a font is specified using named constants that are defined in
the <classname>Font</classname> class. You can specify the style as one of the four
values:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>Font.PLAIN</code>,</li>
<li><code>Font.ITALIC</code>,</li>
<li><code>Font.BOLD</code>, or</li>
<li><code>Font.BOLD + Font.ITALIC</code>.</li>
</ul>

<p>The size of a font is an integer. Size typically ranges from about 9 to 36,
although larger sizes can also be used. The size of a font is usually about
equal to the height of the largest characters in the font, in pixels, but this
is not an exact rule. The size of the default font is 12.</p>

<p>Java uses the class named <code>java.awt.Font</code> for representing fonts. You
can construct a new font by specifying its font name, style, and size in a
constructor:</p>

<pre>Font plainFont = new Font("Serif", Font.PLAIN, 12);
Font bigBoldFont = new Font("SansSerif", Font.BOLD, 24);</pre>

<p>Every graphics context has a current font, which is used for drawing text.
You can change the current font with the <code>setFont()</code> method. For
example, if <code>g</code> is a graphics context and <code>bigBoldFont</code> is a
font, then the command <code>g.setFont(bigBoldFont)</code> will set the current
font of <code>g</code> to <code>bigBoldFont</code>. The new font will be used
for any text that is drawn <i>after</i> the <code>setFont()</code> command is given.
You can find out the current font
of <code>g</code> by calling the method <code>g.getFont()</code>, which returns an
object of type <classname>Font</classname>.</p>

<p>Every component also has an associated font. It can be set with the instance
method <code>component.setFont(font)</code>, which is defined in the <classname>Component</classname>
class. When a graphics context is created for drawing on a component, the
graphic context's current font is set equal to the font of the component.</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="GUI1.3.4" title="Shapes">

<p>The <classname>Graphics</classname> class includes a large number of instance methods for
drawing various shapes, such as lines, rectangles, and ovals. The shapes are
specified using the <code>(x,y)</code> coordinate system described above. They are
drawn in the current drawing color of the graphics context. The current drawing
color is set to the foreground color of the component when the graphics context
is created, but it can be changed at any time using the <code>setColor()</code>
method.</p>

<p>Some drawing methods were already listed in <localref href="control.8.1"/>.
Here, I describe those methods in more detail and add a few more.
With all these
commands, any drawing that is done outside the boundaries of the component is
ignored. Note that all these methods are in the <classname>Graphics</classname> class, so
they all must be called through an object of type <classname>Graphics</classname>.
It is shown here as <code>g</code>, but of course
the name of the graphics context is up to the programmer.</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>g.drawString(String str, int x, int y)</codedef> &mdash; Draws
the text given by the string <code>str</code>. The string is drawn using
the current color and font of the graphics context. <code>x</code> specifies the
x-coordinate of the left end of the string. <code>y</code> is the y-coordinate of the
baseline of the string. The baseline is a horizontal line on which the
characters rest. Some parts of the characters, such as the tail on a y or g,
extend below the baseline.</li>

<li><codedef>g.drawLine(int x1, int y1, int x2, int y2)</codedef> &mdash; Draws 
a line from the point <code>(x1,y1)</code> to the point
<code>(x2,y2)</code>. The line is drawn as if with a pen that extends one pixel to
the right and one pixel down from the <code>(x,y)</code> point where the pen is
located. For example, if <code>g</code> refers to an object of type
<classname>Graphics</classname>, then the command <code>g.drawLine(x,y,x,y)</code>, which
corresponds to putting the pen down at a point, colors the single pixel with upper left corner
at the point <code>(x,y)</code>.  Remember that coordinates really refer to the lines
between the pixels.</li>

<li><codedef>g.drawRect(int x, int y, int width, int height)</codedef> &mdash; Draws 
the outline of a rectangle. The upper left corner
is at <code>(x,y)</code>, and the width and height of the rectangle are as
specified. If <code>width</code> equals <code>height</code>, then the rectangle is a
square. If the <code>width</code> or the <code>height</code> is negative, then nothing
is drawn. The rectangle is drawn with the same pen that is used for
<code>drawLine()</code>. This means that the actual width of the rectangle as drawn
is <code>width+1</code>, and similarly for the height. There is an extra pixel
along the right edge and the bottom edge. For example, if you want to draw a
rectangle around the edges of the component, you can say "<code>g.drawRect(0, 0,
getWidth()-1, getHeight()-1);</code>".  If you use "<code>g.drawRect(0, 0,
getWidth(), getHeight());</code>", then the right and bottom edges of the
rectangle will be drawn <i>outside</i> the component and will not appear
on the screen.</li>

<li><codedef>g.drawOval(int x, int y, int width, int height)</codedef> &mdash; Draws
the outline of an oval. The oval is one that just
fits inside the rectangle specified by <code>x</code>, <code>y</code>, <code>width</code>,
and <code>height</code>. If <code>width</code> equals <code>height</code>, the oval is a
circle.</li>

<li><codedef>g.drawRoundRect(int x, int y, int width, int height,
int xdiam, int ydiam)</codedef> &mdash; Draws the outline of a rectangle with
rounded corners. The basic rectangle is specified by <code>x</code>, <code>y</code>,
<code>width</code>, and <code>height</code>, but the corners are rounded. The degree of
rounding is given by <code>xdiam</code> and <code>ydiam</code>. The corners are arcs of
an ellipse with horizontal diameter <code>xdiam</code> and vertical diameter
<code>ydiam</code>. A typical value for <code>xdiam</code> and <code>ydiam</code> is 16,
but the value used should really depend on how big the rectangle is.</li>

<li><codedef>g.draw3DRect(int x, int y, int width, int height,
boolean raised)</codedef> &mdash; Draws the outline of a rectangle that is
supposed to have a three-dimensional effect, as if it is raised from the screen
or pushed into the screen. The basic rectangle is specified by <code>x</code>,
<code>y</code>, <code>width</code>, and <code>height</code>. The <code>raised</code> parameter
tells whether the rectangle seems to be raised from the screen or pushed into
it. The 3D effect is achieved by using brighter and darker versions of the
drawing color for different edges of the rectangle. The documentation
recommends setting the drawing color equal to the background color before using
this method. The effect won't work well for some colors.</li>

<li><codedef>g.drawArc(int x, int y, int width, int height, int
startAngle, int arcAngle)</codedef> &mdash; Draws part of the oval that just fits
inside the rectangle specified by <code>x</code>, <code>y</code>, <code>width</code>, and
<code>height</code>. The part drawn is an arc that extends <code>arcAngle</code>
degrees from a starting angle at <code>startAngle</code> degrees. Angles are
measured with 0 degrees at the 3 o'clock position (the positive direction of
the horizontal axis). Positive angles are measured counterclockwise from zero,
and negative angles are measured clockwise. To get an arc of a circle, make
sure that <code>width</code> is equal to <code>height</code>.</li>

<li><codedef>g.fillRect(int x, int y, int width, int
height)</codedef> &mdash; Draws a filled-in rectangle. This fills in the interior
of the rectangle that would be drawn by <code>drawRect(x,y,width,height)</code>.
The extra pixel along the bottom and right edges is not included. The
<code>width</code> and <code>height</code> parameters give the exact width and height
of the rectangle. For example, if you wanted to fill in the entire component,
you could say "<code>g.fillRect(0, 0, getWidth(),
getHeight());</code>"</li>

<li><codedef>g.fillOval(int x, int y, int width, int
height)</codedef> &mdash; Draws a filled-in oval.</li>

<li><codedef>g.fillRoundRect(int x, int y, int width, int height,
int xdiam, int ydiam)</codedef> &mdash; Draws a filled-in rounded rectangle.</li>

<li><codedef>g.fill3DRect(int x, int y, int width, int height,
boolean raised)</codedef> &mdash; Draws a filled-in three-dimensional
rectangle.</li>

<li><codedef>g.fillArc(int x, int y, int width, int height, int
startAngle, int arcAngle)</codedef> &mdash; Draw a filled-in arc. This looks like
a wedge of pie, whose crust is the arc that would be drawn by the
<code>drawArc</code> method.</li>

</ul>
   
</subsection>
   
<subsection  id="GUI1.3.5" title="Graphics2D">

<p>All drawing in Java is done through an object of type <classname>Graphics</classname>. The
<classname>Graphics</classname> class provides basic commands for such things as drawing
shapes and text and  for selecting a drawing color. These commands are adequate in many cases, but
they fall far short of what's needed in a serious computer graphics program.
Java has another class, <classname>Graphics2D</classname>, that provides a larger
set of drawing operations. <classname>Graphics2D</classname> is a sub-class of
<classname>Graphics</classname>, so all the methods from the <classname>Graphics</classname> class are
also available in a <classname>Graphics2D</classname>.</p>

<p>The <code>paintComponent()</code> method of a <code>JComponent</code> gives you a
graphics context of type <classname>Graphics</classname> that you can use for drawing on the
component. In fact, the graphics context actually belongs to the sub-class
<classname>Graphics2D</classname>, and can be type-cast to
gain access to the advanced <classname>Graphics2D</classname> drawing methods:</p>

<pre>public void paintComponent(Graphics g) {
   super.paintComponent(g);
   Graphics2D g2;
   g2 = (Graphics2D)g;
    .
    . // Draw on the component using g2.
    .
}</pre>

<p>I mention <classname>Graphics2D</classname> here for completeness.
I will cover some important aspects of <classname>Graphics2D</classname>
in <localref href="GUI2.2"/>, but a full treatment is more than we will have
time for in this book.  However, there are two simple applications 
that I would like to start using now, without explaining how they work.
If <code>g2</code> is a variable of type <classname>Graphics2D</classname>, 
as in the <code>paintComponent()</code> method above, then the 
intimidating-looking command</p>

<pre>g2.setRenderingHint( RenderingHints.KEY_ANTIALIASING, 
                                RenderingHints.VALUE_ANTIALIAS_ON );</pre>

<np>turns on antialiasing in the graphics context.  Aliasing is a jagged appearance
that can be seen when shapes are drawn using pixels.  Antialiasing tries to reduce
the jaggedness.  It can make diagonal lines and the outlines of ovals look much nicer.
It can also improve the appearance of text.  Another useful command is</np>

<pre>g2.setStroke( new BasicStroke(lineWidth) );</pre>

<np>where <code>lineWidth</code> is an integer or a float.  This command can be used to
draw thicker lines.  Lines drawn after the command will be <code>lineWidth</code> pixels
wide.  This also affects the thickness of the outlined shapes drawn by methods such as
<code>g.drawRect</code> and <code>g.drawOval()</code>.</np>

</subsection>

<subsection id="GUI1.3.6" title="An Example">
   
<p>Let's use some of the material covered in this section to write a subclass
of <classname>JPanel</classname> for use as a drawing surface.  
All the drawing will be done in the
<code>paintComponent()</code> method of the panel class.
The panel will draw multiple copies of a message on a black background.
Each copy of the message is in a random color. Five different fonts are used,
with different sizes and styles. The message can be specified in the constructor;
if the default constructor is used, the message is the string "Java!". The
panel works OK no matter what  its size.</p>

<p>There is one problem with the way this class works. When the panel's
<code>paintComponent()</code> method is called, it chooses random colors, fonts,
and locations for the messages. The information about which colors, fonts, and
locations are used is not stored anywhere. The next time
<code>paintComponent()</code> is called, it will make different random choices and
will draw a different picture.  If you resize a window containing the panel,
the picture will be continually redrawn as the size of the window is changed!
To avoid that, you would store enough information about the picture in instance variables
to enable the <code>paintComponent()</code> method to draw the same picture each
time it is called.</p>

<p>The source code for the panel class is shown below. I use an instance variable called
<code>message</code> to hold the message that the panel will display. There are
five instance variables of type <classname>Font</classname> that represent different sizes
and styles of text. These variables are initialized in the constructor
and are used in the <code>paintComponent()</code> method.</p>

<p>The <code>paintComponent()</code> method for the panel simply draws 25
copies of the message. For each copy, it chooses one of the five fonts at
random, and it uses <code>g.setFont()</code> to select that font for drawing.
It creates a random HSB color and uses <code>g.setColor()</code> to select
that color for drawing. It then chooses random <code>(x,y)</code> coordinates for
the location of the message. The <code>x</code> coordinate gives the horizontal
position of the left end of the string. The formula used for the <code>x</code>
coordinate is "<code>-50&nbsp;+ (int)(Math.random() * (width+40))</code>". This gives a random
integer in the range from <code>-50</code> to <code>width-10</code>. This makes it
possible for the string to extend beyond the left edge or the right edge of the
panel. Similarly, the formula for <code>y</code> allows the string to extend
beyond the top and bottom.</p>


<p>Here is the complete source code for the <classname>RandomStringsPanel</classname>:</p>

<pre>import java.awt.*;
import javax.swing.JPanel;

/**
 * This panel displays 25 copies of a message.  The color and 
 * position of each message is selected at random.  The font
 * of each message is randomly chosen from among five possible
 * fonts.  The messages are displayed on a black background.
 * Note:  The style of drawing used here is poor, because every
 * time the paintComponent() method is called, new random values are
 * used.  This means that a different picture will be drawn each time.  
 */
public class RandomStringsPanel extends JPanel {

    private String message;  // The message to be displayed.  This can be set in
                             // the constructor.  If no value is provided in the
                             // constructor, then the string "Java!" is used.

    private Font font1, font2, font3, font4, font5;  // The five fonts.

    /**
     * Default constructor creates a panel that displays the message "Java!".
     */
    public RandomStringsPanel() {
        this(null);  // Call the other constructor, with parameter null.
    }

    /**
     * Constructor creates a panel to display 25 copies of a specified message.
     * @param messageString The message to be displayed.  If this is null,
     * then the default message "Java!" is displayed.
     */
    public RandomStringsPanel(String messageString) {

        message = messageString;
        if (message == null)
            message = "Java!";

        font1 = new Font("Serif", Font.BOLD, 14);
        font2 = new Font("SansSerif", Font.BOLD + Font.ITALIC, 24);
        font3 = new Font("Monospaced", Font.PLAIN, 30);
        font4 = new Font("Dialog", Font.PLAIN, 36);
        font5 = new Font("Serif", Font.ITALIC, 48);

        setBackground(Color.BLACK);

    }

    /**
     * The paintComponent method is responsible for drawing the content of the panel.
     * It draws 25 copies of the message string, using a random color, font, and
     * position for each string.
     */
    public void paintComponent(Graphics g) {

        super.paintComponent(g);  // Call the paintComponent method from the 
                                  // superclass, JPanel.  This simply fills the 
                                  // entire panel with the background color, black.
        
        Graphics2D g2 = (Graphics2D)g;  // (To make the text smoother.)
        g2.setRenderingHint( RenderingHints.KEY_ANTIALIASING, 
                                RenderingHints.VALUE_ANTIALIAS_ON );

        int width = getWidth();
        int height = getHeight();

        for (int i = 0; i &lt; 25; i++) {

            // Draw one string.  First, set the font to be one of the five
            // available fonts, at random.  

            int fontNum = (int)(5*Math.random()) + 1;
            switch (fontNum) {
            case 1:
                g.setFont(font1);
                break;
            case 2:
                g.setFont(font2);
                break;
            case 3:
                g.setFont(font3);
                break;
            case 4:
                g.setFont(font4);
                break;
            case 5:
                g.setFont(font5);
                break;
            } // end switch

            // Set the color to a bright, saturated color, with random hue.

            float hue = (float)Math.random();
            g.setColor( Color.getHSBColor(hue, 1.0F, 1.0F) );

            // Select the position of the string, at random.

            int x,y;
            x = -50 + (int)(Math.random()*(width+40));
            y = (int)(Math.random()*(height+20));

            // Draw the message.

            g.drawString(message,x,y);

        } // end for

    } // end paintComponent()


}  // end class RandomStringsPanel
</pre>
  
   
</subsection>


<subsection id="GUI1.3.7" title="Where is main()?">

<p>The source code for the <classname>RandomStringsPanel</classname> class can be 
found in the example file <sourceref href="RandomStringsPanel.java"/>.  You can
compile that file, but you won't be able to run the compiled class.  The problem is
that the class doesn't have a <code>main()</code> routine.  Only a class that has a
<code>main()</code> routine can be run as a program.</p>

<p>Another problem is that a <classname>JPanel</classname> is not something that
can stand on its own.  It has to be placed into a container such as another
panel or a window.  In general, to make a complete program, we need a <code>main()</code>
routine that will create a window of type <classname>JFrame</classname>.  It can then
create a panel and place the panel in the window.  Here is a class with a
<code>main()</code> routine that does this:</p>

<pre>
import javax.swing.JFrame;

public class RandomStrings {
    
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        JFrame window = new JFrame("Java!");
        RandomStringsPanel content = new RandomStringsPanel();
        window.setContentPane(content);
        window.setDefaultCloseOperation(JFrame.EXIT_ON_CLOSE);
        window.setLocation(120,70);
        window.setSize(350,250);
        window.setVisible(true);
    }

}</pre>

<np>This class is defined by the file <sourceref href="RandomStrings.java"/>.  You can compile
and run the program, as long as the <classname>RandomStringsPanel</classname> class is also 
available.</np>

<p>The main routine is not logically a part of the panel class.  It is just one way
of using a panel.  However, it's possible to include <code>main()</code> as part of the
panel class, even if it doesn't logically belong there.  This makes it possible to run
the panel class as a program, and it has the advantage of keeping everything in one
file.  For an example, you can look at
<sourceref href="RandomStringsPanelWithMain.java"/>, which is identical to
the original class except for the addition of a <code>main()</code> routine.
Although it might not be great style, I will usually take a similar approach
in future examples.</p>

<p>I am not going to discuss the
details of using <classname>JFrame</classname> here, but you can look ahead
and find them in <localref href="GUI1.8.3"/>.  You won't completely understand
my <code>main()</code> routines until you read that section.</p>

</subsection>   

   
</section>