<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="GUI1.4" title="Mouse Events">
   
<p><start><big>E</big>vents are central</start> to programming for a graphical
user interface. A GUI program doesn't have a <code>main()</code> routine that
outlines what will happen when the program is run, in a step-by-step process
from beginning to end. Instead, the program must be prepared to respond to
various kinds of events that can happen at unpredictable times and in an order
that the program doesn't control. The most basic kinds of events are generated
by the mouse and keyboard. The user can press any key on the keyboard, move the
mouse, or press a button on the mouse. The user can do any of these things at
any time, and the computer has to respond appropriately.</p>

<p>In Java, events are represented by objects. When an event occurs, the system
collects all the information relevant to the event and constructs an object to
contain that information. Different types of events are represented by objects
belonging to different classes. For example, when the user presses one of the
buttons on a mouse, an object belonging to a class called <classname>MouseEvent</classname>
is constructed. The object contains information such as the source of the event (that is, the component on
which the user clicked), the <code>(x,y)</code> coordinates of the point in the
component where the click occurred, the exact time of the click, and which button on the mouse was pressed.
When the user presses a key on the keyboard, a <classname>KeyEvent</classname> is created.
After the event object is constructed, it can be passed as a parameter to a
designated method. By writing that method, the programmer says what
should happen when the event occurs.</p>

<p>As a Java programmer, you get a fairly high-level view of events. There is a
lot of processing that goes on between the time that the user presses a key or
moves the mouse and the time that a subroutine in your program is called to
respond to the event. Fortunately, you don't need to know much about that
processing. But you should understand this much: Even though you didn't
write it, there is a routine running somewhere that executes a loop of the form</p>

<pre>while the program is still running:
    Wait for the next event to occur
    Call a subroutine to handle the event</pre>

<p>This loop is called an <newword>event loop</newword>. Every GUI
program has an event loop. In Java, you don't have to write the loop. It's part
of "the system." If you write a GUI program in some other language, you might
have to provide a main routine that runs the event loop.</p>

<p>In this section, we'll look at handling mouse events in Java, and we'll
cover the framework for handling events in general. The <localref href="GUI1.5">next
section</localref> will cover keyboard-related events and timer events. 
Java also has other types of events, which are produced by GUI components.
These will be introduced in <localref href="GUI1.6"/>.</p>

<subsection id="GUI1.4.1" title="Event Handling">

<p>For an event to have any effect, a program must detect the event and react
to it. In order to detect an event, the program must "listen" for it. Listening
for events is something that is done by an object called an <newword>event listener</newword>. 
An event listener object must contain instance
methods for handling the events for which it listens. For example, if an object
is to serve as a listener for events of type <classname>MouseEvent</classname>, then it must
contain the following method (among several others):</p>

<pre>public void mousePressed(MouseEvent evt) { . . . }</pre>

<np>The body of the method defines how the object responds when it is notified
that a mouse button has been pressed. The parameter, <code>evt</code>, contains
information about the event. This information can be used by the listener
object to determine its response.</np>

<p>The methods that are required in a mouse event listener are specified in an
<code>interface</code> named <classname>MouseListener</classname>. To be used as a listener for
mouse events, an object must implement this <classname>MouseListener</classname> interface.
Java <code>interfaces</code> were covered in <localref href="OOP.7"/>. 
(To review briefly: An <code>interface</code> in Java is just a list of
instance methods. A class can "implement" an interface by doing two things:
First, the class must be declared to implement the interface, as in "<code>class
MouseHandler implements MouseListener</code>" or "<code>class MyPanel extends
JPanel implements MouseListener</code>";  and second, the class must include a
definition for each instance method specified in the interface. An
<code>interface</code> can be used as the type for a variable or formal parameter.
We say that an <i>object</i> implements the <classname>MouseListener</classname> interface if it
belongs to a <i>class</i> that implements the <classname>MouseListener</classname> interface. Note
that it is not enough for the object to include the specified methods. It must
also belong to a class that is specifically declared to implement the
interface.)</p>

<p>Many events in Java are associated with GUI components. For example, when
the user presses a button on the mouse, the associated component is the one
that the user clicked on. Before a listener object can "hear" events associated
with a given component, the listener object must be registered with the
component. If a <classname>MouseListener</classname> object, <code>mListener</code>, needs to
hear mouse events associated with a <classname>Component</classname> object, <code>comp</code>, the
listener must be <newword>registered</newword> with the component by
calling</p>

<pre>comp.addMouseListener(mListener);</pre> 

<np>The <code>addMouseListener()</code> method is an instance method in class
<classname>Component</classname>, and so can be used with any GUI component object. In our
first few examples, we will listen for events on a <classname>JPanel</classname> that is being used as
a drawing surface.</np>

<p>The event classes, such as <classname>MouseEvent</classname>, and the listener interfaces,
such as <classname>MouseListener</classname>, are defined in the package
<code>java.awt.event</code>. This means that if you want to work with events, you
should either include the line "<code>import java.awt.event.*;</code>" at the beginning of
your source code file or import the individual classes and interfaces.</p>

<p>Admittedly, there is a large number of details to tend to when you want to
use events. To summarize, you must</p>

<ol>
<li>Put the import specification "<code>import java.awt.event.*;</code>" (or individual imports)
at the beginning of your source code;</li>
<li>Declare that some class implements the appropriate listener interface, such
as <classname>MouseListener</classname>;</li>
<li>Provide definitions in that class for the methods specified by the
interface;</li>
<li>Register an object that belongs to the listener class 
with the component that will generate the
events by calling a method such as <code>addMouseListener()</code> in the
component.</li>
</ol>

<p>Any object can act as an event listener, provided that it implements the
appropriate interface. A component can listen for the events that it itself
generates. A panel can listen for events from components that are contained
in the panel. A special class can be created just for the purpose of defining
a listening object. Many people consider it to be good form to use anonymous
inner classes to define listening objects (see <localref href="OOP.8.3"/>),
and named nested classes can also be appropriate.
You will see all of these patterns in examples in this textbook.</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="GUI1.4.2" title="MouseEvent and MouseListener">

<p>The <classname>MouseListener</classname> interface specifies these five instance
methods:</p>

<pre>public void mousePressed(MouseEvent evt);
public void mouseReleased(MouseEvent evt);
public void mouseClicked(MouseEvent evt);
public void mouseEntered(MouseEvent evt);
public void mouseExited(MouseEvent evt);</pre>

<p>The <code>mousePressed</code> method is called as soon as the user presses down
on one of the mouse buttons, and <code>mouseReleased</code> is called when the user
releases a button. These are the two methods that are most commonly used, but
any mouse listener object must define all five methods; you can leave the body
of a method empty if you don't want to define a response. The
<code>mouseClicked</code> method is called if the user presses a mouse button and
then releases it, without moving the mouse. (When the user does this,
all three routines&mdash;<code>mousePressed</code>, <code>mouseReleased</code>, and
<code>mouseClicked</code>&mdash;will be called in that order.) In most cases, you
should define <code>mousePressed</code> instead of <code>mouseClicked</code>. The
<code>mouseEntered</code> and <code>mouseExited</code> methods are called when the
mouse cursor enters or leaves the component. For example, if you want the
component to change appearance whenever the user moves the mouse over the
component, you could define these two methods.</p>

<p>As a first example, we will look at a small addition to the <classname>RandomStringsPanel</classname>
example from the <localref href="GUI1.3.6">previous section</localref>. In the new version,
the panel will repaint itself when the user clicks on it.  In order for this to happen,
a mouse listener should listen for mouse events on the panel, and when the listener
detects a <code>mousePressed</code> event, it should respond by calling the
<code>repaint()</code> method of the panel.</p>

   
<p>For the new version of the program, we need an object that implements the
<classname>MouseListener</classname> interface.  One way to create the
object is to define a separate class, such as:</p>

<pre>import java.awt.Component;
import java.awt.event.*;

/**
 * An object of type RepaintOnClick is a MouseListener that
 * will respond to a mousePressed event by calling the repaint()
 * method of the source of the event.  That is, a RepaintOnClick
 * object can be added as a mouse listener to any Component;
 * when the user clicks that component, the component will be
 * repainted.
 */
public class RepaintOnClick implements MouseListener {

   public void mousePressed(MouseEvent evt) {
      Component source = (Component)evt.getSource();
      source.repaint();  // Call repaint() on the Component that was clicked.
   }

   public void mouseClicked(MouseEvent evt) { }
   public void mouseReleased(MouseEvent evt) { }
   public void mouseEntered(MouseEvent evt) { }
   public void mouseExited(MouseEvent evt) { }

}</pre>

<np>This class does three of the four things that we need to do in order
to handle mouse events:  First, it imports <code>java.awt.event.*</code>
for easy access to event-related classes.  Second, it is declared that
the class "<code>implements MouseListener</code>".  And third, it provides
definitions for the five methods that are specified in the
<classname>MouseListener</classname> interface.  (Note that four of the 
methods have empty bodies, since we don't want to do anything in response
to those events.)</np>
   
<p>We must do one more thing to set up the event handling for this example:
We must register an event-handling object as a listener with the component
that will generate the events.  In this case, the mouse events that we are
interested in will be generated by an object of type <classname>RandomStringsPanel</classname>.
If <code>panel</code> is a variable that refers to the panel object,
we can create a mouse listener object and register it with the panel with
the statements:</p>
  
<pre>RepaintOnClick listener = new RepaintOnClick();  // Create MouseListener object.
panel.addMouseListener(listener);  // Register MouseListener with the panel.</pre>
 
<np>This could be done, for example, in the <code>main()</code> routine where
the panel is created.  Once the <code>listener</code> has been registered in this way,
it will be notified of
mouse events on the panel.  When a <code>mousePressed</code> event occurs, the
<code>mousePressed()</code> method in the <code>listener</code> will be called.
The code in this method calls the <code>repaint()</code> method in the
component that is the source of the event, that is, in the panel.  The result
is that the <code>RandomStringsPanel</code> is repainted with its strings
in new random colors, fonts, and positions.</np>
   
<p>Although we have written the <classname>RepaintOnClick</classname> class for use
with our <classname>RandomStringsPanel</classname> example, the event-handling
class contains no reference at all to the <classname>RandomStringsPanel</classname>
class.  How can this be?  The <code>mousePressed()</code> method in
class <classname>RepaintOnClick</classname> looks at the source of the event,
and calls its <code>repaint()</code> method.  If we have registered the
<classname>RepaintOnClick</classname> object as a listener on a
<classname>RandomStringsPanel</classname>, then it is that panel that is
repainted.  But the listener object could be used with any type of component,
and it would work in the same way.</p>
   
<p>Similarly, the <classname>RandomStringsPanel</classname> class contains no
reference to the <classname>RepaintOnClick</classname> class&mdash;in fact,
<classname>RandomStringsPanel</classname> was written before we even knew
anything about mouse events!  The panel will
send mouse events to any object that has registered with it as a mouse listener.
It does not need to know anything about that object except that it is capable
of receiving mouse events.</p>
   
<p>The relationship between an object that generates an event and an object
that responds to that event is rather loose.   The relationship is set up by
registering one object to listen for events from the other object.  This is
something that can potentially be done from outside both objects.  Each object
can be developed independently, with no knowledge of the internal operation
of the other object.  This is the essence of <newword>modular design</newword>:  Build a complex
system out of modules that interact only in straightforward, easy to understand
ways.  Then each module is a separate design problem that can be tackled independently.
Java's event-handling framework is designed to offer strong support for
modular design.
</p>   
   
<p>To make this clearer, let's look at a new version of <sourceref href="RandomStrings.java"/>,
the program from <localref href="GUI1.3.7"/> that uses <classname>RandomStringsPanel</classname>.
The new version is <sourceref href="ClickableRandomStrings.java"/>.  For convenience, I have added
<classname>RepaintOnClick</classname> as a static nested class, although it would work just as well
as a separate class:</p>
   
<pre>import java.awt.Component;
import java.awt.event.MouseEvent;
import java.awt.event.MouseListener;
import javax.swing.JFrame;

/**
 * Displays a window that shows 25 copies of the string "Java!" in
 * random colors, fonts, and positions.  The content of the window
 * is an object of type RandomStringsPanel.  When the user clicks
 * the window, the content of the window is repainted, with the 
 * strings in newly selected random colors, fonts, and positions.
 */
public class ClickableRandomStrings {
    
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        JFrame window = new JFrame("Click Me to Redraw!");
        RandomStringsPanel content = new RandomStringsPanel();
        <newcode>content.addMouseListener( new RepaintOnClick() );</newcode>        
        window.setContentPane(content);
        window.setDefaultCloseOperation(JFrame.EXIT_ON_CLOSE);
        window.setLocation(120,70);
        window.setSize(350,250);
        window.setVisible(true);
    }
    
    private static class RepaintOnClick implements MouseListener {

        public void mousePressed(MouseEvent evt) {
            Component source = (Component)evt.getSource();
            source.repaint();
        }

        public void mouseClicked(MouseEvent evt) { }
        public void mouseReleased(MouseEvent evt) { }
        public void mouseEntered(MouseEvent evt) { }
        public void mouseExited(MouseEvent evt) { }

    }

} end class ClickableRandomStrings</pre>
   
</subsection>
   
<subsection id="GUI1.4.3" title="MouseEvent Data">
 
<p>Often, when a mouse event occurs, you want to know the location of the mouse
cursor. This information is available from the <classname>MouseEvent</classname>
parameter to the event-handling method, which
contains instance methods that return information about the event. 
If <code>evt</code> is the parameter, then you can find out
the coordinates of the mouse cursor by calling  <code>evt.getX()</code> and
<code>evt.getY()</code>. These methods return integers which give the <code>x</code>
and <code>y</code> coordinates where the mouse cursor was positioned at the time
when the event occurred. The
coordinates are expressed in the <localref href="GUI1.3.1">coordinate system</localref> 
of the component that
generated the event, where the top left corner of the component is (0,0).</p>

<p>The user can hold down certain <newword>modifier keys</newword>
while using the mouse. The possible modifier keys include: the Shift key, the
Control key, the Alt key (called the Option key on the Mac), and the Meta
key (called the Command or Apple key on the Mac). 
You might want to respond to a mouse event differently when the user
is holding down a modifier key. The boolean-valued instance methods
<code>evt.isShiftDown()</code>, <code>evt.isControlDown()</code>,
<code>evt.isAltDown()</code>, and <code>evt.isMetaDown()</code> can be called to test
whether the modifier keys are pressed.</p>

<p>You might also want to have different responses depending on whether the
user presses the left mouse button, the middle mouse button, or the right mouse
button.   For events triggered by a mouse button, 
you can determine which button was pressed or released by calling
<code>evt.getButton()</code>, which returns one of the integer constants
<code>MouseEvent.BUTTON1</code>, <code>MouseEvent.BUTTON2</code>, or <code>MouseEvent.BUTTON3</code>
for the left, middle, and right buttons.
For events such as mouseEntered and mouseExited that are not triggered by buttons,
<code>evt.getButton()</code> returns <code>MouseEvent.NOBUTTON</code>.</p>

<p>Now, not every mouse has a middle button and a right button, and Java deals with
that fact in a somewhat peculiar way.  If the user clicks with the right mouse
button, then <code>evt.isMetaDown()</code> will return true, even if the user
was not holding down the Meta key.  Similarly, if the user clicks with the
middle mouse button, then <code>evt.isAltDown()</code> will return true, even
if the user is not holding down the Alt/Option key.  By using these functions,
you can design an interface that will work even on computers that lack a middle
or right mouse button.  Note that there is a subtle difference between these functions
and <code>evt.getButton()</code>:  <code>evt.getButton()</code> really only applies
to mousePressed, mouseReleased, and mouseClicked events, while <code>evt.isMetaDown()</code>
and <code>evt.isAltDown()</code> are useful in any mouse event.  I will often 
use them instead of <code>evt.getButton()</code>.</p>

<p>As an example, consider a <classname>JPanel</classname> that does the
following:  Clicking on the panel with the
left mouse button will place a red rectangle on the panel at the point
where the mouse was clicked.  Clicking with the right
mouse button will place a
blue oval on the panel. Holding down the Shift key while clicking will clear the
panel by removing all the shapes that have been placed.  You can try the sample
program <sourceref href="SimpleStamper.java"/>.  Here is what the panel looks like
after some shapes have been added:</p>

<img src="simple-stamper.png" width="398" height="275" alt="a SillyStamper panel"
      tex="simple-stamper.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<p>There are several ways to write this example. There could be a separate class to handle
mouse events, as in the previous example.  However, in this case, I decided to let
the panel itself respond to mouse events.  Any object can be a mouse listener, as long
as it implements the <classname>MouseListener</classname> interface.  In this case,
the panel class implements the <classname>MouseListener</classname> interface, 
so the object that represents the main panel of the program can be the mouse
listener for the program.  The constructor for the panel class contains the statement</p>

<pre>addMouseListener(this);</pre>

<np>which is equivalent to saying <code>this.addMouseListener(this)</code>.  Now, the
ordinary way to register a mouse listener is to say <code>X.addMouseListener(Y)</code>
where <code>Y</code> is the listener and <code>X</code> is the component that will
generate the mouse events.  In the statement <code>addMouseListener(this)</code>,
both roles are played by <code>this</code>; that is, "this object" (the panel) is
generating mouse events and is also listening for those events.  Although this might
seem a little strange, you should get used to seeing things like this.  In a large
program, however, it's usually a better idea to write a separate class to do
the listening in order to have a more organized division of responsibilities.
</np>

<p>The source code for the panel class is shown below.  I have included a <code>main()</code>
routine to allow the class to be run as a program, as discussed in <localref href="GUI1.3.7"/>.
You should check how the instance
methods in the <classname>MouseEvent</classname> object are used. You can also check for the
Four Steps of Event Handling ("<code>import java.awt.event.*</code>",
"<code>implements MouseListener</code>",  definitions for the
event-handling methods, and "<code>addMouseListener</code>"):</p>

<pre>import java.awt.*;
import java.awt.event.*;
import javax.swing.*;

/**
 * A simple demonstration of MouseEvents.  Shapes are drawn
 * on a black background when the user clicks the panel.  If
 * the user Shift-clicks, the panel is cleared.  If the user
 * right-clicks the panel, a blue oval is drawn.  Otherwise,
 * when the user clicks, a red rectangle is drawn.  The contents of
 * the panel are not persistent.  For example, they might disappear 
 * if the panel is resized.
 * This class has a main() routine to allow it to be run as an application.
 */
public class SimpleStamper extends JPanel implements MouseListener {

    public static void main(String[] args) {
        JFrame window = new JFrame("Simple Stamper");
        SimpleStamper content = new SimpleStamper();
        window.setContentPane(content);
        window.setDefaultCloseOperation(JFrame.EXIT_ON_CLOSE);
        window.setLocation(120,70);
        window.setSize(450,350);
        window.setVisible(true);
    }

    // ----------------------------------------------------------------------
   
   /**
    * This constructor simply sets the background color of the panel to be black
    * and sets the panel to listen for mouse events on itself.
    */
   public SimpleStamper() {
      setBackground(Color.BLACK);
      addMouseListener(this);
   }
   

   /**
    *  Since this panel has been set to listen for mouse events on itself, 
    *  this method will be called when the user clicks the mouse on the panel.
    *  This method is part of the MouseListener interface.
    */
   public void mousePressed(MouseEvent evt) {
      
      if ( evt.isShiftDown() ) {
            // The user was holding down the Shift key.  Just repaint the panel.
            // Since this class does not define a paintComponent() method, the 
            // method from the superclass, JPanel, is called.  That method simply
            // fills the panel with its background color, which is black.  The 
            // effect is to clear the panel.
         repaint();
         return;
      }
      
      int x = evt.getX();  // x-coordinate where user clicked.
      int y = evt.getY();  // y-coordinate where user clicked.
      
      Graphics g = getGraphics(); // Graphics context for drawing directly.
                                  // <newcode>NOTE: This is considered to be bad style!</newcode>
      
      if ( evt.isMetaDown() ) {
             // User right-clicked at the point (x,y). Draw a blue oval centered 
             // at the point (x,y). (A black outline around the oval will make it 
             // more distinct when shapes overlap.)
         g.setColor(Color.BLUE);  // Blue interior.
         g.fillOval( x - 30, y - 15, 60, 30 );
         g.setColor(Color.BLACK); // Black outline.
         g.drawOval( x - 30, y - 15, 60, 30 );
      }
      else {
            // User left-clicked (or middle-clicked) at (x,y). 
            // Draw a red rectangle centered at (x,y).
         g.setColor(Color.RED);   // Red interior.
         g.fillRect( x - 30, y - 15, 60, 30 );
         g.setColor(Color.BLACK); // Black outline.
         g.drawRect( x - 30, y - 15, 60, 30 );
      }
      
      g.dispose();  // We are finished with the graphics context, so dispose of it.
      
   } // end mousePressed();
   
   
   // The next four empty routines are required by the MouseListener interface.
   // They don't do anything in this class, so their definitions are empty.
   
   public void mouseEntered(MouseEvent evt) { }
   public void mouseExited(MouseEvent evt) { }
   public void mouseClicked(MouseEvent evt) { }
   public void mouseReleased(MouseEvent evt) { }
   
} // end class SimpleStamper</pre>
   
   
<np>Note, by the way, that this class violates the rule that all
drawing should be done in a <code>paintComponent()</code> method. The rectangles
and ovals are drawn directly in the <code>mousePressed()</code> routine. To make
this possible, I need to obtain a graphics context by saying 
"<code>g&nbsp;=&nbsp;getGraphics()</code>". After using <code>g</code> for drawing, I call
<code>g.dispose()</code> to inform the operating system that I will no longer be
using <code>g</code> for drawing.  I do not advise doing this
type of direct drawing if it can be avoided, but you can see that it does work
in this case.</np>


</subsection>

<subsection id="GUI1.4.4" title="MouseMotionListeners and Dragging">

<p>Whenever the mouse is moved, it generates events. The operating system of
the computer detects these events and uses them to move the mouse cursor on the
screen. It is also possible for a program to listen for these "mouse motion"
events and respond to them. The most common reason to do so is to implement
<newword>dragging</newword>. Dragging occurs when the user moves the
mouse while holding down a mouse button.</p>

<p>The methods for responding to mouse motion events are defined in an
interface named <classname>MouseMotionListener</classname>. This interface specifies two
event-handling methods:</p>

<pre>public void mouseDragged(MouseEvent evt);
public void mouseMoved(MouseEvent evt);</pre>

<p>The <code>mouseDragged</code> method is called if the mouse is moved while a
button on the mouse is pressed. If the mouse is moved while no mouse button is
down, then <code>mouseMoved</code> is called instead. The parameter, <code>evt</code>,
is an object of type <classname>MouseEvent</classname>, which contains the <code>x</code> and
<code>y</code> coordinates of the mouse's location, as usual. As long as the user continues
to move the mouse, one of these methods will be called over and over. (So many
events are generated that it would be inefficient for a program to hear them
all, if it doesn't want to do anything in response. This is why the mouse
motion event-handlers are defined in a separate interface from the other mouse
events: You can listen for the mouse events defined in <classname>MouseListener</classname>
without automatically hearing all mouse motion events as well.)</p>

<p>If you want your program to respond to mouse motion events, you must create
an object that implements the <classname>MouseMotionListener</classname> interface, and you
must register that object to listen for events. The registration is done by
calling a component's <code>addMouseMotionListener()</code> method. The object will
then listen for <code>mouseDragged</code> and <code>mouseMoved</code> events associated
with that component. In most cases, the listener object will also implement the
<classname>MouseListener</classname> interface so that it can respond to the other mouse
events as well.</p>

<p>(To get a better idea of how mouse events work, you should try the sample program
<sourceref href="SimpleTrackMouse.java"/>.  This program
responds to any of the seven different kinds of mouse events
by displaying the coordinates of the mouse, the type of event, and a list of
the modifier keys that are down (Shift, Control, Meta, and Alt). 
You can experiment with the program to see what happens as you do various
things with the mouse.  I also encourage you to read the source code. 
You should now be familiar with all the techniques that it uses.)</p>

   
<p>It is interesting to look at what a program needs to do in order to respond
to dragging operations. In general, the response involves three methods:
<code>mousePressed()</code>, <code>mouseDragged()</code>, and <code>mouseReleased()</code>.
The dragging gesture starts when the user presses a mouse button, it continues
while the mouse is dragged, and it ends when the user releases the button. This
means that the programming for the response to one dragging gesture must be
spread out over the three methods! Furthermore, the <code>mouseDragged()</code>
method can be called many times as the mouse moves. To keep track of what is
going on between one method call and the next, you need to set up some instance
variables. In many applications, for example, in order to process a
<code>mouseDragged</code> event, you need to remember the previous coordinates of
the mouse. You can store this information in two instance variables
<code>prevX</code> and <code>prevY</code> of type <ptype>int</ptype>.  It can also
be useful to save the starting coordinates, where the original <code>mousePressed</code> event
occurred, in instance variables.   And I suggest having a
<ptype>boolean</ptype> variable, <code>dragging</code>, which is set to <code>true</code>
while a dragging gesture is being processed. This is necessary because in many applications, not
every <code>mousePressed</code> event starts a dragging operation to which you want to respond. The
<code>mouseDragged</code> and <code>mouseReleased</code> methods can use the value of
<code>dragging</code> to check whether a drag operation is actually in progress.
You might need other instance variables as well, but in general outline, a class
that handles mouse dragging looks like this:</p>

<pre>import java.awt.event.*;
   
public class MouseDragHandler implements MouseListener, MouseMotionListener {

   private int startX, startY; // Point where the original mousePress occurred. 
   private int prevX, prevY;   // Most recently processed mouse coords.
   private boolean dragging;   // Set to true when dragging is in process.
   . . . // other instance variables for use in dragging
   
   public void mousePressed(MouseEvent evt) {
      if ( <i>we-want-to-start-dragging</i> ) {
          dragging = true;
          startX = evt.getX();  // Remember starting position.
          startY = evt.getY();
          prevX = startX;       // Remember most recent coords.
          prevY = startY;
             . 
             . // Other processing.
             .
      }
   }
   
   public void mouseDragged(MouseEvent evt) {
       if ( dragging == false )  // First, check if we are 
           return;               //   processing a dragging gesture.
       int x = evt.getX(); // Current position of Mouse.
       int y = evt.getY();
         .  
         .  // Process a mouse movement from (prevX, prevY) to (x,y).
         .
       prevX = x;  // Remember the current position for the next call.
       prevY = y;
   }
   
   public void mouseReleased(MouseEvent evt) {
       if ( dragging == false )  // First, check if we are 
           return;               //   processing a dragging gesture.
       dragging = false;  // We are done dragging.
        .
        .  // Other processing and clean-up.
        .
   }

}</pre>


<p>As an example, let's look at a typical use of dragging: allowing the user to
sketch a curve by dragging the mouse. This example also shows many other
features of graphics and mouse processing. In the program, you can
draw a curve by dragging the mouse on a large white drawing area, and you can
select a color for
drawing by clicking on one of several colored rectangles to the right of the
drawing area. The complete source code can be found in <sourceref href="SimplePaint.java"/>.
Here is a picture of the program after some drawing has been done:</p>

<img src="simple-paint.png" width="442" height="304" alt="screenshot from SimplePaing showing a simple drawing"
      tex="simple-paint.eps" texscale="0.5"/>

<p>I will discuss a few aspects of the source code
here, but I encourage you to read it carefully in its entirety. There are
lots of informative comments in the source code.  </p>

<p>The panel for this example is designed to work for any reasonable
size, that is, unless the panel is too small. This means that
coordinates are computed in terms of the actual width and height of the panel.
(The width and height are obtained by calling <code>getWidth()</code> and
<code>getHeight()</code>.) This makes things quite a bit harder than they
would be if we assumed some particular fixed size for the panel. Let's look at
some of these computations in detail. For example, the large white drawing
area extends from <code>y&nbsp;=&nbsp;3</code> to <code>y&nbsp;=&nbsp;height&nbsp;-&nbsp;3</code> vertically and
from <code>x&nbsp;=&nbsp;3</code> to <code>x&nbsp;=&nbsp;width&nbsp;-&nbsp;56</code> horizontally.  These numbers
are needed in order to interpret the meaning of a mouse click.  They take into
account a gray border around the panel and the color palette along the right
edge of the panel. The gray border is 3 pixels wide.  The colored rectangles are 50
pixels wide.  Together with the 3-pixel border around the panel and 
a 3-pixel divider between the drawing area and the colored
rectangles, this adds up to put the right edge of the drawing area 56
pixels from the right edge of the panel.</p>

<p>A white square labeled "<code>CLEAR</code>" occupies a 50-by-50 pixel region
beneath the colored rectangles on the right edge of the panel.
Allowing for this square, we can figure out how
much vertical space is available for the seven colored rectangles, and then
divide that space by 7 to get the vertical space available for each rectangle.
This quantity is represented by a variable, <code>colorSpace</code>. Out of this
space, 3 pixels are used as spacing between the rectangles, so the height of
each rectangle is <code>colorSpace&nbsp;-&nbsp;3</code>. The top of the <code>N</code>-th
rectangle is located <code>(N*colorSpace&nbsp;+&nbsp;3)</code> pixels down from the top of
the panel, assuming that we count the rectangles starting with zero. This is because there are
<code>N</code> rectangles above the <code>N</code>-th rectangle, each of which uses
<code>colorSpace</code> pixels. The extra 3 is for the border at the top of the
panel. After all that, we can write down the command for drawing the
<code>N</code>-th rectangle:</p>

<pre>g.fillRect(width - 53, N*colorSpace + 3, 50, colorSpace - 3);</pre>
   
<np>That was not easy! But it shows the kind of careful thinking and precision
graphics that are sometimes necessary to get good results.</np>

<p>The mouse in this program is used to do three different things: Select a
color, clear the drawing, and draw a curve. Only the third of these involves
dragging, so not every mouse click will start a dragging operation. The
<code>mousePressed()</code> method has to look at the <code>(x,y)</code> coordinates
where the mouse was clicked and decide how to respond. If the user clicked on
the <code>CLEAR</code> rectangle, the drawing area is cleared by calling
<code>repaint()</code>. If the user clicked somewhere in the strip of colored
rectangles, the corresponding color is selected for drawing. This involves computing which color
the user clicked on, which is done by dividing the <code>y</code> coordinate by
<code>colorSpace</code>. Finally, if the user clicked on the drawing area, a drag
operation is initiated. In this case, a boolean variable, <code>dragging</code>, is set to
<code>true</code> so that the <code>mouseDragged</code> and <code>mouseReleased</code>
methods will know that a curve is being drawn. The code for this follows the
general form given above. The actual drawing of the curve is done in the
<code>mouseDragged()</code> method, which draws a line from the previous location of
the mouse to its current location. Some effort is required to make sure that
the line does not extend beyond the white drawing area of the panel. This is
not automatic, since as far as the computer is concerned, the border and the
color bar are part of the drawing surface. If the user drags the mouse outside
the drawing area while drawing a line, the <code>mouseDragged()</code> routine
changes the <code>x</code> and <code>y</code> coordinates to make them lie within the
drawing area.</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="GUI1.4.5" title="Anonymous Event Handlers and Adapter Classes" shorttitle="Anonymous Event Handlers">

<p>As I mentioned above, it is a fairly common practice to use anonymous inner
classes to define listener objects. As discussed in <localref href="OOP.8.3"/>,
a special form of the <code>new</code> operator is
used to create an object that belongs to an anonymous class. For example, a
mouse listener object can be created with an expression of the form:</p>

<pre>new MouseListener() {
   public void mousePressed(MouseEvent evt) { . . . }
   public void mouseReleased(MouseEvent evt) { . . . }
   public void mouseClicked(MouseEvent evt) { . . . }
   public void mouseEntered(MouseEvent evt) { . . . }
   public void mouseExited(MouseEvent evt) { . . . }
}</pre>

<np>This is all just one long expression that both defines an unnamed class and
creates an object that belongs to that class. To use the object as a mouse
listener, it can be passed as the parameter to some component's
<code>addMouseListener()</code> method in a command of the form:</np>

<pre><newcode>component.addMouseListener(</newcode> new MouseListener() {
      public void mousePressed(MouseEvent evt) { . . . }
      public void mouseReleased(MouseEvent evt) { . . . }
      public void mouseClicked(MouseEvent evt) { . . . }
      public void mouseEntered(MouseEvent evt) { . . . }
      public void mouseExited(MouseEvent evt) { . . . }
   } <newcode>);</newcode></pre>

<p>Now, in a typical application, most of the method definitions in this class
will be empty. A class that implements an <code>interface</code> must provide
definitions for all the methods in that interface, even if the definitions are
empty. To avoid the tedium of writing empty method definitions in cases like
this, Java provides <newword>adapter classes</newword>. An adapter
class implements a listener interface by providing empty definitions for all
the methods in the interface. An adapter class is useful only as a basis for
making subclasses. In the subclass, you can define just those methods that you
actually want to use. For the remaining methods, the empty definitions that are
provided by the adapter class will be used. The adapter class <classname>MouseAdapter</classname>
implements both the <classname>MouseListener</classname> interface and the
<classname>MouseMotionListener</classname> interface, so it can be used as a basis for
creating a listener for any mouse event.  As an example,
if you want a mouse listener that only responds to mouse-pressed events, you
can use a command of the form:</p>

<pre>component.addMouseListener( new <newcode>MouseAdapter()</newcode> {
      public void mousePressed(MouseEvent evt) { . . . }
   } );</pre>

<np>To see how this works in a real example, let's write another version of the
<classname>ClickableRandomStrings</classname> program from <localref href="GUI1.4.2"/>.
This version uses an anonymous class based on
<classname>MouseAdapter</classname> to handle mouse events:</np>

<pre>import java.awt.Component;
import java.awt.event.MouseAdapter;
import java.awt.event.MouseEvent;
import java.awt.event.MouseListener;
import javax.swing.JFrame;

public class ClickableRandomStrings2 {
   
   public static void main(String[] args) {
      JFrame window = new JFrame("Random Strings");
      RandomStringsPanel content = new RandomStringsPanel();

      <newcode>content.addMouseListener( new MouseAdapter() { 
            // Register a mouse listener that is defined by an anonymous subclass
            // of MouseAdapter.  This replaces the RepaintOnClick class that was
            // used in the original version.
         public void mousePressed(MouseEvent evt) {
            Component source = (Component)evt.getSource();
            source.repaint();
         }
      } );</newcode>

      window.setContentPane(content);
      window.setDefaultCloseOperation(JFrame.EXIT_ON_CLOSE);
      window.setLocation(100,75);
      window.setSize(300,240);
      window.setVisible(true);
   }

}</pre>
   
<p>Anonymous inner classes can be used for other purposes besides event handling.
For example, suppose that you want to define a subclass of <classname>JPanel</classname>
to represent a drawing surface.  The subclass will only be used once.  It will redefine
the <code>paintComponent()</code> method, but will make no other changes to
<classname>JPanel</classname>.  It might make sense to define the subclass as
an anonymous inner class.  You will see this pattern used in some future examples.</p>

</subsection>
   
</section>