<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE intro SYSTEM "../javanotes7.dtd" >

<intro>
<p><start><big>C</big>omputer programs are</start> only useful if they interact
with the rest of the world in some way. This interaction is referred to as
<newword>input/output</newword>, or <newword>I/O</newword>. 
Up until now, this book has concentrated on just one 
type of interaction: interaction with the user, through either a
graphical user interface or a command-line interface. But the user is only one
possible source of information and only one possible destination for
information. We have already encountered one other type of input/output, since
<classname>TextIO</classname> can read data from files and write data
to files.  However, Java has an input/output framework that provides much
more power and flexibility than does <classname>TextIO</classname>,
and that covers other kinds of I/O in addition to files.  Most importantly,
it supports communication over network connections.
In Java, the most common type of input/output involving files and networks is based on
<newword>streams</newword>, which are objects that support I/O
commands that are similar to those that you have already used.
In fact, standard output (<code>System.out</code>) and
standard input (<code>System.in</code>) are examples of streams.</p>

<p>Working with files and networks requires familiarity with exceptions, which
were covered in <localref href="robustness.3"/>. Many of
the subroutines that are used can throw checked exceptions, which require mandatory
exception handling. This generally means calling the subroutine in a
<code>try..catch</code> statement that can deal with the exception if one
occurs.  Effective network communication also requires the use of
threads, which will be covered in <localref href="threads"/>.
We will look at the basic networking API in this chapter, but
we will return to the topic of threads and networking in <localref href="threads.4"/>.
</p>
</intro>