<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE quiz SYSTEM "../javanotes7.dtd" >

<quiz>
   
<question>
<ques><p>In Java, input/output is
done using streams. Streams are an <i>abstraction.</i> Explain what this means
and why it is important.</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>A stream represents a source
from which data can be read or a destination to which data can be written. A
stream is an abstraction because it represents the abstract idea of a source or
destination of data, as opposed to specific, concrete sources and destinations
such as a particular file or network connection. The stream abstraction is
important because it allows programmers to do input/output using the same
methods for a wide variety of data sources and destinations. It hides the
details of working with files, networks, and the screen and keyboard.</p>
</ans>
</question>
   
   
<question>
<ques><p>Java has two types of
streams: character streams and byte streams. Why? What is the difference
between the two types of streams?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>Character streams are for
working with data in human-readable format, that is, data expressed as
sequences of characters. Byte streams are for data expressed in the
machine-readable format that is used internally in the computer to represent
the data while a program is running. It is very efficient for a computer to
read and write data in machine format, since no translation of the data is
necessary. However, if a person must deal directly with the data, then
character streams should be used so that the data is presented in
human-readable form.</p>
</ans>
</question>
   
   
<question>
<ques><p>What is a <i>file?</i> Why are files necessary?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>A file is a collection of data
that has been given a name and stored on some permanent storage device such as
a hard disk or USB memory stick. Files are necessary because data stored in the
computer's RAM is lost whenever the computer is turned off. Data that is to be
saved permanently must be stored in a file. (Furthermore, RAM is very expensive
compared to space on a disk drive, so a computer's hard disk can typically
store much more data than would fit in the computer's RAM, even if the computer
were left turned on all the time.)</p>
</ans>
</question>
   
   
<question>
<ques><p>What is the point of the
following statement?</p>
<pre>out = new PrintWriter( new FileWriter("data.dat") );</pre>
<np>Why would you need a statement that involves two different stream classes,
<classname>PrintWriter</classname> and <classname>FileWriter</classname>?</np>
</ques>
<ans><p> The <classname>PrintWriter</classname> class
is being used as a "wrapper" for the <classname>FileWriter</classname> class. A
<classname>FileWriter</classname> is a stream object that knows how to send individual
characters to a file. By wrapping this in a <classname>PrintWriter</classname>, you get the
ability to write other data types such as <ptype>ints</ptype>, <ptype>doubles</ptype>, and
<classname>Strings</classname> to the file using the <classname>PrintWriter's</classname> <code>print()</code>
and <code>println()</code> methods. Wrapping the <code>FileWriter</code> in a
<classname>PrintWriter</classname> adds capabilities to the file output stream but still
sends the data to the same destination.</p>
</ans>
</question>
   
   
<question>
<ques><p>The package <code>java.io</code>
includes a class named <classname>URL</classname>. What does an object of type <classname>URL</classname>
represent, and how is it used?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>A url is an address for a web
page (or other information) on the Internet. For example,
"http://math.hws.edu/javanotes/index.html" is a url that refers to the main
page of the current edition of this on-line textbook. A <classname>URL</classname> object
represents such an address. Once you have a <classname>URL</classname> object, you can call
its <code>openConnection()</code> method to access the information at the web
address that it represents.</p>
</ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>What is the purpose of the <classname>JFileChooser</classname>
class?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>An object of type <classname>JFileChooser</classname> represents a
dialog box that can be used in a GUI program to let the user select a file
that is to be used for input or for output.</p>
</ans>
</question>
   
   
<question>
<ques><p>Explain what is meant by the
<i>client / server</i> model of network communication.</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>In the client/server model, a
server program runs on a computer somewhere on the Internet and "listens" for
connection requests from client programs. The server makes some service
available. A client program connects to the server to access that service. For
example, a Web server has a collection of Web pages. A Web browser acts as a
client for the Web server. It makes a connection to the server and sends a
request for one of its pages. The server responds by transmitting a copy of the
requested page back to the client.</p>
</ans>
</question>
   
   
<question>
<ques><p>What is a <i>socket</i>?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>A socket represents one endpoint
of a network connection. A program uses a socket to communicate with another
program over the network. Data written by a program to the socket at one end of
the connection is transmitted to the socket on the other end of the connection,
where it can be read by the program at that end.</p>
</ans>
</question>
   
   
<question>
<ques><p>What is a <classname>ServerSocket</classname> and how is it used?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>A <classname>ServerSocket</classname> is used
by a server program to listen for connection requests from client programs. If
<code>listener</code> refers to an object that belongs to Java's
<classname>ServerSocket</classname> class, then calling the function
<code>listener.accept()</code> will wait for a connection request and will return a
<classname>Socket</classname> object that can be used to communicate with the client that
made the request.</p>
</ans>
</question>
   
   
   
<question>
<ques><p>What is meant by an <i>element</i> in an XML document?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>An element consists of a tag (possibly containing attributes), a matching end-tag, 
and everything in between.  There are also empty elements where an empty element consists
of a single self-closing tag.  An element can contain textual content and nested
elements.  For example, in the XML fragment</p>
<pre>
&lt;testresult score="82"&gt;&lt;name&gt;Joe Smith&lt;/name&gt;&lt;subject&gt;Math&lt;/subject&gt;&lt;/testresult&gt;
</pre>
<np>the entire fragment is an element, while <code>&lt;name&gt;Joe Smith&lt;/name&gt;</code>
and <code>&lt;subject&gt;Math&lt;/subject&gt;</code> are nested elements inside
the <code>&lt;testresult&gt;</code> element.  "Joe Smith" and "Math" are examples of
textual content, and <code>score</code> is an attribute with value <code>82</code>.</np>
</ans>
</question>
   
   
<question>
<ques><p>What is it about XML that makes it suitable for representing
almost any type of data?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>XML is a syntax for building data representation languages.  In XML,
the names of tags and the structure of a document can be chosen to be whatever
is most appropriate for the type of data that is being represented.  The
tag names can be chosen to give <i>meaningful</i> descriptions of the data.
This contrasts with HTML documents, which can include only a certain fixed
set of tags.  (XML also has the advantage of being a widely accepted standard
that is supported in just about every programming language.)</p>
</ans>
</question>
   
   
<question>
<ques><p>Write a complete program
that will display the first ten lines from a text file. The lines should be
written to standard output, <code>System.out</code>. The file name is given as the
command-line argument <code>args[0]</code>. You can assume that the file contains
at least ten lines. Don't bother to make the program robust.  Do not use
<classname>TextIO</classname> to process the file; read from the file using
methods covered in this chapter.</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>I will give three different solutions.  The first uses the non-standard
<classname>TextReader</classname> class from <localref href="IO.1.4"/> to read the
lines from the file. The other two solutions use the standard classes
<classname>BufferedReader</classname> and <classname>Scanner</classname>.
All of these classes make it easy to read a line of text from an input stream.</p>

<p>For each program, I do everything in one big <code>try</code> statement. If
anything goes wrong, an error message is printed in the <code>catch</code> clause
of the <code>try</code> statement. For example, if the program is run with no
command-line argument, an <classname>IndexOutOfBoundsException</classname> will be generated
when the program refers to <code>args[0]</code>. If a file is specified, but it
doesn't exist, then a <classname>FileNotFoundException</classname> will occur. (The
exercise says to assume that the file has at least ten lines, but if there are
fewer than ten lines in the file, <classname>TextReader</classname> and 
<classname>Scanner</classname> will throw an exception, while <classname>BufferedReader</classname>
will just print a <code>null</code> for each missing line.)</p>


<pre>import java.io.*;
// (TextReader.class must be made available to this program.)
public class TenLinesWithTextReader {

   public static void main(String[] args) {
      try {
         TextReader in = new TextReader( new FileReader(args[0]) );
         for (int lineCt = 0; lineCt &lt; 10; lineCt++)) {
            String line = in.getln();
            System.out.println(line);
         }
      }
      catch (Exception e) {
         System.out.println("Error: " + e);
      }
   }
   
}  // end class TenLinesWithTextReader

//-----------------------------------------------------------------   
   
import java.io.*;
public class TenLinesWithBufferedReader {

   public static void main(String[] args) {
      try {
         BufferedReader in = new BufferedReader( new FileReader(args[0]) );
         for (int lineCt = 0; lineCt &lt; 10; lineCt++)) {
            String line = in.readLine();
            System.out.println(line);
         }
      }
      catch (Exception e) {
         System.out.println("Error: " + e);
      }
   }
   
}  // end class TenLinesWithBufferedReader

//-----------------------------------------------------------------   

import java.io.*;
import java.util.Scanner;
public class TenLinesWithScanner {

   public static void main(String[] args) {
      try {
         Scanner scanner = new Scanner( new File(args[0]) );
         for (int lineCt = 0; lineCt &lt; 10; lineCt++)) {
            String line = scanner.nextLine();
            System.out.println(line);
         }
      }
      catch (Exception e) {
         System.out.println("Error: " + e);
      }
   }
   
}  // end class TenLinesWithScanner</pre>
</ans>
</question>
   
   
</quiz>