<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="IO.2" title="Files">
   
<p><start><big>T</big>he data and programs</start> in a computer's main memory
survive only as long as the power is on. For more permanent storage, computers
use <newword>files</newword>, which are collections of data stored on
a hard disk, on a USB memory stick, on a CD-ROM, or on some other type of storage
device. Files are organized into <newword>directories</newword>
(sometimes called <newword>folders</newword>). A directory can hold other directories, as well
as files. Both directories and files have names that are used to identify
them.</p>

<p>Programs can read data from existing files. They can create new files and
can write data to files. In Java, such input and output can be done using streams.
Human-readable character data can be read from a file using an object belonging to
the class <classname>FileReader</classname>, which is a subclass of <classname>Reader</classname>.
Similarly, data can be written to a file in human-readable format through an object
of type <classname>FileWriter</classname>, a subclass of <classname>Writer</classname>. For files that
store data in machine format, the appropriate I/O classes are
<classname>FileInputStream</classname> and <classname>FileOutputStream</classname>. In this section, I will
only discuss character-oriented file I/O using the <classname>FileReader</classname> and
<classname>FileWriter</classname> classes. However, <classname>FileInputStream</classname> and
<classname>FileOutputStream</classname> are used in an exactly parallel fashion. All these
classes are defined in the <code>java.io</code> package.</p>


<subsection id="IO.2.1" title="Reading and Writing Files">

<p>The <classname>FileReader</classname> class has a constructor which takes the name of a
file as a parameter and creates an input stream that can be used for reading
from that file. This constructor will throw an exception of type
<classname>FileNotFoundException</classname> if the file doesn't exist. 
For example, suppose you have a file named
"<code>data.txt</code>", and you want your program to read data from that file. You
could do the following to create an input stream for the file:</p>

<pre>FileReader data;   // (Declare the variable before the
                   //   try statement, or else the variable
                   //   is local to the try block and you won't
                   //   be able to use it later in the program.)
                        
try {
   data = new FileReader("data.txt");  // create the stream
}
catch (FileNotFoundException e) {
   ... // do something to handle the error&mdash;maybe, end the program
}</pre>

<p>The <classname>FileNotFoundException</classname> class is a subclass of
<classname>IOException</classname>, so it would be acceptable to catch <classname>IOExceptions</classname>
in the above <code>try...catch</code> statement. More generally, just about any
error that can occur during input/output operations can be caught by a
<code>catch</code> clause that handles <classname>IOException</classname>.</p>

<p>Once you have successfully created a <classname>FileReader</classname>, you can start
reading data from it. But since <classname>FileReaders</classname> have only the primitive
input methods inherited from the basic <classname>Reader</classname> class, you will probably
want to wrap your <classname>FileReader</classname> in a <classname>Scanner</classname>, in
a <classname>TextReader</classname>, or in
some other wrapper class. (The <classname>TextReader</classname> class is not a standard part
of Java; it is described in <localref href="IO.1.4"/>.
<classname>Scanner</classname> is discussed in <localref href="IO.1.5"/>.) To
create a <classname>TextReader</classname> for reading from a file named <code>data.dat</code>,
you could say:</p>

<pre>TextReader data;

try {
   data = new TextReader( new FileReader("data.dat") );
}
catch (FileNotFoundException e) {
   ... // handle the exception
}</pre>

<np>To use a <classname>Scanner</classname> to read from the file, you can construct the
scanner in a similar way.  However, it is more common to construct it from an object
of type <classname>File</classname> (to be covered <localref href="IO.2.2">below</localref>):</np>

<pre>Scanner in;

try {
   in = new Scanner( new File("data.dat") );
}
catch (FileNotFoundException e) {
   ... // handle the exception
}</pre>


<np>Once you have a <classname>Scanner</classname> or <classname>TextReader</classname> for
reading from a file, you can get data from the file using exactly the same methods that
work with any <classname>Scanner</classname> or <classname>TextReader</classname>.
When you read from a file using either of these, exceptions can occur.  Since the exceptions
in this case are not checked exceptions, you are not forced to enclose your input commands
in a <code>try..catch</code> statement, but it is usually a good idea to do it anyway.</np>

<p>Working with output files is no more difficult than this. You simply create
an object belonging to the class <classname>FileWriter</classname>. You will probably want to
wrap this output stream in an object of type <classname>PrintWriter</classname>. For example,
suppose you want to write data to a file named "<code>result.dat</code>". Since the
constructor for <classname>FileWriter</classname> can throw an exception of type
<classname>IOException</classname>, you should use a <code>try..catch</code> statement:</p>

<pre>PrintWriter result;

try {
   result = new PrintWriter(new FileWriter("result.dat"));
}
catch (IOException e) {
   ... // handle the exception
}</pre>

<np>However, as with <classname>Scanner</classname>, it is more common to use a
constructor that takes a <classname>File</classname> as parameter; this will
automatically wrap the File in a FileWriter before creating the PrintWriter:</np>

<pre>PrintWriter result;

try {
   result = new PrintWriter(new File("result.dat"));
}
catch (IOException e) {
   ... // handle the exception
}</pre>

<np>You can even use just a <classname>String</classname> as the parameter to the
constructor, and it will be interpreted as a file name (but you should remember that
a <classname>String</classname> in the <classname>Scanner</classname> constructor
does not name a file; instead the file will read characters from the string itself).</np>

<p>If no file named <code>result.dat</code> exists, a new file will be created. If
the file already exists, then the current contents of the file will be erased
and replaced with the data that your program writes to the file.   This will be
done without any warning.  To avoid overwriting a file that already exists, you
can check whether a file of the same name already exists before trying to create
the stream, as discussed later in this section.  An
<classname>IOException</classname> might occur in the <classname>PrintWriter</classname>
constructor if, for example, you are trying to create a
file on a disk that is "write-protected," meaning that it cannot be modified.</p>

<p>When you are finished with a <classname>PrintWriter</classname>,
you should call its <code>flush()</code> method, such as "<code>result.flush()</code>",
to make sure that all the output has been set to its destination.  If you forget to
do this, you might find that some of the data that you have written to a file
has not actually shown up in the file.</p>

<p>After you are finished using a file, it's a good idea to <newword>close</newword> 
the file, to tell the operating system that you are
finished using it.  You can close a file by calling the <code>close()</code> method of the
associated <classname>PrintWriter</classname>, <classname>TextReader</classname>, or 
<classname>Scanner</classname>.  
Once a file has been closed, it is no longer possible to
read data from it or write data to it, unless you open it again as a new
stream. (Note that for most stream classes, the <code>close()</code> method can
throw an <classname>IOException</classname>, which must be handled; however, 
<classname>PrintWriter</classname>, <classname>TextReader</classname>, and <classname>Scanner</classname>
override this method so that it cannot throw such exceptions.)
If you forget to close a file, the file will ordinarily be
closed automatically when the program terminates or when the file object
is garbage collected, but it is better not to depend on this.</p>

<p>As a complete example, here is a program that will read numbers from a file
named <code>data.dat</code>, and will then write out the same numbers in reverse
order to another file named <code>result.dat</code>. It is assumed that
<code>data.dat</code> contains only real numbers.
The input file is read using a <classname>Scanner</classname>.
Exception-handling is used to check for
problems along the way. Although the application is not a particularly useful
one, this program demonstrates the basics of working with files. (By the way,
at the end of this program, you'll find our first useful example of a <code>finally</code>
clause in a <code>try</code> statement. When the computer executes a <code>try</code>
statement, the commands in its <code>finally</code> clause are guaranteed to be
executed, no matter what.  See <localref href="robustness.3.2"/>.)</p>

<pre>import java.io.*;
import java.util.ArrayList;

/**
 * Reads numbers from a file named data.dat and writes them to a file
 * named result.dat in reverse order.  The input file should contain
 * exactly one real number per line.
 */
public class ReverseFile {

    public static void main(String[] args) {

        TextReader data;     // Character input stream for reading data.
        PrintWriter result;  // Character output stream for writing data.

        ArrayList&lt;Double&gt; numbers;  // An ArrayList for holding the data.

        numbers = new ArrayList&lt;Double&gt;();

        try {  // Create the input stream.
            data = new TextReader(new FileReader("data.dat"));
        }
        catch (FileNotFoundException e) {
            System.out.println("Can't find file data.dat!");
            return;  // End the program by returning from main().
        }

        try {  // Create the output stream.
            result = new PrintWriter(new FileWriter("result.dat"));
        }
        catch (IOException e) {
            System.out.println("Can't open file result.dat!");
            System.out.println("Error: " + e);
            data.close();  // Close the input file.
            return;        // End the program.
        }

        try {

            // Read numbers from the input file, adding them to the ArrayList.

            while ( data.eof() == false ) {  // Read until end-of-file.
                double inputNumber = data.getlnDouble();
                numbers.add( inputNumber );
            }

            // Output the numbers in reverse order.

            for (int i = numbers.size()-1; i >= 0; i--)
                result.println(numbers.get(i));
            
            result.flush();  // Make sure data is actually sent to the file.
            
            if (result.checkError())
                System.out.println("Some error occurred while writing the file.");
            else
                System.out.println("Done!");

        }
        catch (IOException e) {
            // Some problem reading the data from the input file.
            // (Note that PrintWriter doesn't throw exceptions on output errors.)
            System.out.println("Input Error: " + e.getMessage());
        }
        finally {
            // Finish by closing the files, whatever else may have happened.
            data.close();
            result.close();
        }

    }  // end of main()

} // end class ReverseFileWithTextReader
</pre>

<np>A version of this program that uses a <classname>Scanner</classname> instead
of a <classname>TextReader</classname> can be found in 
<sourceref href="ReverseFileWithScanner.java"/>.  Note that the <classname>Scanner</classname>
version does not need the final <code>try..catch</code> from the <classname>TextReader</classname> version, 
since the <classname>Scanner</classname> method for reading data doesn't throw an <classname>IOException</classname>.
Instead, the program will simply stop reading data from the file if it encounters anything other
than a number in the input.</np>
   
<break/>

<p>As mentioned at the end of <localref href="robustness.3.2"/>, the pattern of creating or opening 
a "resource," using it, and then closing the resource is a very common one, and the pattern
is supported by the syntax of the <code>try..catch</code> statement.  Files are resources
in this sense, as are <classname>Scanner</classname>, <classname>TextReader</classname>,
and all of Java's I/O streams.  All of these things define <code>close()</code> methods,
and it is good form to close them when you are finished using them.  Since they all
implement the <classname>AutoCloseable</classname> interface, they are all resources
in the sense required by <code>try..catch</code>.  A <code>try..catch</code> statement
can be used to automatically close a resource when the <code>try</code> statement ends,
which eliminates the need to close it by hand in a <code>finally</code> clause.
This assumes that you will open the resource and use it in the same <code>try..catch</code>.
</p>

<p>As an example, the sample program <sourceref href="ReverseFileWithResources.java"/>
is another version of the example we have been looking at.  In this case, <code>try..catch</code>
statements using the resource pattern are used to read the data from a file and to write
the data to a file.  My original program opened a file in one <code>try</code> statement
and used it in another <code>try</code> statement.  The resource pattern requires that it all
be done in one <code>try</code>, which requires some reorganization of the code (and can sometimes
make it harder to determine the exact cause of an exception).  Here is the <code>try..catch</code>
statement from the sample program that opens the input file, reads from it, and closes it automatically.
</p>

<pre>try( TextReader data = new TextReader(new FileReader("data.dat")) ) {
    // Read numbers, adding them to the ArrayList.
    while ( data.eof() == false ) {  // Read until end-of-file.
        double inputNumber = data.getlnDouble();
        numbers.add( inputNumber );
    }
}
catch (FileNotFoundException e) {
        // Can only be caused by the TextReader constructor
    System.out.println("Can't open input file data.dat!");
    System.out.println("Error: " + e);
    return;  // Return from main(), since an error has occurred.
             //  (Otherwise, the program would try to do the output!)
}
catch (IOException e) {
        // Can occur when the TextReader tries to read a number.
    System.out.println("Error while reading from file: " + e);
    return;  // Return from main(), since an error has occurred.
}</pre>

<np>The resource, <code>data</code>, is constructed on the first line.  The syntax requires
a declaration of the resource, with an initial value, in parentheses after the
word "try."  It's possible to have several resource declarations, separated by
semicolons.  They will be closed in the order opposite to the order in which they
are declared.</np>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="IO.2.2" title="Files and Directories">


<p>The subject of file names is actually more complicated than I've let on so
far. To fully specify a file, you have to give both the name of the file and
the name of the directory where that file is located. A simple file name like
"data.dat" or "result.dat" is taken to refer to a file in a directory that is
called the <newword>current directory</newword> (also known as the "default
directory" or "working directory"). The current directory is not a permanent
thing. It can be changed by the user or by a program. Files not in the current
directory must be referred to by a <newword>path name</newword>,
which includes both the name of the file and information about the directory
where it can be found.</p>

<p>To complicate matters even further, there are two types of path names,
<newword>absolute path names</newword> and <newword>relative path names</newword>. 
An absolute path name uniquely identifies
one file among all the files available to the computer. It contains full
information about which directory the file is in and what the file's name is. A
relative path name tells the computer how to locate the file starting from the
current directory.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the syntax for file names and path names varies somewhat
from one type of computer to another. Here are some examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>data.dat</code> &mdash; on any computer, this would be a file named "data.dat"
in the current directory.</li>
<li><code>/home/eck/java/examples/data.dat</code> &mdash; This is an absolute path name
in a UNIX operating system, including Linux and Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X. 
It refers to a file named data.dat in a directory
named examples, which is in turn in a directory named java,&nbsp;&dots;.</li>
<li><code>C:\eck\java\examples\data.dat</code> &mdash; An absolute path name on a 
Windows computer.</li>
<li><code>examples/data.dat</code> &mdash; a relative path name under UNIX. "examples"
is the name of a directory that is contained within the current directory, and
data.dat is a file in that directory. The corresponding relative path name
for Windows would be <code>examples\data.dat</code>.</li>
<li><code>../examples/data.dat</code> &mdash; a relative path name in UNIX that means "go to the
directory that contains the current directory, then go into a directory named examples
inside that directory, and look there for a file named data.dat."  In general, "<code>..</code>"
means "go up one directory."  The corresponding path on Windows is
<code>..\examples\data.dat</code>.</li>
</ul>

<np>When working on the command line, it's safe
to say that if you stick to using simple file names only, and if the
files are stored in the same directory with the program that will use them,
then you will be OK.   Later in this section, we'll look at a convenient way of
letting the user specify a file in a GUI program, which allows you to avoid the issue of
path names altogether.</np>
   
<p>It is possible for a Java program to find out the absolute path names
for two important directories, the current directory and the user's home
directory.  You can then use the path name, for example, in a constructor for 
a <classname>File</classname> or a <classname>PrintWriter</classname>.
The names of these directories are <newword>system properties</newword>,
and they can be read using the function calls:
</p>
   
<ul>
<li><codedef>System.getProperty("user.dir")</codedef> &mdash; returns the
absolute path name of the current directory as a <classname>String</classname>.</li>
<li><codedef>System.getProperty("user.home")</codedef> &mdash; returns the
absolute path name of the user's home directory as a <classname>String</classname>.</li>
</ul>

<p>To avoid some of the problems caused by differences in path names between platforms, Java
has the class <code>java.io.File</code>. An object belonging to this class
represents a file. More precisely, an object of type <classname>File</classname> represents a
file <b>name</b> rather than a file as such. The file to which the name
refers might or might not exist. Directories are treated in the same way as
files, so a <classname>File</classname> object can represent a directory just as easily as it
can represent a file.</p>

<p>A <classname>File</classname> object has a constructor, "<code>new&nbsp;</code><code>File(String)</code>",
that creates a <classname>File</classname> object from a path name. The name can be a simple
name, a relative path, or an absolute path. For example, 
<code>new</code>&nbsp;<code>File("data.dat")</code> 
creates a <classname>File</classname> object that refers to a file
named data.dat, in the current directory. Another constructor, 
"<code>new</code>&nbsp;<code>File(File,String)</code>", has two parameters. 
The first is a <classname>File</classname>
object that refers to a directory. The second can be the
name of the file in that directory or a relative path from that directory to the file.</p>

<p><classname>File</classname> objects contain several useful instance methods. Assuming that
<code>file</code> is a variable of type <classname>File</classname>, here are some of the methods
that are available:</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>file.exists()</codedef> &mdash; This
<ptype>boolean</ptype>-valued function returns <code>true</code> if the file named by the
<classname>File</classname> object already exists. You can use this method if you want to
avoid overwriting the contents of an existing file when you create a new
output stream.</li>

<li><codedef>file.isDirectory()</codedef> &mdash; This
<ptype>boolean</ptype>-valued function returns <code>true</code> if the <classname>File</classname>
object refers to a directory. It returns <code>false</code> if it refers to a
regular file or if no file with the given name exists.</li>

<li><codedef>file.delete()</codedef> &mdash; Deletes the file, if
it exists.  Returns a <ptype>boolean</ptype> value to indicate whether
the file was successfully deleted.</li>

<li><codedef>file.list()</codedef> &mdash; If the <code>File</code>
object refers to a directory, this function returns an array of type
<code>String[]</code> containing the names of the files in that directory.
Otherwise, it returns <code>null</code>. The method <code>file.listFiles()</code>
is similar, except that it returns an array of <classname>File</classname>
instead of an array of <classname>String</classname>.</li>
</ul>
   
<p>Here, for example, is a program that will list the names of all the files in
a directory specified by the user.  In this example, I have used a
<classname>Scanner</classname> to read the user's input:</p>

<pre>import java.io.File;
import java.util.Scanner;

/**
 * This program lists the files in a directory specified by
 * the user.  The user is asked to type in a directory name.
 * If the name entered by the user is not a directory, a
 * message is printed and the program ends.
 */
public class DirectoryList {

   
   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
      String directoryName;  // Directory name entered by the user.
      File directory;        // File object referring to the directory.
      String[] files;        // Array of file names in the directory.
      Scanner scanner;       // For reading a line of input from the user.

      scanner = new Scanner(System.in);  // scanner reads from standard input.

      System.out.print("Enter a directory name: ");
      directoryName = scanner.nextLine().trim();
      directory = new File(directoryName);
      
      if (directory.isDirectory() == false) {
          if (directory.exists() == false)
             System.out.println("There is no such directory!");
          else
             System.out.println("That file is not a directory.");
      }
      else {
          files = directory.list();
          System.out.println("Files in directory \"" + directory + "\":");
          for (int i = 0; i &lt; files.length; i++)
             System.out.println("   " + files[i]);
      }
   
   } // end main()

} // end class DirectoryList</pre>

<p>All the classes that are used for reading data from files and writing data
to files have constructors that take a <classname>File</classname> object as a parameter. For
example, if <code>file</code> is a variable of type <classname>File</classname>, and you want to
read character data from that file, you can create a <classname>FileReader</classname> to do
so by saying <code>new</code>&nbsp;<code>FileReader(file)</code>.</p>


</subsection>
   
<subsection id="IO.2.3" title="File Dialog Boxes">
   

<p>In many programs, you want the user to be able to select the file that is
going to be used for input or output. If your program lets the user type in the
file name, you will just have to assume that the user understands how to work
with files and directories. But in a graphical user interface, the user expects
to be able to select files using a <newword>file dialog box</newword>, 
which is a window that a program can open when it wants the
user to select a file for input or output. Swing includes a
platform-independent technique for using file dialog boxes in the form of a
class called <classname>JFileChooser</classname>. This class is part of the package
<code>javax.swing</code>. We looked at using some basic dialog boxes in 
<localref href="GUI1.8.2"/>. File dialog boxes are similar to those, but
are just a little more complicated to use.</p>

<p>A file dialog box shows the user a list of files and sub-directories in some
directory, and makes it easy for the user to specify a file in that directory.
The user can also navigate easily from one directory to another. The most
common constructor for <classname>JFileChooser</classname> has no parameter
and sets the starting directory in the dialog box to be the user's home directory.
There are also constructors that specify the starting directory explicitly:
</p>

<pre>new JFileChooser( File startDirectory )

new JFileChooser( String pathToStartDirectory )</pre>
   
<p>Constructing a <classname>JFileChooser</classname> object does not make the dialog box
appear on the screen. You have to call a method in the object to do that.
There are two different methods that can be used because there are two types of
file dialog: An <newword>open file dialog</newword> allows the user
to specify an existing file to be opened for reading data into the program; a
<newword>save file dialog</newword> lets the user specify a file,
which might or might not already exist, to be opened for writing data from the
program. File dialogs of these two types are opened using the
<code>showOpenDialog</code> and <code>showSaveDialog</code> methods.
These methods make the dialog box appear on the screen; the methods do
not return until the user selects a file or cancels the dialog.</p>

<p>A file dialog box always has a <newword>parent</newword>, another
component which is associated with the dialog box. The parent is specified as a
parameter to the <code>showOpenDialog</code> or <code>showSaveDialog</code> methods.
The parent is a GUI component, and can often be specified as "<code>this</code>" in
practice, since file dialogs are often used in instance methods of GUI component classes.
(The parameter can also be <code>null</code>, in which case an invisible component is
created to be used as the parent.) Both <code>showOpenDialog</code> and <code>showSaveDialog</code>
have a return value, which will be one of the constants
<code>JFileChooser.CANCEL_OPTION</code>, <code>JFileChooser.ERROR_OPTION</code>, or
<code>JFileChooser.APPROVE_OPTION</code>. If the return value is
<code>JFileChooser.APPROVE_OPTION</code>, then the user has selected a file. If the
return value is something else, then the user did not select a file. The user
might have clicked a "Cancel" button, for example. You should always check the
return value, to make sure that the user has, in fact, selected a file. If that
is the case, then you can find out which file was selected by calling the
<classname>JFileChooser's</classname> <code>getSelectedFile()</code> method, which returns an object of
type <classname>File</classname> that represents the selected file.</p>

<p>Putting all this together, we can look at a typical subroutine that reads
data from a file that is selected using a <classname>JFileChooser</classname>:</p>

<pre>public void readFile() {
   if (fileDialog == null)   // (fileDialog is an instance variable)
      fileDialog = new JFileChooser();
   fileDialog.setDialogTitle("Select File for Reading");
   fileDialog.setSelectedFile(null);  // No file is initially selected.
   int option = fileDialog.showOpenDialog(this);
       // (Using "this" as a parameter to showOpenDialog() assumes that the
       //  readFile() method is an instance method in a GUI component class.)
   if (option != JFileChooser.APPROVE_OPTION)
      return;  // User canceled or clicked the dialog's close box.
   File selectedFile = fileDialog.getSelectedFile();
   TextReader in;  // (or use some other wrapper class)
   try {
      FileReader stream = new FileReader(selectedFile); // (or a FileInputStream)
      in = new TextReader( stream );
   }
   catch (Exception e) {
      JOptionPane.showMessageDialog(this,
          "Sorry, but an error occurred while trying to open the file:\n" + e);
      return;
   }
   try {
      .
      .  // Read and process the data from the input stream, in.
      .
   }
   catch (Exception e) {
      JOptionPane.showMessageDialog(this,
          "Sorry, but an error occurred while trying to read the data:\n" + e);
   }
   finally {
      in.close();
   }
}</pre>
   
<np>One fine point here is that the variable <code>fileDialog</code> is an instance
variable of type <classname>JFileChooser</classname>, not a local variable.  This allows the
file dialog to continue to exist between calls to <code>readFile()</code>.
The main effect of this is that the dialog box will keep the same selected
directory from one call of <code>readFile()</code> to the next.  When the
dialog reappears, it will show the same directory that the user selected
the previous time it appeared.  This is probably what the user expects.</np>
   
<p>Note that it's common to do some configuration of a <classname>JFileChooser</classname> before
calling <code>showOpenDialog</code> or <code>showSaveDialog</code>. For example, the
instance method <code>setDialogTitle(String)</code> is used to specify a title
to appear in the title bar of the window. And <code>setSelectedFile(File)</code> is
used to set the file that is selected in the dialog box when it appears. This
can be used to provide a default file choice for the user.  In the <code>readFile()</code>
method, above, <code>fileDialog.setSelectedFile(null)</code> specifies that
no file is pre-selected when the dialog box appears. Otherwise, the selected file could
be carried over from the previous time the file dialog was used.</p>

<p>Writing data to a file is similar, but it's a good idea to add a check
to determine whether the output file that is selected by the user already
exists.  In that case, ask the user whether to replace the file.
Here is a typical subroutine for writing to a user-selected file:</p>

<pre>public void writeFile() {
   if (fileDialog == null)      
      fileDialog = new JFileChooser();  // (fileDialog is an instance variable)
   File selectedFile = new File("output.txt"); // (default output file name)
   fileDialog.setSelectedFile(selectedFile);  // Specify a default file name.
   fileDialog.setDialogTitle("Select File for Writing");
   int option = fileDialog.showSaveDialog(this);
   if (option != JFileChooser.APPROVE_OPTION)
      return;  // User canceled or clicked the dialog's close box.
   selectedFile = fileDialog.getSelectedFile();
   if (selectedFile.exists()) {  // Ask the user whether to replace the file.
      int response = JOptionPane.showConfirmDialog( this,
            "The file \"" + selectedFile.getName()
                + "\" already exists.\nDo you want to replace it?", 
            "Confirm Save",
            JOptionPane.YES_NO_OPTION, 
            JOptionPane.WARNING_MESSAGE );
      if (response != JOptionPane.YES_OPTION)
         return;  // User does not want to replace the file.
   }
   PrintWriter out;  // (or use some other wrapper class)
   try {
      out = new PrintWriter( selectedFile );
   }
   catch (Exception e) {
      JOptionPane.showMessageDialog(this,
          "Sorry, but an error occurred while trying to open the file:\n" + e);
      return;
   }
   try {
      .
      .  // Write data to the output stream, out. (Does not throw exceptions.)
      .
     out.flush();
     out.close();
     if (out.checkError())   // (need to check for errors in PrintWriter)
        throw new IOException("Error occurred while trying to write file.");
   }
   catch (Exception e) {
      JOptionPane.showMessageDialog(this,
          "Sorry, but an error occurred while trying to write the data:\n" + e);
   }
}</pre>


<p>The <code>readFile()</code> and <code>writeFile()</code> routines
presented here can be used, with just a few changes, when you need to read
or write a file in a GUI program.
We'll look at some more complete examples of using files and file dialogs in
the <localref href="IO.3">next section</localref>.</p>

   
</subsection>
</section>