<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes7.dtd" >

<section id="IO.4" title="Networking">
   
<p><start><big>A</big>s far as a program is concerned</start>, a network is just
another possible source of input data, and another place where data can be
output. That does oversimplify things, because networks are not as
easy to work with as files are. But in Java, you can do network communication
using input streams and output streams, just as you can use such streams to
communicate with the user or to work with files. Nevertheless, opening a
network connection between two computers is a bit tricky, since there are two
computers involved and they have to somehow agree to open a connection. And
when each computer can send data to the other, synchronizing communication can
be a problem. But the fundamentals are the same as for other forms of I/O.</p>

<p>One of the standard Java packages is called <code>java.net</code>. This package
includes several classes that can be used for networking. Two different styles
of network I/O are supported. One of these, which is fairly high-level, is
based on the World-Wide Web, and provides the sort of network communication
capability that is used by a Web browser when it downloads pages for you to
view. The main classes for this style of networking are <code>java.net.URL</code>
and <code>java.net.URLConnection</code>. An object of type <classname>URL</classname> is an
abstract representation of a <newword>Universal Resource Locator</newword>, 
which is an address for an HTML document or other resource on
the Web.  A <classname>URLConnection</classname> represents a network connection to such a
resource.</p>

<p>The second style of I/O, which is more general and more important,
views the network at a lower level. It is based on
the idea of a <newword>socket</newword>. A socket is used by a
program to establish a connection with another program on a network.
Communication over a network involves two sockets, one on each of the computers
involved in the communication. Java uses a class called
<code>java.net.Socket</code> to represent sockets that are used for network
communication. The term "socket" presumably comes from an image of physically
plugging a wire into a computer to establish a connection to a network, but it
is important to understand that a socket, as the term is used here, is simply
an object belonging to the class <classname>Socket</classname>. In particular, a program can
have several sockets at the same time, each connecting it to another program
running on some other computer on the network&mdash;or even running on the 
same computer. All these connections use the same physical network connection.</p>

<p>This section gives a brief introduction to these basic networking classes,
and shows how they relate to input and output streams.</p>



<subsection id="IO.4.1" title="URLs and URLConnections">

<p>The <classname>URL</classname> class is used to represent resources on the World-Wide Web.
Every resource has an address, which identifies it uniquely and contains enough
information for a Web browser to find the resource on the network and retrieve
it. The address is called a "url" or "universal resource locator."
(URLs can actually refer to resources from other sources besides the web;
after all, they are "universal".)</p>

<p>An object belonging to the <classname>URL</classname> class represents such an address.
Once you have a <classname>URL</classname> object, you can use it to open a
<classname>URLConnection</classname> to the resource at that address. A url is ordinarily
specified as a string, such as "<code>http://math.hws.edu/eck/index.html</code>".
There are also <newword>relative url's</newword>. A relative url
specifies the location of a resource relative to the location of another url,
which is called the <newword>base</newword> or <newword>context</newword> 
for the relative url. For example, if the context is
given by the url <code>http://math.hws.edu/eck/</code>, then the incomplete,
relative url "<code>index.html</code>" would really refer to
<code>http://math.hws.edu/eck/index.html</code>.</p>

<p>An object of the class <classname>URL</classname> is not simply a string, but it can be
constructed from a string representation of a url. A <classname>URL</classname> object can
also be constructed from another <classname>URL</classname> object, representing a context,
plus a string that specifies a url relative to that context. These constructors
have prototypes</p>

<pre>public URL(String urlName) throws MalformedURLException</pre>

<np>and</np>

<pre>public URL(URL context, String relativeName) throws MalformedURLException</pre>

<np>Note that these constructors will throw an exception of type
<classname>MalformedURLException</classname> if the specified strings don't represent legal
url's. The <classname>MalformedURLException</classname> class is a subclass of
<classname>IOException</classname>, and it requires mandatory exception handling.</np>

<p>Once you have a valid <classname>URL</classname> object, you can call its
<code>openConnection()</code> method to set up a connection. This method returns a
<classname>URLConnection</classname>. The <classname>URLConnection</classname> object can, 
in turn, be used
to create an <classname>InputStream</classname> for reading data from the resource
represented by the URL. This is done by calling its <code>getInputStream()</code>
method. For example:</p>

<pre>URL url = new URL(urlAddressString);
URLConnection connection = url.openConnection();
InputStream in = connection.getInputStream();</pre>

<np>The <code>openConnection()</code> and <code>getInputStream()</code> methods can both
throw exceptions of type <classname>IOException</classname>. Once the <classname>InputStream</classname>
has been created, you can read from it in the usual way, including wrapping it
in another input stream type, such as <classname>BufferedReader</classname>, or using
a <classname>Scanner</classname>.  Reading from the
stream can, of course, generate exceptions.</np>

<p>One of the other useful instance methods in the <classname>URLConnection</classname> class
is <code>getContentType()</code>, which returns a <classname>String</classname> that describes
the type of information available from the URL. The return value can be
<code>null</code> if the type of information is not yet known or if it is not
possible to determine the type. The type might not be available until after the
input stream has been created, so you should generally call
<code>getContentType()</code> after <code>getInputStream()</code>. The string returned
by <code>getContentType()</code> is in a format called a <newword>mime type</newword>. 
Mime types include "text/plain", "text/html", "image/jpeg",
"image/png", and many others. All mime types contain two parts: a general type,
such as "text" or "image", and a more specific type within that general
category, such as "html" or "png". If you are only interested in text data, for
example, you can check whether the string returned by <code>getContentType()</code>
starts with "text". (Mime types were first introduced to describe the content
of email messages. The name stands for "Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions."
They are now used almost universally to specify the type of information in a
file or other resource.)</p>

<p>Let's look at a short example that uses all this to read the data from a
URL. This subroutine opens a connection to a specified URL, checks that the
type of data at the URL is text, and then copies the text onto the screen. Many
of the operations in this subroutine can throw exceptions. They are handled by
declaring that the subroutine "<code>throws IOException</code>" and leaving it up to the main
program to decide what to do when an error occurs.</p>

<pre>static void readTextFromURL( String urlString ) throws IOException {

     /* Open a connection to the URL, and get an input stream
       for reading data from the URL. */

     URL url = new URL(urlString);
     URLConnection connection = url.openConnection();
     InputStream urlData = connection.getInputStream();

     /* Check that the content is some type of text.  Note: If 
        getContentType() method were called before getting the input 
        stream, it is possible for contentType to be null only because 
        no connection can be made.  The getInputStream() method will 
        throw an error if no connection can be made. */

     String contentType = connection.getContentType();
     System.out.println("Stream opened with content type: " + contentType);
     System.out.println();
     if (contentType == null || contentType.startsWith("text") == false)
          throw new IOException("URL does not seem to refer to a text file.");
     System.out.println("Fetching context from " + urlString + " ...");
     System.out.println();

     /* Copy lines of text from the input stream to the screen, until
       end-of-file is encountered  (or an error occurs). */

     BufferedReader in;  // For reading from the connection's input stream.
     in = new BufferedReader( new InputStreamReader(urlData) );

     while (true) {
          String line = in.readLine();
          if (line == null)
               break;
          System.out.println(line);
     }
     in.close();

} // end readTextFromURL()</pre>

<np>A complete program that uses this subroutine can be found in the file
<sourceref href="FetchURL.java"/>.  When you run the program, you can specify 
the URL on the command line; if not, you will be prompted to enter the URL.
For this program, a URL can begin with "http://" for a URL that refers to
a resource on the web, with "file://" for a URL that refers to a file on
your computer, or with "ftp://" for a URL that uses the "File Transfer Protocol."
If it does not start with any of these, then "http://" is added to the start
of the URL.  Try the program with URL <code>math.hws.edu/javanotes</code> to 
fetch the front page of this textbook on the web.  Try it with some bad inputs
to see the various errors that can occur.</np>
   
</subsection>
   
   
<subsection id="IO.4.2" title="TCP/IP and Client/Server">

<p>Communication over the Internet is based on a pair of protocols called the
<newword>Transmission Control Protocol</newword> and the <newword>Internet Protocol</newword>,
which are collectively referred
to as <newword>TCP/IP</newword>. (In fact, there is a more basic communication protocol called UDP
that can be used instead of TCP in certain applications. UDP is supported in
Java, but for this discussion, I'll stick to TCP/IP, which provides
reliable two-way communication between networked computers.)</p>

<p>For two programs to communicate using TCP/IP, each program must create a
socket, as discussed earlier in this section, and those sockets must be
connected. Once such a connection is made, communication takes place using
input streams and output streams. Each program has its own input stream and its
own output stream. Data written by one program to its output stream is
transmitted to the other computer. There, it enters the input stream of the
program at the other end of the network connection. When that program reads
data from its input stream, it is receiving the data that was transmitted to it
over the network.</p>

<p>The hard part, then, is making a network connection in the first place. Two
sockets are involved. To get things started, one program must create a socket
that will wait passively until a connection request comes in from another
socket. The waiting socket is said to be <newword>listening</newword>
for a connection. On the other side of the connection-to-be, another program
creates a socket that sends out a connection request to the listening socket.
When the listening socket receives the connection request, it responds, and the
connection is established. Once that is done, each program can obtain an input
stream and an output stream for sending data over the connection. Communication takes place
through these streams until one program or the other <newword>closes</newword> the connection.</p>

<p>A program that creates a listening socket is sometimes said to be a
<newword>server</newword>, and the socket is called a <newword>server socket</newword>. 
A program that connects to a server is called a
<newword>client</newword>, and the socket that it uses to make a
connection is called a <newword>client socket</newword>. The idea is
that the server is out there somewhere on the network, waiting for a connection
request from some client. The server can be thought of as offering some kind of
service, and the client gets access to that service by connecting to the
server. This is called the <newword>client/server model</newword> of
network communication. In many actual applications, a server program can
provide connections to several clients at the same time. When a client connects
to a server's listening socket, that socket does not stop listening. Instead,
it continues listening for additional client connections at the same time that
the first client is being serviced. To do this, it is necessary to use
threads. We'll look at how it works in the <localref href="threads">next chapter</localref>.</p>

<p>The <classname>URL</classname> class that was discussed at the beginning of this section
uses a client socket behind the scenes to do any necessary network
communication. On the other side of that connection is a server program that
accepts a connection request from the <classname>URL</classname> object, reads a request from
that object for some particular file on the server computer, and responds by
transmitting the contents of that file over the network back to the
<classname>URL</classname> object. After transmitting the data, the server closes the
connection.</p>

<break/>
   
<p>A client program has to have some way to specify
which computer, among all those on the network, it wants to communicate with.
Every computer on the Internet has an <newword>IP&nbsp;address</newword>
which identifies it. Many computers
can also be referred to by <newword>domain names</newword> such as
math.hws.edu or www.whitehouse.gov. (See <localref href="overview.7"/>.)
Traditional (or <newword>IPv4</newword>) IP addresses are 32-bit integers.  
They are usually written
in the so-called "dotted decimal" form, such as <code>64.89.144.135</code>, 
where each of the four numbers in the address represents an 8-bit 
integer in the range 0 through 255.  A new version of the Internet Protocol, 
<newword>IPv6</newword>, is currently being introduced.
IPv6 addresses are 128-bit integers and are usually written in hexadecimal form
(with some colons and maybe some extra information thrown in).
In actual use, IPv6 addresses are still fairly rare.</p>

<p>A computer can have several IP addresses, and can have both IPv4 and IPv6 addresses.
Usually, one of these is the <newword>loopback address</newword>, which can be
used when a program wants to communicate with another program <i>on the
same computer</i>.  The loopback address has IPv4 address 127.0.0.1 and can
also, in general, be referred to using the domain name <newword>localhost</newword>.
In addition, there can be one or more IP addresses associated with physical
network connections.  Your computer probably has some utility for displaying
your computer's IP addresses.   I have written a small Java program,
<sourceref href="ShowMyNetwork.java"/>, that does the same thing.  When I run
<code>ShowMyNetwork</code> on my computer, the output is:</p>
   
<pre>   en1 :  /192.168.1.47  /fe80:0:0:0:211:24ff:fe9c:5271%5  
   lo0 :  /127.0.0.1  /fe80:0:0:0:0:0:0:1%1  /0:0:0:0:0:0:0:1%0</pre>
   
<np>The first thing on each line is a network interface name, which
is really meaningful only to the computer's operating system.  The same line
also contains the IP addresses for that interface.  In this example,
<code>lo0</code> refers to the loopback address, which has IPv4 address
127.0.0.1 as usual.  The most important number here is <code>192.168.1.47</code>, 
which is the IPv4 address that can be used for communication over the network.
(The slashes at the start of each address are not part of the actual address.)
The other numbers in the output are IPv6 addresses.</np>
   
<p>Now, a single computer might have several programs doing network
communication at the same time, or one program communicating with several other
computers. To allow for this possibility, a network connection actually has a
<newword>port number</newword> in combination with an IP address. A
port number is just a 16-bit positive integer. A server does not simply listen for
connections&mdash;it listens for connections <i>on a particular port</i>. A potential
client must know both the Internet address (or domain name) of the computer on which the server
is running and the port number on which the server is listening. A Web server,
for example, generally listens for connections on port 80; other standard
Internet services also have standard port numbers. (The standard port numbers
are all less than 1024, and are reserved for particular services.
If you create your own server programs, you should use
port numbers greater than 1024.)</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="IO.4.3" title="Sockets in Java">  
   

<p>To implement TCP/IP connections, the <code>java.net</code> package provides two
classes, <classname>ServerSocket</classname> and <classname>Socket</classname>. 
A <classname>ServerSocket</classname>
represents a listening socket that waits for connection requests from clients.
A <classname>Socket</classname> represents one endpoint of an actual network connection. A
<classname>Socket</classname> can be a client socket that sends a connection request
to a server. But a <classname>Socket</classname> can also be created by a server to handle a
connection request from a client. This allows the server to create multiple
sockets and handle multiple connections. A <classname>ServerSocket</classname> does not
itself participate in connections; it just listens for connection requests and
creates <classname>Sockets</classname> to handle the actual connections.</p>


<p>When you construct a <code>ServerSocket</code> object, you have to specify the
port number on which the server will listen. The specification for the
constructor is</p>

<pre>public ServerSocket(int port) throws IOException</pre>
   
<np>The port number must be in the range 0 through 65535, and should generally
be greater than 1024.   The constructor might throw a <classname>SecurityException</classname>
if a smaller port number is specified.  An <classname>IOException</classname> can
occur if, for example, the specified port number is already in use.
(A parameter value of 0 in this method tells the server socket to listen on any
available port.)</np>

<p>As soon as a <classname>ServerSocket</classname> is created, it starts listening for
connection requests. The <code>accept()</code> method in the <classname>ServerSocket</classname>
class accepts such a request, establishes a connection with the client, and
returns a <classname>Socket</classname> that can be used for communication with the client.
The <code>accept()</code> method has the form</p>

<pre>public Socket accept() throws IOException</pre>

<np>When you call the <code>accept()</code> method, it will not return until a
connection request is received (or until some error occurs). The method is said
to <newword>block</newword> while waiting for the connection. (While
the method is blocked, the program&mdash;or more exactly, the thread&mdash;that called the method can't do anything
else. If there are other threads in the same program, they can proceed.) You can call
<code>accept()</code> repeatedly to accept multiple connection requests.  The
<classname>ServerSocket</classname> will continue listening for connections until it is
closed, using its <code>close()</code> method, or until some error occurs, or
until the program is terminated in some way.</np>

<p>Suppose that you want a server to listen on port 1728, and that you want
it to continue to accept connections as long as the program is running.
Suppose that you've written a method <code>provideService(Socket)</code> to handle the
communication with one client. Then the basic form of the server program would
be:</p>

<pre>try {
   ServerSocket server = new ServerSocket(1728);
   while (true) {
      Socket connection = server.accept();
      provideService(connection);
   }
}
catch (IOException e) {
   System.out.println("Server shut down with error: " + e);
}</pre>
  

<p>On the client side, a client socket is created using a constructor in the
<classname>Socket</classname> class. To connect to a server on a known computer and port, you
would use the constructor</p>

<pre>public Socket(String computer, int port) throws IOException</pre>

<np>The first parameter can be either an IP number or a domain name. This
constructor will block until the connection is established or until an error
occurs.</np>
   
<p>Once you have a connected socket, no matter how it was created, 
you can use the <classname>Socket</classname>
methods <code>getInputStream()</code> and <code>getOutputStream()</code> to obtain
streams that can be used for communication over the connection.  These methods
return objects of type <classname>InputStream</classname> and <classname>OutputStream</classname>,
respectively.  Keeping all
this in mind, here is the outline of a method for working with a client
connection:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Open a client connection to a specified server computer and
 * port number on the server, and then do communication through
 * the connection.
 */
void doClientConnection(String computerName, int serverPort) {
   Socket connection;
   InputStream in;
   OutputStream out;
   try {
      connection = new Socket(computerName,serverPort);
      in = connection.getInputStream();
      out = connection.getOutputStream();
   }
   catch (IOException e) {
      System.out.println(
          "Attempt to create connection failed with error: " + e);
      return;
   }
    .
    .  // Use the streams, in and out, to communicate with the server.
    .
   try {
      connection.close();
          // (Alternatively, you might depend on the server
          //  to close the connection.)
   }
   catch (IOException e) {
   }
}  // end doClientConnection()</pre>

<p>All this makes network communication sound easier than it really is. (And if
you think it sounded hard, then it's even harder.) If networks were completely
reliable, things would be almost as easy as I've described. The problem,
though, is to write robust programs that can deal with network and human error.
I won't go into detail here.  However, what I've covered here
should give you the basic ideas of network programming, and it is enough to
write some simple network applications.  Let's look at a few working examples of client/server
programming.</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="IO.4.4" title="A Trivial Client/Server">

<p>The first example consists of two programs. The source code files
for the programs are <sourceref href="DateClient.java"/> and
<sourceref href="DateServer.java"/>.  One is a simple network client and the
other is a matching server. The client makes a connection to the server, reads
one line of text from the server, and displays that text on the screen. The
text sent by the server consists of the current date and time on the computer
where the server is running. In order to open a connection, the client must
know the computer on which the server is running and the port on which it is
listening. The server listens on port number 32007. The port number could be
anything between 1025 and 65535, as long as the server and the client use the same
port. Port numbers between 1 and 1024 are reserved for standard services and
should not be used for other servers. The name or IP number of the computer on
which the server is running can be specified as a command-line argument. For
example, if the server is running on a computer named math.hws.edu, then you
could run the client with the command "<code>java DateClient math.hws.edu</code>".
If a computer is not specified on the command line, then the user is prompted
to enter one.  Here is the complete client program:</p>

<pre>import java.net.*;
import java.util.Scanner;
import java.io.*;

/**
 * This program opens a connection to a computer specified
 * as the first command-line argument.  If no command-line
 * argument is given, it prompts the user for a computer
 * to connect to.  The connection is made to
 * the port specified by LISTENING_PORT.  The program reads one
 * line of text from the connection and then closes the
 * connection.  It displays the text that it read on
 * standard output.  This program is meant to be used with
 * the server program, DataServer, which sends the current
 * date and time on the computer where the server is running.
 */
public class DateClient {

    public static final int LISTENING_PORT = 32007;

    public static void main(String[] args) {

        String hostName;         // Name of the server computer to connect to.
        Socket connection;       // A socket for communicating with server.
        BufferedReader incoming; // For reading data from the connection.

        /* Get computer name from command line. */

        if (args.length > 0)
            hostName = args[0];
        else {
            Scanner stdin = new Scanner(System.in);
            System.out.print("Enter computer name or IP address: ");
            hostName = stdin.nextLine();
        }

        /* Make the connection, then read and display a line of text. */

        try {
            connection = new Socket( hostName, LISTENING_PORT );
            incoming = new BufferedReader( 
                             new InputStreamReader(connection.getInputStream()) );
            String lineFromServer = incoming.readLine();
            if (lineFromServer == null) {
                    // A null from incoming.readLine() indicates that
                    // end-of-stream was encountered.
                throw new IOException("Connection was opened, " + 
                        "but server did not send any data.");
            }
            System.out.println();
            System.out.println(lineFromServer);
            System.out.println();
            incoming.close();
        }
        catch (Exception e) {
            System.out.println("Error:  " + e);
        }

    }  // end main()


} //end class DateClient</pre>

<p>Note that all the communication with the server is done in a
<code>try..catch</code> statement. This will catch the <classname>IOExceptions</classname> 
that can be
generated when the connection is opened or closed and when data is read
from the input stream. The connection's input stream is wrapped
in a <classname>BufferedReader</classname>,
which has a <code>readLine()</code> method that makes it easy to read
one line of text.  (See <localref href="IO.1.4"/>.)</p>

<p>In order for this program to run without error, the server program must be
running on the computer to which the client tries to connect. By the way, it's
possible to run the client and the server program on the same computer. For
example, you can open two command windows, start the server in one window and
then run the client in the other window. To make things like this easier, most
computers will recognize the domain name <code>localhost</code>
and the IP number <code>127.0.0.1</code> as referring to "this
computer." This means that the command "<code>java DateClient localhost</code>" will tell
the <classname>DateClient</classname> program to connect to a server running on the same
computer.  If that command doesn't work, try "<code>java DateClient 127.0.0.1</code>".</p>

<p>The server program that corresponds to the <classname>DateClient</classname> client
program is called <classname>DateServer</classname>. The <classname>DateServer</classname> program creates a
<classname>ServerSocket</classname> to listen for connection requests on port 32007. After
the listening socket is created, the server will enter an infinite loop in
which it accepts and processes connections. This will continue until the
program is killed in some way&mdash;for example by typing a <code>CONTROL-C</code> in the
command window where the server is running. When a connection request is received from
a client, the server calls a subroutine to handle the connection. In the
subroutine, any <classname>Exception</classname> that occurs is caught, so that it will not
crash the server. Just because a connection to one client has failed for some reason, it does not
mean that the server should be shut down; the error might have been the fault of the
client.  The connection-handling subroutine creates a <classname>PrintWriter</classname> for
sending data over the connection. It writes the current date and time to this
stream and then closes the connection. (The standard class
<code>java.util.Date</code> is used to obtain the current time. An object of type
<classname>Date</classname> represents a particular date and time. The default constructor,
"<code>new&nbsp;Date()</code>", creates an object that represents the time when the
object is created.) The complete server program is as follows:</p>

<pre>import java.net.*;
import java.io.*;
import java.util.Date;

/**
 * This program is a server that takes connection requests on
 * the port specified by the constant LISTENING_PORT.  When a
 * connection is opened, the program sends the current time to
 * the connected socket.  The program will continue to receive
 * and process connections until it is killed (by a CONTROL-C,
 * for example).  Note that this server processes each connection
 * as it is received, rather than creating a separate thread
 * to process the connection.
 */
public class DateServer {

    public static final int LISTENING_PORT = 32007;

    public static void main(String[] args) {

        ServerSocket listener;  // Listens for incoming connections.
        Socket connection;      // For communication with the connecting program.

        /* Accept and process connections forever, or until some error occurs.
           (Note that errors that occur while communicating with a connected 
           program are caught and handled in the sendDate() routine, so
           they will not crash the server.) */

        try {
            listener = new ServerSocket(LISTENING_PORT);
            System.out.println("Listening on port " + LISTENING_PORT);
            while (true) {
                    // Accept next connection request and handle it.
                connection = listener.accept(); 
                sendDate(connection);
            }
        }
        catch (Exception e) {
            System.out.println("Sorry, the server has shut down.");
            System.out.println("Error:  " + e);
            return;
        }

    }  // end main()


    /**
     * The parameter, client, is a socket that is already connected to another 
     * program.  Get an output stream for the connection, send the current time, 
     * and close the connection.
     */
    private static void sendDate(Socket client) {
        try {
            System.out.println("Connection from " +  
                    client.getInetAddress().toString() );
            Date now = new Date();  // The current date and time.
            PrintWriter outgoing;   // Stream for sending data.
            outgoing = new PrintWriter( client.getOutputStream() );
            outgoing.println( now.toString() );
            outgoing.flush();  // Make sure the data is actually sent!
            client.close();
        }
        catch (Exception e){
            System.out.println("Error: " + e);
        }
    } // end sendDate()


} //end class DateServer</pre>

<p>When you run <classname>DateServer</classname> in a command-line interface, it will sit and
wait for connection requests and report them as they are received. To make the
<classname>DateServer</classname> service permanently available on a computer, the program
would be run as a <newword>daemon</newword>. A daemon is a
program that runs continually on a computer, independently of any user. The
computer can be configured to start the daemon automatically as soon as the
computer boots up. It then runs in the background, even while the computer is
being used for other purposes. For example, a computer that makes pages
available on the World Wide Web runs a daemon that listens for requests for web
pages and responds by transmitting the pages. It's just a souped-up analog of
the <classname>DateServer</classname> program! However, the question of how to set up a
program as a daemon is not one I want to go into here. For testing purposes,
it's easy enough to start the program by hand, and, in any case, my examples
are not really robust enough or full-featured enough to be run as serious
servers. (By the way, the word "daemon" is just an alternative spelling of
"demon" and is usually pronounced the same way.)</p>

<p>Note that after calling <code>outgoing.println()</code> to send a line of data to the
client, the server program calls <code>outgoing.flush()</code>. The <code>flush()</code>
method is available in every output stream class. Calling it ensures that data
that has been written to the stream is actually sent to its destination. You
should generally call this function every time you use an output stream to send data over
a network connection. If you don't do so, it's possible that the stream will
collect data until it has a large batch of data to send. This is done for
efficiency, but it can impose unacceptable delays when the client is waiting
for the transmission. It is even possible that some of the data might remain
untransmitted when the socket is closed, so it is especially important to call
<code>flush()</code> before closing the connection. This is one of those
unfortunate cases where different implementations of Java can behave
differently. If you fail to flush your output streams, it is possible that your
network application will work on some types of computers but not on others.</p>
   
</subsection>
   
<subsection id="IO.4.5" title="A Simple Network Chat">

<p>In the <classname>DateServer</classname> example, the server transmits information and the
client reads it. It's also possible to have two-way communication between
client and server. As a first example, we'll look at a client and server that
allow a user on each end of the connection to send messages to the other user.
The program works in a command-line interface where the users type in their
messages. In this example, the server waits for a connection from a single
client and then closes down its listener so that no other clients can connect.
After the client and server are connected, both ends of the connection work in
much the same way. The user on the client end types a message, and it is
transmitted to the server, which displays it to the user on that end. Then the
user of the server types a message that is transmitted to the client. Then the
client user types another message, and so on. This continues until one user or
the other enters "quit" when prompted for a message. When that happens, the
connection is closed and both programs terminate. The client program and the
server program are very similar. The techniques for opening the connections
differ, and the client is programmed to send the first message while the server
is programmed to receive the first message. The client and server programs
can be found in the files <sourceref href="CLChatClient.java"/> and
<sourceref href="CLChatServer.java"/>.   (The name "CLChat" stands
for "command-line chat.")  Here is the source code for the
server; the client is similar:</p>

<pre>import java.net.*;
import java.util.Scanner;
import java.io.*;

/**
 * This program is one end of a simple command-line interface chat program.
 * It acts as a server which waits for a connection from the CLChatClient 
 * program.  The port on which the server listens can be specified as a 
 * command-line argument.  If it is not, then the port specified by the
 * constant DEFAULT_PORT is used.  Note that if a port number of zero is 
 * specified, then the server will listen on any available port.
 * This program only supports one connection.  As soon as a connection is 
 * opened, the listening socket is closed down.  The two ends of the connection
 * each send a HANDSHAKE string to the other, so that both ends can verify
 * that the program on the other end is of the right type.  Then the connected 
 * programs alternate sending messages to each other.  The client always sends 
 * the first message.  The user on either end can close the connection by 
 * entering the string "quit" when prompted for a message.  Note that the first 
 * character of any string sent over the connection must be 0 or 1; this
 * character is interpreted as a command.
 */
public class CLChatServer {

    /**
     * Port to listen on, if none is specified on the command line.
     */
    static final int DEFAULT_PORT = 1728;

    /**
     * Handshake string. Each end of the connection sends this  string to the 
     * other just after the connection is opened.  This is done to confirm that 
     * the program on the other side of the connection is a CLChat program.
     */
    static final String HANDSHAKE = "CLChat";

    /**
     * This character is prepended to every message that is sent.
     */
    static final char MESSAGE = '0';

    /**
     * This character is sent to the connected program when the user quits.
     */
    static final char CLOSE = '1';


    public static void main(String[] args) {

        int port;   // The port on which the server listens.

        ServerSocket listener;  // Listens for a connection request.
        Socket connection;      // For communication with the client.

        BufferedReader incoming;  // Stream for receiving data from client.
        PrintWriter outgoing;     // Stream for sending data to client.
        String messageOut;        // A message to be sent to the client.
        String messageIn;         // A message received from the client.

        Scanner userInput;        // A wrapper for System.in, for reading
                                  // lines of input from the user.

        /* First, get the port number from the command line,
            or use the default port if none is specified. */

        if (args.length == 0) 
            port = DEFAULT_PORT;
        else {
            try {
                port= Integer.parseInt(args[0]);
                if (port &lt; 0 || port &gt; 65535)
                    throw new NumberFormatException();
            }
            catch (NumberFormatException e) {
                System.out.println("Illegal port number, " + args[0]);
                return;
            }
        }

        /* Wait for a connection request.  When it arrives, close
           down the listener.  Create streams for communication
           and exchange the handshake. */

        try {
            listener = new ServerSocket(port);
            System.out.println("Listening on port " + listener.getLocalPort());
            connection = listener.accept();
            listener.close();  
            incoming = new BufferedReader( 
                    new InputStreamReader(connection.getInputStream()) );
            outgoing = new PrintWriter(connection.getOutputStream());
            outgoing.println(HANDSHAKE);  // Send handshake to client.
            outgoing.flush();
            messageIn = incoming.readLine();  // Receive handshake from client.
            if (! HANDSHAKE.equals(messageIn) ) {
                throw new Exception("Connected program is not a CLChat!");
            }
            System.out.println("Connected.  Waiting for the first message.");
        }
        catch (Exception e) {
            System.out.println("An error occurred while opening connection.");
            System.out.println(e.toString());
            return;
        }

        /* Exchange messages with the other end of the connection until one side
           or the other closes the connection.  This server program waits for 
           the first message from the client.  After that, messages alternate 
           strictly back and forth. */

        try {
            userInput = new Scanner(System.in);
            System.out.println("NOTE: Enter 'quit' to end the program.\n");
            while (true) {
                System.out.println("WAITING...");
                messageIn = incoming.readLine();
                if (messageIn.length() > 0) {
                        // The first character of the message is a command. If 
                        // the command is CLOSE, then the connection is closed.  
                        // Otherwise, remove the command character from the 
                        // message and proceed.
                    if (messageIn.charAt(0) == CLOSE) {
                        System.out.println("Connection closed at other end.");
                        connection.close();
                        break;
                    }
                    messageIn = messageIn.substring(1);
                }
                System.out.println("RECEIVED:  " + messageIn);
                System.out.print("SEND:      ");
                messageOut = userInput.nextLine();
                if (messageOut.equalsIgnoreCase("quit"))  {
                        // User wants to quit.  Inform the other side
                        // of the connection, then close the connection.
                    outgoing.println(CLOSE);
                    outgoing.flush();  // Make sure the data is sent!
                    connection.close();
                    System.out.println("Connection closed.");
                    break;
                }
                outgoing.println(MESSAGE + messageOut);
                outgoing.flush(); // Make sure the data is sent!
                if (outgoing.checkError()) {
                    throw new IOException("Error occurred while transmitting message.");
                }
            }
        }
        catch (Exception e) {
            System.out.println("Sorry, an error has occurred.  Connection lost.");
            System.out.println("Error:  " + e);
            System.exit(1);
        }

    }  // end main()



} //end class CLChatServer
</pre>

<p>This program is a little more robust than <classname>DateServer</classname>. For one thing,
it uses a <newword>handshake</newword> to make sure that a client who
is trying to connect is really a <classname>CLChatClient</classname> program. A handshake is
simply information sent between a client and a server as part of setting up a
connection, before any actual data is sent.
In this case, each side of the connection sends a string to the
other side to identify itself. The handshake is part of the <newword>protocol</newword> 
that I made up for communication between
<classname>CLChatClient</classname> and <classname>CLChatServer</classname>. 
A protocol is a detailed specification of what data and messages can be exchanged
over a connection, how they must be represented, and what order they can be
sent in.  When you design a
client/server application, the design of the protocol is an important
consideration. Another aspect of the <code>CLChat</code> protocol is that after the handshake, every
line of text that is sent over the connection begins with a
character that acts as a command. If the character is 0, the rest of the line
is a message from one user to the other. If the character is 1, the line
indicates that a user has entered the "quit" command, and the connection is to
be shut down.</p>

<p>Remember that if you want to try out this program on a single computer, you
can use two command-line windows. In one, give the command "<code>java CLChatServer</code>"
to start the server. Then, in the other, use the command "<code>java CLChatClient
localhost</code>" to connect to the server that is running on the same machine.
Note that if you run <classname>CLChatClient</classname> without specifying a
computer on the command line, then you will be asked to type in the name or
IP address of the server computer.</p>
   

</subsection>

</section>
