<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE exercises SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<exercises>

<exercise>
<exercise-question><p>Rewrite the <classname>PhoneDirectory</classname> class
from <localref href="arrays.4.2"/> so that it uses a <classname>TreeMap</classname>
to store directory entries, instead of an array.  (Doing this was suggested
in <localref href="generics.3.1"/>.)  You should also write a short program
to test the class.</p>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss><p>The class that you are asked to write for this exercise
really is very trivial.  Everything that the class needs to do is already done
by the <classname>TreeMap</classname> class, and <classname>TreeMap</classname>
does much more besides.  In fact the only reason to write the <classname>PhoneDirectory</classname>
class is to <b>hide</b> a lot of the capabilities of <classname>TreeMaps</classname>.
A <classname>PhoneDirectory</classname> object is a "thin wrapper" around a <classname>TreeMap</classname>
object.  It allows only the operations <code>getNumber(name)</code> and
<code>putNumber(name,number)</code>.  Each of these can be implemented in a single line,
as a call to one of the methods in the <classname>TreeMap</classname>.  The
<classname>PhoneDirectory</classname> does provide nice, meaningful names
for the methods, and it adds a check to the implementation of <code>putNumber(name,number)</code>
to ensure that <code>name</code> and <code>number</code> are not <code>null</code>.</p>
<p>It would be nice for phone directories to have a few more capabilities.  A method for
listing the contents of the directory would be especially nice, so I have added one
to my class even though there was no such method in the original <classname>PhoneDirectory</classname>
class.  The print method uses a for-each loop to iterate through the entry set of
the phone directory. It is very similar to examples in <localref href="generics.3.2"/>
Even with this addition, though, the <classname>PhoneDirectory</classname> class is
still very far from being useful in real applications.</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="PhoneDirectoryWithTreeMap">import java.util.Map;
import java.util.TreeMap;

/**
 * A phone directory holds a list of names with a phone number for
 * each name.  It is possible to find the number associated with
 * a given name, and to specify the phone number for a given name.
 * (This version of the class uses a TreeMap to store the data.)
 */
public class PhoneDirectoryWithTreeMap {


/**
 * The TreeMap that will store the data.  Both key and value are
 * of type String.  The key represents a name and the value represents
 * the associated phone number.
 */
private TreeMap&lt;String,String&gt; data;
   
   
   /**
    * Constructor creates an initially empty directory.
    */
   public PhoneDirectoryWithTreeMap() {
      data = new TreeMap&lt;String,String&gt;();
   }
   
   
   /**
    * Finds the phone number, if any, for a given name.
    * @return The phone number associated with the name; if the name does
    *    not occur in the phone directory, then the return value is null.
    */
   public String getNumber( String name ) {
         return data.get(name);
   }

   
   /**
    * Associates a given name with a given phone number.  If the name
    * already exists in the phone directory, then the new number replaces
    * the old one.  Otherwise, a new name/number pair is added.  The
    * name and number should both be non-null.  An IllegalArgumentException
    * is thrown if this is not the case.
    */
   public void putNumber( String name, String number ) {
      if (name == null || number == null)
          throw new IllegalArgumentException("name and number cannot be null");
      data.put(name,number);
   }
   
   
   /**
    *  Write the contents of the phone directory to System.out.
    */
   public void print() {
      for ( Map.Entry&lt;String,String&gt; entry : data.entrySet() )
         System.out.println( entry.getKey() + ":  " + entry.getValue() );
   }

} // end class PhoneDirectoryWithTreeMap

</prog></pre>

<p>Here is a very small program to test the class:</p>

<pre><prog name="TestPhoneDirectoryWithTreeMap">
public class TestPhoneDirectoryWithTreeMap {

   public static void main(String[] args) {
       PhoneDirectoryWithTreeMap directory = new PhoneDirectoryWithTreeMap();
       System.out.println("This program creates a PhoneDirectoryWithTreeMap and");
       System.out.println("adds several entries.  It then prints the contents of");
       System.out.println("directory and does a few lookups.");
       System.out.println();
       directory.putNumber("Fred","555-1234");
       directory.putNumber("Barney","555-2345");
       directory.putNumber("Wilma","555-3456");
       System.out.println("Contents are:");
       System.out.println();
       directory.print();
       System.out.println();
       System.out.println("Number for Fred is " + directory.getNumber("Fred"));
       System.out.println("Number for Wilma is " + directory.getNumber("Wilma"));
       System.out.println("Number for Tom is " + directory.getNumber("Tom"));
          // The output from the last line should be null.
   }

}
</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>
   

   
<exercise id="generics.ex.2">
<exercise-question><p>In mathematics, several
operations are defined on sets. The <newword>union</newword> of two
sets A and B is a set that contains all the elements that are in A together
with all the elements that are in B. The <newword>intersection</newword> 
of A and B is the set that contains elements that
are in both A and B. The <newword>difference</newword> of A and B is
the set that contains all the elements of A <b>except</b> for those elements
that are also in&nbsp;B.</p>

<p>Suppose that <code>A</code> and <code>B</code> are variables of type <code>set</code> in
Java. The mathematical operations on <code>A</code> and <code>B</code> can be computed
using methods from the <classname>Set</classname> interface. In particular: 
<code>A.addAll(B)</code> computes the <i>union</i> of <code>A</code> and <code>B</code>;
<code>A.retainAll(B)</code> computes the <i>intersection</i> of <code>A</code> and
<code>B</code>; and <code>A.removeAll(B)</code> computes the <i>difference</i> of <code>A</code>
and <code>B</code>. (These operations change the contents of the set <code>A</code>,
while the mathematical operations create a new set without changing <code>A</code>,
but that difference is not relevant to this exercise.)</p>

<p>For this exercise, you should write a program that can be used as a "set
calculator" for simple operations on sets of non-negative integers. (Negative
integers are not allowed.) For input and output, a set of such integers will be written as a list
of integers, separated by commas and, optionally, spaces and enclosed in square
brackets. For example: <code>[1,2,3]</code> or
<code>[17,&nbsp;42,&nbsp;9,&nbsp;53,&nbsp;108]</code>. The characters <code>+</code>,
<code>*</code>, and <code>-</code> will be used for the union, intersection, and
difference operations. The user of the program will type in lines of input
containing two sets, separated by an operator. The program should perform the
operation and print the resulting set. Here are some examples:</p>

<pre>          Input                                 Output
         -------------------------           -------------------
          [1, 2, 3] + [3,  5,  7]             [1, 2, 3, 5, 7]
          [10,9,8,7] * [2,4,6,8]              [8]
          [ 5, 10, 15, 20 ] - [ 0, 10, 20 ]   [5, 15]</pre>

<p>To represent sets of non-negative integers, use 
sets of type <classname>TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;</classname>. Read the user's input,
create two <classname>TreeSets</classname>, and use the appropriate <classname>TreeSet</classname> method
to perform the requested operation on the two sets. Your program should be able
to read and process any number of lines of input. If a line contains a syntax
error, your program should not crash. It should report the error and move on to
the next line of input. (Note: To print out a <classname>Set</classname>, <code>A</code>, of
<classname>Integers</classname>, you can just say <code>System.out.print(A)</code>. I've chosen
the syntax for sets to be the same as that used by the system for outputting a
set.)</p>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss><p>This program would be <b>much</b> easier to write if we could assume that
the user's input was in the correct format. Unfortunately, the exercise says
that we have to detect errors in the user's input and handle them by printing
error messages. To do this we have to constantly look ahead while reading the
user's input, to see whether the input agrees with what we are expecting. The
techniques for doing this were covered for the example 
<sourceref chapter="8" href="LengthConverter2.java"/> from <localref href="robustness.2.2"/>.
We can use the function <code>TextIO.peek()</code>
to look ahead at the next character in the user's input. We need to be able
to skip past any blanks in the input.  Instead of writing my own method to do
that, I use the method <code>TextIO.skipBlanks()</code> in my program.</p>


<p>My program uses exceptions to handle
the errors. Exceptions make it possible to organize the error-handling code in
a straightforward way. When an error is discovered, an exception is thrown. The
main program uses a <code>try..catch</code> statement to try to process one line
of input. If an error occurs, the program does not crash. The error is caught,
an error message is printed, and the program continues. I throw an error of
type <classname>IllegalArgumentException</classname> when an error is found. This exception
is a standard part of Java, but it might be better style to define a new error
class to represent the specific type of error that occurs in this program.</p>

<p>My program uses a method named <code>calc()</code> to read and process one line
of input. This method in turn uses another method, <code>readSet()</code> to read
each of the two sets of integers from the input line. Without error handling,
an algorithm for <code>readSet()</code> would be:</p>

<pre>Start with an empty set.
Read the '[' that begins the set.
Repeat:
   Read the next number and add it to the set.
   If the next character is ']':
      break.
   Read the comma that separates one number from the next.
Read the ']'.
Return the set.</pre>

<np>To turn this into a robust routine, we just have to check, before reading
anything, that the next character is legal. If not, throw an exception. This
adds a lot of code, but the nice thing about throwing exceptions is that it
doesn't disturb the logical flow of the routine.</np>

<p>There is one possible bug in the algorithm as given. It assumes that there is at
least one number in the set. But in mathematics, a set can be empty. I decided
to allow for the possibility of empty sets in my program. See the solution,
below.</p>

<p>An algorithm for the <code>calc()</code> method is even more straightforward.
Again, the basic algorithm ignores the possibility of errors:</p>

<pre>Read the first set, A.
Read the operator.
Read the second set, B.
if the operator is '+'
   A.addAll(B)  // Sets A equal to the union of A and B.
else if the operator is '*'
   A.retainAll(B)  // Sets A to the intersection.
else
   A.removeAll(B)  // Sets A to the difference.
Print A.</pre>

<np>In the program, an error check has to be added to make sure that there is a legal operator
in the correct position. I also add an error check to make sure that there is
no extra data on the line.</np>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre>
<prog name="SetCalc">import textio.TextIO;
import java.util.TreeSet;


/**
 * This program is a very simple "set calculator" that can compute
 * the intersection, union, and set difference of two sets of 
 * non-negative integers.  Each line of the user's input contains two 
 * such sets, separated by one of the operators +, *, or -, standing
 * for union, intersection, and set difference respectively.  A set
 * must be given in the form of a list of non-negative integers, separated
 * by commas, and enclosed in square brackets.  For example:
 * [1, 2, 3] + [4, 3, 10, 0].  Spaces can occur anywhere in the input.
 * If an error is found in the input, the program will report it.
 * The program ends when the user inputs an empty line.
 *
 * This program is mainly a demonstration of Sets.
 */


public class SetCalc {

   public static void main(String[] args) {

      System.out.println("This program will compute union, intersection,");
      System.out.println("and set difference of sets of integers.");
      System.out.println("");
      System.out.println("");
      System.out.println("Enter set computations (press return to end):");

      while (true) {
         char ch;
         System.out.print("\n? ");
         TextIO.skipBlanks();
         if (TextIO.peek() == '\n') {
               // The input line is empty.  
               // Exit the loop and end the program.
            break;
         }
         try {
            calc(); // Reads and processes one line of input.
         }
         catch (IllegalArgumentException e) {
               // An error was found in the input line.
            System.out.println("Error in input: " + e.getMessage());
         }
         TextIO.getln();  // Read and discard the rest of the line.
                          // If there was no error, the only thing that
                          // is discarded is the end-of-line character.
      }

   } // end main()


   /**
    * Read a line of input, consisting of two sets separated by
    * an operator.  Perform the operation and output the value.
    * If any syntax error is found in the input, an
    * IllegalArgumentException is thrown
    */
   private static void calc() {

      TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt; A, B;  // The two sets of integers.
      char op;                // The operator, +, *, or -.

      A = readSet(); // Read the first set.

      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      if (TextIO.peek() != '*' &amp;&amp; TextIO.peek() != '+' 
                                         &amp;&amp; TextIO.peek() != '-')
         throw new IllegalArgumentException(
         "Expected *, +, or  - after first set.");
      op = TextIO.getAnyChar(); // Read the operator.

      B = readSet(); // Read the second set.

      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      if (TextIO.peek() != '\n')
         throw new IllegalArgumentException("Extra unexpected input.");

      // Perform the operation.  This modifies set A to represent
      // the answer.  Display the answer by printing out A. The
      // output format for a set of integers is the same as the
      // input format used by this program.

      if (op == '+')
         A.addAll(B);     // Union.
      else if (op == '*')
         A.retainAll(B);  // Intersection.
      else
         A.removeAll(B);  // Set difference.
      
      System.out.print("Value:  " + A);

   } // end calc()


   /**
    * Reads a set of non-negative integers from standard input,
    * and stores them in a TreeSet that contains objects belonging
    * to the wrapper class Integer.  The set must be enclosed
    * between square brackets and must contain a list of zero or
    * more non-negative integers, separated by commas.  Spaces 
    * are allowed anywhere.  If the input is not of the correct
    * form, an IllegalArgumentException is thrown.
    */
   private static TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt; readSet() {

      TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt; set = new TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;();  // The set that will be read.

      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      if (TextIO.peek() != '[')
         throw new IllegalArgumentException("Expected '[' at start of set.");
      TextIO.getAnyChar(); // Read the '['.

      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      if (TextIO.peek() == ']') {
            // The set has no integers.  This is the empty set, which
            // is legal.  Return the value.
         TextIO.getAnyChar(); // Read the ']'.
         return set;
      }

      while (true) {
            // Read the next integer and add it to the set.
         TextIO.skipBlanks();
         if (! Character.isDigit(TextIO.peek()))
            throw new IllegalArgumentException("Expected an integer.");
         int n = TextIO.getInt(); // Read the integer.
         set.add( Integer.valueOf(n) );  // (Could have just said set.add(n)!)
         TextIO.skipBlanks();
         if (TextIO.peek() == ']')
            break;  // ']' marks the end of the set.
         else if (TextIO.peek() == ',')
            TextIO.getAnyChar(); // Read a comma and continue.
         else
            throw new IllegalArgumentException("Expected ',' or ']'.");
      }

      TextIO.getAnyChar(); // Read the ']' that ended the set.

      return set;

   } // end readSet()


} // end class SetCalc
</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>
   
   
<exercise>
<exercise-question><p>The fact that Java has a
<classname>HashMap</classname> class means that no Java programmer has to write an
implementation of hash tables from scratch&mdash;unless, of course, that programmer is a
computer science student.</p>
<p>For this exercise, you should write a hash table in which both the keys and the values are of
type <classname>String</classname>.  (This is not an exercise in generic programming;
do not try to write a generic class.)
Write an implementation of hash tables from scratch. Define the following
methods: <code>get(key)</code>, <code>put(key,value)</code>, <code>remove(key)</code>,
<code>containsKey(key)</code>, and <code>size()</code>. 
Remember that every object, <code>obj</code>, has a method <code>obj.hashCode()</code>
that can be used for computing a hash code for the object,
so at least you don't have to define your own hash function. 
Do not use <b>any</b> of Java's built-in generic types; create your own linked
lists using nodes as covered in <localref href="recursion.2.2"/>.  However,
you are <b>not</b> required to increase the size of the table when
it becomes too full.</p>
<p>You should also write a short program to test your solution.</p>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss><p>Hash tables are discussed in <localref href="generics.3.3"/>.
A hash table is just an array of linked lists. Each linked list holds all
the items in the table that share the same hash code. Initially, all the lists
are empty (represented as <code>null</code> in the array). We need to be able to
add and delete items in the list. Methods for inserting and deleting
items can be found in <localref href="recursion.2.2"/>.
In a hash table, the order of items in a particular
list doesn't matter, so I simply insert each new item at the beginning of the
list. This makes the insert operation fairly simple. Deletion, however, is more
complicated, since we need to be able to delete an item no matter where it
occurs in a list.</p>

<p>A hash table really contains pairs of items, where each pair consists of a
key and an associated value.  To implement this, I use linked lists in which
each node contains both a key 
and a value, as well as the pointer to the next node in the list. The
end of a list is marked, as usual, by a <code>null</code> pointer. The nodes are
defined by a static nested class:</p>

<pre>private static class ListNode {
   String key;
   String value;
   ListNode next;
}</pre>

<np>The array of linked lists that stores all the data is of type
<atype>ListNode[]</atype>. Each item in the array is either <code>null</code> to indicate
an empty list, or it is a pointer to the first node in a linked list.</np>

<p>Given any key, we can find the linked list that should contain that key by
looking at the hash code of the key. The code computed by calling
<code>key.hashCode()</code>, which returns a value of type <ptype>int</ptype>. We need a value that is in the
range of legal indices for the array. As noted in <localref href="generics.3.3"/>,
the value can be computed as <code>Math.abs(key.hashCode())&nbsp;%&nbsp;table.length</code>, 
where <code>table</code> is the array.</p>

<p>The hash code is used in all the methods that deal with keys, to decide which
linked list to look at. Once a list has been selected, the operations on the
list are pretty straightforward (given all the information and code in <localref href="recursion.2.2"/>), 
so I will not discuss them further here. You can look at the solution, below.</p>

<p>Although it is not required by the exercise, I defined a <code>resize()</code>
method that is used to increase the size of the table when the table becomes
too full. I call this method in the <code>put()</code> method when the table
becomes more than 3/4 full.  The hash table class has an instance variable, <code>count</code>, that
is equal to the number of items in the array, so it only necessary to check the value of
<code>count</code> when deciding to increase the array size.  Having <code>count</code>
is also important for implementing the <code>size()</code> method efficiently, since
<code>size()</code> can simply return <code>count</code> as its return value.</p>

<p>(By the way, the statement that "<code>count</code> is equal to the number of items
in the array"" is a class invariant for the <classname>HashTable</classname> class.
(See <localref href="robustness.2.3"/>.)
It is important that all of the methods in the class maintain the truth of this
class invariant.")</p>

<p>A major part of developing a class for general use is testing. It's
important to design a testing procedure that will test all aspects of the
class. For this problem, I wrote a testing program that would allow me to test
each of the methods in the class. I also added a method <code>dump()</code> to the
class; this method displays the entire hash table. This method does not really belong
in the class, since users of a hash table shouldn't care how the data is
stored. But I needed it to make sure that my <code>resize()</code> method is
working properly and that I could delete items correctly from all positions in
the lists (beginning, middle, and end).</p>
   
<p>By the way, you might be tempted to try to write a generic version of
<classname>HashTable</classname> in which the types of the keys and values are
given as type parameters in the definition of the class.  Unfortunately, you
would run into problems as soon as you tried to use an array in your class.
Generic classes don't work well with arrays, because arrays of generic type
can't be created at run time, as noted in <localref href="generics.1.3"/>.</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code><p><b><u>The HashTable Class</u></b></p>
<pre><prog name="HashTable">/**
 * This file defines a HashTable class.  Keys and values in the table are of 
 * type String.  Keys cannot be null.  The default constructor creates a table 
 * that initially has 64 locations, but a different initial size can be specified 
 * as a parameter to the constructor.  The table increases in size if it 
 * becomes more than 3/4 full.
 */
public class HashTable {

   /**
    * Keys that have the same hash code are placed together in a linked list.  
    * This private nested class is used internally to implement linked lists.  
    * A ListNode holds a (key,value) pair.  
    */
   private static class ListNode {
      String key;
      String value;
      ListNode next;  // Pointer to next node in the list;
                      // A null marks the end of the list.
   }

   private ListNode[] table;  // The hash table, represented as
                              // an array of linked lists.

   private int count;  // The number of (key,value) pairs in the
                       // hash table.

   
   /**
    * Create a hash table with an initial size of 64.
    */
   public HashTable() {
      table = new ListNode[64];
   }

   
   /**
    * Create a hash table with a specified initial size.
    * Precondition: initalSize &gt; 0.
    */
   public HashTable(int initialSize) {
      if (initialSize &lt;= 0)
         throw new IllegalArgumentException("Illegal table size");
      table = new ListNode[initialSize];
   }

   
   /**
    * This method is NOT part of the usual interface for a hash table.  
    * It is here only to be used for testing purposes, and should be 
    * removed before the class is released for general use.  This 
    * lists the (key,value) pairs in each location of the table.
    */
   void dump() {
      System.out.println();
      for (int i = 0; i &lt; table.length; i++) {
             // Print out the location number and the list of
             // key/value pairs in this location.
         System.out.print(i + ":");
         ListNode list = table[i]; // For traversing linked list number i.
         while (list != null) {
            System.out.print("  (" + list.key + "," + list.value + ")");
            list = list.next;
         }
         System.out.println();
      }
   } // end dump()

   
   /**
    * Associate the specified value with the specified key.
    * Precondition:  The key is not null.
    */
   public void put(String key, String value) {
      
      assert key != null : "The key must be non-null";
      
      int bucket = hash(key); // Which location should this key be in?
      
      ListNode list = table[bucket]; // For traversing the linked list
                                     // at the appropriate location.
      while (list != null) {
            // Search the nodes in the list, to see if the key already exists.
         if (list.key.equals(key))
            break;
         list = list.next;
      }
      
      // At this point, either list is null, or list.key.equals(key).
      
      if (list != null) {
            // Since list is not null, we have found the key.
            // Just change the associated value.
         list.value = value;
      }
      else {
             // Since list == null, the key is not already in the list.
             // Add a new node at the head of the list to contain the
             // new key and its associated value.
         if (count &gt;= 0.75*table.length) {
               // The table is becoming too full.  Increase its size
               // before adding the new node.
            resize();
            bucket = hash(key);  // Recompute hash code, since it
                                 // depends on the table size.
         }
         ListNode newNode = new ListNode();
         newNode.key = key;
         newNode.value = value;
         newNode.next = table[bucket];
         table[bucket] = newNode;
         count++;  // Count the newly added key.
      }
   }

   
   /**
    * Retrieve the value associated with the specified key in the table, 
    * if there is any.  If not, the value null will be returned.
    * @param key The key whose associated value we want to find
    * @return the associated value, or null if there is no associated value
    */
   public String get(String key) {
      
      int bucket = hash(key);  // At what location should the key be?
      
      ListNode list = table[bucket];  // For traversing the list.
      while (list != null) {
            // Check if the specified key is in the node that
            // list points to.  If so, return the associated value.
         if (list.key.equals(key))
            return list.value;
         list = list.next;  // Move on to next node in the list.
      }
      
      // If we get to this point, then we have looked at every
      // node in the list without finding the key.  Return
      // the value null to indicate that the key is not in the table.
      
      return null;  
   }

   
   /**
    * Remove the key and its associated value from the table,
    * if the key occurs in the table.  If it does not occur,
    * then nothing is done.
    */
   public void remove(String key) {  
      
      int bucket = hash(key);  // At what location should the key be?
      
      if (table[bucket] == null) {
            // There are no keys in that location, so key does not
            // occur in the table.  There is nothing to do, so return.
         return; 
      }
      
      if (table[bucket].key.equals(key)) {
            // If the key is the first node on the list, then
            // table[bucket] must be changed to eliminate the
            // first node from the list.
         table[bucket] = table[bucket].next;
         count--; // Remove new number of items in the table.
         return;
      }
      
      // We have to remove a node from somewhere in the middle
      // of the list, or at the end.  Use a pointer to traverse
      // the list, looking for a node that contains the
      // specified key, and remove it if it is found.
      
      ListNode prev = table[bucket];  // The node that precedes
                                      // curr in the list.  Prev.next
                                      // is always equal to curr.
      ListNode curr = prev.next;  // For traversing the list,
                                  // starting from the second node.
      while (curr != null &amp;&amp; ! curr.key.equals(key)) {
         curr = curr.next;
         prev = curr;
      }
      
      // If we get to this point, then either curr is null,
      // or curr.key is equal to key.  In the latter case,
      // we have to remove curr from the list.  Do this
      // by making prev.next point to the node after curr,
      // instead of to curr.  If curr is null, it means that
      // the key was not found in the table, so there is nothing
      // to do.
      
      if (curr != null) {
         prev.next = curr.next;
         count--;  // Record new number of items in the table.
      }
   }

   
   /**
    * Test whether the specified key has an associated value in the table.
    * @param key The key that we want to search for.
    * @return true if the key exists in the table, false if not
    */
   public boolean containsKey(String key) {
      
      int bucket = hash(key);  // In what location should key be?
      
      ListNode list = table[bucket];  // For traversing the list.
      while (list != null) {
            // If we find the key in this node, return true.
         if (list.key.equals(key))
            return true;
         list = list.next;
      }
      
      // If we get to this point, we know that the key does
      // not exist in the table.
      
      return false;
   }

   
   /**
    * Return the number of key/value pairs in the table.
    */
   public int size() {
      return count;
   }


   /**
    * Compute a hash code for the key; key cannot be null.
    * The hash code depends on the size of the table as
    * well as on the value returned by key.hashCode().
    */
   private int hash(Object key) {
      return (Math.abs(key.hashCode())) % table.length;
   }

   
   /**
    * Double the size of the table, and redistribute the
    * key/value pairs to their proper locations in the
    * new table.
    */
   private void resize() {
      ListNode[] newtable = new ListNode[table.length*2];
      for (int i = 0; i &lt; table.length; i++) {
             // Move all the nodes in linked list number i into the new table.  
             // No new ListNodes are created.  The existing ListNode for each
             // key/value pair is moved to the newtable.  This is done by 
             // changing the "next" pointer in the node and by making a pointer 
             // in the new table point to the node.
         ListNode list = table[i]; // For traversing linked list number i.
         while (list != null) {
               // Move the node pointed to by list to the new table.
            ListNode next = list.next;  // The is the next node in the list.
               // Remember it, before changing the value of list!
            int hash = (Math.abs(list.key.hashCode())) % newtable.length;
               // hash is the hash code of list.key that is 
               // appropriate for the new table size.  The
               // next two lines add the node pointed to by list
               // onto the head of the linked list in the new table
               // at position number hash.
            list.next = newtable[hash];
            newtable[hash] = list;
            list = next;  // Move on to the next node in the OLD table.
         }
      }
      table = newtable;  // Replace the table with the new table.
   } // end resize()
   

} // end class HashTable

</prog></pre>
<p><b><u>A Class for Testing:</u></b></p>
<pre>
<prog name="TestHashTable">import textio.TextIO;

/**
 * A little program to test the HashTable class.  Note that I
 * start with a really small table so that I can easily test
 * the resize() method.
 */

public class TestHashTable {

   public static void main(String[] args){
      HashTable table = new HashTable(2);  // Initial size of table is 2.
      String key,value;
      while (true) {
         System.out.println("\nMenu:");
         System.out.println("   1. test put(key,value)");
         System.out.println("   2. test get(key)");
         System.out.println("   3. test containsKey(key)");
         System.out.println("   4. test remove(key)");
         System.out.println("   5. show complete contents of hash table.");
         System.out.println("   6. EXIT");
         System.out.print("Enter your command:  ");
         switch ( TextIO.getlnInt()) {
         case 1:
            System.out.print("\n   Key = ");
            key = TextIO.getln();
            System.out.print("   Value = ");
            value = TextIO.getln();
            table.put(key,value);
            break;         
         case 2:
            System.out.print("\n   Key = ");
            key = TextIO.getln();
            System.out.println("   Value is " + table.get(key));
            break;         
         case 3:
            System.out.print("\n   Key = ");
            key = TextIO.getln();
            System.out.println("   containsKey(" + key + ") is " 
                  + table.containsKey(key));
            break;         
         case 4:
            System.out.print("\n   Key = ");
            key = TextIO.getln();
            table.remove(key);
            break;         
         case 5:
            table.dump();
            break;
         case 6:
            return;  // End program by returning from main()         
         default:
            System.out.println("   Illegal command.");
         break;
         }
         System.out.println("\nHash table size is " + table.size());
      }
   }

} // end class TestHashTable
</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>
   

<exercise>
<exercise-question><p>A <newword>predicate</newword> is a boolean-valued function with one parameter.
Java has the parameterized functional interface <atype>Predicate&lt;T&gt;</atype>,
from package <code>java.util.function</code>,
to represent predicates.  The definition of <atype>Predicate&lt;T&gt;</atype> could be:</p>

<pre>public interface Predicate&lt;T&gt; {
    public boolean test( T obj );
}</pre>

<p>The idea is that an object that implements this interface knows how to
"test" objects of type <classname>T</classname>
in some way.   Java already has some methods that use predicates, such as the
<code>removeIf(p)</code> method that is defined for any <classname>Collection</classname>.
(See <localref href="generics.6.1"/>).  However, this exercise asks you to write
a few similar methods yourself.  Define a class that contains 
the following generic static methods for working with predicate objects.
The name of the class should be <classname>Predicates</classname>, in analogy
with the standard class <classname>Collections</classname> that provides various
<code>static</code> methods for working with collections.  You should
<b>not</b> use the stream API for this exercise.</p>

<pre>public static &lt;T&gt; void remove(Collection&lt;T&gt; coll, Predicate&lt;T&gt; pred)
   // Remove every object, obj, from coll for which pred.test(obj) 
   // is true.  (This does the same thing as coll.removeIf(pred).)
   
public static &lt;T&gt; void retain(Collection&lt;T&gt; coll, Predicate&lt;T&gt; pred)
   // Remove every object, obj, from coll for which
   // pred.test(obj) is false.  (That is, retain the
   // objects for which the predicate is true.)
   
public static &lt;T&gt; List&lt;T&gt; collect(Collection&lt;T&gt; coll, Predicate&lt;T&gt; pred)
   // Return a List that contains all the objects, obj,
   // from the collection, coll, such that pred.test(obj)
   // is true.
   
public static &lt;T&gt; int find(ArrayList&lt;T&gt; list, Predicate&lt;T&gt; pred)
   // Return the index of the first item in list
   // for which the predicate is true, if any.
   // If there is no such item, return -1.</pre>
   
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss><p>The code for this exercise is pretty short, but it
involves some advanced ideas, including methods with bounded type parameters
(from <localref href="generics.5.4"/>).  Aside from that,
the main point of the exercise is to work with predicates and to see how they are
useful in generic programming. The operation of finding all the items in a
collection that satisfy some condition is very common. The code to do it is not
hard to write, but even so, it is nice to have it done once and for all. In this
exercise, the condition that the items have to satisfy is represented as a
<classname>Predicate</classname>. The <code>collect()</code> method provides a general way to
find all the items that satisfy the condition. The items, in this case,
are to be dumped into a <classname>List</classname>.</p>

<p>The implementation of the <code>collect()</code> method simply uses a
for-each loop to go through the collection, <code>coll</code>, and puts every
item that satisfies the predicate into a list. The method returns an object of
type <classname>List</classname>, but <classname>List</classname> is only an interface. Any real list must
belong to one of the classes that implement this interface, such as
<classname>LinkedList</classname> or <classname>ArrayList</classname>. I create the list as an
<classname>ArrayList</classname>, but a <classname>LinkedList</classname> would also be reasonable.</p>

<pre>/**
 * Return a List that contains all the objects, obj, from the collection, 
 * coll, for which pred.test(obj) is true.
 */
public static &lt;T&gt; List&lt;T&gt; collect(Collection&lt;T&gt; coll, Predicate&lt;T&gt; pred) {
   List&lt;T&gt; list = new ArrayList&lt;T&gt;();
   for ( T item : coll ) {
      if (pred.test(item))
         list.add(item);
   }
   return list;
} // end collect()</pre>

<p>The <code>remove()</code> and <code>retain()</code> methods are similar to
<code>collect()</code>, except that instead of making a new collection, they modify
the collection, <code>coll</code>.  A for-each loop cannot modify the collection
over which it is iterating, so the <code>remove()</code> and <code>retain()</code> methods
will have to use <classname>Iterators</classname>.  Recall that if <code>iter</code>
is an <classname>Iterator</classname> for a collection, then the method
<code>iter.remove()</code> will remove from the collection the item that was seen
most recently by the iterator.  The <code>remove()</code> method can be written
as:</p>
   
<pre>/**
 * Remove every object, obj, from coll for which pred.test(obj) is true.
 */
public static &lt;T&gt; void remove(Collection&lt;T&gt; coll, Predicate&lt;T&gt; pred) {
   Iterator&lt;T&gt; iter = coll.iterator();
   while (iter.hasNext()) {
      T item = iter.next();
      if (pred.test(item))
         iter.remove();
   }
} // end remove()</pre>
   
<np>The <code>retain()</code> method is almost identical to this, and the
<code>find()</code> method is easy to write using an ordinary <code>for</code>
loop.  See my solution, below.</np>

<p>If you look at the documentation for <atype>Predicate&lt;T&gt;</atype>,
you will see that it defines a method <code>negate()</code>.  (It is defined
in the interface as a <code>default</code> method.  A functional interface can
only define one abstract method, but it can define additional methods if they are
default methods.)  If <code>pred</code>
is a predicate, then <code>pred.negate()</code> that is true when pred is false
and is false when pred is true.  This means that <code>retain()</code> could
actually be defined simply as</p>

<pre>public static &lt;T&gt; void retain(Collection&lt;T&gt; coll, Predicate&lt;T&gt; pred) {
    remove( coll, pred.negate() );
}</pre>

<p>My test program creates some collections and applies the methods from
the <classname>Predicates</classname> class to them. My collections contain objects of type
<classname>Integer</classname> and I made two <classname>Predicates</classname> that work on objects of
this type. One way to create such a predicate is to write a class that implements the interface
<classname>Predicate&lt;Integer&gt;</classname>, and then to make an object belonging to
that class. For example, I could have defined the class:</p>

<pre>/**
 * An object of type Even tests an Object of type Integer to see whether the 
 * integer that it represents is an even number. Note that the test() method 
 * should only be applied to non-null values of type Integer.
 */
static class Even implements Predicate&lt;Integer&gt; {
   public boolean test(Integer i) {
      if ( i % 2 == 0 )
         return true;
      else
         return false;
   }
} // end class Even</pre>

<np>The predicate object could then created with a command:</np>

<pre>Predicate&lt;Integer&gt; pred = new Even():</pre>

<np>But of course, it is also possible to define the
predicate more simply as a lambda expression:</np>

<pre>Predicate&lt;Integer&gt; pred = i -> (i % 2 == 0);</pre>

<np>or, of course, we could simply use the lambda expression
at the point where the predicate is needed.  For example:</np>

<pre>result = Predicates.collect(coll, i -&gt; (i % 2 == 0) )</pre>

<np>I hope that you can see how using the lambda expression simpliies
the code quite a bit!</np>

</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
   
<p><b><u>The Predicates Class:</u></b></p>

<pre><prog name="Predicates">import java.util.Collection;
import java.util.Iterator;
import java.util.ArrayList;
import java.util.List;
import java.util.function.Predicate;

/**
 * This class defines some static methods for working
 * with Collections and Predicates.  (The Predicate
 * interface is NOT a standard part of Java.)
 */
public class Predicates {

   
   /**
    * Remove every object, obj, from coll for which pred.test(obj) is true.
    */
   public static &lt;T&gt; void remove(Collection&lt;T&gt; coll, Predicate&lt;T&gt; pred) {
      Iterator&lt;T&gt; iter = coll.iterator();
      while (iter.hasNext()) {
         T item = iter.next();
         if (pred.test(item))
            iter.remove();
      }
   } // end remove()

   
   /**
    * Remove every object, obj, from coll for which pred.test(obj) is false.  
    * (That is, retain the objects for which the predicate is true.)
    */
   public static &lt;T&gt; void retain(Collection&lt;T&gt; coll, Predicate&lt;T&gt; pred){
      Iterator&lt;T&gt; iter = coll.iterator();
      while (iter.hasNext()) {
         T item = iter.next();
         if ( ! pred.test(item) )
            iter.remove();
      }
   } // end retain()
   
   
   /**
    * Return a List that contains all the objects, obj, from the collection, 
    * coll, for which pred.test(obj) is true.
    */
   public static &lt;T&gt; List&lt;T&gt; collect(Collection&lt;T&gt; coll, Predicate&lt;T&gt; pred) {
      List&lt;T&gt; list = new ArrayList&lt;T&gt;();
      for ( T item : coll ) {
         if (pred.test(item))
            list.add(item);
      }
      return list;
   } // end collect()

   
   /**
    * Return the index of the first item in list for which the predicate is true, if any.
    * If there is no such item, return -1.
    */
   public static &lt;T&gt; int find(ArrayList&lt;T&gt; list, Predicate&lt;T&gt; pred) {
      // 
      for (int i = 0; i &lt; list.size(); i++) {
         T item = list.get(i);
         if (pred.test(item))
            return i;
      }
      return -1;
   } // end find()

   
} // end class Predicates

</prog></pre>
   
<p><b><u>The Test program:</u></b></p>
   
<pre>
<prog name="TestPredicates">import java.util.*;
import java.util.function.Predicate;

/**
 * Perform some simple tests on the Predicates class.
 */
public class TestPredicates {

   /**
    * For convenience make a Collection containing some integers.  The Collection 
    * is actually a TreeSet, but that is not relevant to the main program.
    */
   static Collection&lt;Integer&gt; makeSet() {
      Collection&lt;Integer&gt; set = new TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;();
      set.add(Integer.valueOf(32));
      set.add(Integer.valueOf(17));
      set.add(Integer.valueOf(142));
      set.add(Integer.valueOf(56));
      set.add(Integer.valueOf(1899));
      set.add(Integer.valueOf(57));
      set.add(Integer.valueOf(999));
      set.add(Integer.valueOf(86));
      set.add(Integer.valueOf(83));
      set.add(Integer.valueOf(100));
      return set;
   } // end makeSet()

   /**
    * Main routine tests the Predicates class by making Collections of Integers 
    * and applying the methods from the Predicates class to them.
    */
   public static void main(String[] args) {

      Collection&lt;Integer&gt; coll;    // A collection (from makeSet() method).

      List&lt;Integer&gt; result;        // The result of applying collect() to coll.

      Predicate&lt;Integer&gt; pred = i -> (i % 2 == 0);  // Tests if an Integer is even.

      coll = makeSet();
      System.out.println("Original collection: " + coll);

      Predicates.remove(coll,pred);
      System.out.println("Remove evens: " + coll);

      coll = makeSet();
      Predicates.retain(coll,pred);
      System.out.println("Retain evens: " + coll);

      coll = makeSet();
      result = Predicates.collect(coll,pred);
      System.out.println("Collect evens: " + result);

      ArrayList&lt;Integer&gt; list = new ArrayList&lt;Integer&gt;();
      int i = Predicates.find(list,pred);
      System.out.println("Find first even: at index " + i);


      pred = n -> (n > 100);        // Tests if an Integer is bigger than 100.

      coll = makeSet();
      System.out.println("Original collection: " + coll);

      Predicates.remove(coll,pred);
      System.out.println("Remove big: " + coll);

      coll = makeSet();
      Predicates.retain(coll,pred);
      System.out.println("Retain big: " + coll);

      coll = makeSet();
      result = Predicates.collect(coll,pred);
      System.out.println("Collect big: " + result);

      list = new ArrayList&lt;Integer&gt;(coll);
      i = Predicates.find(list,pred);
      System.out.println("Find first big: at index " + i);

   } // end main()

} // end class TestPredicates
</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<exercise-question><p>This is a short exercise in using the stream API. 
Suppose that the class <classname>Score</classname> is defined as</p>

<pre>class ScoreInfo {
    String firstName;
    String lastName;
    int score;
    Score( String lName, String fName, int s ) {
        firstName = fName;
        lastName = lName;
        score = s;
    }
}</pre>

<np>and that <code>scoreData</code> is an array of <classname>ScoreInfos</classname>
containing information about the scores of students on a test.
Use the stream API to do each of the following tasks:</np>
<ul>
<li>print the number of students (without using <code>scoreData.length</code>)</li>
<li>print the average score for all of the students</li>
<li>print the number of students who got an A (score greater than or equal to 90)</li>
<li>use the <code>collect()</code> stream operation to create 
    a <classname>List&lt;String&gt;</classname> that contains the names of students whose score was less than 70;
    the names should be in the form first name followed by last name</li>
<li>print the names from the <classname>List</classname> that was generated in the previous task</li>
<li>print out the student's names and scores, ordered last name</li>
<li>print out the student's names and scores, ordered by score</li>
</ul>
<np>You can put all of the code in <code>main()</code> routine and include
<classname>ScoreInfo</classname> as a <code>static</code> nested class.
Do not use <b>any</b> for loops or other control structures.  Do everything
using the stream API.  For testing your code, you can use this array:</np>

<pre>private static ScoreInfo[] scoreData = new ScoreInfo[] {
        new Score("Smith","John",70),
        new Score("Doe","Mary",85),
        new Score("Page","Alice",82),
        new Score("Cooper","Jill",97),
        new Score("Flintstone","Fred",66),
        new Score("Rubble","Barney",80),
        new Score("Smith","Judy",48),
        new Score("Dean","James",90),
        new Score("Russ","Joe",55),
        new Score("Wolfe","Bill",73),
        new Score("Dart","Mary",54),
        new Score("Rogers","Chris",78),
        new Score("Toole","Pat",51),
        new Score("Khan","Omar",93),
        new Score("Smith","Ann",95)
};</pre>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss><p>In each case, to process the values from the array using the stream 
API, we need to make a stream containing those values.  That's done by calling
<code>Arrays.stream(scoreData)</code>.  From there, we just need to apply the
appropriate stream operators to get the desired results.  I have added some
comments on each of the assigned tasks to the program.</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="StreamTest">import java.util.List;
import java.util.Arrays;
import java.util.stream.Collectors;

/**
 * This program tests the stream API by doing various computations.
 */
public class StreamTest {

    /**
     * Data for one student about a score on a test.
     */
    private static class ScoreInfo {
        String firstName;
        String lastName;
        int score;
        ScoreInfo( String lName, String fName, int s ) {
            firstName = fName;
            lastName = lName;
            score = s;
        }
    }
    
    /**
     * A test array of StudentInfo that will be used to create streams.
     */
    private static ScoreInfo[] scoreData = new ScoreInfo[] {
            new ScoreInfo("Smith","John",70),
            new ScoreInfo("Doe","Mary",85),
            new ScoreInfo("Page","Alice",82),
            new ScoreInfo("Cooper","Jill",97),
            new ScoreInfo("Flintstone","Fred",66),
            new ScoreInfo("Rubble","Barney",80),
            new ScoreInfo("Smith","Judy",48),
            new ScoreInfo("Dean","James",90),
            new ScoreInfo("Russ","Joe",55),
            new ScoreInfo("Wolfe","Bill",73),
            new ScoreInfo("Dart","Mary",54),
            new ScoreInfo("Rogers","Chris",78),
            new ScoreInfo("Toole","Pat",51),
            new ScoreInfo("Khan","Omar",93),
            new ScoreInfo("Smith","Ann",95)
    };
        
    
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        
        /* The number of students can be computed simply by applying
         * the .count() operation to a stream created from the array. */
        
        long count = Arrays.stream(scoreData).parallel().count();
        System.out.println("Number of students: " + count);
        
        /* To get the average, use the .sum() operation, and divide by count. */
        
        int total = Arrays.stream(scoreData).parallel()
                              .mapToInt( s -> s.score )
                              .sum();
        System.out.printf("Average grade:  %1.2f%n", (double)total/count );
        
        /* To get the number of students who got an A, first filter the
         * stream letting through only students who satisfy the
         * predicate  s -> s.score >= 90.  This predicate returns true
         * only for students whose score is greater than or equal to 90.
         * The number is then computed by applying .count() to the 
         * resulting stream. */
        
        long countA = Arrays.stream(scoreData).parallel()
                   .filter( s -> s.score >= 90 )
                   .count();
        System.out.println("Number who got an A: " + countA);
        System.out.println();
        
        /* To get a list of names of students who failed, first filter
         * the stream to let through only ScoreInfo objects with score
         * less than 70.  Since we want the names of students, we need
         * to convert the stream of ScoreInfo objects into a stream
         * of strings by applying a mapping operation.  Then applying
         * .collect(Collectors.toList()) produces the List that we need. */

        List&lt;String> failing = Arrays.stream(scoreData)
                                          .filter( s -> (s.score &lt; 70) )
                                          .map( s -> (s.firstName + " " + s.lastName) )
                                          .collect( Collectors.toList() );
        
        /* Now we need to print the list, which can easily be done with
         * a for-each loop.  However, it can also be done using .forEach()
         * operation on a stream.  In this case, the String Consumer in the
         * .forEach() operation is given as the method reference 
         * System.out::println.  That is, it is the println() method in the
         * object System.out.  This method reference is the same as writing
         * the lambda expression  s -> System.out.println(s).  */
        
        System.out.println("Failing students: ");
        failing.stream().forEach( System.out::println );
        System.out.println();
        
        /* To print the data ordered by last name, apply the .sorted() operation
         * to sort the values in the stream by last name, then use .forEach()
         * to output the information from each ScoreInfo object in the stream. 
         * The .sorted() operation takes a parameter that is a Comparator for
         * comparing two values from the stream.  In this case, we just
         * compare the lastNames from two ScoreInfo objects, using the standard
         * compareTo() method for Strings. */
        
        System.out.println("Data sorted by last name:");
        Arrays.stream(scoreData)
             .sorted( (s1,s2) -> s1.lastName.compareTo(s2.lastName) )
             .forEach( s -> System.out.printf(
                                 "  %s, %s: %d%n", s.lastName, s.firstName, s.score) );
        System.out.println();
        
        /* The data can be output ordered by score in the same way, using a
         * different comparator in the .sorted() operation. */
        
        System.out.println("Data sorted by score:");
        Arrays.stream(scoreData)
             .sorted( (s1,s2) -> s1.score - s2.score )
             .forEach( s -> System.out.printf(
                                 "  %s, %s: %d%n", s.lastName, s.firstName, s.score) );
        
    }
    
} // end StreamTest
</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>
   
   
<exercise id="generics.ex.5">
<exercise-question><p>An example in
<localref href="generics.4.2"/> concerns the problem of making an index for
a book. A related problem is making a <newword>concordance</newword>
for a document. A concordance lists every word that occurs in the document, and
for each word it gives the line number of every line in the document where the
word occurs. All the subroutines for creating an index that were presented in
<localref href="generics.4.2"/> can also be used to create a concordance. The only real
difference is that the integers in a concordance are line numbers rather than
page numbers.</p>

<p>Write a program that can create a concordance. The document should be read
from an input file, and the concordance data should be written to an output
file. You can use the indexing
subroutines from <localref href="generics.4.2"/>, modified to write the data to <code>TextIO</code>
instead of to <code>System.out</code>. (You will need to make these subroutines
<code>static</code>.) The input and output files should be selected by the user when
the program is run.  The sample program <sourceref href="WordCount.java"/>,
from <localref href="generics.4.4"/>, can be used as a model of how to use files.
That program also has a useful subroutine that reads one word from input.</p>

<p>As you read the file, you want to take each word that you encounter and add
it to the concordance along with the current line number.  Keeping track of
the line numbers is one of the trickiest parts of the problem. In an input file,
the end of each line in the file is
marked by the newline character,&nbsp;'\n'. Every time you encounter this
character, you have to add one to the line number.  WordCount.java
ignores ends of lines.  Because you need to
find and count the end-of-line characters, your program cannot
process the input file in exactly the same way as does WordCount.java.
Also, you will need to detect the end of the file.  The function
<code>TextIO.peek()</code>, which is used to look ahead at the next character
in the input, returns the value <code>TextIO.EOF</code> at end-of-file,
after all the characters in the file have been read.</p>

<p>Because it is so common, don't include the word "the" in your concordance.
Also, do not include words that have length less than&nbsp;3.</p>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss><p>Solving this exercise, for the most part, means collecting subroutines that
were presented in <localref href="generics.4.2"/> into a complete program. 
I copied the method <code>addReference()</code> directly, just making it <code>static</code>
and changing the names of the parameters to names that are more appropriate for
a concordance. I copied <code>printIntegers()</code>, changed its name
to <code>printConcordance</code>, made it static, and changed
"System.out.print" to "TextIO.put" so that it would send its output to the file
selected by the user.</p>
   
<p>In <localref href="generics.4.3"/>, I discussed the problem that arises when
comparing strings that differ only in their use of upper and lower case.  In that
subsection, I used a <classname>Comparator</classname> to solve the problem.
In my solution to this exercise, however, I used the simpler solution of
converting all words to lower case immediately after reading them from the
file.  For lower case words, the default ordering is alphabetical order,
so I don't need a <classname>Comparator</classname>.</p>

<p>It remains to write the <code>main()</code> routine, which is similar in outline
to the <code>main()</code> routine in <code>WordCount.java</code>. One difference is
that we have to keep track of line numbers. We can do this by looking for
new-line characters as we skip over the characters between words. 
While we do this, we have to be on the alert for the special character
<code>TextIO.EOF</code> that is returned by <code>TextIO.peek()</code>
when the end of the file is reached.  A pseudocode algorithm can be given as:</p>

<pre>Open the input files.

Let lineNum = 1.

Repeat:
   
      // Skip over any non-letters in the input, stopping when a
      // letter (marking the beginning of a word) or EOF is found.
      
      while the next character is not end-of-file or a letter:
         Read the next character.
         If it is a new line character:
            Count the line by adding 1 to lineNum
      
      // After the while loop, we are looking at either the end of file
      //    or at a letter that is the beginning of the next word.
      
      If at end-of-file:
         Exit from the loop.
      
      Get the next word from the input file.
      Convert the word to lower case.
      if the word is not "the" and has length &gt; 2:
         Add the word and lineNum to the concordance.

Open the output file.

Print the concordance.</pre>


<p>This can be translated directly (using some code from <sourceref href="WordCount.java"/>)
to give the <code>main()</code> routine.   For reading individual words from
input, the method <code>readNextWord()</code> can be copied directly from
WordCount.java.  (In my program, I used a slightly simpler method named
<code>readWord()</code> which uses the fact that when <code>readWord()</code>
is called by the <code>main()</code> routine, the next character in input
is already known to be a letter.)</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="Concordance">import textio.TextIO;

import java.util.Map;
import java.util.TreeMap;
import java.util.TreeSet;

/**
 * This program makes a concordance for a file.  A concordance
 * lists all the words that occur in the file, along with all
 * the line numbers on which each word occurs.  (Words of
 * length less than 3 are omitted, and "the" is omitted.)  The
 * concordance is written to an output file.  The user selects
 * the input and output files using file dialog boxes.  This
 * program uses the non-standard class, TextIO.
 */
public class Concordance {



/**
 * This TreeMap holds the concordance.  Words from the file
 * are used as keys in the map.  The value associated with
 * each word is a set that contains the line numbers on which
 * the word occurs in the file.  The set contains values
 * belonging to the wrapper class, Integer.
 */
private static TreeMap&lt;String, TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;&gt;  concordance;



public static void main(String[] args) {

   System.out.println("\n\n   This program will ask you to select an input file.");
   System.out.println("It makes a list of all the words that occur in the file");
   System.out.println("along with the line number of each line that contained");
   System.out.println("that word.  This is called a \"concordance\" for the file.");
   System.out.println("   After reading the input file, the program asks you to");
   System.out.println("select an output file.  If you select a file, the list of");
   System.out.println("words will be written to that file; if you cancel, the list");
   System.out.println("be written to standard output.  All words are converted to");
   System.out.println("lower case.\n\n");
   System.out.print("Press return to begin.");
   
   TextIO.getln();  // Wait for user to press return.
   
   try {
      
      // Let user select the input file.  If the user cancels,
      // the program ends immediately.
  
      if (TextIO.readUserSelectedFile() == false) {
         System.out.println("No input file selected.  Exiting.");
         System.exit(0);
      }
         
      // Create the data structure that will hold the concordance.
 
      concordance = new TreeMap&lt;String, TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;&gt;();
  
      int lineNum = 1;  // The number of the line in the input
                        // file that is currently being processed.
      
      // Read words from the file until end of file is reached,
      // and add each word to the data.

      while (true) {
         char ch = TextIO.peek(); // Look ahead at next character
         while ( ch != TextIO.EOF &amp;&amp; ! Character.isLetter(ch) ) {
                   // Skip over non-letter characters, stopping when 
                   // end-of-file (TextIO.EOF) or a letter is seen.  If the
                   // character is an end-of-line character, add 1
                   // to lineNum to reflect the fact that we are moving
                   // on to the next line in the file.
            TextIO.getAnyChar();  // Reads the next character, which is junk.
            if (ch == '\n') {
               lineNum++;  // Start of a new line.
            }
            ch = TextIO.peek();  // Look at the next character.
         }
         if (ch == TextIO.EOF) {
                 // The end-of-file has been reached, so exit from the loop.
            break;
         }
         String word = readWord();  // The next word from the file.
         word = word.toLowerCase();
         if (word.length() > 2  &amp;&amp; !word.equalsIgnoreCase("the")) {
                 // Add the reference to word to the concordance, unless
                 // the word is "the" or the word has length &lt;= 2.
            addReference(word,lineNum);
         }
      }
      
      // Write the data to a user-selected file, or to standard
      // output if the user does not select an output file.

      System.out.println(concordance.size() + " distinct words were found in the file.\n");
      System.out.println();
      if (concordance.size() == 0) {
         System.out.println("No words found in file.");
         System.out.println("Exiting without saving data.");
         System.exit(0);
      }

      TextIO.writeUserSelectedFile(); // If user cancels, output automatically
                                      // goes to standard output.
  
      printConcordance();  // Print the data to the output file.
 
   }
   catch (IllegalArgumentException e) {
      System.out.println( "Sorry, some error occurred:  " + e.getMessage() );
   }

} // end main()


/**
 * Writes the data in the concordance to TextIO.  (The output will go
 * to the output file, if one has been selected; otherwise, it will go
 * to standard output.)  Each line of output contains one word from the
 * file and a list of lines on which that word occurred.  The words
 * are in alphabetical order.
 */
private static void printConcordance() {
   
   for ( Map.Entry&lt;String, TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;&gt;  entry :  concordance.entrySet() ) {
    
      String term = entry.getKey();
      TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt; pageSet = entry.getValue();

      TextIO.put( term + " " );
      for ( int page : pageSet ) {
         TextIO.put( page + " " );
      }
      TextIO.putln();
   
    }
}


/**
 * Add a word reference to the concordance.
 */
private static void addReference(String word, int lineNum) {
   TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt; references; // The set of lines where we have
                                //    previously found the word.
   references = concordance.get(word);
   if (references == null){
          // This is the first reference that we have
          // found for the word.  Make a new set containing
          // the line number and add it to the concordance, with
          // the word as the key.
       TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt; firstRef = new TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;();
       firstRef.add( lineNum );  // lineNum is "autoboxed" to give an Integer!
       concordance.put(word,firstRef);
   }
   else {
         // The variable references is the set of line references
         // that we have found previously for the word.
         // Add the new line number to that set.  This
         // set is already associated to word in the concordance.
      references.add( lineNum ); // pageNum is "autoboxed" to give an Integer!
   }
}


/**
 * Read the next word from TextIO.  It is assumed that the next character
 * in input is a letter.
 *    A word is defined as a sequence of letters.  Also, a word can include
 * an apostrophe if the apostrophe is surrounded by letters on each side.
 * @return the next word from TextIO, or null if an end-of-file is encountered
 */
private static String readWord() {
   char ch = TextIO.peek(); // Look at next character in input.
   assert Character.isLetter(ch);
   String word = "";  // This will be the word that is read.
   while (true) {
      word += TextIO.getAnyChar();  // Append the letter onto word.
      ch = TextIO.peek();  // Look at next character.
      if ( ch == '\'' ) {
             // The next character is an apostrophe.  Read it, and
             // if the following character is a letter, add both the
             // apostrophe and the letter onto the word and continue
             // reading the word.  If the character after the apostrophe
             // is not a letter, the word is done, so break out of the loop.
         TextIO.getAnyChar();   // Read the apostrophe.
         ch = TextIO.peek();    // Look at char that follows apostrophe.
         if (Character.isLetter(ch)) {
            word += "\'" + TextIO.getAnyChar();
            ch = TextIO.peek();  // Look at next char.
         }
         else
            break;
      }
      if ( ! Character.isLetter(ch) ) {
             // If the next character is not a letter, the word is
             // finished, so break out of the loop.
         break;
      }
      // If we haven't broken out of the loop, next char is a letter.
   }
   return word;  // Return the word that has been read.
}


} // end class Concordance
</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>
   
   
<exercise>
<exercise-question><p>The sample program
<sourceref href="SimpleInterpreter.java"/> from <localref href="generics.4.1"/>
can carry out  commands of the form "let variable = expression" or "print expression".
That program can handle expressions that contain variables,
numbers, operators, and parentheses. Extend the program so that it can also
handle the standard mathematical functions <code>sin</code>, <code>cos</code>,
<code>tan</code>, <code>abs</code>, <code>sqrt</code>, and <code>log</code>. For example, the
program should be able to evaluate an expression such as
<code>sin(3*x-7)+log(sqrt(y))</code>, assuming that the variables <code>x</code> and
<code>y</code> have been given values.  Note that the name of a function
must be followed by an expression that is enclosed in parentheses.</p>

<p>In the original program, a symbol table holds a value for each variable that
has been defined. In your program, you should add another type of symbol to the
table to represent standard functions.   You can use the following nested
enumerated type and class for this purpose:</p>

<pre>private enum Functions { SIN, COS, TAN, ABS, SQRT, LOG }

/**
 * An object of this class represents one of the standard functions.
 */
private static class StandardFunction {

   /**
    * Tells which function this is.
    */
   Functions functionCode; 

   /**
    * Constructor creates an object to represent one of 
    * the standard functions
    * @param code which function is represented.
    */
   StandardFunction(Functions code) {
      functionCode = code;
   }

   /**
    * Finds the value of this function for the specified 
    * parameter value, x.
    */
   double evaluate(double x) {
      switch(functionCode) {
      case SIN:
         return Math.sin(x);
      case COS:
         return Math.cos(x);
      case TAN:
         return Math.tan(x);
      case ABS:
         return Math.abs(x);
      case SQRT:
         return Math.sqrt(x);
      default:
         return Math.log(x);
      }
   }

} // end class StandardFunction</pre>
   
<p>Add a symbol to the symbol table to represent each function. The key is the
name of the function and the value is an object of type
<classname>StandardFunction</classname> that represents the function. For example:</p>

<pre>symbolTable.put("sin", new StandardFunction(Function.SIN));</pre>

<np>In SimpleInterpreter.java, the symbol table is a map of type
<classname>HashMap&lt;String,Double&gt;</classname>.  It's not legal to
use a <classname>StandardFunction</classname> as the value in such a map,
so you will have to change the type of the map.  The map has to hold two
different types of objects.  The easy way to make this possible is to create
a map of type <classname>HashMap&lt;String,Object&gt;</classname>.
(A better way is to create a general type to represent objects that
can be values in the symbol table, and to define two subclasses of that
class, one to represent variables and one to represent standard functions,
but for this exercise, you should do it the easy way.)</np>

<p>In your parser, when you encounter a word, you have to be able to tell
whether it's a variable or a standard function. Look up the word in the symbol
table. If the associated object is non-null and is of type <classname>Double</classname>, then
the word is a variable. If it is of type <classname>StandardFunction</classname>, then the
word is a function. Remember that you can test the type of an object using the
<code>instanceof</code> operator. For example: <code>if (obj instanceof Double)</code>.</p>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss><p>The changes that must be made to <sourceref href="SimpleInterpreter.java"/> 
are remarkably small,
aside from defining the <classname>StandardFunction</classname> class. In my solution, I
included this class as a static nested class in my main program class. It would
also make sense to define it as a separate class.</p>

<p>I changed the type of the map to <classname>HashMap&lt;String,Object&gt;</classname>,
as suggested in the exercise.
I added a few lines of code at the beginning of the <code>main()</code> routine to
add the six standard functions to the symbol table, using statements similar to
the example given in the exercise:</p>
   
<pre>symbolTable.put("sin", new StandardFunction(Functions.SIN));
symbolTable.put("cos", new StandardFunction(Functions.COS));
symbolTable.put("tan", new StandardFunction(Functions.TAN));
symbolTable.put("abs", new StandardFunction(Functions.ABS));
symbolTable.put("sqrt", new StandardFunction(Functions.SQRT));
symbolTable.put("log", new StandardFunction(Functions.LOG));</pre>
      
<p>The only other change is in the parsing routines. 
The change is in the <code>primaryValue()</code> method. When a word
is encountered, the computer must check whether the word is a variable or a
standard function. This is done, as suggested in the exercise, by looking up
the word in the symbol table and checking the type of the associated value. If
the word is a standard function, then we have to read and evaluate the argument
of the function and then find the value of the function at that argument value:</p>

<pre>else if ( Character.isLetter(ch) ) {
      // The factor is a variable <newcode>or a standard function</newcode>.  Read its name and
      // look up its value in the symbol table.  If the name is not in the symbol table,
      // an error occurs.  (Note that the values in the symbol table are objects of type 
      // Double <newcode>or StandardFunction</newcode>.)
   String name = readWord();
   <newcode>Object obj = symbolTable.get(name);</newcode>
   if (obj == null)
      throw new ParseError("Unknown word \"" + name + "\"");
   <newcode>assert (obj instanceof Double || obj instanceof StandardFunction);</newcode>
   <newcode>if (obj instanceof Double)</newcode> {
         // The name is a variable; return value of that variable.
      Double val = (Double)obj;
      return val.doubleValue();
   }
   <newcode>else {
         // The name is a standard function.  Read the argument
         // of the function and return the value of the function
         // at that argument.  The argument must be an expression
         // in parentheses.
      StandardFunction func = (StandardFunction)obj;
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      if ( TextIO.peek() != '(' )
         throw new ParseError("Parenthesis missing after standard function");
      TextIO.getChar(); // discard the '('
      double argument = expressionValue();  // read and evaluate expression
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      if ( TextIO.peek() != ')' )
         throw new ParseError("Missing right parenthesis.");
      TextIO.getChar(); // discard the ')'
      return func.evaluate(argument);
   }</newcode>
}</pre>

<p>There is one additional change that I might have made. As the program
stands, it allows the user to use a "let" command to assign a value to one of
the standard function names. For example: "let sin = 42". This effectively
changes the name so that it is a variable, and the standard function is no
longer available for use in expressions. It would probably be better to give an error
message when the user tries to assign a value to a standard function name. This
could be done in the <code>doLetCommand()</code> method.  After reading the
variable name in the "let" command, we have to check whether the name is already
in the symbol table as the name of a standard function:</p>

<pre>private static void doLetCommand() throws ParseError {
   TextIO.skipBlanks();
   if ( ! Character.isLetter(TextIO.peek()) )
      throw new ParseError("Expected variable name after 'let'.");
   String varName = readWord();  // The name of the variable.
   <newcode>Object symbol = symbolTable.get(name);            
   if (symbol != null &amp;&amp; symbol instanceof StandardFunction)
       throw new ParseError("Can't assign a value to a standard function name.");</newcode>
   TextIO.skipBlanks();
   if ( TextIO.peek() != '=' )
      throw new ParseError("Expected '=' operator for 'let' command.");
   TextIO.getChar();
   double val = expressionValue();  // The value of the variable.
   TextIO.skipBlanks();
   if ( TextIO.peek() != '\n' )
      throw new ParseError("Extra data after end of expression.");
   symbolTable.put( varName, val );  // Add to symbol table.
   System.out.println("ok");
}</pre>
   

</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
   
<p><b>Changes from the program <sourceref href="SimpleInterpreter.java"/>
are shown in &newcodestyle;.</b></p>
   
<pre><prog name="SimpleInterpreter2">import textio.TextIO;

/*
    This program can evaluate expressions that can include
    numbers, variables, parentheses, and the operators +,
    -, *, /, and ^ (where ^ indicates raising to a power),
    <newcode>and standard functions sin, cos, tan, abs, sqrt, and log.</newcode>
    A variable name must consist of letters and digits,
    beginning with a letter.  Names are case-sensitive.
    This program accepts commands of two types from the user.
    For a command of the form  print &lt;expression&gt; , the expression
    is evaluated and the value is output.  For a command of
    the form  let &lt;variable&gt; = &lt;expression&gt; , the expression is
    evaluated and the value is assigned to the variable.
    If a variable is used in an expression before it has been
    assigned a value, an error occurs.  A number must begin with 
    a digit (i.e., not a decimal point).

    Commands are formally defined by the BNF rules:

            &lt;command&gt;  ::=  "print" &lt;expression&gt;
                               |  "let" &lt;variable&gt; "=" &lt;expression&gt;

            &lt;expression&gt;  ::=  [ "-" ] &lt;term&gt; [ [ "+" | "-" ] &lt;term&gt; ]...

            &lt;term&gt;  ::=  &lt;factor&gt; [ [ "*" | "/" ] &lt;factor&gt; ]...

            &lt;factor&gt;  ::=  &lt;primary&gt; [ "^" &lt;primary&gt; ]...

            &lt;primary&gt;  ::=  &lt;number&gt; | &lt;variable&gt; | "(" &lt;expression&gt; ")"
                                 <newcode>| &lt;standard-function-name&gt; "(" &lt;expression&gt; ")"</newcode>

    A line of input must contain exactly one such command.  If extra
    data is found on a line after an expression has been read, it is
    considered an error.  The variables "pi" and "e" are defined
    when the program starts to represent the usual mathematical
    constants.

    This program demonstrates the use of a HashMap as a symbol
    table.

    SimpleInterpreter2.java is based on the program SimpleInterpreter.java,
    which did not handle standard functions in expressions.
    
    This program depends on the non-standard class, TextIO.
 */

import java.util.HashMap;

public class SimpleInterpreter2 {

   /**
    * Represents a syntax error found in the user's input.
    */
   private static class ParseError extends Exception {
      ParseError(String message) {
         super(message);
      }
   } // end nested class ParseError
   
   
   <newcode>/**
    * An enumerated type whose values represent the possible
    * standard functions.
    */
   private enum Functions { SIN, COS, TAN, ABS, SQRT, LOG }
   
   
   /**
    * An object of this class represents one of the standard functions.
    * Objects of this type are stored in the symbol table, associated
    * with the name of the standard functions.  Note that an object
    * of this type also knows how to evaluate the corresponding function.
    */
   private static class StandardFunction {

      /**
       * Tells which function this is.
       */
      Functions functionCode; 

      /**
       * Constructor creates an object to represent one of 
       * the standard functions
       * @param code which function is represented.
       */
      StandardFunction(Functions code) {
         functionCode = code;
      }

      /**
       * Finds the value of this function for the specified 
       * parameter value, x.
       */
      double evaluate(double x) {
         switch(functionCode) {
         case SIN:
            return Math.sin(x);
         case COS:
            return Math.cos(x);
         case TAN:
            return Math.tan(x);
         case ABS:
            return Math.abs(x);
         case SQRT:
            return Math.sqrt(x);
         default:
            return Math.log(x);
         }
      }

   } // end class StandardFunction</newcode>



   /**
    * The symbolTable contains information about the values of variables.  When a variable 
    * is assigned a value, it is recorded in the symbol table. The key is the name of the 
    * variable, and the  value is an object of type Double that contains the value of the 
    * variable.  
    *    <newcode>The symbol table can also contain standard functions.  The key is the name of</newcode>
    * <newcode>of the function, and the value is the corresponding StandardFunction object.</newcode>
    */
   private static HashMap&lt;String,<newcode>Object</newcode>&gt; symbolTable;


   public static void main(String[] args) {
      
      // Create the map that represents symbol table.
      
      symbolTable = new HashMap&lt;String,<newcode>Object</newcode>&gt;();

      // To start, add variables named "pi" and "e" to the symbol
      // table.  Their values are the usual mathematical constants.

      symbolTable.put("pi", Math.PI);
      symbolTable.put("e", Math.E);
      
      <newcode>// Add the standard functions to the hash table.
      
      symbolTable.put("sin", new StandardFunction(Functions.SIN));
      symbolTable.put("cos", new StandardFunction(Functions.COS));
      symbolTable.put("tan", new StandardFunction(Functions.TAN));
      symbolTable.put("abs", new StandardFunction(Functions.ABS));
      symbolTable.put("sqrt", new StandardFunction(Functions.SQRT));
      symbolTable.put("log", new StandardFunction(Functions.LOG));</newcode>

      System.out.println("\n\nEnter commands; press return to end.");
      System.out.println("Commands must have the form:\n");
      System.out.println("      print &lt;expression&gt;");
      System.out.println("  or");
      System.out.println("      let &lt;variable&gt; = &lt;expression&gt;");

      while (true) {
         System.out.print("\n?  ");
         TextIO.skipBlanks();
         if ( TextIO.peek() == '\n' ) {
            break;  // A blank input line ends the while loop and the program.
         }
         try {
            String command = TextIO.getWord();
            if (command.equalsIgnoreCase("print"))
               doPrintCommand();
            else if (command.equalsIgnoreCase("let"))
               doLetCommand();
            else
               throw new ParseError("Command must begin with 'print' or 'let'.");
            TextIO.getln();
         }
         catch (ParseError e) {
            System.out.println("\n*** Error in input:    " + e.getMessage());
            System.out.println("*** Discarding input:  " + TextIO.getln());
         }
      }

      System.out.println("\n\nDone.");

   } // end main()


   /**
    * Process a command of the form  let &lt;variable&gt; = &lt;expression&gt;.
    * When this method is called, the word "let" has already
    * been read.  Read the variable name and the expression, and
    * store the value of the variable in the symbol table.
    */
   private static void doLetCommand() throws ParseError {
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      if ( ! Character.isLetter(TextIO.peek()) )
         throw new ParseError("Expected variable name after 'let'.");
      String varName = readWord();  // The name of the variable.
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      if ( TextIO.peek() != '=' )
         throw new ParseError("Expected '=' operator for 'let' command.");
      TextIO.getChar();
      double val = expressionValue();  // The value of the variable.
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      if ( TextIO.peek() != '\n' )
         throw new ParseError("Extra data after end of expression.");
      symbolTable.put( varName, val );  // Add to symbol table.
      System.out.println("ok");
   }


   /**
    * Process a command of the form  print &lt;expression&gt;.
    * When this method is called, the word "print" has already
    * been read.  Evaluate the expression and print the value.
    */
   private static void doPrintCommand() throws ParseError {
      double val = expressionValue();
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      if ( TextIO.peek() != '\n' )
         throw new ParseError("Extra data after end of expression.");
      System.out.println("Value is " + val);
   }


   /**
    * Read an expression from the current line of input and return its value.
    */
   private static double expressionValue() throws ParseError {
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      boolean negative;  // True if there is a leading minus sign.
      negative = false;
      if (TextIO.peek() == '-') {
         TextIO.getAnyChar();
         negative = true;
      }
      double val;  // Value of the expression.
      val = termValue();  // An expression must start with a term.
      if (negative)
         val = -val; // Apply the leading minus sign
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      while ( TextIO.peek() == '+' || TextIO.peek() == '-' ) {
            // Read the next term and add it to or subtract it from
            // the value of previous terms in the expression.
         char op = TextIO.getAnyChar();
         double nextVal = termValue();
         if (op == '+')
            val += nextVal;
         else
            val -= nextVal;
         TextIO.skipBlanks();
      }
      return val;
   } // end expressionValue()


   /**
    * Read a term from the current line of input and return its value.
    */
   private static double termValue() throws ParseError {
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      double val;  // The value of the term.
      val = factorValue();  // A term must start with a factor.
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      while ( TextIO.peek() == '*' || TextIO.peek() == '/' ) {
            // Read the next factor, and multiply or divide
            // the value-so-far by the value of this factor.
         char op = TextIO.getAnyChar();
         double nextVal = factorValue();
         if (op == '*')
            val *= nextVal;
         else
            val /= nextVal;
         TextIO.skipBlanks();
      }
      return val;
   } // end termValue()


   /**
    * Read a factor from the current line of input and return its value.
    */
   private static double factorValue() throws ParseError {
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      double val;  // Value of the factor.
      val = primaryValue();  // A factor must start with a primary.
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      while ( TextIO.peek() == '^' ) {
            // Read the next primary, and exponentiate
            // the value-so-far by the value of this primary.
         TextIO.getChar();
         double nextVal = primaryValue();
         val = Math.pow(val,nextVal);
         if (Double.isNaN(val))
            throw new ParseError("Illegal values for ^ operator.");
         TextIO.skipBlanks();
      }
      return val;
   } // end termValue()


   /**
    *  Read a primary from the current line of input and
    *  return its value.  A primary must be a number,
    *  a variable, or an expression enclosed in parentheses.
    */
   private static double primaryValue() throws ParseError {
      TextIO.skipBlanks();
      char ch = TextIO.peek();
      if ( Character.isDigit(ch) ) {
            // The factor is a number.  Read it and
            // return its value.
         return TextIO.getDouble();
      }
      else if ( Character.isLetter(ch) ) {
            // The factor is a variable <newcode>or a standard function</newcode>.  Read its name and
            // look up its value in the symbol table.  If the name is not in the symbol table,
            // an error occurs.  (Note that the values in the symbol table are objects of type 
            // Double <newcode>or StandardFunction</newcode>.)
         String name = readWord();
         <newcode>Object obj = symbolTable.get(name);</newcode>
         if (obj == null)
            throw new ParseError("Unknown word \"" + name + "\"");
         <newcode>assert (obj instanceof Double || obj instanceof StandardFunction);
         if (obj instanceof Double)</newcode> {
               // The name is a variable; return value of that variable.
            Double val = (Double)obj;
            return val.doubleValue();
         }
         <newcode>else {
               // The name is a standard function.  Read the argument
               // of the function and return the value of the function
               // at that argument.  The argument must be an expression
               // in parentheses.
            StandardFunction func = (StandardFunction)obj;
            TextIO.skipBlanks();
            if ( TextIO.peek() != '(' )
               throw new ParseError("Parenthesis missing after standard function");
            TextIO.getChar(); // discard the '('
            double argument = expressionValue();  // read and evaluate expression
            TextIO.skipBlanks();
            if ( TextIO.peek() != ')' )
               throw new ParseError("Missing right parenthesis.");
            TextIO.getChar(); // discard the ')'
            return func.evaluate(argument);
         }</newcode>
      }
      else if ( ch == '(' ) {
            // The factor is an expression in parentheses.
            // Return the value of the expression.
         TextIO.getAnyChar();  // Read the "("
         double val = expressionValue();
         TextIO.skipBlanks();
         if ( TextIO.peek() != ')' )
            throw new ParseError("Missing right parenthesis.");
         TextIO.getAnyChar();  // Read the ")"
         return val;
      }
      else if ( ch == '\n' )
         throw new ParseError("End-of-line encountered in the middle of an expression.");
      else if ( ch == ')' )
         throw new ParseError("Extra right parenthesis.");
      else if ( ch == '+' || ch == '-' || ch == '*' || ch == '/')
         throw new ParseError("Misplaced operator.");
      else
         throw new ParseError("Unexpected character \"" + ch + "\" encountered.");
   }


   /**
    *  Reads a word from input.  A word is any sequence of
    *  letters and digits, starting with a letter.  When 
    *  this subroutine is called, it should already be
    *  known that the next character in the input is
    *  a letter.
    */
   private static String readWord() {
      String word = "";  // The word.
      char ch = TextIO.peek();
      while (Character.isLetter(ch) || Character.isDigit(ch)) {
         word += TextIO.getChar(); // Add the character to the word.
         ch = TextIO.peek();
      }
      return word;
   }

} // end class SimpleInterpreter2
</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>
   
   

      
</exercises>
