<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="generics.2" title="Lists and Sets">
   

<p><start><big>I</big>n the previous section</start>, we looked at the general
properties of collection classes in Java. In this section, we look at some
specific collection classes and how to use them. These classes can be divided
into two main categories: lists and sets. A list consists of a sequence of items
arranged in a linear order. A list has a definite order, but is not necessarily
sorted into ascending order.
A set is a collection that has no duplicate
entries. The elements of a set might or might not be arranged into some
definite order.  I will also briefly discuss a third category of
collection known as a "priority queue."</p>



<subsection id="generics.2.1" title="ArrayList and LinkedList">

<p>There are two obvious ways to represent a list: as a dynamic array and as a
linked list. We've encountered these already in 
<localref href="arrays.3"/> and <localref href="recursion.2"/>. Both of these
options are available in generic form as the collection classes
<code>java.util.ArrayList</code> and <code>java.util.LinkedList</code>. These
classes are part of the Java Collection Framework.  Each implements the interface
<classname>List&lt;T&gt;</classname>, and therefore the interface <classname>Collection&lt;T&gt;</classname>.
An object of type <classname>ArrayList&lt;T&gt;</classname>
represents an ordered sequence of objects of type <classname>T</classname>,
stored in an array that will grow in size whenever necessary as new items are added. An object of type
<classname>LinkedList&lt;T&gt;</classname> also
represents an ordered sequence of objects of type <classname>T</classname>, but
the objects are stored in nodes that are linked
together with pointers.</p>

<p>Both list classes support the basic list operations that are defined in
the interface <classname>List&lt;T&gt;</classname>, and an abstract data
type is defined by its operations, not by its representation. So why two
classes? Why not a single List class with a single representation? The problem
is that there <b>is</b> no single representation of lists for which all list
operations are efficient. For some operations, linked lists are more efficient
than arrays. For others, arrays are more efficient. In a particular application
of lists, it's likely that only a few operations will be used frequently. You
want to choose the representation for which the frequently used operations will
be as efficient as possible.</p>

<p>Broadly speaking, the <classname>LinkedList</classname> class is more efficient in
applications where items will often be added or removed at the beginning of the
list or in the middle of the list. In an array, these operations require moving
a large number of items up or down one position in the array, to make a space
for a new item or to fill in the hole left by the removal of an item.  In terms
of asymptotic analysis (<localref href="robustness.5"/>), adding an element at the beginning
or in the middle of an array has run time&nbsp;&Theta;(n), where n is the number
of items in the array.  In a
linked list, nodes can be added or removed at any position by changing a few
pointer values, an operation that has run time &Theta;(1).  That is, the 
operation takes only some constant amount of time, independent of how many
items are in the list.</p>
   
<p>On the other hand, the <classname>ArrayList</classname> class is more efficient when
<newword>random access</newword> to items is required.  Random access
means accessing the k-th item in the list, for any integer&nbsp;k.  Random access
is used when you get or change the value stored at a specified position in the list.
This is trivial for an array, with run time &Theta;(1).  
But for a linked list it means starting at the beginning
of the list and moving from node to node along the list for k steps, an
operation that has run time &Theta;(k).</p>
   
<p>Operations that can be done efficiently for both types of lists include sorting and adding
an item at the end of the list.</p>

<p>All lists implement the methods from interface <classname>Collection&lt;T&gt;</classname> 
that were discussed in <localref href="generics.1.4"/>.  These methods include  <code>size()</code>,
<code>isEmpty()</code>, <code>add(T)</code>, <code>remove(Object)</code>, and
<code>clear()</code>. The <code>add(T)</code> method adds the object at the end of
the list. The <code>remove(Object)</code> method involves first finding the object,
which uses linear search and is not very efficient for any list since it involves going through the
items in the list from beginning to end until the object is found. The interface
<classname>List&lt;T&gt;</classname>  adds some methods for accessing list items according to
their numerical positions in the list.  Suppose that <code>list</code> is an object
of type <classname>List&lt;T&gt;</classname>.  Then we have the methods:</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>list.get(index)</codedef> &mdash; returns the
object of type <classname>T</classname> that is
at position <code>index</code> in the list, where <code>index</code> is
an integer. Items are numbered 0, 1, 2, &dots;, <code>list.size()-1</code>. The
parameter must be in this range, or an <classname>IndexOutOfBoundsException</classname> is
thrown.</li>

<li><codedef>list.set(index,obj)</codedef> &mdash; stores the
object <code>obj</code> at position number <code>index</code> in the list, replacing
the object that was there previously. The object <code>obj</code> must be of
type <classname>T</classname>.  This does not change the number of
elements in the list or move any of the other elements.</li>

<li><codedef>list.add(index,obj)</codedef> &mdash; inserts an
object <code>obj</code> into the list at position number <code>index</code>,
where <code>obj</code> must be of type <classname>T</classname>.  The number
of items in the list increases by one, and items that come after position
<code>index</code> move down one position to make room for the new item. The value of
<code>index</code> must be in the range 0 to <code>list.size()</code>, inclusive.
If <code>index</code> is equal to <code>list.size()</code>, then <code>obj</code>
is added at the end of the list.</li>

<li><codedef>list.remove(index)</codedef> &mdash; removes the
object at position number <code>index</code>, and returns that object
as the return value of the method.
Items after this position move up one
space in the list to fill the hole, and the size of the list decreases by one.
The value of <code>index</code> must be in the range 0 to <code>list.size()-1</code>.</li>

<li><codedef>list.indexOf(obj)</codedef> &mdash; returns an
<ptype>int</ptype> that gives the position of <code>obj</code> in the list, if it occurs.
If it does not occur, the return value is <code>-1</code>.  The object <code>obj</code>
can be of any type, not just of type&nbsp;<classname>T</classname>.  If <code>obj</code> occurs
more than once in the list, the index of the first occurrence is returned.</li>
</ul>

<p>These methods are defined both in class <classname>ArrayList&lt;T&gt;</classname> and in class
<classname>LinkedList&lt;T&gt;</classname>, although some of them&mdash;<code>get</code>
and <code>set</code>&mdash;are only efficient for
<classname>ArrayLists</classname>. The class <classname>LinkedList&lt;T&gt;</classname> adds a few additional
methods, which are not defined for an <classname>ArrayList</classname>. If
<code>linkedlist</code> is an object of type <classname>LinkedList&lt;T&gt;</classname>, then we have</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>linkedlist.getFirst()</codedef> &mdash; returns the
object of type <classname>T</classname> that is the first item in the list. The list is not
modified.  If the list is empty when the method is called, an exception of type
<classname>NoSuchElementException</classname> is thrown (the same is true for the
next three methods as well).</li>

<li><codedef>linkedlist.getLast()</codedef> &mdash; returns the
object of type <classname>T</classname> that is the last item in the list. The list is not
modified.</li>

<li><codedef>linkedlist.removeFirst()</codedef> &mdash; removes
the first item from the list, and returns that object of type <classname>T</classname> as its return
value.  The functions <codedef>linkedlist.remove()</codedef> and <codedef>linkedlist.pop()</codedef> 
are also defined, with the same meaning as <code>removeFirst()</code>.</li>

<li><codedef>linkedlist.removeLast()</codedef> &mdash; removes
the last item from the list, and returns that object of type <classname>T</classname> as its return
value.</li>

<li><codedef>linkedlist.addFirst(obj)</codedef> &mdash; adds the
<code>obj</code>, which must be of type <classname>T</classname>, to the beginning of the list.
The function <codedef>linkedlist.push(obj)</codedef> has the same meaning.</li>

<li><codedef>linkedlist.addLast(obj)</codedef> &mdash; adds the
object <code>obj</code>, which must be of type <classname>T</classname>, to the end of the list. 
This is exactly the same as <code>linkedlist.add(obj)</code> but is defined to keep the
naming consistent.</li>
</ul>

<p>There is some redundancy here, apparently to make it easy to use a
<classname>LinkedList</classname> as if it were a stack or a queue. (See 
<localref href="recursion.3"/>.) For example, we can use a
<classname>LinkedList</classname> as a stack by using the methods named <code>push()</code>
and <code>pop()</code>, or as a queue by using <code>add()</code> and <code>remove()</code>
to implement the enqueue and dequeue operations.</p>

<p>If <code>list</code> is an object of type <classname>List&lt;T&gt;</classname>, then the method
<code>list.iterator()</code>, defined in the interface <classname>Collection&lt;T&gt;</classname>, returns
an <classname>Iterator</classname> that can be used to traverse the list from beginning to
end. However, for <classname>Lists</classname>, there is a special type of <classname>Iterator</classname>,
called a <classname>ListIterator</classname>, which offers additional capabilities. 
<classname>ListIterator&lt;T&gt;</classname> is an interface that extends the
interface <classname>Iterator&lt;T&gt;</classname>.  
The method <code>list.listIterator()</code> returns an object of type
<classname>ListIterator&lt;T&gt;</classname>.</p>

<p>A <classname>ListIterator</classname> has the usual <classname>Iterator</classname> methods,
<code>hasNext()</code>, <code>next()</code>, and <code>remove()</code>, but it also has methods
<code>hasPrevious()</code>, <code>previous()</code>, <code>add(obj)</code>, and <code>set(obj)</code>
that make it possible to move backwards in the list, to add an item at the
current position of the iterator, and to replace one of the items in the list.  
To understand how these work, it's best to think of an
iterator as pointing to a position <b>between</b> two list elements, or at
the beginning or end of the list. In this diagram, the items in a list are
represented by squares, and arrows indicate the possible positions of an
iterator:</p>

<img src="list-positions.png" width="320" height="73" 
   alt="Iterator Positions" tex="list-positions.eps" texscale="0.6"/>


<p>If <code>iter</code> is of type <classname>ListIterator&lt;T&gt;</classname>, then 
<code>iter.next()</code> moves
the iterator one space to the right along the list and returns the item that
the iterator passes as it moves. The method <code>iter.previous()</code> moves the
iterator one space to the left along the list and returns the item that it
passes. The method <code>iter.remove()</code> removes an item from the list; the
item that is removed is the item that the iterator passed most recently in a
call to either <code>iter.next()</code> or <code>iter.previous()</code>.  The method
<code>iter.set(obj)</code> works similarly; it replaces the item that would be removed
by <code>iter.remove()</code>.  There is also
a method <code>iter.add(obj)</code> that adds the specified object to the list
at the current position of the iterator (where <code>obj</code> must be of type
<classname>T</classname>).  This can be between two existing items
or at the beginning of the list or at the end of the list.</p>

<p>(By the way, the lists that are used in class <code>LinkedList&lt;T&gt;</code> are
<newword>doubly linked lists</newword>. That is, each node in the
list contains two pointers&mdash;one to the next node in the list and one to the
previous node. This makes it possible to efficiently implement both the
<code>next()</code> and <code>previous()</code> methods of a <code>ListIterator</code>.
Also, to make the <code>addLast()</code> and <code>getLast()</code> methods of a
<classname>LinkedList</classname> efficient, the class <classname>LinkedList&lt;T&gt;</classname> 
includes a "tail pointer" that points to the last node in the list.)</p>

<p>As an example of using a <classname>ListIterator</classname>, suppose that we want to
maintain a list of items that is always sorted into increasing order. When
adding an item to the list, we can use a <classname>ListIterator</classname> to find the
position in the list where the item should be added.  Once the position has been
found, we use the same list iterator to place the item in that position.
The idea is to start at
the beginning of the list and to move the iterator forward past all the items
that are smaller than the item that is being inserted. At that point, the
iterator's <code>add()</code> method can be used to insert the item.
To be more definite, suppose that
<code>stringList</code> is a variable of type <classname>List&lt;String&gt;</classname>.
Assume that the strings that are already in the list are stored in
ascending order and that <code>newItem</code> is a string that we would
like to insert into the list.  The following code will place <code>newItem</code>
in the list in its correct position, so that the modified list is still in
ascending order:</p>

<pre>ListIterator&lt;String&gt; iter = stringList.listIterator();

// Move the iterator so that it points to the position where
// newItem should be inserted into the list.  If newItem is
// bigger than all the items in the list, then the while loop
// will end when iter.hasNext() becomes false, that is, when
// the iterator has reached the end of the list.

while (iter.hasNext()) {
   String item = iter.next();
   if (newItem.compareTo(item) &lt;= 0) {
         // newItem should come BEFORE item in the list.
         // Move the iterator back one space so that
         // it points to the correct insertion point,
         // and end the loop.
      iter.previous();
      break;
   } 
}

iter.add(newItem);</pre>

<p>Here, <code>stringList</code> might be of type <classname>ArrayList&lt;String&gt;</classname>
or of type <classname>LinkedList&lt;String&gt;</classname>.  The
algorithm that is used to insert <code>newItem</code> into the list will be
about equally efficient for both types of lists, and it will even work for other classes that
implement the interface <classname>List&lt;String&gt;</classname>.
You would probably find it
easier to design an insertion algorithm that uses array-like indexing with
the methods <code>get(index)</code> and <code>add(index,obj)</code>. However, that
algorithm would be horribly inefficient for <classname>LinkedLists</classname> because
random access is so inefficient for linked lists.  (By the way, the insertion 
algorithm works when the list is empty.  It might be useful
for you to think about why this is true.)</p>


</subsection>
   
<subsection id="generics.2.2" title="Sorting">
   
<p>Sorting a list is a fairly common operation, and there should really be a
sorting method in the <classname>List</classname> interface. There is not,
presumably because it only makes sense to sort lists of certain types of objects.
However, methods for sorting lists are available as <code>static</code> methods
in the class <code>java.util.Collections</code>. This class contains a variety of
static utility methods for working with collections.  The methods are generic;
that is, they will work for collections of objects of various types.
(You have already seen similar methods for arrays in the <classname>Arrays</classname> class.)
Suppose that <code>list</code> is of type <classname>List&lt;T&gt;</classname>.
The command</p>

<pre>Collections.sort(list);</pre>

<np>can be used to sort the list into ascending order.  The items in the list should
implement the interface <classname>Comparable&lt;T&gt;</classname> 
(see <localref href="generics.1.6"/>). 
The method <code>Collections.sort()</code> will work, for
example, for lists of <classname>String</classname> and for lists
of any of the wrapper classes such as <classname>Integer</classname> and
<classname>Double</classname>.  There is also a sorting method that takes
a <classname>Comparator</classname> as its second argument:</np>

<pre>Collections.sort(list,comparator);</pre>

<np>In this method, the <code>comparator</code> will be used to compare the items in the list. As
mentioned in the <localref href="generics.1.6">previous section</localref>,
a <classname>Comparator</classname> is an object that
defines a <code>compare()</code> method that can be used to compare two objects.
We'll see an example of using a <classname>Comparator</classname> in
<localref href="generics.4"/>.</np>
   
<p>The sorting method that is used by <code>Collections.sort()</code> is the
so-called "merge sort" algorithm, which has both worst-case
and average-case run times that are &Theta;(n*log(n)) for a list of size&nbsp;n.
Although the average run time for MergeSort is a little slower than that of
QuickSort, its worst-case performance is much better than QuickSort's.
(QuickSort was covered in <localref href="recursion.1.3"/>.)
MergeSort also has a nice property called "stability" that we will encounter
at the end of <localref href="generics.4.3"/>.</p>

<p>The <classname>Collections</classname> class has at least two other useful methods for
modifying lists. <code>Collections.shuffle(list)</code> will rearrange the elements
of the list into a random order. <code>Collections.reverse(list)</code> will
reverse the order of the elements, so that the last element is moved to the
beginning of the list, the next-to-last element to the second position, and so
on.</p>

<p>Since an efficient sorting method is provided for <classname>Lists</classname>, there is
no need to write one yourself.</p>

</subsection>

   
<subsection id="generics.2.3" title="TreeSet and HashSet">
   
<p>A set is a collection of objects in which no object occurs more
than once. Sets implement all the methods in the interface 
<classname>Collection&lt;T&gt;</classname>, but do so
in a way that ensures that no element occurs twice in the set. For example, if
<code>set</code> is an object of type <classname>Set&lt;T&gt;</classname>, 
then <code>set.add(obj)</code> will
have no effect on the set if <code>obj</code> is already an element of the set.
Java has two classes that implement the interface <classname>Set&lt;T&gt;</classname>:
<code>java.util.TreeSet</code> and <code>java.util.HashSet</code>.</p>

<p>In addition to being a <classname>Set</classname>, a <classname>TreeSet</classname> has the property
that the elements of the set are arranged into ascending sorted order. An
<classname>Iterator</classname> (or a for-each loop) 
for a <code>TreeSet</code> will always visit the elements of the
set in ascending order.</p>

<p>A <classname>TreeSet</classname> cannot hold arbitrary objects, since there must be a way
to determine the sorted order of the objects it contains. Ordinarily, this
means that the objects in a set of type <classname>TreeSet&lt;T&gt;</classname> should implement the
interface <classname>Comparable&lt;T&gt;</classname>
and that <code>obj1.compareTo(obj2)</code> should be
defined in a reasonable way for any two objects <code>obj1</code> and <code>obj2</code>
in the set. Alternatively, an object of type
<classname>Comparator&lt;T&gt;</classname> can be provided as a parameter
to the constructor when the <classname>TreeSet</classname> is created. In that case, the
<code>compare()</code> method of the
<classname>Comparator</classname> will be used to compare objects that are added to the
set.</p>
   
<p>A <classname>TreeSet</classname> does not use the <code>equals()</code> method to
test whether two objects are the same.  Instead, it uses the <code>compareTo()</code> (or <code>compare()</code>)
method.  This can be a problem.  Recall from <localref href="generics.1.6"/> that
<code>compareTo()</code> can consider two objects to be the same for the purpose
of the comparison even though the objects are not equal.  For a <classname>TreeSet</classname>,
this means that only <b>one</b> of those objects can be in the set.  For example,
if the <classname>TreeSet</classname> contains mailing addresses
and if the <code>compareTo()</code> method
for addresses just compares their zip codes, then the set can contain only
one address in each zip code.  Clearly, this is not right!  But that only means
that you have to be aware of the semantics of <classname>TreeSets</classname>,
and you need to make sure that <code>compareTo()</code> is defined in a reasonable
way for objects that you put into a <classname>TreeSet</classname>.  This will be
true, by the way, for <classname>Strings</classname>, <classname>Integers</classname>,
and many other built-in types, since the <code>compareTo()</code> method for these
types considers two objects to be the same only if they are actually equal.</p>

<p>In the implementation of a <classname>TreeSet</classname>, the elements are stored in
something similar to a binary sort tree. (See <localref href="recursion.4.2"/>.) 
However, the data structure that is used is <b>balanced</b> 
in the sense that all the leaves of the tree are at
about the same distance from the root of the tree.  This ensures that
all the basic operations&mdash;inserting, deleting, and searching&mdash;are
efficient, with worst-case run time &Theta;(log(n)), where n is the
number of items in the set.</p>

<p>The fact that a <classname>TreeSet</classname> sorts its elements and removes duplicates
makes it very useful in some applications. <localref href="arrays.ex.6"/> asked
you to write a program that would read a file and output an alphabetical list of
all the words that occurred in the file, with duplicates removed.  The words
were to be stored in an <classname>ArrayList</classname>, so it was up to you to
make sure that the list was sorted and contained no duplicates.
The same task can be programmed much more easily using a <classname>TreeSet</classname>
instead of a list.  A <classname>TreeSet</classname> automatically eliminates
duplicates, and an iterator for the set will automatically visit the items in
the set in sorted order.  An algorithm for the program, using
a <classname>TreeSet</classname>, would be:</p>

<pre>TreeSet&lt;String&gt; words = new TreeSet&lt;String&gt;();

while there is more data in the input file:
   Let word = the next word from the file
   Convert word to lower case
   words.add(word)   // Adds the word only if not already present.

for ( String w : words ) // for each String w in words
   Output w  // words are output in sorted order</pre>

<np>If you would like to see a complete, working program, you can find it in the
file <sourceref href="WordListWithTreeSet.java"/>.</np>

<p>As another example, suppose that <code>coll</code> is any <code>Collection</code> of
<classname>Strings</classname>. (This would also work for any other type for which 
<code>compareTo()</code> is properly
defined.) We can use a <classname>TreeSet</classname> to sort the items of <code>coll</code> and
remove the duplicates simply by saying:</p>

<pre>TreeSet&lt;String&gt; set = new TreeSet&lt;String&gt;();
set.addAll(coll);</pre>

<np>The second statement adds all the elements of the collection to the set.
Since it's a <classname>Set</classname>, duplicates are ignored. Since it's a
<classname>TreeSet</classname>, the elements of the set are sorted. If you would like to have
the data in some other type of data structure, it's easy to copy the data from
the set. For example, to place the answer in an <classname>ArrayList</classname>, you could
say:</np>

<pre>TreeSet&lt;String&gt; set = new TreeSet&lt;String&gt;();
set.addAll(coll);
ArrayList&lt;String&gt; list = new ArrayList&lt;String&gt;();
list.addAll(set);</pre>

<p>Now, in fact, every one of Java's collection classes has a constructor that
takes a <classname>Collection</classname> as an argument. All the items in that
<classname>Collection</classname> are added to the new collection when it is created. So,
if <code>coll</code> is of type <classname>Collection&lt;String&gt;</classname>, then
"<code>new&nbsp;TreeSet&lt;String&gt;(coll)</code>" creates a <classname>TreeSet</classname> 
that contains the same elements as <code>coll</code>, but with duplicates removed and
in sorted order.  This means that we can
abbreviate the four lines in the above example to the single command:</p>

<pre>ArrayList&lt;String&gt; list = new ArrayList&lt;String&gt;( new TreeSet&lt;String&gt;(coll) );</pre>

<np>This makes a sorted list of the elements of <code>coll</code> with no
duplicates. Although the repeated type parameter, "<code>&lt;String&gt;</code>", makes
it a bit ugly to look at, this is still
a nice example of the power of generic programming.</np>

<break/>

<p>A <classname>HashSet</classname> stores its elements in a <newword>hash table</newword>, 
a type of data structure that I will discuss in the <localref href="generics.3">next
section</localref>. The operations of finding, adding, and removing
elements are implemented very efficiently in hash tables, even more so than for
<classname>TreeSets</classname>. The elements of a <classname>HashSet</classname> are not stored in any
particular order, and so do not need to implement the <classname>Comparable</classname> interface.
(They do, however, need to define a proper "hash code," as we'll see in the next section.)</p>

<p>The <code>equals()</code> method is used to determine whether two objects in
a <classname>HashSet</classname> are to be considered the same.
An <classname>Iterator</classname> for a <classname>HashSet</classname> will visit its
elements in what seems to be a completely arbitrary order, and it's possible
for the order to change completely when a new element is added. 
Use a <classname>HashSet</classname> instead of a
<classname>TreeSet</classname> when the elements it contains are not comparable, or when the
order is not important, or when the small advantage in efficiency is important.</p>

<break/>
   
<p>A note about the mathematics of sets:  In mathematical set theory, the items in a
set are called <newword>members</newword> or <newword>elements</newword> of that set.
Important operations include adding an element to a set, removing an element from a
set, and testing whether a given entity is an element of a set.
Operations that can be performed on two sets include <newword>union</newword>,
<newword>intersection</newword>, and <newword>set difference</newword>.
All these operations are defined in Java for objects of type <classname>Set</classname>,
but with different names.  Suppose that <code>A</code> and <code>B</code> are <classname>Sets</classname>.
Then:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>A.add(x)</code> <b>adds</b> the element <code>x</code> to the set <code>A</code>.</li>
<li><code>A.remove(x)</code> <b>removes</b> the element <code>x</code> from the set <code>A</code>.</li>
<li><code>A.contains(x)</code> <b>tests</b> whether <code>x</code> is an element of the set <code>A</code>.</li>
<li><code>A.addAll(B)</code> computes the <b>union</b> of <code>A</code> and <code>B</code>.</li>
<li><code>A.retainAll(B)</code> computes the <b>intersection</b> of <code>A</code> and <code>B</code>.</li>
<li><code>A.removeAll(B)</code> computes the <b>set difference</b>, <code>A - B</code>.</li>
</ul>
   
<p>There are of course, differences between mathematical sets and sets in Java.
Most important, perhaps, sets in Java must be finite, while in mathematics, most of
the fun in set theory comes from working with infinity.  In mathematics, a set can
contain arbitrary elements, while in Java, a set of type <classname>Set&lt;T&gt;</classname>
can only contain elements of type <classname>T</classname>.  The operation
<code>A.addAll(B)</code> acts by modifying the value of <code>A</code>, while in
mathematics the operation <code>A</code> union <code>B</code> computes a new set,
without changing the value of <code>A</code> or <code>B</code>.  See
<localref href="generics.ex.2"/> for an example of mathematical set operations in Java.</p>

   
</subsection>
   
<subsection id="generics.2.4" title="EnumSet">
   
<p>Enumerated types (or "enums") were introduced in <localref href="basics.3.4"/>.  
Suppose that <classname>E</classname>
is an enumerated type.  Since <classname>E</classname> is a class, it is possible to create
objects of type <classname>TreeSet&lt;E&gt;</classname> and <classname>HashSet&lt;E&gt;</classname>.
However, because enums are so simple, trees and hash tables are not the most efficient
implementation for sets of enumerated type values.  Java provides the class
<code>java.util.EnumSet</code> as an alternative way to create such sets.</p>
   
<p>Sets of enumerated type values are created using <code>static</code> methods
in the class <classname>EnumSet</classname>.  For example, if <code>e1</code>, 
<code>e2</code>, and <code>e3</code> are values belonging to the enumerated type
<classname>E</classname>, then the method</p>
   
<pre>EnumSet.of( e1, e2, e3 )</pre>
   
<np>creates and returns a set of type <classname>EnumSet&lt;E&gt;</classname> that
contains exactly the elements <code>e1</code>, <code>e2</code>, and <code>e3</code>.
The set implements the interface <classname>Set&lt;E&gt;</classname>, so all
the usual set and collection operations are available.  The implementation
of these operations is very efficient.  The implementation uses what is
called a <classname>bit vector</classname>.  A bit is a quantity that has only
two possible values, zero and one.  A set of type <classname>EnumSet&lt;E&gt;</classname>
is represented by a bit vector that contains one bit for each enum constant in the
enumerated type <classname>E</classname>; the bit corresponding to the enum
constant <code>e</code> is 1 if <code>e</code> is a member of the set and is
0 if <code>e</code> is not a member of the set.  The bit vectors for
two sets of type <classname>EnumSet&lt;E&gt;</classname> can be very easily
combined to represent such operations as the union and intersection of two
sets.  The bit vector representation is feasible for <classname>EnumSets</classname>,
but not for other sets in Java, because an enumerated type contains only a
small finite number of enum constants.  (Java actually has a class named
<classname>BitSet</classname> that uses bit vectors to represent finite sets
of non-negative integers, but this class is not part of
the Java Collection Framework and does not implement
the <classname>Set</classname> interface.)</np>
   
<p>The function <code>EnumSet.of()</code> can be used with any positive number of parameters.
All the parameters must be values of the same enumerated type.  Null values are not
allowed. An <classname>EnumSet</classname> cannot contain the value <code>null</code>&mdash;any
attempt to add <code>null</code> to an <classname>EnumSet</classname> will
result in a <classname>NullPointerException</classname>.
</p>
   
<p>There is also a function <code>EnumSet.range(e1,e2)</code> that returns an
<classname>EnumSet</classname> consisting of the enum constants between <code>e1</code>
and <code>e2</code>, inclusive.  The ordering of enum constants is the same as
the order in which they are listed in the definition of the enum.
In <code>EnumSet.range(e1,e2)</code>, <code>e1</code> and <code>e2</code> must
belong to the same enumerated type, and <code>e1</code> must be less than or
equal to <code>e2</code>.</p>
   
<p>If <classname>E</classname> is an enum, then <code>EnumSet.allOf(E.class)</code>
is a set that contains all values of type <classname>E</classname>.
<code>EnumSet.noneOf(E.class)</code> is an <newword>empty set</newword>,
a set of type <classname>EnumSet&lt;E&gt;</classname> that contains no elements at all.
Note that in <code>EnumSet.allOf(E.class)</code> and <code>EnumSet.noneOf(E.class)</code>,
the odd-looking parameter represents the enumerated type class itself.  If <code>eset</code> is a set of
type <classname>EnumSet&lt;E&gt;</classname>, then <code>EnumSet.complementOf(eset)</code>
is a set that contains all the enum constants of <classname>E</classname> that
are <b>not</b> in <code>eset</code>.</p>

<p>As an example, consider a program that keeps schedules of events.  The program
must keep track of repeating events that happen on specified days of the week.
For example, an event might take place only on weekdays, or only on
Wednesdays and Fridays.  In other words, associated with the event is
the <b>set</b> of days of the week on which it takes place.  This information
can be represented using the enumerated type</p>
   
<pre>enum Day { SUNDAY, MONDAY, TUESDAY, WEDNESDAY, THURSDAY, FRIDAY, SATURDAY }</pre>
   
<np>The days of the week on which an event takes place would then be a value
of type <classname>EnumSet&lt;Day&gt;</classname>.  An object of type
<classname>RepeatingEvent</classname> would have an instance variable of type
<classname>EnumSet&lt;Day&gt;</classname> to hold this information.
An event that takes place on Wednesdays and Fridays would have the associated set</np>
   
<pre>EnumSet.of( Day.WEDNESDAY, Day.FRIDAY )</pre>
   
<np>We could define some common sets of <classname>Days</classname> as</np>

<pre>EnumSet&lt;Day&gt; weekday = EnumSet.range( Day.MONDAY, Day.FRIDAY );
EnumSet&lt;Day&gt; weekend = EnumSet.complementOf( weekday );
EnumSet&lt;Day&gt; everyday = EnumSet.allOf( Day.class );</pre>
   
<p><classname>EnumSets</classname> are often used to specify sets of
"options" that are to be applied during some type of processing.  For example,
a program that draws characters in fancy fonts might have various options that
can be applied.  Let's say that the options are bold, italic, underlined, strikethrough,
and boxed.  Note that we are assuming that options can be combined in arbitrary
ways.  For example, you can have italic, boxed, underlined characters. This
just means that we need to keep track of a <b>set</b> of options.  If the
options are represented by the enumerated type
</p>

<pre>enum FontOption { BOLD, ITALIC, UNDERLINED, STRIKETHROUGH, BOXED }</pre>

<np>then a set of options is represented by a value of type 
<classname>EnumSet&lt;FontOption&gt;</classname>.  Suppose that
<code>options</code> is a variable of this type that represents the
set of options that are currently being applied by the program.
Then we can do things like:</np>
   
<ul>
<li><code>options = EnumSet.noneOf( FontOption.class )</code> &mdash; Turn off all options.</li>
<li><code>options = EnumSet.of( FontOption.BOLD )</code> &mdash; Use bold, with no other options.</li>
<li><code>options.add( FontOption.BOLD )</code> &mdash; Add bold to any options that are already on.</li>
<li><code>options.remove( FontOption.UNDERLINED )</code> &mdash; Turn underlining off (if it's on).</li>
</ul>
   
<np>This is a nice, safe way to work with sets of options. Applications like
this are one of the major reasons that enumerated types were introduced.</np>
   
</subsection>

<subsection id="generics.2.5" title="Priority Queues">

<p>A <newword>priority queue</newword> is an ADT that represents a collection of
items, where each item has an assigned "priority" that allows any two items
to be compared.  Operations on a priority queue include <i>add</i>, which adds
an item to the collection, and <i>remove</i>, which removes and returns an item
from the collection that has the minimum priority among items currently in
the collection. (Maximum priority would also be possible, but in Java's version,
the <i>remove</i> operation removes a minimum priority item.)</p>

<p>A simple implementation of priority queue could be achieved by using a linked list
to store the items in the queue in order of increasing priority.  In that case,
<i>remove</i> would simply remove and return the first item in the list.
However, <i>add</i> would have to insert the new item into its correct position
in the list, an operation with average run time &Theta;(n), where n is the number of items
in the list.  In fact, priority queues can be implemented so that both <i>add</i>
and <i>remove</i> have run time &Theta;(log(n)), which is much more efficient.  (The efficient
implementation uses something called a "heap," which is not to be confused with the
heap where objects are created.  I will not discuss the implementation here.)</p>

<p>The parameterized class <classname>PriorityQueue&lt;T&gt;</classname> implements a
priority queue of objects of type <classname>T</classname>.  This class implements
the interface <classname>Collection&lt;T&gt;</classname>.  So, if <code>pq</code>
is a <classname>PriorityQueue</classname>, then it has all the methods defined in
that interface.  But the essential priority queue operations are</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>pq.add(obj)</codedef> &mdash; adds <code>obj</code> to the priority queue, where 
<code>obj</code> must be an object of type <classname>T</classname></li>
<li><codedef>pq.remove()</codedef> &mdash; removes and returns an item of minimal priority.
The return value is an object of type <classname>T</classname>.  Throws an exception if
the queue is empty.</li>
<li><codedef>pq.isEmpty()</codedef> &mdash; tests whether the priority queue is empty.</li>
</ul>

<p>You've probably noticed that I haven't yet mentioned how the priority of items in the
priority queue are determined.  The situation is much like sorting: We need to be able to compare
any two items in the queue.  As with sorting, there are two solutions.  If the items implement
the <classname>Comparable</classname> interface, then they can be compared using the
<code>compareTo()</code> method from that interface.   Alternatively, a <classname>Comparator</classname>
object can be provided as a parameter to the <classname>PriorityQueue</classname> constructor.
In that case, the Comparator's <code>compare</code> method will be used to compare items.</p>

<p>Classes such as <classname>String</classname>, <classname>Integer</classname>, and
<classname>Date</classname> that implement <classname>Comparable</classname> can be used
in a priority queue.  For example, a <classname>PriorityQueue&lt;String&gt;</classname> can be
used to sort strings into lexicographic order: Just <i>add</i> all the strings to the
priority queue, then <i>remove</i> them one-by-one.  Since items are removed from a queue
in order of priority, they will be removed in lexicographic order.  Earlier, I showed how to
use a <classname>TreeSet</classname> to sort and remove duplicates from a collection.
A <classname>PriorityQueue</classname> can be used in a similar way to sort a collection
without removing duplicates.  For example, if <code>coll</code> is of type
<classname>Collection&lt;String&gt;</classname>, then the following code segment will print all the
items from <code>coll</code> in order, including duplicates:</p>

<pre>PriorityQueue&lt;String&gt; pq = new PriorityQueue&lt;String&gt;();
pq.addAll( coll );
while ( ! pq.isEmpty() ) {
    System.out.println( pq.remove() );
}</pre>

<np>(Note, by the way, that we can't use an iterator or a for-each loop to print the
items in this example, since interators and for-each loops do not traverse a
priority queue in ascending order.)</np>

<p>The sample program <sourceref href="WordListWithPriorityQueue.java"/> makes a sorted list of
words from a file without removing duplicates, using a priority queue to hold the words.
It is a minor modification of <sourceref href="WordListWithTreeSet.java"/>.</p>

<p>Although priority queues can be used for sorting, they have other natural applications.
For example, consider the problem of scheduling "jobs" to be executed on a computer,
where each job is assigned a priority and jobs with lower priority should always be executed
before jobs with higher priority.  Jobs can be placed into a priority queue as they are
created.  When the computer removes jobs from the queue for execution, they will be removed
in order of increasing priority.</p>

</subsection>
   


</section>