<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="generics.4" title="Programming with the Java Collection Framework" shorttitle="Programming with the JCF">

   
<p><start><big>I</big>n this section,</start> we'll look at some
programming examples that use classes from the Java Collection
Framework.  The Collection Framework is easy to use, especially
compared to the difficulty of programming new data structures
from scratch.</p>


<subsection id="generics.4.1" title="Symbol Tables">

<p>We begin with a straightforward but important application of maps. When a
compiler reads the source code of a program, it encounters definitions of
variables, subroutines, and classes. The names of these things can be used
later in the program. The compiler has to remember the definition of each name,
so that it can recognize the name and apply the definition when the name is
encountered later in the program. This is a natural application for a
<classname>Map</classname>. The name can be used as a key in the map. The value associated to
the key is the definition of the name, encoded somehow as an object. A map that
is used in this way is called a <newword>symbol table</newword>.</p>

<p>In a compiler, the values in a symbol table can be quite complicated, since
the compiler has to deal with names for various sorts of things, and it needs a
different type of information for each different type of name. We will keep
things simple by looking at a symbol table in another context. Suppose that we
want a program that can evaluate expressions entered by the user, and suppose
that the expressions can contain variables, in addition to operators, numbers,
and parentheses. For this to make sense, we need some way of assigning values
to variables. When a variable is used in an expression, we need to retrieve the
variable's value. A symbol table can be used to store the data that we need.
The keys for the symbol table are variable names. The value associated with a
key is the value of that variable, which is of type <ptype>double</ptype>.
The symbol table will be an object of type <classname>Map&lt;String,Double&gt;</classname>.
(Remember that primitive types such as <ptype>double</ptype> can't be used
as type parameters; a wrapper class such as <classname>Double</classname> must
be used instead.  See <localref href="generics.1.7"/>.)</p>

<p>To demonstrate the idea, we'll use a rather simple-minded program in which
the user types commands such as:</p>

<pre>let x = 3 + 12
print 2 + 2
print 10*x +17
let rate = 0.06
print 1000*(1+rate)</pre>

<p>The program is an interpreter for a very simple language.
The only two commands that the program understands are "print" and "let".
When a "print" command is executed, the computer evaluates the expression and
displays the value. If the expression contains a variable, the computer has to
look up the value of that variable in the symbol table. A "let" command is used
to give a value to a variable. The computer has to store the value of the
variable in the symbol table. (Note: The "variables" I am talking about here
are not variables in the Java program. The Java program is executing a sort of
program typed in by the user. I am talking about variables in the user's
program. The user gets to make up variable names, so there is no way for the
Java program to know in advance what the variables will be.)</p>

<p>In <localref href="recursion.5.2"/>, we saw how to write a program,
<sourceref chapter="9" href="SimpleParser2.java"/>, that can
evaluate expressions that do not contain variables. Here, I will discuss
another example program, 
<sourceref href="SimpleInterpreter.java"/>, that is based on the older
program. I will only talk about the parts that are relevant to the symbol
table.</p>


<p>The program uses a <classname>HashMap</classname> as the symbol table. A <classname>TreeMap</classname>
could also be used, but since the program does not need to access the variables
in alphabetical order, we don't need to have the keys stored in sorted order.
The symbol table in the program is represented by a variable named
<code>symbolTable</code> of type <classname>HashMap&lt;String,Double&gt;</classname>.
At the beginning of the program, the symbol table object is created with the command:
</p>

<pre>symbolTable = new HashMap&lt;&gt;();</pre>

<np>This creates a map that initially contains no key/value associations.
To execute a "let" command, the program uses the symbol table's <code>put()</code> method to
associate a value with the variable name. Suppose that the name of the variable
is given by a <classname>String</classname>, <code>varName</code>, and the value
of the variable is stored in a variable, <code>val</code>, of type <ptype>double</ptype>.
The following command would then set the value associated with the variable
in the symbol table:</np>

<pre>symbolTable.put( varName, val );</pre>
   
<np>In the program <sourceref href="SimpleInterpreter.java"/>, you'll find this in the
method named <code>doLetCommand()</code>. 
The actual value that is stored in the symbol table is an object of
type <classname>Double</classname>.  We can use the <ptype>double</ptype>
value <code>val</code> in the call to <code>put</code> because Java does
an automatic conversion of type <ptype>double</ptype> to <classname>Double</classname>
when necessary.</np>


<p>Just for fun, I decided to pre-define two
variables named "pi" and "e" whose values are the usual mathematical constants
&pi; and <i>e</i>. In Java, the values of these constants are given by
<code>Math.PI</code> and <code>Math.E</code>. To make these variables available to the
user of the program, they are added to the symbol table with the commands:</p>

<pre>symbolTable.put( "pi", Math.PI );
symbolTable.put( "e", Math.E );</pre>

<p>When the program encounters a variable while evaluating an expression, the 
symbol table's <code>get()</code> method is used to retrieve its value.
The function <code>symbolTable.get(varName)</code> returns a value of
type <classname>Double</classname>.  It is possible that the return value
is <code>null</code>; this will happen if no value has ever been assigned
to <code>varName</code> in the symbol table.  It's important to check this
possibility.  It indicates that the user is trying to use a variable that
the user has not defined.  The program considers this to be an error,
so the processing looks something like this:</p>

<pre>Double val = symbolTable.get(varName);
if (val == null) {
   ... // Throw an exception:  Undefined variable.
}
// The value associated to varName is val.doubleValue()</pre>

<np>You will find this code, more or less, in a
method named <code>primaryValue()</code> in <sourceref href="SimpleInterpreter.java"/>.</np>

<p>As you can see from this example, <classname>Maps</classname> are very useful
and are really quite easy to use.</p>


</subsection>
   
<subsection id="generics.4.2" title="Sets Inside a Map">

<p>The objects in a collection or map can be of any type. They can even be
collections. Here's an example where it's natural to store sets as the value 
objects in a map.</p>

<p>Consider the problem of making an index for a book. An index consists of a
list of terms that appear in the book. Next to each term is a list of the pages
on which that term appears. To represent an index in a program, we need a data
structure that can hold a list of terms, along with a list of pages for each
term. Adding new data should be easy and efficient. When it's time to print the
index, it should be easy to access the terms in alphabetical order. There are
many ways this could be done, but I'd like to use Java's generic data
structures and let them do as much of the work as possible.</p>

<p>We can think of an index as a <classname>Map</classname> that associates a list of page
references to each term. The terms are keys, and the value associated with a
given key is the list of page references for that term. A <classname>Map</classname> can be
either a <classname>TreeMap</classname> or a <classname>HashMap</classname>, 
but only a <classname>TreeMap</classname>
will make it easy to access the terms in sorted order. The value associated
with a term is a list of page references. How can we represent such a value? If
you think about it, you see that it's not really a list in the sense of Java's
generic classes. If you look in any index, you'll see that a list of page
references has no duplicates, so it's really a set rather than a list.
Furthermore, the page references for a given term are always printed in
increasing order, so we want a sorted set. This means that we should use a
<classname>TreeSet</classname> to represent each list of page references. The values that we
really want to put in this set are of type <ptype>int</ptype>, but once again we have
to deal with the fact that generic data structures can only hold objects, so we
must use the wrapper class, <classname>Integer</classname>, for the objects in the set.</p>

<p>To summarize, an index will be represented by a <classname>TreeMap</classname>. The keys
for the map will be terms, which are of type <classname>String</classname>. The values in the
map will be <classname>TreeSets</classname> that contain <classname>Integers</classname> 
representing page numbers.  The parameterized type that
we should use for the sets is <classname>TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;</classname>.
For the <classname>TreeMap</classname> that represents the index as a whole,
the key type is <classname>String</classname> and the value type is
<classname>TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;</classname>.  This means that the index has type
</p>
   
<pre>TreeMap&lt; String, TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt; &gt;</pre>
   
<np>This is just the usual <classname>TreeMap&lt;K,V&gt;</classname> with
<code>K=String</code> and <code>V=TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;</code>.  A type name
as complicated as this one can look intimidating, but if you think about
the data structure that we want to represent, it makes sense.</np>

<p>To make an index, we need to start with an empty <classname>TreeMap</classname>. We then work
through the book, and we insert into the map every reference that we want to be in the index.
We then need to print out the data from the
map. Let's leave aside the question of how we find the references
to put in the index, and just look at how the <classname>TreeMap</classname> is used. 
It can be created with the commands:</p>

<pre>TreeMap&lt;String,TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;&gt;  index; // Declare the variable.
index = new TreeMap&lt;&gt;();  // Create the map object.</pre>

<np>(Note that even for this complex type, the type parameters can be omitted
from the constructor.)</np>

<p>Now, suppose that we find a reference to some <code>term</code>
(of type <classname>String</classname>) on some <code>pageNum</code>
(of type <ptype>int</ptype>). We need to
insert this information into the index. To do this, we should look up the term
in the index, using <code>index.get(term)</code>. The return value is either
<code>null</code> or is the set of page references that we have previously found for the
term. If the return value is <code>null</code>, then this is the first page
reference for the term, so we should add the term to the index, with a new set
that contains the page reference we've just found. If the return value is
non-<code>null</code>, we already have a set of page references, and we should just add the new page
reference to the set. Here is a subroutine that does this:</p>

<pre>
/**
 * Add a page reference to the index.
 */
void addReference(String term, int pageNum) {
   TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt; references; // The set of page references that we
                                //    have so far for the term.
   references = index.get(term);
   if (references == null){
          // This is the first reference that we have
          // found for the term.  Make a new set containing
          // the page number and add it to the index, with
          // the term as the key.
       TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt; firstRef = new TreeSet&lt;&gt;();
       firstRef.add( pageNum );  // pageNum is "autoboxed" to give an Integer!
       index.put(term,firstRef);
   }
   else {
         // references is the set of page references
         // that we have found previously for the term.
         // Add the new page number to that set.  This
         // set is already associated to term in the index.
      references.add( pageNum );
   }
}</pre>

<p>The only other thing we need to do with the index is print it out.  We want
to iterate through the index and print out each term, together with the
set of page references for that term.  We could use an <classname>Iterator</classname>
to iterate through the index, but it's much easier to do it with a for-each
loop.  The loop will iterate through the entry set of the map (see <localref href="generics.3.2"/>).
Each "entry" is a key/value pair from the map; the key is a term and the value
is the associated set of page references.
Inside the for-each loop, we will have to print out a set of <classname>Integers</classname>,
which can also be done with a for-each loop.  So, here we have an example of
nested for-each loops.  (You might try to do the same thing entirely with
iterators; doing so should give you some appreciation for the for-each loop!)
Here is a subroutine that will print the index:
</p>


<pre>/**
 * Print each entry in the index.
 */
void printIndex() {
   
    for ( Map.Entry&lt;String,TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;&gt;  entry :  index.entrySet() ) {
    
        String term = entry.getKey();
        TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt; pageSet = entry.getValue();
   
        System.out.print( term + ": " );
        for ( int page : pageSet ) {
            System.out.print( page + " " );
        }
        System.out.println();
   
    }
   
}</pre>
   
<np>The hardest thing here is the name of the type <code>Map.Entry&lt;String,TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;&gt;</code>!
Remember that the entries in a map of type <classname>Map&lt;K,V&gt;</classname> have
type <classname>Map.Entry&lt;K,V&gt;</classname>, so the type parameters in
<code>Map.Entry&lt;String,TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;&gt;</code> are simply copied
from the declaration of <code>index</code>.  Another thing to note is that
I used a loop control variable, <code>page</code>, of type <classname>int</classname> 
to iterate through the elements of <code>pageSet</code>,
which is of type <classname>TreeSet&lt;Integer&gt;</classname>.  You might have expected
<code>page</code> to be of type <classname>Integer</classname>, not <ptype>int</ptype>,
and in fact <classname>Integer</classname> would have worked just as well here.
However, <ptype>int</ptype> does work, because of automatic type conversion:
It's legal to assign a value of type <classname>Integer</classname> to a variable
of type <ptype>int</ptype>.  (To be honest, I was sort of surprised that this worked
when I first tried it!)</np>

<p>This is not a lot of code, considering the complexity of the operations.
I have not written a complete indexing program, but  <localref href="generics.ex.5"/>
presents a problem that is almost identical to the indexing problem.</p>
   
<break/>
   
<p>By the way, in this example, I would prefer to print each list of page references with
the integers separated by commas.  In the
<code>printIndex()</code> method given above, they are separated by spaces.
There is an extra space after the last page reference in the list, but it does
no harm since it's invisible in the printout.  An extra comma at the end
of the list would be annoying.  The lists should be in a form such as "<code>17,42,105</code>" and
not "<code>17,42,105,</code>".  The problem is, how to leave that last comma out.
Unfortunately, this is not so easy to do
with a for-each loop.  It might be fun to look at a few ways to solve this problem.
One alternative is to use an iterator:</p>

<pre>Iterator&lt;Integer&gt;  iter = pageSet.iterator();
int firstPage = iter.next();  // In this program, we know the set has
                              // at least one element.
System.out.print(firstPage);
while ( iter.hasNext() ) {
   int nextPage = iter.next();
   System.out.print("," + nextPage);
}</pre>
   
<p>Another possibility is to use the fact that the <classname>TreeSet</classname> class
defines a method <code>first()</code> that returns the first item in the set, that is,
the one that is smallest in terms of the ordering that is used to compare items in the set.
(It also defines the method <code>last()</code>.)  We can solve our problem using
this method and a for-each loop:</p>
   
<pre>int firstPage = pageSet.first();  // Find out the first page number in the set.
for ( int page : pageSet ) {
   if ( page != firstPage )
      System.out.print(","); // Output comma only if this is not the first page.
   System.out.print(page);
}</pre>
   
<p>Finally, here is an elegant solution using a subset view of the tree.
(See <localref href="generics.3.2"/>.)  Actually, this solution might be
a bit extreme:</p>

<pre>int firstPage = pageSet.first();  // Get first item, which we know exists.
System.out.print(firstPage);      // Print first item, with no comma.
for ( int page : pageSet.tailSet( firstPage+1 ) ) // Process remaining items.
   System.out.print( "," + page );</pre>
   
</subsection>
   
<subsection id="generics.4.3" title="Using a Comparator">

<p>There is a potential problem with our solution to the indexing problem. If
the terms in the index can contain both upper case and lower case letters, then
the terms will <b>not</b> be in alphabetical order! The ordering on <classname>String</classname> is
not alphabetical. It is based on the Unicode codes of the characters in the
string. The codes for all the upper case letters are less than the codes for
the lower case letters. So, for example, terms beginning with "Z" come before
terms beginning with "a". If the terms are restricted to use lower case letters
only (or upper case only), then the ordering would be alphabetical. But suppose
that we allow both upper and lower case, and that we insist on alphabetical
order. In that case, our index can't use the usual ordering for
<code>Strings</code>. Fortunately, it's possible to specify a different method to
be used for comparing the keys of a map. This is a typical use for a
<classname>Comparator</classname>.</p>

<p>Recall that an object that implements the interface <classname>Comparator&lt;T&gt;</classname> 
defines a method for comparing two objects of type&nbsp;<classname>T</classname>:</p>

<pre>public int compare( T obj1, T obj2 )</pre>

<np>This method  should return an integer
that is negative, zero, or positive, depending on whether <code>obj1</code> is less
than, equal to, or greater than <code>obj2</code>. We want to
compare two <classname>Strings</classname> ignoring case.
The <classname>String</classname>
class already includes a method that does that, <code>compareToIgnoreCase()</code>.
But to use a non-default comparison in a <classname>TreeMap</classname>,
we need an object of type <classname>Comparator&lt;String&gt;</classname>. Since
<classname>Comparator</classname> is a functional interface, an easy
way to specify the comparator is to use a lambda expression:</np>

<pre>(a,b) -&gt; a.compareToIgnoreCase(b)</pre>

<np>To solve our indexing problem, we just need to pass this comparator as
a parameter to the <classname>TreeMap</classname> constructor:</np>

<pre>index = new TreeMap&lt;&gt;( (a,b) -&gt; a.compareToIgnoreCase(b) );</pre>

<np>In fact, since the lambda expression is just calling a method that already
exists in the <classname>String</classname> class, it could actually be
given as a method reference (see <localref href="subroutines.4a.4"/>):</np>

<pre>index = new TreeMap&lt;&gt;( String::compareToIgnoreCase );</pre>

<p>This does work.  However, there one technicality. Suppose, for example,
that the indexing program calls <code>addReference("aardvark",56)</code> and that it later
calls <code>addReference("Aardvark",102)</code>. The words "aardvark" and
"Aardvark" differ only in that one of them begins with an upper case letter;
when converted to lower case, they are the same.
When we insert them into the index, do they count as two different terms or as
one term? The answer depends on the way that a <classname>TreeMap</classname> tests objects
for equality. In fact, <classname>TreeMaps</classname> and <classname>TreeSets</classname> always use a
<classname>Comparator</classname> object or a <code>compareTo</code> method to test for equality.
They do <b>not</b> use the <code>equals()</code> method for this purpose.
The <classname>Comparator</classname> that is
used for the <classname>TreeMap</classname> in this example returns the value zero when it is
used to compare "aardvark" and "Aardvark", so the <classname>TreeMap</classname> considers
them to be the same. Page references to "aardvark" and "Aardvark" are combined
into a single list, and when the index is printed it will contain only the first
version of the word that was encountered by the program.  This is probably 
acceptable behavior in this example. If
not, some other technique must be used to sort the terms into alphabetical
order.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="generics.4.4" title="Word Counting">

<p>The final example in this section also deals with storing information
about words.  The problem here is to make a list of all the words that
occur in a file, along with the number of times that each word occurs.
The file will be selected by the user.  The output of the program
will consist of two lists.  Each list contains all the words from
the file, along with the number of times that the word occurred.
One list is sorted alphabetically, and the other is sorted according to 
the number of occurrences, with the most common words at the top and 
the least common at the bottom.  The problem here is a generalization
of <localref href="arrays.ex.6"/>, which asked you to make an
alphabetical list of all the words in a file, without counting
the number of occurrences.</p>
   
<p>My word counting program can be found in the file <sourceref href="WordCount.java"/>.
As the program reads an input file, it must keep track of how many times it
encounters each word. We could simply throw all the words, with duplicates,
into a list and count them later. But that would require a lot of extra storage space and
would not be very efficient. A better method is to keep a counter for each
word. The first time the word is encountered, the counter is initialized to&nbsp;1.
On subsequent encounters, the counter is incremented. To keep track of the data
for one word, the program uses a simple class that holds a word and the counter
for that word. The class is a <code>static</code> nested class:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Represents the data we need about a word:  the word and
 * the number of times it has been encountered.
 */
private static class WordData { 
   String word;
   int count;
   WordData(String w) {
         // Constructor for creating a WordData object when
         // we encounter a new word.
      word = w;
      count = 1;  // The initial value of count is 1.
   }
} // end class WordData</pre>

<p>The program has to store all the <classname>WordData</classname> objects in some sort of
data structure. We want to be able to add new words efficiently. Given a word,
we need to check whether a <classname>WordData</classname> object already exists for that
word, and if it does, we need to find that object so that we can increment its
counter. A <classname>Map</classname> can be used to implement these operations. Given a
word, we want to look up a <classname>WordData</classname> object in the <classname>Map</classname>. This
means that the word is the <b>key</b>, and the <classname>WordData</classname> object is
the <b>value.</b> (It might seem strange that the key is also one of the
instance variables in the value object, but in fact this is a very
common situation: The value object contains all the information about some
entity, and the key is one of those pieces of information; the partial information
in the key is used to retrieve the full information in the value object.) After reading the
file, we want to output the words in alphabetical order, so we should use a
<classname>TreeMap</classname> rather than a <classname>HashMap</classname>. This program converts all
words to lower case so that the default ordering on <code>Strings</code> will put
the words in alphabetical order.  The data is stored in a variable named
<code>words</code> of type <classname>TreeMap&lt;String,WordData&gt;</classname>.
The variable is declared and the map object is created with the statement:</p>
   
<pre>TreeMap&lt;String,WordData&gt; words = new TreeMap&lt;&gt;();</pre>

<p>When the program reads a word from a file, it calls <code>words.get(word)</code>
to find out if that word is already in the map. If the return value is
<code>null</code>, then this is the first time the word has been encountered, so a
new <classname>WordData</classname> object is created and inserted into the map with the
command <code>words.put(word, new WordData(word))</code>. If
<code>words.get(word)</code> is not <code>null</code>, 
then its value is the <classname>WordData</classname>
object for this word, and the program only has to increment the counter in that
object.  The program uses a method <code>readNextWord()</code>, which was
given in <localref href="arrays.ex.6"/>, to read one word from the file.
This method returns <code>null</code> when the end of the file is encountered.
Here is the complete code segment that reads the file and collects the
data:</p>

<pre>String word = readNextWord();
while (word != null) {
   word = word.toLowerCase();  // convert word to lower case
   WordData data = words.get(word);
   if (data == null)
      words.put( word, new WordData(word) );
   else
      data.count++;
   word = readNextWord();
}</pre>

<p>After reading the words and printing them out in alphabetical order, the
program has to sort the words by frequency and print them again. To do
the sorting using a generic algorithm, we can copy the <classname>WordData</classname>
objects into a list and then use the generic method
<code>Collections.sort(list,comparator)</code>, which specifies a comparator
as its second parameter.  The comparator can be given as a lambda expression.</p>

<p>The <classname>WordData</classname> objects that we need are
the values in the map, <code>words</code>.  Recall that <code>words.values()</code> returns a
<classname>Collection</classname> that contains all the values from the map. The constructor for the
<classname>ArrayList</classname> class lets you specify a collection to be copied into the
list when it is created. So, we can use the following commands to create a list of type 
<classname>ArrayList&lt;WordData&gt;</classname> containing the word
data and then sort that list according to frequency:</p>

<pre>ArrayList&lt;WordData&gt; wordsByFrequency = new ArrayList&lt;&gt;( words.values() );
Collections.sort( wordsByFrequency, (a,b) -> b.count - a.count );</pre>

<np>You should notice that these two lines replace a lot of code! It requires
some practice to think in terms of generic data structures and algorithms, but
the payoff is significant in terms of saved time and effort.</np>

<p>The only remaining problem is to print the data. We have
to print the data from all the <classname>WordData</classname> objects twice, first in
alphabetical order and then sorted according to frequency count. The data is in
alphabetical order in the <classname>TreeMap</classname>, or more precisely, in the values of
the <classname>TreeMap</classname>.  We can use a for-each loop to
print the data in the collection <code>words.values()</code>, and the words will appear
in alphabetical order.  Another for-each loop can be used to print the
data in the list <code>wordsByFrequency</code>, and the words will be printed
in order of decreasing frequency.  Here is the code that does it:</p>

<pre>TextIO.putln("List of words in alphabetical order" 
      + " (with counts in parentheses):\n");
for ( WordData data : words.values() )
   TextIO.putln("   " + data.word + " (" + data.count + ")");

TextIO.putln("\n\nList of words by frequency of occurrence:\n");
for ( WordData data : wordsByFrequency )
   TextIO.putln("   " + data.word + " (" + data.count + ")");</pre>
   
<p>You can find the complete word-counting program in the file
<sourceref href="WordCount.java"/>.  Note that for reading and writing
files, it uses the file I/O capabilities of <sourceref href="textio/TextIO.java">TextIO.java</sourceref>,
which were discussed in <localref href="basics.4.4"/>.</p>
   
<p>By the way, if you run the WordCount program on a reasonably large file
and take a look at the output,
it will illustrate something about the <code>Collections.sort()</code> method.
The second list of words in the output is ordered by frequency, but if you
look at a group of words that all have the same frequency, you will see that
the words in that group are in alphabetical order.  The method
<code>Collections.sort()</code> was applied to sort the words by frequency,
but before it was applied, the words were already in alphabetical order.
When <code>Collections.sort()</code> rearranged the words, it did not
change the ordering of words that have the same frequency, so they were
still in alphabetical order within the group of words with that frequency.  This is
because the algorithm used by <code>Collections.sort()</code> is a
<newword>stable</newword> sorting algorithm.  A sorting algorithm is
said to be stable if it satisfies the following condition:  When the algorithm
is used to sort a list according to some property of the items in the
list, then the sort does not change the relative order of items that
have the same value of that property.  That is, if item&nbsp;B comes
after item&nbsp;A in the list before the sort, and if both items have
the same value for the property that is being used as the basis for
sorting, then item&nbsp;B will still come after item&nbsp;A after the
sorting has been done.  Neither SelectionSort nor QuickSort are stable
sorting algorithms.  Insertion sort is stable, but
is not very fast.  Merge sort, the sorting algorithm used by <code>Collections.sort()</code>,
is both stable and fast.</p>
   
<p>I hope that the programming examples in this section have convinced you
of the usefulness of the Java Collection Framework!</p>
   
</subsection>
   
</section>