<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes7.dtd" >

<section id="generics.5" title="Writing Generic Classes and Methods">
   
<p><start><big>S</big>o far in this chapter,</start> you have learned
about using the generic classes and methods that are part of the
Java Collection Framework.  Now, it's time to learn how to write
new generic classes and methods from scratch.  Generic programming produces
highly general and reusable code&mdash;it's very useful for people
who write reusable software libraries to know how to do generic
programming, since it enables them to write code that can be used in
many different situations.  Not every programmer needs to write reusable 
software libraries, but every programmer should know at least a little
about how to do it.  In fact, just to read the Javadoc documentation for
Java's standard generic classes, you need to know some of the syntax that is
introduced in this section.</p>

<p>I will not cover every detail of generic programming in Java in this
section, but the material presented here should be sufficient to cover the
most common cases.</p>
   
<subsection id="generics.5.1" title="Simple Generic Classes">
   
<p>Let's start with an example that illustrates the motivation for generic
programming.  In <localref href="generics.2.1"/>, I remarked that it would
be easy to use a <classname>LinkedList</classname> to implement a queue.
(Queues were introduced in <localref href="recursion.3.2"/>.)
To ensure that the only operations that are performed on the list are
the queue operations <code>enqueue</code>, <code>dequeue</code>, and
<code>isEmpty</code>, we can create a new class that contains the
linked list as a private instance variable.  To implement
queues of strings, for example, we can define the class:</p>
   
<pre>class QueueOfStrings {
   private LinkedList&lt;String&gt; items = new LinkedList&lt;String&gt;();
   public void enqueue(String item) {
      items.addLast(item);
   }
   public String dequeue() {
      return items.removeFirst();
   }
   public boolean isEmpty() {
      return (items.size() == 0);
   }
}</pre>
   
<p>This is a fine and useful class.  But, if this is how we write queue classes, and
if we want queues of <classname>Integers</classname>
or <classname>Doubles</classname> or <classname>JButtons</classname> or any other type,
then we will have to write a different class for each type.  The code for all of these
classes will be almost identical, which seems like a lot of redundant programming.
To avoid the redundancy, we can write a <b>generic</b> <classname>Queue</classname>
class that can be used to define queues of any type of object.</p>
  
<p>The syntax for writing the generic class is straightforward: We replace the specific
type <classname>String</classname> with a type parameter such as&nbsp;<classname>T</classname>,
and we add the type parameter to the name of the class:</p>

<pre>class Queue&lt;T&gt; {
   private LinkedList&lt;T&gt; items = new LinkedList&lt;T&gt;();
   public void enqueue(T item) {
      items.addLast(item);
   }
   public T dequeue() {
      return items.removeFirst();
   }
   public boolean isEmpty() {
      return (items.size() == 0);
   }
}</pre>
   
<p>Note that within the class, the type parameter <classname>T</classname> is used
just like any regular type name.  It's used to declare the return type for
<code>dequeue</code>, as the type of the formal parameter <code>item</code> in
<code>enqueue</code>, and even as the actual type parameter in <classname>LinkedList&lt;T&gt;</classname>.
Given this class definition, we can use parameterized types such
as <classname>Queue&lt;String&gt;</classname> and <classname>Queue&lt;Integer&gt;</classname>
and <classname>Queue&lt;JButton&gt;</classname>.  That is, the <classname>Queue</classname> class
is used in exactly the same way as built-in generic classes like <classname>LinkedList</classname>
and <classname>HashSet</classname>.</p>
   
<p>Note that you don't have to use "T" as the name of the type parameter in the
definition of the generic class.  Type parameters are like formal parameters in subroutines.
You can make up any name you like in the <b>definition</b> of the class.  The
name in the definition will be replaced by an actual type name when the class
is used to declare variables or create objects.  If you prefer to use a more
meaningful name for the type parameter, you might define the <classname>Queue</classname>
class as:</p>
      
<pre>class Queue&lt;<newcode>ItemType</newcode>&gt; {
   private LinkedList&lt;<newcode>ItemType</newcode>&gt; items = new LinkedList&lt;<newcode>ItemType</newcode>&gt;();
   public void enqueue(<newcode>ItemType</newcode> item) {
      items.addLast(item);
   }
   public <newcode>ItemType</newcode> dequeue() {
      return items.removeFirst();
   }
   public boolean isEmpty() {
      return (items.size() == 0);
   }
}</pre>
   
<np>Changing the name from "<code>T</code>" to "<code>ItemType</code>" has absolutely no effect on the meaning
of the class definition or on the way that <classname>Queue</classname> is used.</np>
   
<p>Generic interfaces can be defined in a similar way.
It's also easy to define generic classes and interfaces that have two or more type parameters,
as is done with the standard interface <classname>Map&lt;K,V&gt;</classname>. 
A typical example is the definition of a "Pair" that contains two objects,
possibly of different types.  A simple version of such a class can be defined as:</p>

<pre>class Pair&lt;T,S&gt; {
   public T first;
   public S second;
   public Pair( T a, S b ) {  // Constructor.
      first = a;
      second = b;
   }
}</pre>
   
<np>This class can be used to declare variables and create objects such as:</np>
   
<pre>Pair&lt;String,Color&gt; colorName = new Pair&lt;String,Color&gt;("Red", Color.RED);
Pair&lt;Double,Double&gt; coordinates = new Pair&lt;Double,Double&gt;(17.3,42.8);</pre>
   
<np>Note that in the definition of the constructor in this class, the name "<code>Pair</code>"
does <b>not</b> have type parameters.  You might have expected "<code>Pair&lt;T,S&gt;</code>".
However, the name of the class is "<code>Pair</code>", not "<code>Pair&lt;T,S&gt;</code>",
and within the definition of the class, "<code>T</code>" and "<code>S</code>" are used 
as if they are the names of specific, actual types.  Note in any case that type
parameters are <b>never</b> added to the names of methods or constructors, only
to the names of classes and interfaces.</np>
   
</subsection>
   

<subsection id="generics.5.2" title="Simple Generic Methods">
   
<p>In addition to generic classes, Java also has generic methods.  An example
is the method <code>Collections.sort()</code>, which can sort collections of
objects of any type.  To see how to write generic methods, let's start
with a non-generic method for counting the number of times that a
given string occurs in an array of strings:</p>
   
<pre>/**
 * Returns the number of times that itemToCount occurs in list.  Items in the
 * list are tested for equality using itemToCount.equals(), except in the
 * special case where itemToCount is null.
 */
public static int countOccurrences(String[] list, String itemToCount) {
   int count = 0;
   if (itemToCount == null) {
      for ( String listItem : list )
         if (listItem == null)
            count++;
   }
   else {
      for ( String listItem : list )
         if (itemToCount.equals(listItem))
            count++;
   }
   return count;
}</pre>
 
<p>Once again, we have some code that works for type <classname>String</classname>,
and we can imagine writing almost identical code to work with other types of objects.
By writing a generic method, we get to write a single method definition that will
work for objects of any type.  We need to replace the specific type <classname>String</classname>
in the definition of the method with the name of a type parameter, such as&nbsp;<classname>T</classname>.
However, if that's the only change we make, the compiler will think that "T" is the name
of an actual type, and it will mark it as an undeclared identifier.  We need some way of
telling the compiler that "T" is a type parameter.  That's what the "<code>&lt;T&gt;</code>"
does in the definition of the generic class "<code>class&nbsp;Queue&lt;T&gt;&nbsp;{&nbsp;...</code>".
For a generic method, the "<code>&lt;T&gt;</code>" goes just before the name of the return
type of the method:</p>

<pre>public static &lt;T&gt; int countOccurrences(T[] list, T itemToCount) {
   int count = 0;
   if (itemToCount == null) {
      for ( T listItem : list )
         if (listItem == null)
            count++;
   }
   else {
      for ( T listItem : list )
         if (itemToCount.equals(listItem))
            count++;
   }
   return count;
}   
</pre>
   
<np>The "<code>&lt;T&gt;</code>" marks the method as being generic and specifies the name
of the type parameter that will be used in the definition.  Of course, the name of the
type parameter doesn't have to be "T"; it can be anything.  (The "<code>&lt;T&gt;</code>"
looks a little strange in that position, I know, but it had to go somewhere and
that's just where the designers of Java decided to put it.)</np>
   
<p>Given the generic method definition, we can apply it to objects of any type.
If <code>wordList</code> is a variable of type
<atype>String[]</atype> and <code>word</code> is a variable of type <classname>String</classname>,
then</p>
   
<pre>int ct = countOccurrences( wordList, word );</pre>
   
<np>will count the number of times that <code>word</code> occurs in <code>wordList</code>.
If <code>palette</code> is a variable of type <atype>Color[]</atype> and
<code>color</code> is a variable of type <classname>Color</classname>, then</np>

<pre>int ct = countOccurrences( palette, color );</pre>
   
<np>will count the number of times that <code>color</code> occurs in <code>palette</code>.
If <code>numbers</code> is a variable of type <atype>Integer[]</atype>, then</np>

<pre>int ct = countOccurrences( numbers, 17 );</pre>
   
<np>will count the number of times that <code>17</code> occurs in <code>numbers</code>.
This last example uses autoboxing; the 17 is automatically converted to a value of
type <classname>Integer</classname>.  Note that,
since generic programming in Java applies only to objects, we <b>cannot</b> use
<code>countOccurrences</code> to count the number of occurrences of 17 in an
array of type <atype>int[]</atype>.</np>
   
<p>A generic method can have one or more type parameters, such as the "T" in
<code>countOccurrences</code>.  Note that when a generic method is used, 
as in the function call "<code>countOccurrences(wordlist, word)</code>", 
there is no explicit mention of the type that is substituted for the
type parameter.  The compiler deduces the type from the types of the
actual parameters in the method call.  Since <code>wordlist</code> is
of type <atype>String[]</atype>, the compiler can tell that in
"<code>countOccurrences(wordlist, word)</code>", the type that replaces
<classname>T</classname> is <classname>String</classname>.  This contrasts
with the use of generic classes, as in "<code>new&nbsp;Queue&lt;String&gt;()</code>",
where the type parameter is specified explicitly.</p>
   
<p>The <code>countOccurrences</code> method operates on an array.
We could also write a similar method to count occurrences of an object
in any collection:</p>
   
<pre>public static &lt;T&gt; int countOccurrences(Collection&lt;T&gt; collection, T itemToCount) {
   int count = 0;
   if (itemToCount == null) {
      for ( T item : collection )
         if (item == null)
            count++;
   }
   else {
      for ( T item : collection )
         if (itemToCount.equals(item))
            count++;
   }
   return count;
}</pre>
   
<p>Since <classname>Collection&lt;T&gt;</classname> is itself a generic type,
this method is very general.  It can operate on an <classname>ArrayList</classname>
of <classname>Integers</classname>, a <classname>TreeSet</classname> of <classname>Strings</classname>,
a <classname>LinkedList</classname> of <classname>JButtons</classname>,&nbsp;&dots;.</p>

</subsection>
   

<subsection id="generics.5.3" title="Type Wildcards">
   
<p>There is a limitation on the sort of generic classes and methods that we have
looked at so far:  The type parameter in our examples, usually named <classname>T</classname>,
can be any type at all.  This is OK in many cases, but it means that the only things that
you can do with <classname>T</classname> are things that can be done with <b>every</b> type,
and the only things that you can do with objects of type <classname>T</classname>
are things that you can do with <b>every</b> object.  With the techniques that we have
covered so far, you can't, for example, write a generic method that compares
objects with the <code>compareTo()</code> method, since that
method is not defined for all objects.  The <code>compareTo()</code> method is
defined in the <classname>Comparable</classname> interface.  What we need is a
way of specifying that a generic class or method only applies to objects of
type <classname>Comparable</classname> and not to arbitrary objects.  With that
restriction, we should be free to use <code>compareTo()</code> in the definition of
the generic class or method.</p>

<p>There are two different but related syntaxes for putting restrictions on the
types that are used in generic programming.  One of these is <newword>bounded type parameters</newword>,
which are used as formal type parameters in generic class and method definitions;
a bounded type parameter would be used in place of the simple type parameter <classname>T</classname>
in "<code>class GenericClass&lt;T&gt;&nbsp;...</code>" or in "<code>public static
&lt;T&gt; void genericMethod(...</code>".  The second syntax is <newword>wildcard
types</newword>, which are used as type parameters in the declarations of
variables and of formal parameters in method definitions; a wildcard type could be used in
place of the type parameter <classname>String</classname> in the declaration
statement "<code>List&lt;String&gt;&nbsp;list;</code>" or in the formal parameter list
"<code>void concat(Collection&lt;String&gt;&nbsp;c)</code>".  We will look at
wildcard types first, and we will return to the topic of bounded types later
in this section.</p>
   
<p>Let's start with a simple example in which a wildcard type is useful.
Suppose that <classname>Shape</classname> is
a class that defines a method <code>public void draw()</code>, and suppose that
<classname>Shape</classname> has subclasses such as <classname>Rect</classname> 
and <classname>Oval</classname>.  Suppose that we want a method that can draw
all the shapes in a collection of <classname>Shapes</classname>.  We might try:</p>
   
<pre>public static void drawAll(Collection&lt;Shape&gt; shapes) {
   for ( Shape s : shapes )
      s.draw();
}</pre>

<p>This method works fine if we apply it to a variable of type
<classname>Collection&lt;Shape&gt;</classname>, or <classname>ArrayList&lt;Shape&gt;</classname>,
or any other collection class with type parameter <classname>Shape</classname>.
Suppose, however, that you have a list of <classname>Rects</classname> stored
in a variable named <code>rectangles</code> of type <classname>Collection&lt;Rect&gt;</classname>.
Since <classname>Rects</classname> are <classname>Shapes</classname>, you might
expect to be able to call <code>drawAll(rectangles)</code>.  Unfortunately, this
will not work; a collection of <classname>Rects</classname> is <b>not</b> considered
to be a collection of <classname>Shapes</classname>!  The variable <code>rectangles</code>
cannot be assigned to the formal parameter <code>shapes</code>.  The solution is to
replace the type parameter "<code>Shape</code>" in the declaration of
<code>shapes</code> with the wildcard type "<code>?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;Shape</code>":
</p>

<pre>public static void drawAll(Collection&lt;<newcode>? extends Shape</newcode>&gt; shapes) {
   for ( Shape s : shapes )
      s.draw();
}</pre>

<np>The wildcard type "<code>?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;Shape</code>" means roughly
"any type that is either equal to <classname>Shape</classname> or 
that is a subclass of <classname>Shape</classname>".  When the
parameter <code>shapes</code> is declared to be of type
<classname>Collection&lt;?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;Shape&gt;</classname>, it
becomes possible to call the <code>drawAll</code> method with an actual
parameter of type <classname>Collection&lt;Rect&gt;</classname> since 
<classname>Rect</classname> is a subclass of <classname>Shape</classname>
and therefore matches the wildcard.
We could also pass actual parameters to <code>drawAll</code> of type
<classname>ArrayList&lt;Rect&gt;</classname> or <classname>Set&lt;Oval&gt;</classname>
or <classname>List&lt;Oval&gt;</classname>.  And we can still pass
variables of type <classname>Collection&lt;Shape&gt;</classname>
or <classname>ArrayList&lt;Shape&gt;</classname>, since the class
<classname>Shape</classname> itself matches "<code>?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;Shape</code>".
We have greatly increased the usefulness of the method by using the
wildcard type.</np>

<p>(Although it is not essential, you might be interested in knowing <i>why</i>
Java does not allow a collection of <classname>Rects</classname> to be used
as a collection of <classname>Shapes</classname>, even though every <classname>Rect</classname>
is considered to be a <classname>Shape</classname>.  Consider the rather silly
but legal method that adds an oval to a list of shapes:</p>
   
<pre>static void addOval(List&lt;Shape&gt; shapes, Oval oval) {
   shapes.add(oval);
}</pre>
   
<np>Suppose that <code>rectangles</code> is of type <classname>List&lt;Rect&gt;</classname>.
It's illegal to call <code>addOval(rectangles,oval)</code>, because of the rule that
a list of <classname>Rects</classname> is not a list of <classname>Shapes</classname>.
If we dropped that rule, then <code>addOval(rectangles,oval)</code> would be legal,
and it would add an <classname>Oval</classname> to a list of <classname>Rects</classname>.
This would be bad: Since <classname>Oval</classname> is not a subclass of <classname>Rect</classname>,
an <classname>Oval</classname> is <b>not</b> a <classname>Rect</classname>, 
and a list of <classname>Rects</classname> should never be able to contain an <classname>Oval</classname>.
The method call <code>addOval(rectangles,oval)</code> does not make sense and
<b>should</b> be illegal, so the rule that a collection of <classname>Rects</classname> 
is not a collection of <classname>Shapes</classname> is a good rule.)</np>
   
<p>As another example, consider the method <code>addAll()</code> from the
interface <classname>Collection&lt;T&gt;</classname>.  In my description of
this method in <localref href="generics.1.4"/>, I say that for a collection, <code>coll</code>,
of type <classname>Collection&lt;T&gt;</classname>, <code>coll.addAll(coll2)</code>
"adds all the objects in <code>coll2</code> to <code>coll</code>. The parameter, <code>coll2</code>, 
can be any collection of type <classname>Collection&lt;T&gt;</classname>. However, it can also be 
more general. For example, if <classname>T</classname> is a class and <classname>S</classname> 
is a sub-class of <classname>T</classname>, then <code>coll2</code> can be of type 
<classname>Collection&lt;S&gt;</classname>.  This makes sense because any object of type <classname>S</classname>
is automatically of type <classname>T</classname> and so can legally be added to <code>coll</code>." 
If you think for a moment, you'll see that what I'm
describing here, a little awkwardly, is a use of wildcard types: We don't want to
require <code>coll2</code> to be a collection of objects of type <classname>T</classname>;
we want to allow collections of any subclass of <classname>T</classname>.
To be more specific, let's look at how a similar <code>addAll()</code> method could
be added to the generic <classname>Queue</classname> class that was defined earlier
in this section:</p>

<pre>class Queue&lt;T&gt; {
   private LinkedList&lt;T&gt; items = new LinkedList&lt;T&gt;();
   public void enqueue(T item) {
      items.addLast(item);
   }
   public T dequeue() {
      return items.removeFirst();
   }
   public boolean isEmpty() {
      return (items.size() == 0);
   }
   <newcode>public void addAll(Collection&lt;? extends T&gt; collection) {
         // Add all the items from the collection to the end of the queue
      for ( T item : collection ) 
         enqueue(item);
   }</newcode>
}</pre>
   
<p>Here, <classname>T</classname> is a type parameter in the generic class definition.
We are combining wildcard types with generic classes.
Inside the generic class definition, "<code>T</code>" is used as if it is a specific, though unknown, type.
The wildcard type "<code>?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;T</code>" means some type that is equal to or extends that specific type.
When we create a queue of type <classname>Queue&lt;Shape&gt;</classname>, "<code>T</code>" refers to "Shape",
and the wildcard type "<code>?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;T</code>" in the class definition means
"<code>?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;Shape</code>", meaning that the <code>addAll</code> method of the queue 
can be applied to collections of <classname>Rects</classname> and <classname>Ovals</classname>
as well as to collections of <classname>Shapes</classname>.</p>
   
<p>The for-each loop in the definition of <code>addAll</code> iterates through the
<code>collection</code> using a variable, <code>item</code>, of type <classname>T</classname>.
Now, <code>collection</code> can be of type <classname>Collection&lt;S&gt;</classname>,
where <classname>S</classname> is a subclass of <classname>T</classname>.  Since
<code>item</code> is of type <classname>T</classname>, not <classname>S</classname>,
do we have a problem here?  No, no problem.  As long as <classname>S</classname> is a 
subclass of <classname>T</classname>, a value of type <classname>S</classname> can
be assigned to a variable of type <classname>T</classname>.  The restriction
on the wildcard type makes everything work nicely.</p> 
   
<p>The <code>addAll</code> method adds all the items from a collection to the queue.
Suppose that we wanted to do the opposite: Add all the items that are currently
on the queue to a given collection.  An instance method defined as</p>
   
<pre>public void addAllTo(Collection&lt;T&gt; collection)</pre>
   
<np>would only work for collections whose base type is exactly the same as
<classname>T</classname>.  This is too restrictive.  We need some sort of wildcard.
However, "<code>?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;T</code>" won't work.  Suppose we try it:</np>
   
<pre>public void addAllTo(Collection&lt;? extends T&gt; collection) {
      // Remove all items currently on the queue and add them to collection
   while ( ! isEmpty() ) {
      T item = dequeue();  // Remove an item from the queue.
      collection.add( item );  // Add it to the collection.  <newcode>ILLEGAL!!</newcode>
   }
}</pre>
   
<np>The problem is that we can't add an <code>item</code> of type <classname>T</classname>
to a collection that might only be able to hold items belonging to some
subclass, <classname>S</classname>, of <classname>T</classname>.  The containment is
going in the wrong direction: An <code>item</code> of type <classname>T</classname>
is not necessarily of type <classname>S</classname>.   For example, if we have
a queue of type <classname>Queue&lt;Shape&gt;</classname>, it doesn't make sense
to add items from the queue to a collection of type <classname>Collection&lt;Rect&gt;</classname>,
since not every <classname>Shape</classname> is a <classname>Rect</classname>.
On the other hand, if we have a <classname>Queue&lt;Rect&gt;</classname>, it would
make sense to add items from that queue to a <classname>Collection&lt;Shape&gt;</classname>
or indeed to any collection <classname>Collection&lt;S&gt;</classname> where
<classname>S</classname> is a <b>super</b>class of <classname>Rect</classname>.
</np>
   
<p>To express this type of relationship, we need a new kind of type wildcard:
"<code>?&nbsp;super&nbsp;T</code>".  This wildcard means, roughly, "either <classname>T</classname>
itself or any class that is a superclass of <classname>T</classname>."  For example,
<classname>Collection&lt;?&nbsp;super&nbsp;Rect&gt;</classname> would
match the types <classname>Collection&lt;Shape&gt;</classname>,
<classname>ArrayList&lt;Object&gt;</classname>, and <classname>Set&lt;Rect&gt;</classname>.
This is what we need for our <code>addAllTo</code> method.  With this change,
our complete generic queue class becomes:</p>
   
<pre>class Queue&lt;T&gt; {
   private LinkedList&lt;T&gt; items = new LinkedList&lt;T&gt;();
   public void enqueue(T item) {
      items.addLast(item);
   }
   public T dequeue() {
      return items.removeFirst();
   }
   public boolean isEmpty() {
      return (items.size() == 0);
   }
   public void addAll(Collection&lt;? extends T&gt; collection) {
         // Add all the items from the collection to the end of the queue
      for ( T item : collection ) 
         enqueue(item);
   }
   <newcode>public void addAllTo(Collection&lt;? super T&gt; collection) {
         // Remove all items currently on the queue and add them to collection
      while ( ! isEmpty() ) {
         T item = dequeue();  // Remove an item from the queue.
         collection.add( item );  // Add it to the collection.
      }
   }</newcode>
}</pre>
   
   
<p>In a wildcard type such as "<code>?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;T</code>", <classname>T</classname>
can be an <code>interface</code> instead of a class.  Note that the term
"<code>extends</code>"  (not "<code>implements</code>") is used
in the wildcard type, even if <classname>T</classname> is an interface.  For
example, we will see that <classname>Runnable</classname> is an <code>interface</code>
that defines the method <code>public void run()</code>.  (Runnable objects
are usually associated with threads; see <localref href="threads"/>.)
Here is a method that runs all the objects in a collection of
<classname>Runnables</classname> by executing the <code>run()</code>
method from each runnable object:</p>

<pre>public static runAll( Collection&lt;?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;Runnable&gt; runnables ) {
   for ( Runnable runnable : runnables ) {
      runnable.run();
   }
}</pre>
   
<break/>
   
<p>Wildcard types are used <b>only</b> as type parameters in parameterized
types, such as <classname>Collection&lt;?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;Runnable&gt;</classname>.
The place where a wildcard type is most likely to occur, by far, is
in a formal parameter list, where the wildcard type is used in the declaration of the type
of a formal parameter.  However, they can also be used in a few other places.  
For example, they can be used  in the type specification in a variable declaration 
statement.</p>
   
<p>One final remark: The wildcard type "<code>&lt;?&gt;</code>" is equivalent to
"<code>&lt;?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;Object&gt;</code>".  That is, it matches any possible
type.  For example, the <code>removeAll()</code> method in the generic interface
<classname>Collections&lt;T&gt;</classname> is declared as</p>
   
<pre>public boolean removeAll( Collection&lt;?&gt; c ) { ...</pre>
   
<np>This just means that the <code>removeAll</code> method can be applied to any
collection of any type of object.</np>
   
</subsection>

<subsection id="generics.5.4" title="Bounded Types">
   
<p>Wildcard types don't solve all of our problems.  They allow us to generalize
method definitions so that they can work with collections of objects of various types,
rather than just a single type.  However, they do not allow us to restrict
the types that are allowed as type parameters in a generic class or method definition.
Bounded types exist for this purpose.</p>
   
<p>We start with a small, not very realistic example.  
Suppose that you would like to create groups of GUI
components using a generic class named <classname>ComponentGroup</classname>.
For example, the parameterized type <classname>ComponentGroup&lt;JButton&gt;</classname>
would represent a group of <classname>JButtons</classname>, while 
<classname>ComponentGroup&lt;JPanel&gt;</classname> would represent a group
of <classname>JPanels</classname>.  The class will include methods that can be
called to apply certain operations to all components in the group at once.
For example, there will be an instance method of the form</p>
   
<pre>public void repaintAll() {
   .
   .  // Call the repaint() method of every component in the group.
   .
}</pre>
   
<np>The problem is that the <code>repaint()</code> method is defined in a
<classname>JComponent</classname> object, but not for objects of arbitrary
type.  It wouldn't make sense to allow types such as
<classname>ComponentGroup&lt;String&gt;</classname> or 
<classname>ComponentGroup&lt;Integer&gt;</classname>, since <classname>Strings</classname>
and <classname>Integers</classname> don't have <code>repaint()</code> methods.
We need some way to restrict the type parameter <classname>T</classname>
in <classname>ComponentGroup&lt;T&gt;</classname> so that only <classname>JComponent</classname>
and subclasses of <classname>JComponent</classname> are allowed
as actual type parameters.
We can do this by using the <newword>bounded type</newword> "<code>T&nbsp;extends&nbsp;JComponent</code>"
instead of a plain "<code>T</code>" in the definition of the class:
</np>

<pre>public class ComponentGroup&lt;<newcode>T extends JComponent</newcode>&gt; {
   private ArrayList&lt;T&gt; components; // For storing the components in this group.
   public void repaintAll() {
      for ( JComponent c : components )
         if (c != null)
            c.repaint();
   }
   public void setAllEnabled( boolean enable ) {
      for ( JComponent c : components )
         if (c != null)
            c.setEnabled(enable);
      }
   }
   public void add( T c ) {  // Add a value c, of type T, to the group.
      components.add(c);
   }
   .
   .  // Additional methods and constructors.
   .
}</pre>
   
<p>The restriction "<code>extends JComponent</code>" on <code>T</code> makes it
illegal to create the parameterized types <classname>ComponentGroup&lt;String&gt;</classname> and
<classname>ComponentGroup&lt;Integer&gt;</classname>, since the actual type parameter
that replaces "<code>T</code>" is required to be either <classname>JComponent</classname> itself
or a subclass of <classname>JComponent</classname>.
With this restriction, we know&mdash;and, more important, the compiler knows&mdash;that
the objects in the group are of type <classname>JComponent</classname> and the
operations <code>c.repaint()</code> and <code>c.setEnabled()</code> are defined
for any <code>c</code> in the group.</p>
  
<p>In general, a bounded type parameter "<code>T&nbsp;extends&nbsp;SomeType</code>" means roughly
"a type, <classname>T</classname>, that is either equal to <classname>SomeType</classname>
or is a subclass of <classname>SomeType</classname>", and the upshot is that any
object of type <classname>T</classname> is also of type <classname>SomeType</classname>, and
any operation that is defined for objects of type <classname>SomeType</classname>
is defined for objects of type <classname>T</classname>.  The type
<classname>SomeType</classname> doesn't have to be the name of a class.
It can be any name that represents an actual object type.  For example, it can be
an <code>interface</code> or even a parameterized type.</p>
   
<p>Bounded types and wildcard types are clearly related.
They are, however, used in very different ways.  A bounded type can be used only
as a formal type parameter in the definition of a generic method, class, or interface.
A wildcard type is used most often to declare the type of a formal parameter in a
method and cannot be used as a formal type parameter.  One other difference, by 
the way, is that, in contrast to wildcard types, bounded type parameters can only
use "<code>extends</code>", never "<code>super</code>".</p> 
   
<p>Bounded type parameters can be used when declaring generic methods.
For example, as an alternative to the generic <classname>ComponentGroup</classname>
class, one could write a free-standing generic <code>static</code> method that can
repaint any collection of <classname>JComponents</classname> as follows:</p>
   
<pre>public static &lt;T extends JComponent&gt; void repaintAll(Collection&lt;T&gt; comps) {
   for ( JComponent c : comps )
      if (c != null)
         c.repaint();
}</pre>
   
<np>Using "<code>&lt;T extends JComponent&gt;</code>" as the formal type parameter
means that the method can only be called for collections whose base type is
<classname>JComponent</classname> or some subclass of <classname>JComponent</classname>.
Thus, it is legal to call <code>repaintAll(coll)</code> where <code>coll</code>
is of type <classname>List&lt;JPanel&gt;</classname> but not where
<code>coll</code> is of type <classname>Set&lt;String&gt;</classname>.</np>
   

<p>Note that we don't really need a generic type parameter in this case.  We can
write an equivalent method using a wildcard type:</p>
      
<pre>public static void repaintAll(Collection&lt;? extends JComponent&gt; comps) {
   for ( JComponent c : comps )
      if (c != null)
         c.repaint();
}</pre>

<np>In this situation, the version that uses the wildcard type is to be preferred,
since the implementation is simpler.  However, there are some situations where
a generic method with a bounded type parameter cannot be rewritten using 
a wildcard type. Note that a generic type parameter gives a name, such as <classname>T</classname>,
to the unknown type, while a wildcard type does not give a name to the unknown type.
The name makes it possible to refer to the unknown type in the body of the method
that is being defined.  If a generic method definition uses the generic type name
more than once or uses it outside the formal parameter list of the method,
then the generic type cannot be replaced with a wildcard type.</np>

<p>Let's look at a generic method in which a bounded type parameter is essential.  
In <localref href="generics.2.1"/>, I presented a code segment for inserting
a string into a sorted list of strings, in such a way that the modified list
is still in sorted order.  Here is the same code, but this time in the form
of a method definition (and without the comments):</p>
   
<pre>static void sortedInsert(List&lt;String&gt; sortedList, String newItem) {
   ListIterator&lt;String&gt; iter = sortedList.listIterator();
   while (iter.hasNext()) {
      String item = iter.next();
      if (newItem.compareTo(item) &lt;= 0) {
         iter.previous();
         break;
      } 
   }
   iter.add(newItem);
}</pre>
   
<p>This method works fine for lists of strings, but it would be nice to have
a generic method that can be applied to lists of other types of objects.  The
problem, of course, is that the code assumes that the <code>compareTo()</code>
method is defined for objects in the list, so the method can only work for
lists of objects that implement the <classname>Comparable</classname> interface.
We can't simply use a wildcard type to enforce this restriction.  Suppose we try to do it, by replacing
<classname>List&lt;String&gt;</classname> with 
<classname>List&lt;?&nbsp;extends&nbsp;Comparable&gt;</classname>:</p>

<pre>static void sortedInsert(List&lt;? extends Comparable&gt; sortedList, <newcode>????</newcode> newItem) {
   ListIterator&lt;<newcode>????</newcode>&gt; iter = stringList.listIterator();
   ...</pre>
   
<np>We immediately run into a problem, because we have no name for the unknown
type represented by the wildcard.  We <b>need</b> a name for that type because
the type of <code>newItem</code> and of <code>iter</code> should be the same
as the type of the items in the list.  The problem is solved if we write a
generic method with a bounded type parameter, since then we have a name for
the unknown type, and we can write a valid generic method:</np>
   
<pre>static &lt;T extends Comparable&gt; void sortedInsert(List&lt;T&gt; sortedList, T newItem) {
   ListIterator&lt;T&gt; iter = sortedList.listIterator();
   while (iter.hasNext()) {
      T item = iter.next();
      if (newItem.compareTo(item) &lt;= 0) {
         iter.previous();
         break;
      } 
   }
   iter.add(newItem);
}</pre>

<p>There is still one technicality to cover in this example.  <classname>Comparable</classname>
is itself a parameterized type, but I have used it here without a type parameter.
This is legal but the compiler might give you a warning about using a "raw type."
In fact, the objects in the list should implement the parameterized interface
<classname>Comparable&lt;T&gt;</classname>, since they are being compared to items
of type <classname>T</classname>.  This just means that instead of using
<classname>Comparable</classname> as the type bound, we should use
<classname>Comparable&lt;T&gt;</classname>:</p>
   
<pre>static &lt;T extends <newcode>Comparable&lt;T&gt;</newcode>&gt; void sortedInsert(List&lt;T&gt; sortedList, ...</pre>
   
<break/>
   
<p>With this example, I will leave the topic of generic types and generic programming.
In this chapter, I have occasionally used terms such as "strange" and "weird" to
talk about generic programming in Java.  I will confess that I have some affection
for the more simple-minded generic programming style of Smalltalk.  Nevertheless,
I recognize the power and increased robustness of generics in Java.  I hope that
I have convinced you that using the Java Collection Framework is reasonably
natural and straightforward, and that using it can save you a lot of time and
effort compared to repeatedly recoding the same data structures and algorithms
from scratch.  Things become more technical when you
start writing new generic classes and methods of your own, and the syntax is
(as I've said) a little strange.  But with some practice, you'll get used to the
syntax and will find that it's not that difficult after all.</p>
   



 
</subsection>

<endchapter/>
</section>