<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE intro SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<intro>
<p><start><big>C</big>omputers get a lot of their power</start> from working
with <newword>data structures</newword>. A data structure is an
organized collection of related data. An object is a data structure, combined
usually with some methods, but this
type of data structure&mdash;consisting of a fairly small number of named instance
variables&mdash;is just the beginning. In many cases, programmers build
complicated data structures by hand, by linking objects together. We'll look at
these custom-built data structures in <localref href="recursion"/>.  This
chapter looks at more basic data structures. There is one type of
data structure that is so important and so basic that it is built into every
programming language: the array.</p>

<p>You have already encountered arrays in <localref href="control.7a"/>
and <localref href="OOP.1.4"/>.  We continue the study of arrays in this chapter,
including some new details of their use and some additional array-processing
techniques.  In particular, we will look at the important topic of algorithms for
searching and sorting an array in <localref href="arrays.4"/>.</p>

<p>An array has a fixed size that can't be changed after the array is created.
But in many cases, it is useful to have a data structure that can grow and shrink
as necessary.  In <localref href="arrays.3"/>, we will look at a standard class, 
<classname>ArrayList</classname>, that represents such a data structure.</p>

<p>An array is a numbered sequence of items, all of the same type.  A <newword>record</newword>
is another kind of standard data structure.  Like an array, a record consists of a sequence of items,
but in a record, the items are referred to by name instead of by number, and
the items can be of different types.  Any object in Java can be thought of
as a record in this sense, but Java&nbsp;17 introduced records explicitly 
into the language as a special kind of class with certain restrictions.
We will look at record classes in <localref href="arrays.3a"/>.</p>

</intro>