<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="arrays.3" title="ArrayList">
   
   
<p><start><big>A</big>s we have just seen</start> in <localref href="arrays.2.4"/>,
we can easily encode the dynamic array pattern into a class, but it looks like
we need a different class for each data type.  In fact, Java has a feature called
"parameterized types" that makes it possible to avoid the multitude of classes, and
Java has a single class named <classname>ArrayList</classname> that implements the
dynamic array pattern for all data types that are defined as classes (but not,
directly, for primitive types).</p>
 

<subsection id="arrays.3.1" title="ArrayList and Parameterized Types">   

<p>Java has a standard type with the rather odd name <atype>ArrayList&lt;String&gt;</atype> that represents
dynamic arrays of <classname>Strings</classname>.  Similarly, there is a type <atype>ArrayList&lt;Color&gt;</atype>
that can be used to represent dynamic arrays of <classname>Colors</classname>.  And if
<classname>Player</classname> is a class representing players in a game, then
the type <atype>ArrayList&lt;Player&gt;</atype> can be used to represent a dynamic
array of <classname>Players</classname>.</p>

<p>It might look like we still have a multitude of classes here, but in fact there
is only one class, the <classname>ArrayList</classname> class, defined in the package
<code>java.util</code>.  But <classname>ArrayList</classname> is a 
<newword>parameterized type</newword>.  A parameterized type can take a type
parameter, so that from the single class <classname>ArrayList</classname>,
we get a multitude of types including <atype>ArrayList&lt;String&gt;</atype>,
<atype>ArrayList&lt;Color&gt;</atype>, and in fact <atype>ArrayList&lt;T&gt;</atype>
for any object type <classname>T</classname>.  The type parameter <classname>T</classname>
must be an object type such as a class name or an interface name.  It cannot be
a primitive type.  This means that, unfortunately, you can not have an ArrayList of
<ptype>int</ptype> or an ArrayList of <ptype>char</ptype>.</p>

<p>Consider the type <atype>ArrayList&lt;String&gt;</atype>.  As a type, it can
be used to declare variables, such as</p>

<pre>ArrayList&lt;String&gt; namelist;</pre>

<np>It can also be used as the type of a formal parameter in a subroutine definition,
or as the return type of a subroutine.  It can be used with the <code>new</code>
operator to create objects:</np>

<pre>namelist = new ArrayList&lt;String&gt;();</pre>

<np>The object created in this way is of type <atype>ArrayList&lt;String&gt;</atype> and
represents a dynamic list of strings.  It has instance methods such as
<code>namelist.add(str)</code> for adding a <classname>String</classname> to the list,
<code>namelist.get(i)</code> for getting the string at index <code>i</code>,
and <code>namelist.size()</code> for getting the number of items currently in the list.</np>

<p>But we can also use <classname>ArrayList</classname> with other types.
If <classname>Player</classname> is a class representing players in a game, we can
create a list of players with</p>

<pre>ArrayList&lt;Player&gt; playerList = new ArrayList&lt;Player&gt;();</pre>

<np>Then to add a player, <code>plr</code>, to the game, we just have to say
<code>playerList.add(plr)</code>.  And we can remove player number <code>k</code>
with <code>playerList.remove(k)</code>.</np>

<p>Furthermore if <code>playerList</code> is a local variable, then
its declaration can be abbreviated to</p>

<pre>var playlerList = new ArrayList&lt;Player&gt;();</pre>

<np>using the alternative declaration syntax that was covered in
<localref href="subroutines.7.1a"/>.  The Java compiler uses the
initial value that is assigned to <code>playerList</code> to deduce that
its type is <atype>ArrayList&lt;Player&gt;</atype>.</np>

<p>When you use a type such as <atype>ArrayList&lt;T&gt;</atype>, the compiler will
ensure that only objects of type <classname>T</classname> can be added to the list.
An attempt to add an object that is not of type <classname>T</classname> will be
a syntax error, and the program will not compile.  However, note that objects
belonging to a subclass of <classname>T</classname> can be added to the list, since
objects belonging to a subclass of <classname>T</classname> are still considered to
be of type <classname>T</classname>. Thus, if class <classname>Shape</classname>
has subclasses <classname>Rectangle</classname>, <classname>Oval</classname>
and <classname>RounRect</classname>, then a variable of type
<atype>ArrayList&lt;Shape&gt;</atype> can be used to hold objects of type
<classname>Rectangle</classname>, <classname>Oval</classname>, and <classname>RoundRect</classname>.
(Of course, this is the same way arrays work:  An array of type <atype>T[]</atype>
can hold objects belonging to any subclass of <classname>T</classname>.)
Similarly, if <classname>T</classname> is an interface, then any object that 
implements interface <classname>T</classname> can be added to the list.</p>

<p>An object of type <atype>ArrayList&lt;T&gt;</atype> has all of the instance methods
that you would expect in a dynamic array implementation.  Here are some of the most
useful.  Suppose that <code>list</code> is a variable of type <atype>ArrayList&lt;T&gt;</atype>.
Then we have:</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>list.size()</codedef> &mdash; This function returns
the current size of the list, that is, the number of items currently in the list. 
The only valid positions in the
list are numbers in the range <code>0</code> to <code>list.size()-1</code>. Note that
the size can be zero. A call to the default constructor <code>new&nbsp;ArrayList&lt;T&gt;()</code> 
creates a list of size zero.</li>
<li><codedef>list.add(obj)</codedef> &mdash; Adds an object onto
the end of the list, increasing the size by&nbsp;1. The parameter,
<code>obj</code>, can refer to an object of type <classname>T</classname>, 
or it can be <code>null</code>.</li>
<li><codedef>list.get(N)</codedef> &mdash; This function returns
the value stored at position <code>N</code> in the list.  The return type of
this function is&nbsp;<classname>T</classname>.&nbsp; <code>N</code>
must be an integer in the range <code>0</code> to <code>list.size()-1</code>. If
<code>N</code> is outside this range, an error of type <classname>IndexOutOfBoundsException</classname>
occurs. Calling this function is
similar to referring to <code>A[N]</code> for an array, <code>A</code>, except that you
can't use <code>list.get(N)</code> on the left side of an assignment statement.</li>
<li><codedef>list.set(N, obj)</codedef> &mdash; Assigns the
object, <code>obj</code>, to position <code>N</code> in the <classname>ArrayList</classname>,
replacing the item previously stored at position <code>N</code>. The parameter <code>obj</code>
must be of type <classname>T</classname>.  The integer
<code>N</code> must be in the range from <code>0</code> to <code>list.size()-1</code>. A
call to this function is equivalent to the command <code>A[N]&nbsp;=&nbsp;obj</code> for an
array&nbsp;<code>A</code>.</li>
<li><codedef>list.clear()</codedef> &mdash; Removes all items from the list, setting its size
to zero.</li>
<li><codedef>list.remove(N)</codedef> &mdash; For an integer,
<code>N</code>, this removes the <code>N-th</code> item in the <classname>ArrayList</classname>.
<code>N</code> must be in the range <code>0</code> to <code>list.size()-1</code>. Any items
in the list that come after the removed item are moved up one position. The
size of the list decreases by 1.  This method returns the removed item.</li>
<li><codedef>list.remove(obj)</codedef> &mdash; If the specified
object occurs somewhere in the list, it is removed from the list.
Any items in the list that come after the removed item are moved up one
position. The size of the <classname>ArrayList</classname> decreases by 1. If <code>obj</code>
occurs more than once in the list, only the first copy is removed.  If <code>obj</code>
does not occur in the list, nothing happens; this is not an error. This method
returns a <ptype>boolean</ptype> value that says whether or not an item was
actually removed.</li>
<li><codedef>list.indexOf(obj)</codedef> &mdash; A function that
searches for the object, <code>obj</code>, in the list. If the object
is found in the list, then the first position number where it is found is returned.
If the object is not found, then <code>-1</code> is returned.</li>
</ul>

<np>For the last two methods listed here, <code>obj</code> is compared to
an item in the list by calling <code>obj.equals(item)</code>, unless <code>obj</code>
is null.  This means, for example, that strings are tested for equality by checking
the contents of the strings, not their location in memory.</np>

<p>Java comes with several parameterized classes representing different data structures.
Those classes make up the <newword>Java Collection Framework</newword>.  Here we consider
only <classname>ArrayList</classname>, but we will return to this important topic in
much more detail in <localref href="generics"/>.</p>

<p>By the way, <classname>ArrayList</classname> can also be used as a non-parametrized
type.  This means that you can declare variables and create objects of type <classname>ArrayList</classname>
such as</p>

<pre>ArrayList list = new ArrayList();</pre>

<np>The effect of this is similar to declaring <code>list</code> to be of type
<atype>ArrayList&lt;Object&gt;</atype>.  That is, <code>list</code> can hold
any object that belongs to a subclass of <classname>Object</classname>.  Since every
class is a subclass of <classname>Object</classname>, this means that <b>any</b>
object can be stored in <code>list</code>.</np>

</subsection>
   
<subsection  id="arrays.3.2" title="Wrapper Classes">
   
<p>As I have already noted, parameterized types don't work with the primitive types.
There is no such thing as "<atype>ArrayList&lt;int&gt;</atype>".  However, this limitation
turns out not to be very limiting after all, because of the so-called
<newword>wrapper classes</newword> such as <classname>Integer</classname>
and <classname>Character</classname>.</p>
 
<p>We have already briefly encountered the classes <classname>Double</classname> and
<classname>Integer</classname> in <localref href="basics.5"/>.  These classes
contain the <code>static</code> methods <code>Double.parseDouble()</code>
and <code>Integer.parseInteger()</code> that are used to convert strings to
numerical values, and they contain constants such as <code>Integer.MAX_VALUE</code> and <code>Double.NaN</code>.
We have also encountered the <classname>Character</classname>
class in some examples, with the static method <code>Character.isLetter()</code>,
that can be used to test whether a given value of type <code>char</code> is a
letter.  There is a similar class for each of the other primitive types,
<classname>Long</classname>, <classname>Short</classname>, <classname>Byte</classname>, 
<classname>Float</classname>, and <classname>Boolean</classname>.
These classes are wrapper classes.  Although they
contain useful <code>static</code> members, they have another use as
well:  They are used for representing primitive type
values as objects.</p>
   
<p>Remember that the primitive types are not classes, and values of primitive type
are not objects.  However, sometimes it's useful to treat a primitive value
as if it were an object.  This is true, for example, when you would like to store
primitive type values in an <classname>ArrayList</classname>.
You can't do that literally, but you can "wrap" the
primitive type value in an object belonging to one of the wrapper classes.</p>
   
<p>For example, an object of type <classname>Integer</classname> contains a single instance
variable, of type <ptype>int</ptype>.  The object is a "wrapper" 
for the <ptype>int</ptype> value.  You can get an object that
wraps the <ptype>int</ptype> value <code>42</code> with</p>
   
<pre>Integer n = Integer.valueOf(42);</pre>
   
<np>The value of <code>n</code> has the same information as the value of type
<ptype>int</ptype>, but it is an object. If you want to retrieve the <ptype>int</ptype>
value that is wrapped in the object, you can call the function <code>n.intValue()</code>.
Similarly, you can wrap a <ptype>double</ptype>
in an object of type <classname>Double</classname>, a <ptype>boolean</ptype> value
in an object of type <classname>Boolean</classname>, and so on.  Each wrapper
class has a static <code>valueOf</code>() method for wrapping a primitive type
value in an object.</np>

<p>The method <code>Integer.valueOf()</code> is a <code>static</code> factory method
that returns an object of type <classname>Integer</classname>.
The <classname>Integer</classname> class also has a constructor for creating
objects, but it has been <newword>deprecated</newword>, meaning that it should not be used in new
code and might be removed from the language in the future.  The static factory
method has the advantage that if <code>Integer.valueOf()</code>
is called more than once with the same parameter value, it has the option
of returning the same object each time. 
This is OK because objects of type <classname>Integer</classname> are
<newword>immutable</newword>, that is, the content of the object cannot
be modified after the object has been created.  Someone who gets their
hands on an <classname>Integer</classname> will not be able to 
change the primitive <ptype>int</ptype> value that it represents.<fx> We saw something 
similar for the <classname>Color</classname>
class in <localref href="GUI1.2.1"/>, which also has static factory methods for 
creating immutable objects.</fx></p>



<break/>
   
<p>To make the wrapper classes even easier to use, there is automatic
conversion between a primitive type and the corresponding wrapper class.  For example,
if you use a value of type <ptype>int</ptype> in a context that requires an object
of type <classname>Integer</classname>, the <ptype>int</ptype> will automatically be
wrapped in an <classname>Integer</classname> object. If you say</p>
   
<pre>Integer answer = 42;</pre>
   
<np>the computer will silently read this as if it were</np>
   
<pre>Integer answer = Integer.valueOf(42);</pre>
   
<np>This is called <newword>autoboxing</newword>.   It works in the other direction, too. For example, if
<code>d</code> refers to an object of type <code>Double</code>, you can use <code>d</code>
in a numerical expression such as <code>2*d</code>.  The <ptype>double</ptype> value inside
<code>d</code> is automatically <newword>unboxed</newword> and multiplied by&nbsp;2.  Autoboxing
and unboxing also apply to subroutine calls.  For example, you can pass an actual parameter of type
<ptype>int</ptype> to a subroutine that has a formal parameter of type <classname>Integer</classname>,
and vice versa.  In fact, autoboxing and unboxing make it possible in many circumstances to ignore the difference
between primitive types and objects.</np>
 
<p>This is true in particular for parameterized types.  Although there is no such thing
as "<atype>ArrayList&lt;int&gt;</atype>", there is <atype>ArrayList&lt;Integer&gt;</atype>.
An <atype>ArrayList&lt;Integer&gt;</atype> holds objects of type <classname>Integer</classname>,
but any object of type <classname>Integer</classname> really just represents an <ptype>int</ptype>
value in a rather thin wrapper.  Suppose that we have an object of type 
<atype>ArrayList&lt;Integer&gt;</atype>:</p>

<pre>ArrayList&lt;Integer&gt; integerList;
integerList = new ArrayList&lt;Integer&gt;();</pre>

<np>Then we can, for example, add an object to <code>integerList</code> that represents the number 42:</np>
  
<pre>integerList.add( Integer.valueOf(42) );</pre>

<np>but because of autoboxing, we can actually say</np>

<pre>integerList.add( 42 );</pre>

<np>and the compiler will automatically wrap 42 in an object of type <classname>Integer</classname>
before adding it to the list.  Similarly, we can say</np>

<pre>int num = integerList.get(3);</pre>

<np>The value returned by <code>integerList.get(3)</code> is of type <classname>Integer</classname>
but because of unboxing, the compiler will automatically convert the return value into an
<ptype>int</ptype>, as if we had said</np>

<pre>int num = integerList.get(3)<newcode>.intValue()</newcode>;</pre>

<np>So, in effect, we can pretty much use <code>integerList</code> as if it were
a dynamic array of <ptype>int</ptype> rather than a dynamic array of <classname>Integer</classname>.
Of course, a similar statement holds for lists of other wrapper classes such as
<atype>ArrayList&lt;Double&gt;</atype> and <atype>ArrayList&lt;Character&gt;</atype>.</np>

<p>There is one issue that sometimes causes problems:  A list can hold <code>null</code>
values, and a <code>null</code> does not correspond to any primitive type value.  This
means, for example, that the statement "<code>int num = integerList.get(3);</code>"
can produce a null pointer exception in the case where <code>integerList.get(3)</code>
returns <code>null</code>.  Unless you are sure that all the values in your list are
non-null, you need to take this possibility into account.</p>

</subsection>


<subsection  id="arrays.3.3" title="Programming With ArrayList">

<p>As a simple first example, we can redo <sourceref href="ReverseWithDynamicArray.java"/>,
from the <localref href="arrays.2.4">previous section</localref>, using an
ArrayList instead of a custom dynamic array class.  In this case, we want
to store integers in the list, so we should use <atype>ArrayList&lt;Integer&gt;</atype>.
Here is the complete program:</p>
   
<pre>import textio.TextIO;
import java.util.ArrayList;

/**
 * Reads a list of non-zero numbers from the user, then prints
 * out the input numbers in the reverse of the order in which
 * the were entered.  There is no limit on the number of inputs.
 */
public class ReverseWithArrayList {
    
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        <newcode>ArrayList&lt;Integer&gt; list;
        list = new ArrayList&lt;Integer&gt;();</newcode>
        System.out.println("Enter some non-zero integers.  Enter 0 to end.");
        while (true) {
            System.out.print("? ");
            int number = TextIO.getlnInt();
            if (number == 0)
                break;
            <newcode>list.add(number);</newcode>
        }
        System.out.println();
        System.out.println("Your numbers in reverse are:");
        for (int i = <newcode>list.size()</newcode> - 1; i >= 0; i--) {
            System.out.printf("%10d%n", <newcode>list.get(i)</newcode>);
        }
    }

}</pre>

<p>As illustrated in this example, ArrayLists are commonly processed using
<code>for</code> loops, in much the same way that arrays are processed.
for example, the following loop prints out all the items for a variable <code>namelist</code> of type
<atype>ArrayList&lt;String&gt;</atype>:</p>

<pre>for ( int i = 0; i &lt; namelist.size(); i++ ) {
    String item = namelist.get(i);
    System.out.println(item);
}</pre>

<np>You can also use for-each loops with ArrayLists, so this example could also be written</np>

<pre>for ( String item : namelist ) {
    System.out.println(item);
}</pre>

<p>When working with wrapper classes, the loop control variable in the for-each loop
can be a primitive type variable.  This works because of unboxing.  For example,
if <code>numbers</code> is of type <atype>ArrayList&lt;Double&gt;</atype>, then
the following loop can be used to add up all the values in the list:</p>
  
<pre>double sum = 0;
for ( double num : numbers ) {
   sum = sum + num;
}</pre>

<np>This will work as long as none of the items in the list are <code>null</code>.
If there is a possibility of null values, then you will want to use a loop control
variable of type <classname>Double</classname> and test for nulls.  For example,
to add up all the non-null values in the list:</np>
 
<pre>double sum;
for ( Double num : numbers ) {
    if ( num != null ) {
        sum = sum + num;  // Here, num is SAFELY unboxed to get a double.
    }
}</pre> 

<break/>

<p>For a more complete and useful example, we will look at the program
<sourceref href="SimplePaint2.java"/>.  This is a much improved version of
<sourceref chapter="6" href="SimplePaint.java"/> from
<fx><localref href="GUI1.3.3"/></fx><swing><localref href="GUI1.4.4"/></swing>.
In the new program, the user can sketch curves in a drawing area
by clicking and dragging with the mouse.
The user can select the drawing color using a menu.  The background color of the
drawing area can also be selected using a menu.  And there is a "Control"
menu that contains several commands:  An "Undo" command, which removes the
most recently drawn curve from the screen, a "Clear" command that removes
all the curves, and a "Use Symmetry" checkbox that turns a symmetry feature
on and off. Curves that are drawn by the user when the symmetry option is on
are reflected horizontally and vertically to produce a symmetric pattern.
(Symmetry is there just to look pretty.)</p>

<p>Unlike the original SimplePaint program, this new version
uses a data structure to store information about the picture that has been
drawn by the user. When the user selects a new background color, the canvas
is filled with the new background color, and all of the curves that were 
there previously are redrawn on the new background.  To do that, we need to
store enough data to redraw all of the curves.  Similarly, the Undo
command is implemented by deleting the data for most recently drawn curve,
and then redrawing the entire picture using the remaining data.</p>  

<p>The data structure that we need is implemented using <classname>ArrayLists</classname>.
The main data for an individual curve consists of a list of the points on the curve.  This
data is stored in an object of type 
<fx><atype>ArrayList&lt;Point2D&gt;</atype></fx><swing><atype>ArrayList&lt;Point&gt;</atype></swing>.
(<fx><classname>Point2D</classname></fx><swing><classname>Point</classname></swing> 
is standard class in package <fx><code>javafx.geometry</code></fx><swing><code>java.awt</code></swing>:
A&nbsp;<fx><classname>Point2D</classname></fx><swing><classname>Point</classname></swing> 
can be constructed from two <fx><ptype>double</ptype></fx><swing><ptype>int</ptype></swing>
values, giving the (x,y) coordinates of the point.  And
a&nbsp;<fx><classname>Point2D</classname></fx><swing><classname>Point</classname></swing>
object, <code>pt</code>, has 
<fx>getter methods <code>pt.getX()</code> and <code>pt.getY()</code>
that return the x and y coordinates</fx><swing>instance
variables <code>x</code> and <code>y</code> representing 
the coordinates of the point</swing>.)  But in addition to a list of points
on a curve, to redraw the curve, we also need to know its color,
and we need to know whether the symmetry option should be applied to the curve.
All the data that is needed to redraw the curve is grouped into
an object of type <classname>CurveData</classname> that is defined 
as a nested class in the program:</p>
   
<pre>private static class CurveData {
   Color color;  // The color of the curve.
   boolean symmetric;  // Are horizontal and vertical reflections also drawn?
   ArrayList&lt;Point<fx>2D</fx>&gt; points;  // The points on the curve.
}</pre>
   
<np>However, a picture can contain many curves, not just one, so to store
all the data necessary to redraw the entire picture, we need a <b>list</b>
of objects of type <classname>CurveData</classname>.  For this list,
the program uses an <classname>ArrayList</classname>, <code>curves</code>, declared as</np>
   
<pre>ArrayList&lt;CurveData&gt; curves = new ArrayList&lt;CurveData&gt;();</pre>
   
<np>Here we have a list of objects, where each object contains a list of
points as part of its data!  Let's look at a few examples of processing
this data structure.  When the user clicks the mouse on the drawing surface,
it's the start of a new curve, and a new <classname>CurveData</classname>
object must be created to represent that curve.  The instance
variables in the new <classname>CurveData</classname> object must
also be initialized.  Here is the code from the <code>mousePressed()</code>
routine that does this, where <code>currentCurve</code> is a global
variable of type <code>CurveData</code>:</np>
     
<pre>currentCurve = new CurveData();       // Create a new CurveData object.

currentCurve.color = currentColor;    // The color of a curve is taken from an
                                      // instance variable that represents the
                                      // currently selected drawing color.

currentCurve.symmetric = useSymmetry; // The "symmetric" property of the curve
                                      // is also copied from the current value
                                      // of an instance variable, useSymmetry.

currentCurve.points = new ArrayList&lt;Point<fx>2D</fx>&gt;();  // A new point list object.</pre>

<np>As the user drags the mouse, new points are added to <code>currentCurve</code>,
and line segments of the curve are drawn between points as they are added.  When the
user releases the mouse, the curve is complete, and it is added to
the list of curves by calling</np>

<pre>curves.add( currentCurve );</pre>

<p>When the user changes the background color or selects the "Undo" command,
the picture has to be redrawn.  The program has a 
<fx><code>redraw()</code></fx><swing><code>paintComponent()</code></swing>
method that completely redraws the picture. That method uses the data in the 
list of <classname>CurveData</classname>
to draw all the curves.  The basic structure is a for-each loop that processes
the data for each individual curve in turn.  This has the form:</p>
   
<pre>for ( CurveData curve : curves ) {
   .
   .  // Draw the curve represented by the object, curve, of type CurveData.
   .  
}</pre>
   
<np>In the body of this loop, <code>curve.points</code> is a variable of
type <fx><atype>ArrayList&lt;Point2D&gt;</atype></fx><swing><atype>ArrayList&lt;Point&gt;</atype></swing> 
that holds the list of 
points on the curve.  The <code>i-th</code> point on the curve can be
obtained by calling the <code>get()</code> method of this list:
<code>curve.points.get(i)</code>.  This returns a value of type
<fx><classname>Point2D</classname></fx><swing><classname>Point</classname></swing> which has 
<fx>getter methods named <code>getX()</code> and <code>getY()</code></fx><swing>instance
variables named <code>x</code> and <code>y</code></swing>.  We can refer directly to the
x-coordinate of the <code>i-th</code> point as:</np>
   
<pre>curve.points.get(i).<fx>getX()</fx><swing>x</swing></pre>
   
<np>This might seem rather complicated, but it's a nice example of a complex name
that specifies a path to a desired piece of data: Go to the object, <code>curve</code>.
Inside <code>curve</code>, go to <code>points</code>.  Inside <code>points</code>,
get the <code>i-th</code> item.  And from that item, get the x coordinate
<fx>by calling its <code>getX()</code> method</fx>.  Here is the complete definition of the
method that redraws the picture:</np>
   
<fxdiv>
<pre>private void redraw() {
    g.setFill(backgroundColor);
    g.fillRect(0,0,canvas.getWidth(),canvas.getHeight());
    for ( CurveData curve : curves ) {
        g.setStroke(curve.color);
        for (int i = 1; i &lt; curve.points.size(); i++) {
                // Draw a line segment from point number i-1 to point number i.
            double x1 = curve.points.get(i-1).getX();
            double y1 = curve.points.get(i-1).getY();
            double x2 = curve.points.get(i).getX();
            double y2 = curve.points.get(i).getY();
            drawSegment(curve.symmetric,x1,y1,x2,y2);
        }
    }
}</pre>

<np><code>drawSegment()</code> is a method that strokes the line segment
from <code>(x1,y1)</code> to <code>(x2,y2)</code>.  If the first parameter is
<code>true</code>, it also draws the horizontal and vertical reflections of
that segment.</np>
</fxdiv>
<swingdiv>
<pre>public void paintComponent(Graphics g) {
    super.paintComponent(g);
    Graphics2D g2 = (Graphics2D)g;
    g2.setRenderingHint(RenderingHints.KEY_ANTIALIASING, 
                               RenderingHints.VALUE_ANTIALIAS_ON);
    for ( CurveData curve : curves) {
        g.setColor(curve.color);
        for (int i = 1; i &lt; curve.points.size(); i++) {
                // Draw a line segment from point number i-1 to point number i.
            int x1 = curve.points.get(i-1).x;
            int y1 = curve.points.get(i-1).y;
            int x2 = curve.points.get(i).x;
            int y2 = curve.points.get(i).y;
            g.drawLine(x1,y1,x2,y2);
            if (curve.symmetric) {
                    // Also draw the horizontal and vertical reflections
                    // of the line segment.
                int w = getWidth();
                int h = getHeight();
                g.drawLine(w-x1,y1,w-x2,y2);
                g.drawLine(x1,h-y1,x2,h-y2);
                g.drawLine(w-x1,h-y1,w-x2,h-y2);
            }
        }
    }
} // end paintComponent()
</pre>
</swingdiv>
   
<p>I have mostly been interested here in discussing how the program uses
<classname>ArrayList</classname>, but
I encourage you to read the full source code, <sourceref href="SimplePaint2.java"/>,
and to try out the program.
In addition to serving as an example of using parameterized types, it also serves
as another example of creating and using menus.  You should be able to understand
the entire program.</p>


</subsection>



</section>