<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="arrays.4" title="Searching and Sorting">
   
<p><start><big>T</big>wo array processing techniques</start> that are
particularly common are <newword>searching</newword> and <newword>sorting</newword>. 
Searching here refers to finding an item in the array
that meets some specified criterion. Sorting refers to rearranging all the
items in the array into increasing or decreasing order (where the meaning of
increasing and decreasing can depend on the context).  We have seen in
<localref href="arrays.2.2"/> that Java has some built-in methods for searching
and sorting arrays.  However, a computer science student should be familiar
with the algorithms that are used in those methods.  In this section,
you will learn some algorithms for searching and sorting.</p>

<p>Sorting and searching are often discussed, in a theoretical sort of way,
using an array of numbers as an example. In practical situations, though, more
interesting types of data are usually involved. For example, the array might be
a mailing list, and each element of the array might be an object containing a
name and address. Given the name of a person, you might want to look up that
person's address. This is an example of searching, since you want to find the
object in the array that contains the given name. It would also be useful to be
able to sort the array according to various criteria. One example of sorting
would be ordering the elements of the array so that the names are in
alphabetical order. Another example would be to order the elements of the array
according to zip code before printing a set of mailing labels. (This kind of
sorting can get you a cheaper postage rate on a large mailing.)</p>

<p>This example can be generalized to a more abstract situation in which we
have an array that contains objects, and we want to search or sort the array
based on the value of one of the instance variables in the objects. We can use
some terminology here that originated in work with "databases," which are just
large, organized collections of data. We refer to each of the objects in the
array as a <newword>record</newword>. The instance variables in an
object are then called <newword>fields</newword> of the record. In
the mailing list example, each record would contain a name and address. The
fields of the record might be the first name, last name, street address, state,
city and zip code. For the purpose of searching or sorting, one of the fields
is designated to be the <newword>key</newword> field. Searching then
means finding a record in the array that has a specified value in its key
field. Sorting means moving the records around in the array so that the key
fields of the record are in increasing (or decreasing) order.</p>

<p>In this section, most of my examples follow the tradition of using arrays of
numbers. But I'll also give a few examples using records and keys, to remind
you of the more practical applications.</p>


<subsection id="arrays.4.1" title="Searching">

<p>There is an obvious algorithm for searching for a particular item in an
array: Look at each item in the array in turn, and check whether that item is
the one you are looking for. If so, the search is finished. If you look at
every item without finding the one you want, then you can be sure that the item
is not in the array. It's easy to write a subroutine to implement this
algorithm. Let's say the array that you want to search is an array of
<ptype>ints</ptype>. Here is a method that will search the array for a specified
integer. If the integer is found, the method returns the index of the location
in the array where it is found. If the integer is not in the array, the method
returns the value <code>-1</code> as a signal that the integer could not be
found:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Searches the array A for the integer N.  If N is not in the array,
 * then -1 is returned.  If N is in the array, then the return value is
 * the first integer i that satisfies A[i] == N.
 */
static int find(int[] A, int N) {
      
   for (int index = 0; index &lt; A.length; index++) {
      if ( A[index] == N ) 
         return index;  // N has been found at this index!
   }
   
   // If we get this far, then N has not been found
   // anywhere in the array.  Return a value of -1.
   
   return -1;
   
}</pre>

<p>This method of searching an array by looking at each item in turn is called
<newword>linear search</newword>. If nothing is known about the order
of the items in the array, then there is really no better alternative
algorithm. But if the elements in the array are known to be in increasing or
decreasing order, then a much faster search algorithm can be used. An array in
which the elements are in order is said to be <newword>sorted</newword>. 
Of course, it takes some work to sort an array, but if
the array is to be searched many times, then the work done in sorting it can
really pay off.</p>

<p><newword>Binary search</newword> is a method for searching for a
given item in a <b>sorted</b> array. Although the implementation is not
trivial, the basic idea is simple: If you are searching for an item in a sorted
list, then it is possible to eliminate half of the items in the list by
inspecting a single item. For example, suppose that you are looking for the
number 42 in a sorted array of 1000 integers. Let's assume that the array is
sorted into increasing order. Suppose you check item number 500 in the array,
and find that the item is 93. Since 42 is less than 93, and since the elements
in the array are in increasing order, we can conclude that if 42 occurs in the
array at all, then it must occur somewhere before location 500. All the
locations numbered 500 or above contain values that are greater than or equal
to 93. These locations can be eliminated as possible locations of the number
42.</p>

<p>The next obvious step is to check location 250. If the number at that
location is, say, -21, then you can eliminate locations before 250 and limit
further search to locations between 251 and 499. The next test will limit the
search to about 125 locations, and the one after that to about 62. After just
10 steps, there is only one location left. This is a whole lot better than
looking through every element in the array. If there were a million items, it
would still take only 20 steps for binary search to search the array!
(Mathematically, the number of steps is approximately equal to
the logarithm, in the base 2, of the number of items in the array.)</p>

<p>In order to make binary search into a Java subroutine that searches an array
A for an item <code>N</code>, we just have to keep track of the range of locations
that could possibly contain <code>N</code>. At each step, as we eliminate
possibilities, we reduce the size of this range. The basic operation is to look
at the item in the middle of the range. If this item is greater than
<code>N</code>, then the second half of the range can be eliminated. If it is less
than <code>N</code>, then the first half of the range can be eliminated. If the
number in the middle just happens to be <code>N</code> exactly, then the search is
finished. If the size of the range decreases to zero, then the number
<code>N</code> does not occur in the array. Here is a subroutine that implements
this idea:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Searches the array A for the integer N.
 * Precondition:  A must be sorted into increasing order.
 * Postcondition: If N is in the array, then the return value, i,
 *    satisfies A[i] == N.  If N is not in the array, then the
 *    return value is -1.
 */
static int binarySearch(int[] A, int N) {
      
    int lowestPossibleLoc = 0;
    int highestPossibleLoc = A.length - 1;
    
    while (highestPossibleLoc &gt;= lowestPossibleLoc) {
       int middle = (lowestPossibleLoc + highestPossibleLoc) / 2;
       if (A[middle] == N) {
                 // N has been found at this index!
          return middle;
       }
       else if (A[middle] &gt; N) {
                 // eliminate locations &gt;= middle
          highestPossibleLoc = middle - 1;
       }
       else {
                 // eliminate locations &lt;= middle
          lowestPossibleLoc = middle + 1;   
       }
    }
    
    // At this point, highestPossibleLoc &lt; LowestPossibleLoc,
    // which means that N is known to be not in the array.  Return
    // a -1 to indicate that N could not be found in the array.
 
    return -1;
  
}</pre>

</subsection>

<subsection id="arrays.4.2" title="Association Lists">

<p>One particularly common application of searching is with <newword>association lists</newword>.
The standard example of an association list
is a dictionary. A dictionary associates definitions with words. Given a word,
you can use the dictionary to look up its definition. We can think of the
dictionary as being a list of <newword>pairs</newword> of the form
<code>(w,d)</code>, where <code>w</code> is a word and <code>d</code> is its definition. A
general association list is a list of pairs <code>(k,v)</code>, where <code>k</code> is
some "key" value, and <code>v</code> is a value associated to that key. In general,
we want to assume that no two pairs in the list have the same key. There are two basic
operations on association lists:  Given a key, <code>k</code>, find the value
<code>v</code> associated with <code>k</code>, if any.  And given a key, <code>k</code>,
and a value <code>v</code>, add the pair <code>(k,v)</code> to the association list
(replacing the pair, if any, that had the same key value).  The two operations
are usually called <newword>get</newword> and <newword>put</newword>.</p>

<p>Association lists are very widely used in computer science. For example, a
compiler has to keep track of the location in memory associated with each
variable. It can do this with an association list in which each key is a
variable name and the associated value is the address of that variable in
memory. Another example would be a mailing list, if we think of it as
associating an address to each name on the list. As a related example, consider
a phone directory that associates a phone number to each name.  We'll look
at a highly simplified version of this example.  (This is <b>not</b> meant to be
a realistic way to implement a phone directory!)</p>

<p>The items in the phone directory's association list could be objects belonging to the class:</p>

<pre>class PhoneEntry {
   String name;
   String phoneNum;
}</pre>

<p>The data for a phone directory consists of an array of type
<atype>PhoneEntry[]</atype> and an integer variable to keep track of how many entries
are actually stored in the directory.  The technique of dynamic arrays
(<localref href="arrays.2.4"/>) can be used in order to avoid putting an arbitrary limit on
the number of entries that the phone directory can hold.  Using an
<classname>ArrayList</classname> would be another possibility.
A <classname>PhoneDirectory</classname> class should include instance methods
that implement the "get" and "put" operations.  Here is one possible simple
definition of the class:</p>

<pre>/**
 * A PhoneDirectory holds a list of names with a phone number for
 * each name.  It is possible to find the number associated with
 * a given name, and to specify the phone number for a given name.
 */
public class PhoneDirectory {
   
   /**
    * An object of type PhoneEntry holds one name/number pair.
    */
   private static class PhoneEntry {
      String name;     // The name.
      String number;   // The associated phone number.
   }
   
   private PhoneEntry[] data;  // Array that holds the name/number pairs.
   private int dataCount;      // The number of pairs stored in the array.
   
   /**
    * Constructor creates an initially empty directory.
    */
   public PhoneDirectory() {
      data = new PhoneEntry[1];
      dataCount = 0;
   }
   
   /**
    * Looks for a name/number pair with a given name.  If found, the index
    * of the pair in the data array is returned.  If no pair contains the
    * given name, then the return value is -1.  This private method is
    * used internally in getNumber() and putNumber().
    */
   private int find( String name ) {
      for (int i = 0; i &lt; dataCount; i++) {
         if (data[i].name.equals(name))
            return i;  // The name has been found in position i.
      }
      return -1;  // The name does not exist in the array.
   }
   
   /**
    * Finds the phone number, if any, for a given name.
    * @return The phone number associated with the name; if the name does
    *    not occur in the phone directory, then the return value is null.
    */
   public String getNumber( String name ) {
      int position = find(name);
      if (position == -1)
         return null;   // There is no phone entry for the given name.
      else
         return data[position].number;
   }
   
   /**
    * Associates a given name with a given phone number.  If the name
    * already exists in the phone directory, then the new number replaces
    * the old one.  Otherwise, a new name/number pair is added.  The
    * name and number should both be non-null.  An IllegalArgumentException
    * is thrown if this is not the case.
    */
   public void putNumber( String name, String number ) {
      if (name == null || number == null)
         throw new IllegalArgumentException("name and number cannot be null");
      int i = find(name);
      if (i &gt;= 0) {
             // The name already exists, in position i in the array.
             // Just replace the old number at that position with the new.
         data[i].number = number;
      }
      else {
            // Add a new name/number pair to the array.  If the array is
            // already full, first create a new, larger array.
         if (dataCount == data.length) {
            data = Arrays.copyOf( data, 2*data.length );
         }
         PhoneEntry newEntry = new PhoneEntry();  // Create a new pair.
         newEntry.name = name;
         newEntry.number = number;
         data[dataCount] = newEntry;   // Add the new pair to the array.
         dataCount++;
      }
   }

} // end class PhoneDirectory</pre>
   
<p>The class defines a private instance method, <code>find()</code>, that
uses linear search to find the position of a given name in the
array of name/number pairs.  The <code>find()</code> method is used both in the
<code>getNumber()</code> method and in the <code>putNumber()</code> method.
Note in particular that <code>putNumber(name,number)</code> has to check whether the
name is in the phone directory. If so, it just changes the number in the
existing entry; if not, it has to create a new phone entry and add it to the
array.</p>

<p>This class could use a lot of improvement. For one thing, it would be nice
to use binary search instead of simple linear search in the <code>getNumber</code>
method. However, we could only do that if the list of PhoneEntries were sorted
into alphabetical order according to name. In fact, it's really not all that
hard to keep the list of entries in sorted order, as you'll see in the
next subsection.</p>

<p>I will mention that association lists are also called "maps," and Java has
a standard parameterized type named <classname>Map</classname> that implements
association lists for keys and values of any type.  The implementation is <b>much</b>
more efficient than anything you can do with basic arrays. You will encounter this
class in <localref href="generics"/>.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="arrays.4.3" title="Insertion Sort">

<p>We've seen that there are good reasons for sorting arrays. There are many
algorithms available for doing so. One of the easiest to understand is the
<newword>insertion sort</newword> algorithm. This technique is also
applicable to the problem of <b>keeping</b> a list in sorted order as you add
new items to the list. Let's consider that case first:</p>

<p>Suppose you have a sorted list and you want to add an item to that list. If
you want to make sure that the modified list is still sorted, then the item
must be inserted into the right location, with all the smaller items coming
before it and all the bigger items after it. This will mean moving each of the
bigger items up one space to make room for the new item.</p>
   
<pre>/*
 * Precondition:  itemsInArray is the number of items that are
 *    stored in A.  These items must be in increasing order
 *    (A[0] &lt;= A[1] &lt;= ... &lt;= A[itemsInArray-1]).
 *    The array size is at least one greater than itemsInArray.
 * Postcondition:  The number of items has increased by one,
 *    newItem has been added to the array, and all the items
 *    in the array are still in increasing order.
 * Note:  To complete the process of inserting an item in the
 *    array, the variable that counts the number of items
 *    in the array must be incremented, after calling this
 *    subroutine.
 */
static void insert(int[] A, int itemsInArray, int newItem) {
      
   int loc = itemsInArray - 1;  // Start at the end of the array.
   
   /* Move items bigger than newItem up one space;
      Stop when a smaller item is encountered or when the
      beginning of the array (loc == 0) is reached. */
   
   while (loc &gt;= 0 &amp;&amp; A[loc] &gt; newItem) {
      A[loc + 1] = A[loc];  // Bump item from A[loc] up to loc+1.
      loc = loc - 1;        // Go on to next location.
   }
   
   A[loc + 1] = newItem;  // Put newItem in last vacated space.

}</pre>

<p>Conceptually, this could be extended to a sorting method if we were to take
all the items out of an unsorted array, and then insert them back into the
array one-by-one, keeping the list in sorted order as we do so. Each insertion
can be done using the <code>insert</code> routine given above. In the actual
algorithm, we don't really take all the items from the array; we just remember
what part of the array has been sorted:</p>

<pre>static void insertionSort(int[] A) {
      // Sort the array A into increasing order.
      
   int itemsSorted; // Number of items that have been sorted so far.

   for (itemsSorted = 1; itemsSorted &lt; A.length; itemsSorted++) {
         // Assume that items A[0], A[1], ... A[itemsSorted-1] 
         // have already been sorted.  Insert A[itemsSorted]
         // into the sorted part of the list.
         
      int temp = A[itemsSorted];  // The item to be inserted.
      int loc = itemsSorted - 1;  // Start at end of list.
      
      while (loc &gt;= 0 &amp;&amp; A[loc] &gt; temp) {
         A[loc + 1] = A[loc]; // Bump item from A[loc] up to loc+1.
         loc = loc - 1;       // Go on to next location.
      }
      
      A[loc + 1] = temp; // Put temp in last vacated space.
   }
}</pre>

<p>Here is an illustration of one stage in insertion sort. It shows
what happens during one execution of the <code>for</code> loop in the above method,
when <code>itemsSorted</code> is&nbsp;5:</p>

<img src="insertion-sort.png" width="506" height="324" tex="insertion-sort.eps" texscale="0.75"
   alt="(Illustration of Insertion Sort)" />


</subsection>

<subsection id="arrays.4.4" title="Selection Sort">

<p>Another typical sorting method uses the idea of finding the biggest item in
the list and moving it to the end&mdash;which is where it belongs if the list is
to be in increasing order. Once the biggest item is in its correct location,
you can then apply the same idea to the remaining items. That is, find the
next-biggest item, and move it into the next-to-last space, and so forth. This
algorithm is called <newword>selection sort</newword>. It's easy to
write:</p>

<pre>static void selectionSort(int[] A) {
      // Sort A into increasing order, using selection sort
      
   for (int lastPlace = A.length-1; lastPlace &gt; 0; lastPlace--) {
         // Find the largest item among A[0], A[1], ...,
         // A[lastPlace], and move it into position lastPlace 
         // by swapping it with the number that is currently 
         // in position lastPlace.
         
      int maxLoc = 0;  // Location of largest item seen so far.
      
      for (int j = 1; j &lt;= lastPlace; j++) {
         if (A[j] &gt; A[maxLoc]) {
               // Since A[j] is bigger than the maximum we've seen
               // so far, j is the new location of the maximum value
               // we've seen so far.
            maxLoc = j;  
         }
      }
      
      int temp = A[maxLoc];  // Swap largest item with A[lastPlace].
      A[maxLoc] = A[lastPlace];
      A[lastPlace] = temp;
      
   }  // end of for loop
   
}</pre>


<break/>

<p>A variation of selection sort is used in the <classname>Hand</classname> class that was
introduced in <localref href="OOP.4.1"/>. (By the way, you are
finally in a position to fully understand the source code for
the <classname>Hand</classname> class from that section; note that
it uses <classname>ArrayList</classname>.
The source file is <sourceref chapter="5" href="Hand.java"/>.)</p>

<p>In the <classname>Hand</classname> class, a hand of playing cards is represented by an
<atype>ArrayList&lt;Card&gt;</atype>.
The objects stored in the list are of type <classname>Card</classname>. A
<classname>Card</classname> object contains instance methods <code>getSuit()</code> and
<code>getValue()</code> that can be used to determine the suit and value of the
card. In my sorting method, I actually create a new list and move the cards
one-by-one from the old list to the new list. The cards are selected from
the old list in increasing order. In the end, the new list becomes the hand
and the old list is discarded. This is not the most efficient procedure.
But hands of cards are so small that the inefficiency is negligible. Here is
the code for sorting cards by suit:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Sorts the cards in the hand so that cards of the same suit are
 * grouped together, and within a suit the cards are sorted by value.
 * Note that aces are considered to have the lowest value, 1.
 */
public void sortBySuit() {
   ArrayList&lt;Card&gt; newHand = new ArrayList&lt;Card&gt;();
   while (hand.size() &gt; 0) {
      int pos = 0;  // Position of minimal card.
      Card c = hand.get(0);  // Minimal card.
      for (int i = 1; i &lt; hand.size(); i++) {
         Card c1 = hand.get(i);
         if ( c1.getSuit() &lt; c.getSuit() ||
              (c1.getSuit() == c.getSuit() &amp;&amp; c1.getValue() &lt; c.getValue()) ) {
            pos = i;  // Update the minimal card and location.
            c = c1;
         }
      }
      hand.remove(pos);  // Remove card from original hand.
      newHand.add(c);    // Add card to the new hand.
   }
   hand = newHand;
}</pre>
   

<p>This example illustrates the fact that comparing items in a list is not
usually as simple as using the operator "<code>&lt;</code>".  In this case,
we consider one card to be less than another if the suit of the first card
is less than the suit of the second, and also if the suits are the same and
the value of the second card is less than the value of the first.  The second
part of this test ensures that cards with the same suit will end up sorted
by value.</p>
   
<p>Sorting a list of <classname>Strings</classname> raises a similar problem:
the "<code>&lt;</code>" operator is not defined for strings.  However, the
<classname>String</classname> class does define a <code>compareTo</code> method.
If <code>str1</code> and <code>str2</code> are of type <classname>String</classname>,
then</p>

<pre>str1.compareTo(str2)</pre>
   
<np>returns an <ptype>int</ptype> that is 0 when <code>str1</code> is equal to
<code>str2</code>, is less than 0 when <code>str1</code> precedes <code>str2</code>,
and is greater than 0 when <code>str1</code> follows <code>str2</code>. For example,
you can test whether <code>str1</code> precedes or is equal to <code>str2</code> by
testing</np>

<pre>if ( str1.compareTo(str2) &lt;= 0 )</pre>

<np>The definition of "precedes" and "follows" for strings uses what is called
<newword>lexicographic ordering</newword>, which is based on the Unicode
values of the characters in the strings.  Lexicographic ordering is not
the same as alphabetical ordering, even for strings that consist entirely
of letters (because in lexicographic ordering, all the upper case letters
come before all the lower case letters).  However, for words consisting
strictly of the 26 lower case letters in the English alphabet, lexicographic
and alphabetic ordering are the same.  (The same holds true if the strings consist
entirely of  uppercase letters.)  The method <code>str1.compareToIgnoreCase(str2)</code>
compares the two strings after converting any characters that they contain
to lower case.</np>
 
<break/>

<p>Insertion sort and selection sort are suitable for sorting fairly small
arrays (up to a few hundred elements, say). There are more complicated sorting
algorithms that are much faster than insertion sort and selection sort for
large arrays, to the same degree that binary search is faster than linear search.
The standard method <code>Arrays.sort</code> uses these fast sorting algorithms.
I'll discuss one such algorithm in <localref href="recursion"/>.</p>

   
</subsection>

<subsection id="arrays.4.5" title="Unsorting">

<p>I can't resist ending this section on sorting with a related problem that is
much less common, but is a bit more fun. That is the problem of putting the
elements of an array into a random order. The typical case of this problem is
shuffling a deck of cards. A good algorithm for shuffling is similar to
selection sort, except that instead of moving the biggest item to the end of
the list, an item is selected at random and moved to the end of the list. Here
is a subroutine to shuffle an array of <code>ints</code>:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Postcondition:  The items in A have been rearranged into a random order.
 */
static void shuffle(int[] A) {
   for (int lastPlace = A.length-1; lastPlace &gt; 0; lastPlace--) {
         // Choose a random location from among 0,1,...,lastPlace.
      int randLoc = (int)(Math.random()*(lastPlace+1));
         // Swap items in locations randLoc and lastPlace.
      int temp = A[randLoc];
      A[randLoc] = A[lastPlace];
      A[lastPlace] = temp;
   }
}</pre>

</subsection>
   
</section>