<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE quiz SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<quiz>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Describe the object that is created by the following statement, and give
an example of how it might be used in a program:</p>
<pre>BufferedImage OSC = new BufferedImage(32,32,BufferedImage.TYPE_INT_RGB);</pre>
</ques>
<ans><p>A <classname>BufferedImage</classname> is a region in memory that can
be used as a drawing surface.  In this statement, the image that is created is
32 pixels wide and 32 pixels high, and the color of each pixel is an
RGB color that has red, green, and blue components in the range 0 to 255.
The picture in a <classname>BufferedImage</classname> can easily be
copied into a graphics context <code>g</code> by calling one of the
<code>g.drawImage</code> methods.  However, since the image is so small
in this case, it seems more likely that is going to be used to define
an <classname>ImageIcon</classname> or perhaps a <classname>Cursor</classname>.</p>
</ans>
</question>

   
<question>
<ques><p>Many programs depend on <i>resource files</i>.  What is meant by a resource in
this sense?  Give an example.</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>In addition to the program code itself, programs often use other types of
data such as images and sounds.  These are said to be resources for the program.
In order to run, the program must be able to locate and load the resources.
An example of a resource is a small image file that will be used by the program
to define a custom cursor.</p>
</ans>
</question>

   
<question>
<ques><p>What is the <classname>FontMetrics</classname> class used for?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>An object that belongs to the
class <classname>FontMetrics</classname> can be used to obtain information about the sizes of
characters and strings that are drawn in a specific font. The font is specified
when the <classname>FontMetrics</classname> object is created. If <code>fm</code> is a variable
of type <classname>FontMetrics</classname>, then, for example, <code>fm.stringWidth(str)</code>
gives the width of the string <code>str</code> and <code>fm.getHeight()</code> is the
usual amount of vertical space allowed for one line of text. This information
could be used, for example, for positioning the string in a component.</p>
</ans>
</question>

   
<question>
<ques><p>If a <classname>Color</classname>, <code>c</code>, is created as
<code>c&nbsp;=&nbsp;new&nbsp;Color(0,0,255,125)</code>, what is the effect of drawing
with this color?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>When a color is constructed from four integers, the fourth parameter
is the alpha component of the color.  When drawing, the alpha component is
interpreted as the degree of opaqueness of the color.  If the alpha
component is less than its maximum possible value, 255, then the color
is partially transparent.  In this case, <code>c</code> represents a blue
color that is about 50% transparent.  When a pixel is colored with
<code>c</code>, the pixel does not become entirely blue.  Instead, the
new color of the pixel is obtained by blending <code>c</code>
with the previous color of the pixel.  The effect is like adding
a blue tint to the pixel, or like looking at the previous color of
the pixel through blue-colored glass.</p>
</ans>
</question>

   
<question>
<ques><p>What is <i>antialiasing</i>?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>Antialiasing is used to make shapes that are drawn look less "jagged."
The jaggedness is called "aliasing," and it arises because shapes have to
be drawn by coloring individual pixels.  If antialiasing is off, then the
only decision is either to color a pixel or not to color it.  As a result,
a boundary that should be a smooth curve will look like a jagged staircase.
When antialiasing is on, the amount of color that is applied to a pixel
depends on how much of that pixel is covered by the ideal geometric shape.
For pixels along the boundary of the shape, the color of the shape will be
blended with the previous color of the pixel.
Although antialiasing does not produce a perfect result, it does tend
to make pictures look better.</p>
</ans>
</question>

   
<question>
<ques><p>How is the <classname>ButtonGroup</classname> class used?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>A <classname>ButtonGroup</classname> object is used with a
set of radio buttons (or radio button menu items), to make sure that
at most one of the radio buttons in the group can be selected at
any given time.  To use the <classname>ButtonGroup</classname> class,
you have to create a <classname>ButtonGroup</classname> object,
<code>grp</code>.  Then each radio button, <code>rb</code>, that is supposed to
be part of the group is added to the group by calling <code>grp.add(rb)</code>.
Nothing further needs to be done with the <classname>ButtonGroup</classname>
object.</p>
</ans>
</question>

   
<question>
<ques><p>What does the acronym <i>MVC</i> stand for, and how does it apply to the
<classname>JTable</classname> class?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>MVC stands for "Model-View-Controller."  In a <classname>JTable</classname>,
the <i>view</i> is the actual visible component on the screen.  The <i>model</i>
is the collection of data that specifies, among other things, what appears in each
cell of the table and in the column headings.
The model is represented by a separate object from the object
that represents the view.  The <i>controller</i> is responsible for interaction
with the user.  It consists mostly of a bunch of listener objects that listen
for events generated when the user interacts with the table.  The listeners
respond by making changes in the model, which will in turn cause a change in the
view.</p>
</ans>
</question>

   
<question>
<ques><p>Describe the picture that is produced by the following
<code>paintComponent()</code> method:</p>
<pre>
public void paintComponent(Graphics g) {
   super.paintComponent(g);
   Graphics2D g2 = (Graphics2D)g;
   g2.translate( getWidth()/2, getHeight()/2 );
   g2.rotate( 30 * Math.PI / 180 );
   g2.fillRect(0,0,100,100);
}</pre>
</ques>
<ans><p>This shows a filled black square that is 100-by-100 pixels in size.
The corner of the square is at the center of the component that is being painted,
and the top side of the square descends at a 30 degree angle from that point.
(The <code>translate</code> command moves the origin, <code>(0,0)</code> to the
point <code>(getWidth()/2,getHeight()/2)</code>, so that when the <code>fillRect</code>
command places the corner of the square at <code>(0,0)</code>, the corner actually
appears at the center of the component.  Furthermore, the <code>rotate</code>
command rotates the picture by 30 degrees in a clockwise direction about
the origin.  This means that the top of the square is rotated from the
horizontal position onto a line that is 30 degrees clockwise from the horizontal.
That line descends at a 30 degree angle.</p>
</ans>
</question>

   
<question>
<ques><p>What is meant by <i>Internationalization</i> of a program?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>Internationalization refers to writing the program in a way that
will make it easy to adapt the program for use in a variety of "locales."
For example, it should be easy to translate all the strings that are used
in the program into other languages.  To make this possible the strings
should not be hard coded into the program itself.  Instead, they are
placed in a separate resource file, so that the program can be translated
into another language simply by writing a resource file for that language.
(Internationalization also applies to the format that is used for dates
and numbers.)</p>
</ans>
</question>

   
<question>
<ques><p>Suppose that the class that you are writing has an instance method
<code>doOpen()</code> (with no parameters) that is meant to be used to open
a file selected by the user.  Write a code segment that creates an
<classname>Action</classname> that represents the action of opening
a file.  Then show how to create a button and a menu item from that 
action.</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>Here is the code for the three parts of the problem:</p>
   
<pre>Action openAction = new AbstractAction( "Open..." ) {
   public void actionPerformed( ActionEvent e ) {
      doOpen();
   }
};

JButton openButton = new JButton( openAction );
   
JMenuItem openCommand = new JMenuItem( openAction );</pre>
   
<p>(Since <classname>Action</classname> is only an interface,
the class <classname>AbstractAction</classname> has to be used to
create the action object.  The most natural way to write the code
is to create an anonymous inner class that is a subclass of
<classname>AbstractAction</classname>.  This subclass must define
the <code>actionPerformed()</code> method&mdash;which in this case
only has to call the <code>doOpen()</code> method.  As an alternative
to creating the <classname>JMenuItem</classname>, the action could
have simply been added directly to a <classname>JMenu.</classname> By the way,
the "..." in the name of the action is there, by convention, to
tell the user that selecting this command will cause a dialog
box to pop up.)</p>
</ans>
</question>

   
</quiz>