<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="GUI2.3" title="Actions and Buttons">
   
<p><start><big>F</big>or the past two sections</start>, we have been looking
at some  of the more advanced aspects of the Java graphics API.  But the
heart of most graphical user interface programming is using GUI components.
In this section and the next, we'll be looking at <classname>JComponents</classname>.
We'll cover several component classes that were not covered in <localref href="GUI1"/>,
as well as some additional features of classes that were covered there.</p>
   
<p>This section is mostly about buttons.  Buttons are among the simplest of
GUI components, and it seems like there shouldn't be all that much to say
about them.  However, buttons are not as simple as they seem.  For one thing,
there are many different types of buttons.  The basic functionality of
buttons in Java is defined by the class <code>javax.swing.AbstractButton</code>.
Subclasses of this class represent push buttons, check boxes, and radio
buttons.  Menu items are also considered to be buttons.  The
<classname>AbstractButton</classname> class defines a surprisingly
large API for controlling the appearance of buttons.  This section will
cover part of that API, but you should see the class documentation for
full details.</p>
   
<p>In this section, we'll also encounter a few classes that do not themselves define
buttons but that are related to the button API, starting with "actions."</p>
   
   
<subsection id="GUI2.3.1" title="Action and AbstractAction">
   
<p>The <classname>JButton</classname> class represents push buttons.  Up until
now, we have created push buttons using the constructor</p>
   
<pre>public JButton(String text);</pre>
   
<np>which specifies text that will appear on the button.  We then added an
<classname>ActionListener</classname> to the button, to respond when the
user presses it.  Another way to create a <classname>JButton</classname> is
using an <classname>Action</classname>.  The <classname>Action</classname>
interface represents the general idea of some action that can be performed,
together with properties associated with that action, such as a name for
the action, an icon that represents the action, and whether the action
is currently enabled or disabled.  <classname>Actions</classname> are
usually defined using the class <classname>AbstractAction</classname>,
an <code>abstract</code> class which includes a method</np>
   
<pre>public void actionPerformed(ActionEvent evt)</pre>
   
<np>that must be defined in any concrete subclass.  Often, this is done
in an anonymous inner class.  (Unfortunately, you can't use a lambda
expression here, because <classname>Action</classname> is not a 
functional interface.)  For example, suppose that <code>display</code>
is an object that has a <classname>clear()</classname> method.  Then
an <classname>Action</classname> object that represents the action 
"clear the display" can be defined as:</np>
   
<pre>Action clearAction = new AbstractAction("Clear") {
   public void actionPerformed(ActionEvent evt) { 
      display.clear();
   }
};</pre>
   
<np>The parameter, <code>"Clear"</code>, in the constructor of the
<classname>AbstractAction</classname> is the name of the action.  Other
properties can be set by calling the method <code>putValue(key,value)</code>,
which is part of the <classname>Action</classname> interface.  For example,</np>
   
<pre>clearAction.putValue(Action.SHORT_DESCRIPTION, "Clear the Display");</pre>
   
<np>sets the <code>SHORT_DESCRIPTION</code> property of the action to
have the value "Clear the Display".  The <code>key</code> parameter 
in the <code>putValue()</code> method is usually given as one of several
constants defined in the <classname>Action</classname> interface.  As
another example, you can change the name of an action by using
<code>Action.NAME</code> as the <code>key</code> in the <code>putValue()</code>
method.</np>
   
<p>Once you have an <classname>Action</classname>, you can use it in the constructor
of a button.  For example, using the action <code>clearAction</code> defined
above, we can create the <classname>JButton</classname></p>
   
<pre>JButton clearButton = new JButton( clearAction );</pre>
   
<np>The name of the action will be used as the text of the button,
and some other properties of the button will be taken from properties of the
action.  For example, if the <code>SHORT_DESCRIPTION</code> property of the
action has a value, then that value is used as the tooltip text for
the button.  (The tooltip text appears when the user hovers the mouse
over the button.)  Furthermore, when you change a property of the
action, the corresponding property of the button will also be
changed.  For example, changing the Action's property associated with the key
<code>Action.NAME</code> will also change the text on the button.</np>
   
<p>The <classname>Action</classname> interface defines a <code>setEnabled()</code>
method that is used to enable and disable the action.  The <code>clearAction</code> action can be enabled
and disabled by calling <code>clearAction.setEnabled(true)</code> and
<code>clearAction.setEnabled(false)</code>.  When you do this, any button that
has been created from the action is also enabled or disabled at the same time.</p>
   
<p>Now of course, the question is, <b>why</b> should you want to use <classname>Actions</classname>
at all?  One advantage is that using actions can help you to organize your code
better.  You can create separate objects that represent each of the actions that
can be performed in your program.  This represents a nice division of responsibility.
Of course, you could do the same thing with individual <classname>ActionListener</classname>
objects, but then you couldn't associate descriptions and other properties with
the actions.</p>
   
<p>More important is the fact that <classname>Actions</classname> can also be used in
other places in the Java API.  You can use an <classname>Action</classname> to create
a <classname>JMenuItem</classname> in the same way as for a <classname>JButton</classname>:</p>
   
<pre>JMenuItem clearCommand = new JMenuItem( clearAction );</pre>
   
<np>A <classname>JMenuItem</classname>, in fact, is a kind of button and shares many
of the same properties that a <classname>JButton</classname> can have.  You can use
the <b>same</b> <classname>Action</classname> to create both a button and a menu
item (or even several of each if you want).
Whenever you enable or disable the action or change its name, the button and the
menu item will <b>both</b> be changed to match.  If you change the <code>NAME</code>
property of the action, the text of both the menu item and the button will be
set to the new name of the action.  If you disable the action, both menu item
and button will be disabled.  You can think of the button and
the menu items as being two presentations of the <classname>Action</classname>,
and you don't have to keep track of the button or menu item after you create them.
You can do everything that you need to do by manipulating the <classname>Action</classname>
object.</np>
      
<p>By the way, if you want to add a menu item that is defined by an <classname>Action</classname>
to a menu, you don't even need to create the <classname>JMenuItem</classname> yourself.
You can add the action object directly to the menu, and the menu item will be created
from the properties of the action.  For example, if <code>menu</code> is a <classname>JMenu</classname>
and <code>clearAction</code> is an <classname>Action</classname>, you can simply say
<code>menu.add(clearAction)</code>.</p>

<p><classname>Actions</classname> have some other useful properties that we will encounter
later in this section.</p>
   
</subsection>
      
   
<subsection id="GUI2.3.2" title="Icons on Buttons">
   
<p>In addition to&mdash;or instead of&mdash;text, buttons can also show icons.
Icons are represented by the <classname>Icon</classname> interface and are usually
created as <classname>ImageIcons</classname>, as discussed in <localref href="GUI2.1.4"/>.
For example, here is a picture of a button that displays an image of a large "X"
as its icon:</p>
   
<img src="button-with-icon.png" width="134" height="38" 
   alt="a JButton with both text and an icon" tex="button-with-icon.eps" texscale="0.75"/>
   
<np>The icon for a button can be set by calling the button's <code>setIcon()</code> method,
or by passing the icon object as a parameter to the constructor when the button is created.
To create the button shown above, I created an <classname>ImageIcon</classname> from a
<classname>BufferedImage</classname> on which I drew the picture that I wanted, and
I constructed the <classname>JButton</classname> using a constructor that takes
both the text and the icon for the button as parameters.  Here's the code segment
that does it:</np>
   
<pre>BufferedImage image = new BufferedImage(24,24,BufferedImage.TYPE_INT_RGB);
 
Graphics2D g2 = (Graphics2D)image.getGraphics();
g2.setColor(Color.LIGHT_GRAY);             // Draw the image for the icon.
g2.fillRect(0,0,24,24);
g2.setStroke( new BasicStroke(3) );        //    Use thick lines.
g2.setColor(Color.BLACK);
g2.drawLine(4,4,20,20);                    //    Draw the "X".
g2.drawLine(4,20,20,4);
g2.dispose();

Icon clearIcon = new ImageIcon(image);     // Create the icon.

JButton clearButton = new JButton("Clear the Display", clearIcon);</pre>   

<p>You can create a button with an icon but no text by using a constructor
that takes just the icon as parameter.  Another alternative is for the
button to get its icon from an <classname>Action</classname>.  When a button
is constructed from an action, it takes its icon from the value of the
action property <code>Action.SMALL_ICON</code>.  For example, suppose that
we want to use an action named <code>clearAction</code> to create the
button shown above.  This could be done with:</p>

<pre>clearAction.putValue( Action.SMALL_ICON, clearIcon );
JButton clearButton = new JButton( clearAction );</pre>
   
<np>The icon could also be associated with the action by passing it
as a parameter to the constructor of an <classname>AbstractAction</classname>:</np>
   
<pre>Action clearAction = new AbstractAction("Clear the Display", clearIcon) {
   public void actionPerformed(ActionEvent evt) {
      .
      .  // Carry out the action.
      .
   }  
}
JButton clearButton = new JButton( clearAction );</pre>

<np>The <code>SMALL_ICON</code> for an <classname>Action</classname> will also be 
used by a <classname>JMenuItem</classname> created from the action.
(An action can also have an icon associated with the key 
<code>Action.LARGE_ICON_KEY</code>.  If it does, then a <classname>JButton</classname>
will use the "large" icon in preference to the "small" icon.  However, a
<classname>JMenuItem</classname> will only use a small icon.)</np>
   

<p>The appearance of buttons can be tweaked in many ways.  For example, you
can change the size of the gap between the button's text and its icon.  You can
associate additional icons with a button that are used when the button is
in certain states, such as when it is pressed or when it is disabled.  
It is even possible to change the positioning of the text with respect to
the icon.  For example, to place the text centered below the icon on
a button, you can say:</p>

<pre>button.setHorizontalTextPosition(JButton.CENTER);
button.setVerticalTextPosition(JButton.BOTTOM);</pre>
   
<np>These methods and many others are defined in the
class <classname>AbstractButton</classname>.  This class is a superclass
for <classname>JMenuItem</classname>, as well as for <classname>JButton</classname>
and for the classes that define check boxes and radio buttons.</np>
   
<p>Finally, I will mention that it is possible to use icons on <classname>JLabels</classname>
in much the same way that they can be used on <classname>JButtons</classname>.
Placing an <classname>ImageIcon</classname> on a <classname>JLabel</classname>
can be a convenient way to add a static image to your GUI.</p>
   
</subsection>
   
   
<subsection id="GUI2.3.3" title="Making Choices">

<p>The <classname>JCheckBox</classname> class was covered in 
<localref href="GUI1.6.3"/>, and the equivalent for use in menus,
<classname>JCheckBoxMenuItem</classname>, in <localref href="GUI1.8.1"/>.
A checkbox lets the user make a choice between two alternatives.
A checkbox has two states, selected and not selected, and the user
can change the state by clicking on the check box.  The state
of a checkbox can also be set programmatically by calling its
<code>setSelected()</code> method, and the current value of the
state can be checked using the <code>isSelected()</code> method.</p>

   
<p>Closely related to checkboxes are <newword>radio buttons</newword>.
Like a checkbox, a radio button can be either selected or not.  However,
radio buttons are expected to occur in groups, and at most one radio button in a
group can be selected at any given time.  Radio button groups let the user
make a choice among several alternatives.  In Java, a radio button is represented
by an object of type <classname>JRadioButton</classname>. When used in isolation, a
<classname>JRadioButton</classname> acts just like a <classname>JCheckBox</classname>, 
and it has the same
methods and events. Ordinarily, however, a <classname>JRadioButton</classname> is used in a
group. A group of radio buttons is represented by an object belonging to the
class <classname>ButtonGroup</classname>. A <classname>ButtonGroup</classname> is <b>not</b> a component
and does not itself have a visible representation on the screen. A
<classname>ButtonGroup</classname> works behind the scenes to organize a group of radio
buttons, to ensure that at most one button in the group can be selected at any given
time.</p>

<p>To use a group of radio buttons, you must create a <classname>JRadioButton</classname>
object for each button in the group, and you must create one object of type
<classname>ButtonGroup</classname> to organize the individual buttons into a group. Each
<classname>JRadioButton</classname> must be added individually to some container, so that it
will appear on the screen. (A <classname>ButtonGroup</classname> plays no role in the
placement of the buttons on the screen.) Each <classname>JRadioButton</classname> must also
be added to the <classname>ButtonGroup</classname>, which has an <code>add()</code> method for
this purpose. If you want one of the buttons to be selected initially, you
can call <code>setSelected(true)</code> for that button. If you don't do this, then
none of the buttons will be selected until the user clicks on one of them.</p>

<p>As an example, here is how you could set up a set of radio buttons that can
be used to select a color:</p>

<pre>JRadioButton redRadio, blueRadio, greenRadio, yellowRadio;
         // Variables to represent the radio buttons.
         // These should probably be instance variables, so
         // that they can be used throughout the program.
 
ButtonGroup colorGroup = new ButtonGroup();

redRadio = new JRadioButton("Red");  // Create a button.
colorGroup.add(redRadio);            // Add it to the group.
   
blueRadio = new JRadioButton("Blue");
colorGroup.add(blueRadio);
 
greenRadio = new JRadioButton("Green");
colorGroup.add(greenRadio);
 
yellowRadio = new JRadioButton("Yellow");
colorGroup.add(yellowRadio);
 
redRadio.setSelected(true);  // Make an initial selection.</pre>

<np>The individual buttons must still be added to a container if they are to
appear on the screen. If you want to respond immediately when the user clicks
on one of the radio buttons, you can register an <classname>ActionListener</classname> for
each button.  Just as for
checkboxes, it is not always necessary to register listeners for radio buttons.
In some cases, you can simply check the state of each button when you need to
know it, using the button's <code>isSelected()</code> method.</np>
         
<p>You can add the equivalent of a group of radio buttons to a menu by using
the class <classname>JRadioButtonMenuItem</classname>.  To use this class,
create several objects of this type, and create a <classname>ButtonGroup</classname>
to manage them.  Add each <classname>JRadioButtonMenuItem</classname> to
the <classname>ButtonGroup</classname>, and also add them to
a <classname>JMenu</classname>.  If you want one of the items to be selected
initially, call its <code>setSelected()</code> method to set its selection state
to true.  You can add <classname>ActionListeners</classname> to each
<classname>JRadioButtonMenuItem</classname> if you need to take some action
when the user selects the menu item; if not, you can simply check the selected states
of the buttons whenever you need to know them.  As an example, suppose that
<code>menu</code> is a <classname>JMenu</classname>.  Then you can add a
group of buttons to <code>menu</code> as follows:</p>
   
<pre>JRadioButtonMenuItem selectRedItem, selectGreenItem, selectBlueItem;
   // These might be defined as instance variables
ButtonGroup group = new ButtonGroup();
selectRedItem = new JRadioButtonMenuItem("Red");
group.add(selectRedItem);
menu.add(selectRedItem);
selectGreenItem = new JRadioButtonMenuItem("Green");
group.add(selectGreenItem);
menu.add(selectGreenItem);
selectBlueItem = new JRadioButtonMenuItem("Blue");
group.add(selectBlueItem);
menu.add(selectBlueItem);</pre>

<break/>
   
<p>When it's drawn on the screen, a <classname>JCheckBox</classname> includes
a little box that is either checked or unchecked to show the state of the box.
That box is actually a pair of <classname>Icons</classname>.
One icon is shown when the check box is unselected; the other is shown when it
is selected.  You can change the appearance of the check box by substituting
different icons for the standard ones.</p>
   
<p>The icon that is shown when the check box is unselected is just the main
icon for the <classname>JCheckBox</classname>.  You can provide a different
unselected icon in the constructor or you can change the icon using the
<code>setIcon()</code> method of the <classname>JCheckBox</classname> object.
To change the icon that is shown when the check box is selected, use
the <code>setSelectedIcon()</code> method of the <classname>JCheckBox</classname>.
All this applies equally to <classname>JRadioButton</classname>,
<classname>JCheckBoxMenuItem</classname>, and <classname>JRadioButtonMenuItem</classname>.
</p>
   
<p>An example of this can be found in the sample program <sourceref href="ToolBarDemo.java"/>,
which is discussed in the next subsection.  That program creates a set of radio buttons
that use custom icons.  The buttons are created by the following method:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Create a JRadioButton and add it to a specified button group.  The button
 * is meant for selecting a drawing color in the display.  The color is used to 
 * create two custom icons, one for the unselected state of the button and one
 * for the selected state.  These icons are used instead of the usual
 * radio button icons.
 * @param c the color of the button, and the color to be used for drawing.
 *    (Note that c has to be "final" since it is used in the anonymous inner
 *    class that defines the response to ActionEvents on the button.)
 * @param grp the ButtonGroup to which the radio button will be added.
 * @param selected if true, then the state of the button is set to selected.
 * @return the radio button that was just created; sorry, but the button
 *    is not as pretty as I would like!
 */
private JRadioButton makeColorRadioButton(final Color c, 
                                           ButtonGroup grp, boolean selected) {
   
   /* Create an ImageIcon for the normal, unselected state of the button,
      using a BufferedImage that is drawn here from scratch. */
   
   BufferedImage image = new BufferedImage(30,30,BufferedImage.TYPE_INT_RGB);
   Graphics g = image.getGraphics();
   g.setColor(Color.LIGHT_GRAY);
   g.fillRect(0,0,30,30);
   g.setColor(c);
   g.fill3DRect(1, 1, 24, 24, true);
   g.dispose();
   Icon unselectedIcon = new ImageIcon(image);
   
   /* Create an ImageIcon for the selected state of the button. */
 
   image = new BufferedImage(30,30,BufferedImage.TYPE_INT_RGB);
   g = image.getGraphics();
   g.setColor(Color.DARK_GRAY);
   g.fillRect(0,0,30,30);
   g.setColor(c);
   g.fill3DRect(3, 3, 24, 24, false);
   g.dispose();
   Icon selectedIcon = new ImageIcon(image);
   
   /* Create and configure the button. */

   JRadioButton button = new JRadioButton(unselectedIcon);
   button.setSelectedIcon(selectedIcon);
   button.addActionListener( new ActionListener() {
      public void actionPerformed(ActionEvent e) {
           // The action for this button sets the current drawing color
           // in the display to c.
         display.setCurrentColor(c);
      }
   });
   grp.add(button);
   if (selected)
      button.setSelected(true);

   return button;
} // end makeColorRadioButton </pre>
   
<break/>

   
<p>It is possible to create radio buttons and check boxes&mdash;both the
regular sort and the corresponding menu items&mdash;from <classname>Actions</classname>.
The button or checkbox takes its name, main icon, tooltip text, and enabled/disabled state from the
action. And the Action's <code>actionPerformed()</code> method is called when the user
changes the state. Furthermore, an action has a property named <code>Action.SELECTED_KEY</code>, which 
means that the action itself can have a selected state.  By default, the
value of the <code>SELECTED_KEY</code> property is <code>null</code> and is not
used for anything.  However, you can set the value to be true or false by calling
<code>action.putValue(Action.SELECTED_KEY,true)</code> or
<code>action.putValue(Action.SELECTED_KEY,false)</code>.  Once you have done so,
the action's <code>SELECTED_KEY</code> property and the selected state of any
checkbox or radio button created from the action will automatically be kept
in sync.  You can find out the current value of the property by calling
<code>action.getValue(Action.SELECTED_KEY)</code>.  Note that the value of
a property is actually an object.  When you set the value to <code>true</code>
or <code>false</code>, the value is wrapped in an object of type
<classname>Boolean</classname>.  The return type of <code>action.getValue()</code>
is <classname>Object</classname>, so you will probably need to type-cast the return value
to <classname>Boolean</classname>.</p>

<break/>

<p>Java has another component that lets the user choose from a set of options:
the <classname>JComboBox</classname>.  A combo box contains a list of items,
but only displays the currently selected items.  The user clicks the combo box
to see a pop-up list of options and can then select from the list.  The functionality
is similar to a group of radio buttons.</p>

<p><classname>JComboBox</classname> is a parameterized class, where the type parameter
specifies the type of items that that combo box can hold.  Most commonly, the items
are strings, and the type is <atype>JComboBox&lt;String&gt;</atype>.  This is the only
case I will discuss.
When a <classname>JComboBox&lt;String&gt;</classname> object is first constructed, it initially contains
no items. An item is added to the bottom of the list of options by calling the combo box's instance
method, <code>addItem(str)</code>, where <code>str</code> is the string that will be
displayed in the menu.</p>

<p>For example, the following code will create an object of type
<classname>JComboBox</classname> that contains the options Red, Blue, Green, and Black:</p>

<pre>JComboBox&lt;String&gt; colorChoice = new JComboBox&lt;String&gt;();
colorChoice.addItem("Red");
colorChoice.addItem("Blue");
colorChoice.addItem("Green");
colorChoice.addItem("Black");</pre>

<p>You can call the <code>getSelectedIndex()</code> method of a <classname>JComboBox</classname>
to find out which item is currently selected. This method returns an integer
that gives the position of the selected item in the list, where the items are
numbered starting from zero. Alternatively, you can call
<code>getSelectedItem()</code> to get the selected item itself. (This method
returns a value of type <classname>Object</classname>&mdash;even when the items
are limited to being strings.)  You can change the selection by
calling the method <code>setSelectedIndex(n)</code>, where <code>n</code> is an integer
giving the position of the item that you want to select.</p>

<p>The most common way to use a <classname>JComboBox</classname> is to call its
<code>getSelectedIndex()</code> method when you have a need to know which item is
currently selected. However, 
<classname>JComboBox</classname> components generate <classname>ActionEvents</classname> when
the user selects an item, and you can register
an <classname>ActionListener</classname> with the <classname>JComboBox</classname> if you want to respond
to such events as they occur.</p>

<p><classname>JComboBoxes</classname> have a nifty feature, which is probably not all that
useful in practice. You can make a <classname>JComboBox</classname> "editable" by calling its
method <code>setEditable(true)</code>. If you do this, the user can edit the
selection by clicking on the <classname>JComboBox</classname> and typing. This allows the
user to make a selection that is not in the pre-configured list that you
provide. (The "Combo" in the name "JComboBox" refers to the fact that it's a
kind of combination of menu and text-input box.) If the user has edited the
selection in this way, then the <code>getSelectedIndex()</code> method will return
the value <code>-1</code>, and <code>getSelectedItem()</code> will return the string
that the user typed. An <classname>ActionEvent</classname> is triggered if the user presses
return while typing in the <classname>JComboBox</classname>.</p>

<break/>

<p>There is a lot of information in this section.  The sample program <sourceref href="ChoiceDemo.java"/>
demonstrates the use of combo boxes, check boxes, and radio buttons&mdash;including the
use of Actions with check boxes and radio buttons.  I encourage you to run the program to see
how these things work and to read the source code.  The source code has a lot of comments to
explain what is going on.</p>
   
</subsection>
   
      
<subsection id="GUI2.3.4" title="Toolbars">
   
<p>It has become increasingly common for programs to have a row of small buttons
along the top or side of the program window that offer access to some of the
commonly used features of the program.  The row of buttons is known as a
<newword>tool bar</newword>.  Typically, the buttons in a tool bar are presented
as small icons, with no text.  Tool bars can also contain other components,
such as <classname>JTextFields</classname> and <classname>JLabels</classname>.</p>
   
<p>In Swing, tool bars are represented by the class <classname>JToolBar</classname>.
A <classname>JToolBar</classname> is a container that can hold other components.
It is also itself a component, and so can be added to other containers.  In general,
the parent component of the tool bar should use a <classname>BorderLayout</classname>.
The tool bar should occupy one of the edge positions&mdash;<code>NORTH</code>,
<code>SOUTH</code>, <code>EAST</code>, or <code>WEST</code>&mdash;in the
<classname>BorderLayout</classname>.  Furthermore, the other three edge positions
should be empty.  The reason for this is that it might be possible (depending
on the platform and configuration) for the user to drag the tool bar from one edge position in
the parent container to another.  It might even be possible for the user to drag the
tool bar off its parent entirely, so that it becomes a separate window.</p>

<p>Here is a picture of a toolbar.  This
is from the sample program <sourceref href="ToolBarDemo.java"/>, which I
discuss below:</p>

<img src="toolbar.png" width="304" height="50" alt="a free-floating toolbar"
    tex="toolbar.eps" texscale="0.75"/>
   

<p>In the demo program, the user can draw colored curves in a large drawing area.  
The first three buttons in the tool bar are a set
of radio buttons that control the drawing color.  The fourth
button is a push button that the user can click to clear the drawing.
</p>
   
<p>Tool bars are easy to use.  You just have to create the <classname>JToolBar</classname>
object, add it to a container, and add some buttons and possibly other components to
the tool bar.  One fine point is adding space to a tool bar, such as the gap between
the radio buttons and the push button in the above picture.  You can leave
a gap by adding a separator to the tool bar.  For example:</p>
   
<pre>toolbar.addSeparator(new Dimension(20,20));</pre>
   
<np>This adds an invisible 20-by-20 pixel block to the tool bar.  This will appear
as a 20 pixel gap between components.</np>
   
<p>Here is the constructor from the <code>ToolBarDemo</code> program. 
It shows how to create the tool bar and place it in a container.  Note that
class <classname>ToolBarDemo</classname> is a subclass of <classname>JPanel</classname>,
and the tool bar and display are added to the panel object that is being constructed:</p>
   
<pre>public ToolBarDemo() {
   
   setLayout(new BorderLayout(2,2));
   setBackground(Color.GRAY);
   setBorder(BorderFactory.createLineBorder(Color.GRAY,2));
   
   display = new Display();  // the area where the user draws.
   add(display, BorderLayout.CENTER);
   
   JToolBar toolbar = new JToolBar();
   add(toolbar, BorderLayout.NORTH);
   
   ButtonGroup group = new ButtonGroup();
   toolbar.add( makeColorRadioButton(Color.RED,group,true) );
   toolbar.add( makeColorRadioButton(Color.GREEN,group,false) );
   toolbar.add( makeColorRadioButton(Color.BLUE,group,false) );
   
   toolbar.addSeparator(new Dimension(20,20));
   
   toolbar.add( makeClearButton() );
   
}</pre>
   
<p>If you want a vertical tool bar that can be placed in the <code>EAST</code>
or <code>WEST</code> position of a <classname>BorderLayout</classname>,
you should specify the orientation in the tool bar's constructor:</p>
   
<pre>JToolBar toolbar = new JToolBar( JToolBar.VERTICAL );</pre>
   
<np>The default orientation is <code>JToolBar.HORIZONTAL</code>.  The
orientation is adjusted automatically when the user drags the tool bar
into a new position.  If you want to prevent the user from dragging
the tool bar, just say <code>toolbar.setFloatable(false)</code>.</np>

</subsection>
   
   
<subsection id="GUI2.3.5" title="Keyboard Accelerators">
   
<p>In most programs, commonly used menu commands have keyboard equivalents.
The user can type the keyboard equivalent instead of selecting the command
from the menu, and the result will be exactly the same.  Typically, for
example, the "Save" command has keyboard equivalent <code>CONTROL-S</code>,
and the "Undo" command corresponds to <code>CONTROL-Z</code>.  (Under
Mac OS, the keyboard equivalents for these commands would probably
be <code>META-S</code> and <code>META-Z</code>, where <code>META</code>
refers to holding down the "apple" key.)  The keyboard equivalents
for menu commands are referred to as <newword>accelerators</newword>.</p>
   
<p>The class <code>javax.swing.KeyStroke</code> is used to represent
key strokes that the user can type on the keyboard.  Keystrokes can
refer to pressing a key, releasing a key, or typing a character,
possibly while holding down one or more of the
modifier keys <code>control</code>, <code>shift</code>, <code>alt</code>,
and <code>meta</code>. The <classname>KeyStroke</classname> class has
a convenient static method, <code>getKeyStroke(String)</code>, that makes it easy to 
create key stroke objects representing key pressed events.  For example,</p>

<pre>KeyStroke.getKeyStroke( "ctrl S" )</pre>
   
<np>returns a <classname>KeyStroke</classname> that represents the action
of pressing the "S" key while holding down the control key.  In addition
to "ctrl", you can use the modifiers "shift", "alt", and "meta" in the
string that describes the key stroke.  You can even combine several modifiers,
so that</np>
   
<pre>KeyStroke.getKeyStroke( "ctrl shift Z" )</pre>
   
<np>represents the action of pressing the "Z" key while holding down both
the control and the shift keys.  When the key stroke involves pressing a
character key, the character must appear in the string in upper case
form.  You can also have key strokes that correspond to non-character
keys.  The number keys can be referred to as "1", "2", etc., while
certain special keys have names such as "F1", "ENTER", and "LEFT"
(for the left arrow key).  The class <classname>KeyEvent</classname>
defines many constants such as <code>VK_ENTER</code>, <code>VK_LEFT</code>,
and <code>VK_S</code>.  The names that are used for keys in the
keystroke description are just these constants with the leading
"<code>VK_</code>" removed.</np>

<p>There are at least two ways to associate a keyboard accelerator with
a menu item.  One is to use the <code>setAccelerator()</code> method
of the menu item object:</p>
   
<pre>JMenuItem saveCommand = new JMenuItem( "Save..." );
saveCommand.setAccelerator( KeyStroke.getKeyStroke("ctrl S") );</pre>
   
<np>The other technique can be used if the menu item is created from 
an <classname>Action</classname>.  The action property
<code>Action.ACCELERATOR_KEY</code> can be used to associate a
<classname>KeyStroke</classname> with an <classname>Action</classname>.
When a menu item is created from the action, the keyboard accelerator
for the menu item is taken from the value of this property.  For
example, if <code>redoAction</code> is an <classname>Action</classname>
representing a "Redo" action, then you might say:</np>
   
<pre>redoAction.putValue( Action.ACCELERATOR_KEY, 
                              KeyStroke.getKeyStroke("ctrl shift Z") );
JMenuItem redoCommand = new JMenuItem( redoAction );</pre>
   
<np>or, alternatively, you could simply add the action to a <classname>JMenu</classname>,
<code>editMenu</code>, with <code>editMenu.add(redoAction)</code>.
(Note, by the way, that accelerators apply only to menu items, not to
push buttons.  When you create a <classname>JButton</classname> from an
action, the <code>ACCELERATOR_KEY</code> property of the action is ignored.)</np>
   
<p>Note that you can use accelerators for <classname>JCheckBoxMenuItems</classname>
and <classname>JRadioButtonMenuItems</classname>, as well as for simple
<classname>JMenuItems</classname>.</p>
   
<p>For examples of using keyboard accelerators, see <sourceref href="ChoiceDemo.java"/>
and the solution to <localref href="GUI2.ex.2"/>.</p>
   
<break/>
   
<p>By the way, as noted above, in the Mac&nbsp;OS operating system, the
meta (or apple) key is usually used for keyboard accelerators instead of
the control key.  Java has a way of determining the correct modifier
for the computer on which it is running.  However, it requires the
use of a different method for constructing the <classname>KeyStroke</classname>.  The 
function call</p>

<pre>int shortcutMask = Toolkit.getDefaultToolkit().getMenuShortcutKeyMaskEx()</pre>

<np>returns a "mask" that can be used to represent the correct modifier key when
the keystroke is created by the function</np>

<pre>KeyStroke stoke = KeyStroke( keyCode, shortcutMask );</pre>

<np>The first parameter, <code>keyCode</code>, is one of the constants
such as <code>KeyEvent.VK_Z</code> that represent keys on the keyboard.
For example, <code>KeyStroke.getKeyStroke(KeyEvent.VK_Z,shortcutMask)</code>
represents the action of pressing the Z key while holding down the
meta key on a Mac or the control key on Windows or Linux.  It is possible
to add other modifiers to the <code>shortcutMask</code> to account for
holding down the shift or alt keys; see the documentation.</np>

<p>As an example, here is a
code segment that is used in <sourceref href="ChoiceDemo.java"/> to make
a "Quit" menu item that will have the appropriate modifier key for
the computer on which the program is running</p>

<pre>int shortcutMask = Toolkit.getDefaultToolkit().getMenuShortcutKeyMasEx();
KeyStroke quitKeyStroke = KeyStroke.getKeyStroke(KeyEvent.VK_Q, shortcutMask);
JMenuItem quit = new JMenuItem("Quit");
quit.setAccelerator(quitKeyStroke);
quit.addActionListener( evt -> System.exit(0) );
controlMenu.add(quit);</pre>
   
</subsection>
   
   
<subsection id="GUI2.3.6" title="HTML on Buttons">
   
<p>As a final stop in this brief tour of ways to spiff up your buttons,
I'll mention the fact that the text that is displayed on a button can
be specified in HTML format.  HTML is the markup language that is used to
write web pages.  I don't cover it in this book, but I will explain a
few things that you can do with it.  HTML allows you to apply color or italics
or other styles to just part of the text on your buttons.  It also makes
it possible to have buttons that display multiple lines of text.
(You can also use HTML on <classname>JLabels</classname>,
which can be even more useful.)   
Here's a picture of a button with HTML text (along with a "Java" icon):</p>
   
<img src="java-button.png" width="226" height="100" alt="button with HTML text"
   tex="java-button.eps" texscale="0.75"/>
   
<p>If the string of text that is applied to a button starts with "<code>&lt;html&gt;</code>",
then the string is interpreted as HTML.  The string does not have to use strict
HTML format; for example, you don't need a closing <code>&lt;/html&gt;</code> at the end of
the string.  To get multi-line text, use <code>&lt;br&gt;</code> in the string
to represent line breaks.  If you would like the lines of text to be center
justified, include the entire text (except for the <code>&lt;html&gt;</code>) between
<code>&lt;center&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;/center&gt;</code>.  For example,</p>
   
<pre>JButton button = new JButton(
               "&lt;html&gt;&lt;center&gt;This button has&lt;br&gt;two lines of text&lt;/center&gt;" );</pre>
   
<np>creates a button that displays two centered lines of text.  You can apply italics
to part of the string by enclosing that part between <code>&lt;i&gt;</code> and
<code>&lt;/i&gt;</code>.  Similarly, use <code>&lt;b&gt;...&lt;/b&gt;</code>
for bold text and <code>&lt;u&gt;...&lt;/u&gt;</code> for underlined text.
For green text, enclose the text between <code>&lt;font&nbsp;color=green&gt;</code>
and <code>&lt;/font&gt;</code>.  You can, of course, use other colors
in place of "green."  The "Java" button that is shown above was created using:</np>
   
<pre>JButton javaButton = new JButton( "&lt;html&gt;&lt;u&gt;Now&lt;/u&gt; is the time for&lt;br&gt;" +
                           "a nice cup of &lt;font color=red&gt;coffee&lt;/font&gt;." );</pre>
   
<np>and then adding the Java image as an icon for the button.</np>
   
   
</subsection>
   
   
</section>