<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE quiz SYSTEM "../javanotes7.dtd" >

<quiz>


<question>
<ques><p>What is meant by the <i>basetype</i> of an array?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>The base type of an array refers
to the type of the items that can be stored in that array. For example, the
base type of the array of type <atype>Color[]</atype> is 
<classname>Color</classname>.</p>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>What is the purpose of the following variable-arity method? What are
the values of <code>same(1,2,3)</code>, <code>same(17,17,17,17)</code>,
and <code>same(2)</code>?  Why?</p>
<pre>static double same( int... value ) {
    for (int i = 1; i &lt; value.length; i++) {
        if ( value[i-1] != value[i] )
            return false;
    }
    return true;
}</pre>
</ques>
<ans><p>This function can be called with any number of integer parameters. It tests
whether all of the parameter values are equal.  The value of
<code>same(1,2,3)</code> is <code>false</code>.  The function begins by 
comparing 1 and 2; since they are not equal, it immediately returns <code>false</code>.
The value of <code>same(17,17,17,17)</code> is <code>true</code>.  The function compares
<code>value[0]</code> with <code>value[1]</code>, <code>value[1]</code> with <code>value[2]</code>,
and <code>value[2]</code> with <code>value[3]</code>.  All of these values are 17, so the routine
goes through the <code>for</code> loop without returning <code>false</code>, and the
"<code>return true</code>" statement after the end of the loop is executed.
For <code>same(2)</code>, <code>value.length</code> is 1, and the body of the
<code>loop</code> is never executed; the return value is <code>true</code>.</p></ans>
</question>
   
   
<question>
<ques><p>What does it mean to sort an array?</p>
</ques>
<ans><p>To sort an array means to
rearrange the items in the array so that they are in increasing or decreasing
order (according to some criterion).</p>
<p>(Note: To be more accurate, we should say "non-decreasing" instead of
"increasing" and "non-increasing" instead of "decreasing."  An array can
contain duplicate values, and in that case, its elements can'be be put
into strictly increasing or strictly decreasing order.)</p>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>What is the main advantage of binary search over linear search?  What is the
main disadvantage?</p></ques>
<ans><p>The advantage of binary search is that it is much faster.  On a list of
one million items, linear search would take an average of five hundred thousand steps to find an
item, whereas binary search would take only 20 steps.  The disadvantage is that
binary search only works on a sorted list, so some extra work must be done to
sort the list or to keep the list in sorted order as it is created.</p></ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>What is meant by a
<i>dynamic array?</i> What is the advantage of a dynamic array over a regular
array?</p></ques>
<ans><p>A dynamic array is like an array
in that it is a data structure that stores a sequence of items, all of the same
type, in numbered locations. It is different from an array in that there is no
preset upper limit on the number of items that it can contain. This is an
advantage in situations where a reasonable value for the size of the array is
not known at the time it is created.</p></ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>What does it mean to say that <classname>ArrayList</classname> is a
parameterized type?</p></ques>
<ans><p>A class name is a type, but as a parameterized type, 
<classname>ArrayList</classname> does not define just one type.
Instead, for every object type <classname>T</classname>, there is a type
<atype>ArrayList&lt;T&gt;</atype>.  <classname>T</classname>&nbsp;is a
"type parameter."  An object of type <atype>ArrayList&lt;T&gt;</atype> is a list that can only hold objects of
type <classname>T</classname>.  We can have <atype>ArrayList&lt;String&gt;</atype> to
represent lists of <classname>Strings</classname>, <atype>ArrayList&lt;Integer&gt;</atype>
to represent lists of <classname>Integers</classname>, and so one.  The fact that
<classname>ArrayList</classname> is a parameterized type means that we don't have
to create a new class for each type of list.</p></ans>
</question>
   

<question>
<ques><p>Suppose that a variable <code>strlst</code> has been declared as</p>
<pre>ArrayList&lt;String&gt; strlst = new ArrayList&lt;String&gt;();</pre>
<np>Assume that the list is not empty and that all the items in the list
are non-null. Write a code segment that will find and print the string in the list
that comes first in lexicographic order.</np>
</ques> 
<ans><p>Strings can be compared for lexicographic order using the <code>compareTo</code>
instance method in the <classname>String</classname> class.
We can find the smallest string as follows:</p>
<pre>String smallest = strlst.get(0);
for (int i = 1; i &lt; strlist.size(); i++) {
   String nextString = strlst.get(i);
   if ( nextString.compareTo(smallest) &lt; 0 ) 
       smallest = nextString;
}
System.out.println("The smallest string lexicographically is " + smallest);</pre>
<np>Alternatively, a for-each loop could be used:</np>
<pre>String smallest = strlst.get(0);
for (String item : strlst) {
   if ( item.compareTo(smallest) &lt; 0 ) 
       smallest = item;
}
System.out.println("The smallest string lexicographically is " + smallest)</pre>
<p>Not that in this version, the first item in the list is compared to itself
as the first step in the loop.  There is no easy way to leave that item out
of the for-each loop.</p>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Show the exact output
produced by the following code segment.</p>
<pre>char[][] pic = new char[6][6];
for (int i = 0; i &lt; 6; i++)
   for (int j = 0; j &lt; 6; j++) {
      if ( i == j  ||  i == 0  ||  i == 5 )
         pic[i][j] = '*';
      else
         pic[i][j] = '.';
   }
for (int i = 0; i &lt; 6; i++) {
   for (int j = 0; j &lt; 6; j++)
      System.out.print(pic[i][j]);
   System.out.println();
}</pre></ques>
<ans><p>The output consists of six
lines, with each line containing six characters. In the first line, <code>i</code>
is 0, so all the characters are *'s. In the last line, i is 5, so all the
characters are *'s. In each of the four lines in the middle, one of the
characters is a * and the rest are periods. The output is</p>
<pre>******
.*....
..*...
...*..
....*.
******</pre>
<p>It might help to look at the array items that are printed on each line. Note
that <code>pic[row][col]</code> is '*' if <code>row</code> is 0 or if <code>row</code> is 5
or if <code>row</code> and <code>col</code> are equal.</p>
<pre>pic[0][0] pic[0][1] pic[0][2] pic[0][3] pic[0][4] pic[0][5] 
pic[1][0] pic[1][1] pic[1][2] pic[1][3] pic[1][4] pic[1][5] 
pic[2][0] pic[2][1] pic[2][2] pic[2][3] pic[2][4] pic[2][5] 
pic[3][0] pic[3][1] pic[3][2] pic[3][3] pic[3][4] pic[3][5] 
pic[4][0] pic[4][1] pic[4][2] pic[4][3] pic[4][4] pic[4][5] 
pic[5][0] pic[5][1] pic[5][2] pic[5][3] pic[5][4] pic[5][5]</pre>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Write a complete static method
that finds the largest value in an array of <code>ints</code>. The method
should have one parameter, which is an array of type <code>int[]</code>. The
largest number in the array should be returned as the value of the
method.</p></ques>
<ans><p>One possible answer is:</p>
<pre>public static int getMax(int[] list) {
   
   int max = list[0];  // This is the largest item seen so far.
   
   for (int i = 1; i &lt; list.length; i++) {
         // Look at each item in the array.  If the item is
         // bigger than max, then set max equal to the item.
       if (list[i] &gt; max)
          max = list[i];
   }
   
   // At this point, max is the largest item in the whole array.
   
   return max;
   
} // end getMax</pre>
<np>(Note that this method throws an exception if the
parameter <code>list</code> is null or if it is an array of
length&nbsp;0.  The exception is thrown by the line
"<code>int&nbsp;max&nbsp;=&nbsp;list[0];".  The reference
to <code>list[0]</code> causes a <classname>NullPointerException</classname></code>
if <code>list</code> is null and an <classname>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</classname>
if the array has length zero.)</np>
</ans>
</question>

   
<question>
<ques><p>Suppose that temperature
measurements were made on each day of 2014 in each of 100 cities. The
measurements have been stored in an array</p>
<pre>int[][]  temps  =  new  int[100][365];</pre>
<np>where <code>temps[c][d]</code> holds the measurement for city number <code>c</code>
on the <code>d</code><sup>th</sup> day of the year. Write a code segment that will
print out the average temperature, over the course of the whole year, for each
city. The average temperature for a city can be obtained by adding up all 365
measurements for that city and dividing the answer by 365.0.</np></ques>
<ans><p>A pseudocode outline of the
answer is</p>
<pre>For each city {
   Add up all the temperatures for that city
   Divide the total by 365 and print the answer
}</pre>
<np>Adding up all the temperatures for a given city itself requires a for loop,
so the code segment looks like this:</np>
<pre>for (int city = 0; city &lt; 100; city++) {
    int total = 0;  // total of temperatures for this city
    for (int day = 0; day &lt; 365; day++)
       total = total + temps[city][day];
    double avg = total / 365.0;  // average temp for this city
    System.out.println("Average temp for city number " 
             + city + " is " + avg);
}</pre></ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>Suppose that a class,
<classname>Employee,</classname> is defined as follows:</p>
<pre>class Employee {
   String lastName;
   String firstName;
   double hourlyWage;
   int yearsWithCompany;
}</pre>
<np>Suppose that data about 100 employees is <b>already</b> stored in an
array:</np>
<pre>Employee[] employeeData = new Employee[100];</pre>
<np>Write a code segment that will output the first name, last name, and hourly
wage of each employee who has been with the company for 20 years or more.  Write two
versions of the code segment, one that uses a regular <code>for</code> loop, and one that 
uses a for-each loop.</np></ques>
<ans><p>(The data for the i-th employee
is stored in an object that can be referred to as <code>employeeData[i]</code>. The
four pieces of data about that employee are members of this object and can be
referred to as:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>employeeData[i].firstName</code></li>
<li><code>employeeData[i].lastName</code></li>
<li><code>employeeData[i].hourlyWage</code></li>
<li><code>employeeData[i].yearsWithCompany</code></li>
</ul>
<np>The code segment uses a for loop to consider each employee in the
array.)</np>
<pre>for (int i=0; i &lt; 100; i++) {
    if ( employeeData[i].yearsWithCompany &gt;= 20 )
        System.out.println(employeeData[i].firstName + " " +
                      employeeData[i].lastName + ": " +
                      employeeData[i].hourlyWage);
}</pre>
<np>Using a for-each loop:</np>
<pre>for ( Employee emp : employeeData ) {
    if ( emp.yearsWithCompany &gt;= 20 )
        System.out.println(emp.firstName + " " +
                      emp.lastName + ": " +
                      emp.hourlyWage);
}</pre>
</ans>
</question>


<question>
<ques><p>What is the purpose of the
following subroutine? What is the meaning of the value that it returns, in
terms of the value of its parameter?</p>
<pre>static double[] sums( double[][] data ) {
    double[] answers = new double[ data.length ];
    for (int i = 0; i &lt; data.length; i++) {
        double sum = 0;
        for (int j = 0; j &lt; data[i].length; i++)
            sum = sum + data[i][j];
        answers[i] = sum;
    }
    return answers;
}</pre>
</ques>
<ans><p>The purpose of this subroutine is to find the sum of the numbers in each
row of the parameter array <code>data</code>.  The answer is returned as 
a one-dimensional array of double.  The value of <code>answers[i]</code> is the
sum of the numbers in row number <code>i</code> of <code>data</code>.
</p>
<p>(In the first two lines of the method, <code>data.length</code> is the
number of rows in <code>data</code>.  In the nested <code>for</code> loop,
<code>data[i].length</code> is the number of values in the <code>i</code>-th row.)</p></ans>
</question>



</quiz>