<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="arrays.1" title="Array Details">
   
   
<p><start><big>A</big>rray basics have been discussed</start> in previous chapters,
but there are still details of Java syntax to be filled in, and there is a lot more to say
about using arrays.  This section looks at some of the syntactic details, 
with more information about array processing to come in the rest of the
chapter.</p>
   
<p>To briefly review some of the basics&dots;.  An array is a numbered sequence
of <i>elements</i>, and each element acts like a separate variable.  All of the
elements are of the same type, which is called the <i>base type</i> of the array.
The array as a whole also has a type.  If the base type is <classname>btype</classname>,
then the array is of type <atype>btype[]</atype>.  Each element in the array
has an <i>index</i>, which is just its numerical position in the sequence of elements.
If the array is <code>A</code>, then the i-th element of the array is <code>A[i]</code>.
The number of elements in an array is called its <i>length</i>.  The length of
an array <code>A</code> is <code>A.length</code>.  The length of an array can't
be changed after the array is created.  The elements of the array <code>A</code>
are <code>A[0]</code>, <code>A[1]</code>, &dots;, <code>A[A.length-1]</code>.
An attempt to refer to an array element with an index outside the range
from zero to <code>A.length-1</code> causes an <classname>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</classname>.
</p>

<p>Arrays in Java are objects, so an array variable can only <b>refer</b> to an array;
it does <b>not</b> contain the array.  The value of an array variable can also be <code>null</code>.
In that case, it does not refer to any array, and an attempt to refer to an
array element such as <code>A[i]</code> will cause a <classname>NullPointerException</classname>.
Arrays are created using a special form of the <code>new</code> operator. For
example,</p>

<pre>int[] A = new int[10];</pre>

<np>creates a new array with base type <ptype>int</ptype> and length 10, and it sets
the variable <code>A</code> to refer to the newly created array.</np>



<subsection id="arrays.1.1" title="For-each Loops">   

<p>Arrays are often processed using <code>for</code> loops.  A <code>for</code>
loop makes it easy to process each element in an array from beginning to end.  For
example, if <code>namelist</code> is an array of <classname>Strings</classname>, 
then all the values in the list can be printed using</p>

<pre>for (int i = 0; i &lt; namelist.length; i++) {
    System.out.println( namelist[i] );
}</pre>

<p>This type of processing is so common that there is an alternative form of
the <code>for</code> loop that makes it easier to write.  The alternative
is called a <newword>for-each loop</newword>.   It is probably easiest to
start with an example.  Here is a for-each loop for printing all the values
in an array of <classname>Strings</classname>:</p>

<pre>for ( String name : namelist ) {
    System.out.println( name );
}</pre>

<np>The meaning of "<code>for (String name : namelist)</code>" is
"for each String, name, in the array, namelist, do the following".  The effect
is that the variable <code>name</code> takes on each of the values in <code>namelist</code>
in turn, and the body of the loop is executed for each of those values.  Note that
there is no array index in the loop.  The loop control variable, <code>name</code>,
represents one of the values in the array, not the index of one of the values.
</np>

<p>The for-each loop is meant specifically for processing all the values
in a data structure, and we will see in <localref href="generics"/> that it applies to other
data structures besides arrays.  The for-each loop makes it possible to process the
values without even knowing the details of how the data is structured.  In the
case of arrays, it lets you avoid the complications of using array indices.</p>

<p>A for-each loop
will perform the same operation for each value that is stored
in an array.  
If <code>itemArray</code> is an array of type <atype>BaseType[]</atype>,
then a for-each loop for <code>itemArray</code> has the form:</p>
   
<pre>for ( BaseType item : itemArray ) {
   .
   .  // process the item
   .
}</pre>
   
<np>As usual, the braces are optional if there is only one statement inside the loop.
In this loop, <code>item</code> is the loop control variable.  It is
declared as a variable of type <classname>BaseType</classname>, where
<classname>BaseType</classname> is the base type of the array.  (In a
for-each loop, the loop control variable <b>must</b> be declared in the
loop; it cannot be a variable that already exists outside the loop.)  
When this loop is executed, each value from the array is assigned
to <code>item</code> in turn and the body of the loop is executed for each
value.  Thus, the above loop is exactly equivalent to:</np>
   
<pre>for ( int index = 0; index &lt; itemArray.length; index++ ) {
   BaseType item;
   item = itemArray[index];  // Get one of the values from the array
     .
     .  // process the item
     .  
}</pre>
   
<p>For example, if <code>A</code> is an array of type <atype>int[]</atype>, then
we could print all the values from <code>A</code> with the for-each loop:</p>
   
<pre>for ( int item : A )
   System.out.println( item );</pre>

<np>and we could add up all the positive integers in <code>A</code> with:</np>
   
<pre>int sum = 0;   // This will be the sum of all the positive numbers in A.
for ( int item : A ) {
   if (item &gt; 0)
      sum = sum + item;
}</pre>
   
<p>The for-each loop is not always appropriate.  For example, there is no
simple way to use it to process the items in just a part of an array, or to
process the elements in reverse order.
However, it does make the code a little simpler when you do want to process all the values, in order.
since it eliminates any need to use array indices.</p>   
   
<p>It's important to note that a for-each loop processes the <b>values</b> in
the array, not the <b>elements</b> (where an element means the actual memory
location that is part of the array).  For example, consider the following
incorrect attempt to fill an array of integers with 17's:</p>
   
<pre>int[] intList = new int[10];
for ( int item : intList ) {   <newcode>// INCORRECT! DOES NOT MODIFY THE ARRAY!</newcode>
   item = 17;
}</pre>
   
<np>The assignment statement <code>item = 17</code> assigns the value 17 to
the loop control variable, <code>item</code>.  However, this has nothing to
do with the array.  When the body of the loop is executed, the
value from one of the elements of the array is copied into <code>item</code>.
The statement <code>item&nbsp;=&nbsp;17</code> replaces that copied value
but has no effect on the array element from which it was copied; the
value in the array is not changed.  The loop is equivalent to</np>
  
<pre>int[] intList = new int[10];
for ( int i = 0; i &lt; intList.length; i++ ) {
   int item = intList[i];
   item = 17;
}</pre>
   
<np>which certainly does not change the value of any element in the array.</np>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="arrays.1.2" title="Variable Arity Methods">

<p>Before Java 5, every method in Java had a fixed arity.
(The <newword>arity</newword> of a method is defined as the number
of parameters in a call to the method.)  In a fixed arity method, the number
of parameters must be the same in every call to the method and must be the same
as the number of formal parameters in the method's definition.  Java&nbsp;5 introduced
<newword>variable arity methods</newword>.  In a variable arity method, different
calls to the method can have different numbers of parameters.  For example,
the formatted output method <code>System.out.printf</code>, which was introduced
in <localref href="basics.4.1"/>, is a variable arity method.  The first
parameter of <code>System.out.printf</code> must be a <classname>String</classname>,
but it can have any number of additional parameters, of any types.</p>

<p>Calling a variable arity method is no different from calling any other
sort of method, but writing one requires some new syntax.  As an example,
consider a method that can compute the average of any number of values of
type <ptype>double</ptype>.  The definition of such a method could begin
with:</p>
   
<pre>public static double average( double...  numbers ) {</pre>
   
<np>Here, the <code>...</code> after the type name, <code>double</code>, 
is what makes this a variable arity method.  It indicates
that any number of values of type <ptype>double</ptype> can be provided when
the subroutine is called, so that for example <code>average(1,4,9,16)</code>, 
<code>average(3.14,2.17)</code>, <code>average(0.375)</code>, and even
<code>average()</code> are all legal calls to this method.  Note that 
actual parameters of type <ptype>int</ptype> can be passed to <code>average</code>.
The integers will, as usual, be automatically converted to real numbers.</np>

<p>When the method is called, the values of all the actual parameters
that correspond to the variable arity parameter are placed into an array,
and it is this array that is actually passed to the method.  That is,
in the body of a method, a variable arity parameter of type
<classname>T</classname> actually looks like an ordinary parameter of type
<atype>T[]</atype>.  The length of the array tells you how many actual parameters
were provided in the method call.  In the <code>average</code> example, the body
of the method would see an array named <code>numbers</code> of type <atype>double[]</atype>.
The number of actual parameters in the method call would be <code>numbers.length</code>,
and the values of the actual parameters would be <code>numbers[0]</code>,
<code>numbers[1]</code>, and so on.  A complete definition of the method would be:
</p>
   
<pre>public static double average( double... numbers ) {
        // Inside this method, numbers is of type double[].
   double sum;      // The sum of all the actual parameters.
   double average;  // The average of all the actual parameters.
   sum = 0;
   for (int i = 0; i &lt; numbers.length; i++) {
      sum = sum + numbers[i];  // Add one of the actual parameters to the sum.
   }
   average = sum / numbers.length;
   return average;
}</pre>


<p>By the way, it is possible to pass a single array
to a variable arity method, instead of a list of individual values.  For example, suppose that
<code>salesData</code> is a variable of type <atype>double[]</atype>. Then
it would be legal to call <code>average(salesData)</code>, and this would compute
the average of all the numbers in the array.</p>

<p>The formal parameter list in the definition of a variable-arity method can 
include more than one parameter, but the <code>...</code> can only be applied to the
very last formal parameter.</p>
   
<p>As an example, consider a method that can draw a polygon through
any number of points.  The points are given as values of type <classname>Point</classname>,
where an object of type <classname>Point</classname> has two instance variables,
<code>x</code> and <code>y</code>, of type <ptype>double</ptype>.
In this case, the method has one ordinary parameter&mdash;the
graphics context that will be used to draw the polygon&mdash;in addition to the
variable arity parameter.  Remember that inside the definition of the
method, the parameter <code>points</code> becomes an array of 
<classname>Points</classname>:</p>
   
<pre>public static void drawPolygon(GraphicsContext g, Point... points) {
    if (points.length &gt; 1) {  // (Need at least 2 points to draw anything.)
       for (int i = 0; i &lt; points.length - 1; i++) {
           // Draw a line from i-th point to (i+1)-th point
           g.strokeLine( points[i].x, points[i].y, points[i+1].x, points[i+1].y );
       }
       // Now, draw a line back to the starting point.
       g.strokeLine( points[points.length-1].x, points[points.length-1].y,
                       points[0].x, points[0].y );
    }
}</pre>

<np>When this method is called, the subroutine call statement must have one actual parameter
of type <classname>GraphicsContext</classname>, which can be followed by any number of
actual parameters of type <classname>Point</classname>.</np>
   
<p>For a final example, let's look at a method that strings together all of the
values in a list of strings into a single, long string.  This example uses a for-each
loop to process the array:</p>

<pre>public static String concat( String... values ) {
   StringBuilder buffer;  // Use a StringBuilder for more efficient concatenation.
   buffer = new StringBuilder();  // Start with an empty StringBuilder.
   for ( String str : values ) { // A "for each" loop for processing the values.
       buffer.append(str); // Add string to the buffer.
   }
   return buffer.toString(); // return the contents of the buffer
}</pre>

<np>Given this method definition, the method call <code>concat("Hello", "World")</code>
would return the string "HelloWorld", and <code>concat()</code> would
return an empty string. Since a variable arity method can also accept an
array as actual parameter, we could also call <code>concat(lines)</code>
where <code>lines</code> is of type <atype>String[]</atype>.  This would 
concatenate all the elements of the array into a single string.</np>

</subsection>
   
<subsection  id="arrays.1.3" title="Array Literals">
  
<p>We have seen that it is possible to initialize an array variable 
with a list of values at the time it is declared.
For example,</p>

<pre>int[] squares = { 1, 4, 9, 16, 25, 36, 49 };</pre>

<np>This initializes <code>squares</code> to refer to a newly created array
that contains the seven values in the list.</np>


<p>A list initializer of this form can be used <b>only</b> in a declaration
statement, where it gives an initial value to a newly declared array variable. It
cannot be used in an assignment statement to assign a value to a variable that
already existed. However, there is another, similar notation for
creating a new array that can be used in other places. The notation uses 
another form of the <code>new</code>
operator to both create a new array object and fill it with values.
(The rather odd syntax
is similar to the syntax for anonymous inner classes, which were discussed in
<localref href="OOP.8.3"/>.) As an example, to assign a new value to
an array variable, <code>cubes</code>, of type <atype>int[]</atype>, you could
use:</p>

<pre>cubes = new int[] { 1, 8, 27, 64, 125, 216, 343 };</pre>

<np>This is an assignment statement rather than a declaration, so the
array initializer syntax, without "<code>new int[]</code>," would not
be legal here.  The general syntax for this form of the 
<code>new</code> operator is</np>

<pre>new <bnf>base-type</bnf> [ ] { <bnf>list-of-values</bnf> }</pre>

<np>This is actually an expression whose value is a reference to a newly created
array object.  In this sense, it is an "array literal," since it is something that you can type
in a program to represent a value. This means that it can be used in any
context where an object of type <bnf>base-type</bnf><code>[]</code> is legal.
For example, you could pass the newly created array as an actual parameter to
a subroutine.  Consider the following utility method for creating a menu
from an array of strings.  (Menus were discussed in <localref href="GUI1.6.2"/>.)</np>

<pre>/**
 * Creates a Menu.  The names for the MenuItems in the menu are
 *     given as an array of Strings.
 * @param menuName  the name for the Menu that is to be created.
 * @param itemNames  an array holding the text that appears in each
 *     MenuItem.  If a null value appears in the array, the corresponding
 *     item in the menu will be a separator rather than a MenuItem.
 * @return  the menu that has been created and filled with items.
 */
public static Menu createMenu( String menuName, String[] itemNames ) {
    Menu menu = new Menu(menuName);
    for ( String itemName : itemNames ) {
        if ( itemName == null ) {
            menu.getItems().add( new SeparatorMenuItem() );
        }
        else {
            MenuItem item = new MenuItem(itemName);
            menu.getItems().add(item);
        }
    }
    return menu;
}
</pre>

<np>The second parameter in a call to <code>createMenu</code> is an array of 
strings.  The array that is passed as an actual parameter could be created
in place, using the <code>new</code> operator.  For example, 
we can use the following statement to create an entire File menu:</np>

<pre>Menu fileMenu = createMenu( "File", 
              <newcode>new String[] { "New", "Open", "Close", null, "Quit" }</newcode> );</pre>
   
<np>This should convince you that
being able to create and use an array "in place" in this way can be very convenient,
in the same way that anonymous inner classes are convenient.  (However, this
example could have been done even more conveniently if <code>createMenu()</code>
had been written as a variable arity method!)</np>
   
<p>By the way, it is perfectly legal to use the "<code>new BaseType[] {&nbsp;&dots;&nbsp;}</code>" syntax
instead of the array initializer syntax in the declaration of an array variable.  For example,
instead of saying:</p>
   
<pre>int[] primes = { 2, 3, 5, 7, 11, 13, 17, 19 };</pre>
   
<np>you can say, equivalently,</np>
   
<pre>int[] primes = new int[] { 2, 3, 5, 7, 11, 17, 19 };</pre>
   
<np>In fact, rather than use a special notation that works only in the context
of declaration statements, I sometimes prefer to use the second form.</np>

<break/>

<p>One final note: For historical reasons, an array declaration such as</p>

<pre>int[] list;</pre>

<np>can also be written as</np>
   
<pre>int list[];</pre>

<np>which is a syntax used in the languages C and C++. However, this alternative
syntax does not really make much sense in the context of Java, and it is
probably best avoided. After all, the intent is to declare a variable of a
certain type, and the name of that type is "<atype>int[]</atype>". It makes sense to
follow the "<bnf>type-name</bnf>  <bnf>variable-name</bnf>;" syntax for such declarations.</np>
  
</subsection>


<subsection id="arrays.1.4" title="Introducing Records">

<p>An array is a simple data structure in which members are numbered and all
members have the same type.  A <newword>record</newword> is another kind
of simple data structure in which members can have different types and
are referred to by name instead of by number.  In Java, classes can
be used to represent records, but the term "record" has not traditionally
been used.  However, there are plans to introduce records into Java explicitly,
and they are available in Java&nbsp;15 as a preview feature.  A record
in Java is a kind of object, and a record type is a special kind of class that is
defined similarly to an ordinary class.  For example:
</p>

<pre>record FullName(String firstName, String lastName) { }</pre>

<np>This defines a class named <classname>FullName</classname> that
can be used in the same way as other classes, such as to declare
variables.  The <classname>FullName</classname> class has instance
variables named <code>firstName</code> and <code>lastName</code>.
The "{&nbsp;}" at the end of the definition is an
empty class body.  The class body for a record type can contain
static members, and it can define instance methods.  However, it
cannot add additional instance variables.  The class is automatically
<code>final</code>, which means that it cannot be extended by
subclasses.  If the record definition is nested inside another
class, then the record class is automatically static.  These restrictions
make sense, because a record is supposed to be a simple container
for a fixed set of named fields.</np>

<p>A record type automatically includes a constructor, with one
parameter corresponding to each instance variable.  This constructor
simply initializes the instance variables.  For example, an
object of type <classname>FullName</classname> can be created with</p>

<pre>FullName fn = new FullName("Jane", "Doe");</pre>

<np>Accessor, or "getter", methods for the instance variables are also automatically
defined, but instead of using the typical <code>getXXX()</code> naming convention
for getter methods, their names are the same as the names of the instance
variables.  For example, for the <classname>FullName</classname> variable
defined above, the instance variables would be accessed as <code>fn.firstName()</code>
and <code>fn.lastName()</code>.  A record type also provides reasonable default
definitions for several methods inherited from class <classname>Object</classname>:
<code>toString()</code>, <code>equals()</code>, and <code>hashCode()</code>.</np>

<p>Because records are a preview feature in Java 15, certain command-line options
must be added to the <code>javac</code> and <code>java</code> commands when
compiling and running a program that uses records with a Java&nbsp;15 JDK.
For example,</p>

<pre>javac --enable-preview --release=15 RecordDemo.java
java --enable-preview RecordDemo</pre>

</subsection>

</section>