<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="arrays.5" title="Two-dimensional Arrays">
   

<p><start><big>T</big>wo-dimensional arrays</start> were introduced in <localref href="control.7a.5"/>,
but we haven't done much with them since then.  A 2D array has a type such as
<atype>int[][]</atype> or <atype>String[][]</atype>, with two pairs of square brackets. The
elements of a 2D array are arranged in rows and columns, and the <code>new</code> operator
for 2D arrays specifies both the number of rows and the number of columns.  For example,</p>

<pre>int[][] A;
A = new int[3][4];</pre>

<np>This creates a 2D array of <ptype>int</ptype> that has 12 elements arranged in 3 rows
and 4 columns.  Although I haven't mentioned it, there are initializers for 2D arrays.
For example, this statement creates the 3-by-4 array that is shown in the picture below:</np>

<pre>int[][]  A  =  {  {  1,  0, 12, -1 },
                  {  7, -3,  2,  5 },
                  { -5, -2,  2, -9 }
               };</pre>

<np>An array initializer for a 2D array contains the rows of A, separated by commas
and enclosed between braces.  Each row, in turn, is a list of values separated by commas
and enclosed between braces.  There are also 2D array literals with a similar syntax
that can be used anywhere, not just in declarations.  For example,</np>

<pre>A  =  new int[][] {  {  1,  0, 12, -1 },
                     {  7, -3,  2,  5 },
                     { -5, -2,  2, -9 }
                  };</pre>

<np>All of this extends naturally to three-dimensional, four-dimensional, and even higher-dimensional
arrays, but they are not used very often in practice.</np>


<subsection id="arrays.5.1" title="The Truth About 2D Arrays">

<p>But before we go any farther, there is a little surprise.  Java does not actually have
two-dimensional arrays.  In a true 2D array, all the elements of the array occupy a
continuous block of memory, but that's not true in Java.  The syntax for array
types is a clue:  For any type <classname>BaseType</classname>, we should be able 
to form the type <atype>BaseType[]</atype>, meaning "array of <classname>BaseType</classname>."
If we use <atype>int[]</atype> as the base type, the type that we get is 
"<atype>int[][]</atype> meaning "array of <atype>int[]</atype>" or "array of array
of <ptype>int</ptype>."  And in fact, that's what happens. The elements in a 
2D array of type <atype>int[][]</atype> are variables of type <atype>int[]</atype>.
And remember that a variable of type <atype>int[]</atype> can only hold a pointer
to an array of <ptype>int</ptype>.  So, a 2D array is really an array of pointers,
where each pointer can refer to a one-dimensional array.  Those one-dimensional
arrays are the rows of the 2D array.  A picture will help to explain this.
Consider the 3-by-4 array <code>A</code> defined above.
</p>

<img src="two-dimensional-array.png" width="437" height="360" 
   tex="two-dimensional-array.eps" texscale="0.75" bordered="true"
   alt="(Illustration of 3-by-4 array as a grid and as an array of arrays)"/>


<p>For the most part, you can ignore the reality and keep the picture of a grid
in mind. Sometimes, though, you will need to remember that each row in the grid
is really an array in itself. These arrays can be referred to as <code>A[0]</code>,
<code>A[1]</code>, and <code>A[2]</code>. Each row is in fact a value of type
<atype>int[]</atype>. It could, for example, be passed to a subroutine that asks for
a parameter of type <atype>int[]</atype>.</p>

<p>Some of the consequences of this structure are a little subtle.  For example,
thinking of a 2D array, <code>A</code>, as an array of arrays, we see that
<code>A.length</code> makes sense and is equal to the number of rows of <code>A</code>.
If <code>A</code> has the usual shape for a 2D array, then the number of columns in
<code>A</code> would be the same as the number of elements in the first row, that
is, <code>A[0].length</code>.  But there is no rule that says that all of the rows
of <code>A</code> must have the same length (although an array created with
<code>new&nbsp;BaseType[rows][columns]</code> will always have that form).
Each row in a 2D array is a separate one-dimensional
array, and each of those arrays can have a different length.  In fact, it's even possible
for a row to be <code>null</code>.  For example, the statement</p>

<pre>A = new int[3][];</pre>

<np>with no number in the second set of brackets, creates an array of 3 elements where
all the elements are <code>null</code>.  There are places for three rows, but no actual rows
have been created.  You can then create the rows <code>A[0]</code>, <code>A[1]</code>, and
<code>A[2]</code> individually.</np>

<p>As an example, consider a <newword>symmetric matrix</newword>.  A symmetric matrix, <code>M</code>, is
a two-dimensional array in which the number of rows is equal to the number of columns
and satisfying <code>M[i][j]</code> equals <code>M[j][i]</code> for all <code>i</code> and 
<code>j</code>.  Because of this equality, we only really need to store
<code>M[i][j]</code> for <code>i&nbsp;&gt;=&nbsp;j</code>.  We can store the data
in a "triangular matrix":</p>

<img src="symmetric-matrix.png" width="560" height="156" alt="symmetric matrix as triangular matrix"
    tex="symmetric-matrix.eps" texscale="0.75" bordered="true"/>

<np>It's easy enough to make a triangular array, if we create each row separately.  To create
a 7-by-7 triangular array of <ptype>double</ptype>, we can use the code segment</np>

<pre>double[][] matrix = new double[7][]; // rows have not yet been created!
for (int i = 0; i &lt; 7; i++) {
    matrix[i] = new double[i+1];  // Create row i with i + 1 elements.
}</pre>

<np>We just have to remember that if we want to know the value of the matrix at <code>(i,j)</code>,
and if <code>i&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;j</code>, then we actually have to get the value of <code>matrix[j][i]</code>
in the triangular matrix.  And similarly for setting values.  It's easy to write a class to
represent symmetric matrices:</np>

<pre>
/**
 * Represents symmetric n-by-n matrices of real numbers.
 */
public class SymmetricMatrix {
    
    private double[][] matrix;  // A triangular matrix to hold the data.
    
    /**
     * Creates an n-by-n symmetric matrix in which all entries are 0.
     */
    public SymmetricMatrix(int n) {
        matrix = new double[n][];
        for (int i = 0; i &lt; n; i++)
            matrix[i] = new double[i+1];
    }
    
    /**
     * Returns the matrix entry at position (row,col).  (If row &lt; col,
     * the value is actually stored at position (col,row).)
     */
    public double get( int row, int col ) {
        if (row &gt;= col)
            return matrix[row][col];
        else
            return matrix[col][row];
    }
    
    /**
     * Sets the value of the matrix entry at (row,col).  (If row &lt; col,
     * the value is actually stored at position (col,row).)
     */
    public void set( int row, int col, double value ) {
        if (row &gt;= col)
            matrix[row][col] = value;
        else
            matrix[col][row] = value;
    }
    
    /**
     * Returns the number of rows and columns in the matrix.
     */
    public int size() {
        return matrix.length;  // The size is the number of rows.
    }

} // end class SymmetricMatrix</pre>

<np>This class is in the file <sourceref href="SymmetricMatrix.java"/>,
and a small program to test it can be found in <sourceref href="TestSymmetricMatrix.java"/>.</np>

<p>By the way, the standard function <code>Arrays.copyOf()</code> can't make a full copy
of a 2D array in a single step.  To do that, you need to copy each row separately.  To make
a copy of a two-dimensional array of <ptype>int</ptype>, for example:</p>

<pre>
int[][] B = new int[A.length][];  // B has as many rows as A.
for (int i = 0; i &lt; A.length; i++) {
    B[i] = Arrays.copyOf(A[i], A[i].length)); // Copy row i.
}</pre>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="arrays.5.2" title="Conway's Game Of Life">

<p>As an example of more typical 2D array processing, let's look at a very well-known example:
John Conway's Game of Life, invented by mathematician John Horton Conway in 1970.
This Game of Life is not really a game (although sometimes it's
referred to as a "zero-person game" that plays itself).  It's a "two-dimensional cellular
automaton."  This just means that it's a grid of cells whose content changes over time
according to definite, deterministic rules.  In Life, a cell can only have two possible
contents: It can be "alive" or "dead."  We will use
a 2D array to represent the grid, with each element of the array representing the content
of one cell in the grid.  In the game, an initial grid is set up in which each cell is 
marked as either alive or dead.  After that, the game "plays itself."  The grid
evolves through a series of time steps.  The contents of the grid at each time step
are completely determined by the contents at the previous time step, according to 
simple rules:  Each cell in the grid looks at its eight neighbors (horizontal, vertical,
and diagonal) and counts how many of its neighbors are alive.  Then the state of the
cell in the next step is determined by the rules:</p>

<ul>
<li>If the cell is alive in the current time step:  If the cell has 2 or 3 living neighbors,
then the cell remains alive in the next time step; otherwise, it dies. (A living cell dies of
loneliness if it has 0 or 1 living neighbor, and of overcrowding if it has more than 3 living neighbors.)</li>
<li>If the cell is dead in the current time step:  If the cell has 3 living neighbors,
then the cell becomes alive in the next time step; otherwise, it remains dead.  (Three living cells
give birth to a new living cell.)</li>
</ul>

<np>Here's a picture of part of a Life board, showing the same board before and after the
rules have been applied. The rules are applied to every cell in the grid.  The picture shows
how they apply to four of the cells:</np>

<img src="life-rules.png" width="537" height="229" alt="two generations in the game, showing how rules are applied"
     tex="life-rules.eps" texscale="0.6" bordered="true"/>

<p>The Game of Life is interesting because it gives rise to many interesting and surprising
patterns.  (Look it up on Wikipedia.)  Here, we are just interested in writing a program to
simulate the game.  The complete program can be found in the file <sourceref href="Life.java"/>.
In the program, the life grid is shown as a grid of squares in which dead squares are black and
living squares are white.  (The program uses <sourceref href="MosaicCanvas.java"/> from
<localref href="subroutines.6"/> to represent the grid, so you will also need that file to compile
and run the program.)  In the program, you can fill the life board randomly with dead 
and alive cells, or you can use the mouse to set up the game board.  There is a "Step" button
that will compute one time-step of the game, and a "Start" button that will run time steps
as an animation.</p>

<p>We'll look at some of the array processing involved in implementing the Game of Life for this program.
Since a cell can only be alive or dead, it is natural to use a two-dimensional array
of <atype>boolean[][]</atype> to represent the states of all the cells.  The array is named
<code>alive</code>, and <code>alive[r][c]</code> is true when the cell in row <code>r</code>,
column <code>c</code> is alive.  The number of rows and the number of 
columns are equal and are given
by a constant, <code>GRID_SIZE</code>.  So, for example, to fill the Life grid with random
values, the program uses simple nested <code>for</code> loops:</p>

<pre>for (int r = 0; r &lt; GRID_SIZE; r++) {
    for (int c = 0; c &lt; GRID_SIZE; c++) {
           // Use a 25% probability that the cell is alive.
        alive[r][c] = (Math.random() &lt; 0.25);
    }
}</pre>

<np>Note that the expression <code>(Math.random() &lt; 0.25)</code> is a true/false
value that can be assigned to a <ptype>boolean</ptype> array element.  The array is also
used to set the color of the cells on the screen.  Since the grid of cells is displayed on screen as a
<classname>MosaicCanvas</classname>, setting the colors is done using the MosaicCanvas API.
Note that the actual drawing is done in the <classname>MosaicCanvas</classname> class
(which has its own 2D array of type <atype>Color[][]</atype> to keep
track of the colors of each cell).  The Life program just has to set the colors in the mosaic,
using the MosaicCanvas API.
This is done in the program in a method named <code>showBoard()</code> that is
called each time the board changes.  Again, simple nested <code>for</code>
loops are used to set the color of each square in the grid:</np>

<pre>for (int r = 0; r &lt; GRID_SIZE; r++) {
    for (int c = 0; c &lt; GRID_SIZE; c++) {
        if (alive[r][c])
            display.setColor(r,c,Color.WHITE);
        else
            display.setColor(r,c,null);  // Shows the background color, black.
    }
}</pre>

<p>Of course, the most interesting part of the program is computing the new state
of the board by applying the rules to the current state.  The rules apply to 
each individual cell, so again we can use nested for loops to work through all
the cells on the board, but this time the processing is more complicated.  Note first
that we can't make changes to the values in the array as we work through it,
since we will need to know the old state of a cell when  processing its neighboring cells.
In fact, the program uses a second array to hold the new board as it is being created.
When the new board is finished, it can be substituted for the old board.  The algorithm
goes like this in pseudocode:</p>

<pre>let newboard be a new boolean[][] array
for each row r:
    for each column c:
        Let N be the number of neighbors of cell (r,c) in the alive array
        if ((N is 3) or (N is 2 and alive[r][c]))
            newboard[r][c] = true;
        else
            newboard[r][c] = false;
alive = newboard</pre>

<np>Note that at the end of the process, <code>alive</code> is pointing to a
new array.  This doesn't matter as long as the contents of the array represent the
new state of the game.  The old array will be garbage collected.  The test for
whether <code>newboard[r][c]</code> should be <code>true</code> or <code>false</code>
might not be obvious, but it implements the rules correctly.  We still need to
work on counting the neighbors.  Consider the cell in row <code>r</code> and
column <code>c</code>.  If it's not at an edge of the board, then it's clear where
its neighbors are:</np>

<img src="life-neighbors.png" width="279" height="180" alt="rows and columns neighboring a given cell"
      tex="life-neighbors.eps" texscale="0.6" bordered="true"/>

<np>The row above row number <code>r</code> is row number <code>r-1</code>, and the row
below is <code>r+1</code>.  Similarly for the columns.  We just have to look at the
values of <code>alive[r-1][c-1]</code>, <code>alive[r-1][c]</code>, <code>alive[r-1][c+1]</code>, 
<code>alive[r][c-1]</code>, <code>alive[r][c+1]</code>, <code>alive[r+1][c-1]</code>, 
<code>alive[r+1][c]</code>, and <code>alive[r+1][c+1]</code>, and count the number that
are <code>true</code>.  (You should make sure that you understand how the array indexing works
here.)</np>

<p>But there is a problem when the cell is along one of the edges of the grid.  In that
case, some of the array elements in the list don't exist, and an attempt to use them
will cause an exception.  To avoid the exception, we have to give special consideration to
cells along the edges.  One idea is that before referencing any array element, check that
the array element actually exists.  In that case, the code for neighbor counting becomes</p>

<pre>if (r-1 &gt;= 0 &amp;&amp; c-1 &gt;= 0 &amp;&amp; alive[r-1][c-1])
    N++; // A cell at position (r-1,c-1) exists and is alive.
if (r-1 &gt;= 0 &amp;&amp; alive[r-1][c])
    N++; // A cell at position (r-1,c) exists and is alive.
if (r-1 &gt;= 0 &amp;&amp; c+1 &lt;= GRID_SIZE &amp;&amp; alive[r-1][c+1])
    N++; // A cell at position (r-1,c+1) exists and is alive.
// and so on...</pre>

<np>All the possible exceptions are avoided.  But in my program, I actually do something
that is common in 2D computer games&mdash;I pretend that the left edge of the board is
attached to the right edge and the top edge to the bottom edge.  For example, for a
cell in row&nbsp;0, we say that the row "above" is actually the bottom row, row
number <code>GRID_SIZE-1</code>.  I use variables to represent the positions above, below, left,
and right of a given cell.  The code turns out to be simpler than the code shown above.
Here is the complete method for computing the new board:</np>

<pre>private void doFrame() { // Compute the new state of the Life board.
    boolean[][] newboard = new boolean[GRID_SIZE][GRID_SIZE];
    for ( int r = 0; r &lt; GRID_SIZE; r++ ) {
        int above, below; // rows considered above and below row number r
        int left, right;  // columns considered left and right of column c
        above = r &gt; 0 ? r-1 : GRID_SIZE-1;  // (for "?:" see <localref href="basics.5.5"/>)
        below = r &lt; GRID_SIZE-1 ? r+1 : 0;
        for ( int c = 0; c &lt; GRID_SIZE; c++ ) {
            left =  c &gt; 0 ? c-1 : GRID_SIZE-1;
            right = c &lt; GRID_SIZE-1 ? c+1 : 0;
            int n = 0; // number of alive cells in the 8 neighboring cells
            if (alive[above][left])
                n++;
            if (alive[above][c])
                n++;
            if (alive[above][right])
                n++;
            if (alive[r][left])
                n++;
            if (alive[r][right])
                n++;
            if (alive[below][left])
                n++;
            if (alive[below][c])
                n++;
            if (alive[below][right])
                n++;
            if (n == 3 || (alive[r][c] &amp;&amp; n == 2))
                newboard[r][c] = true;
            else
                newboard[r][c] = false;
        }
    }
    alive = newboard;
}</pre>

<p>Again, I urge you to check out the source code, <sourceref href="Life.java"/>, and
try the program.  Don't forget that you will also need <sourceref href="MosaicCanvas.java"/>.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="arrays.5.3" title="Checkers">

<p>As a final example for this chapter, we'll look at a more substantial example of using a 2D array. 
This is the longest program that we have encountered so far, with 745 lines of
code.  The program lets two users play checkers against each other.
The checkers game is played on an eight-by-eight board, which is based on an
example from <localref href="GUI1.5.1"/>.  The players are called "red" and "black,"
after the color of their checkers.  I'm not going to explain the rules of checkers here;
possibly you can learn them by trying out the program.</p>

<p>In the program, a player
moves by clicking on the piece that they want to move, and then clicking on the empty square to
which it is to be moved. As an aid to the players,
any square that the current player can legally click at a given time
is highlighted with a brightly colored border. 
The square containing a piece that has been selected to be moved, if any, 
is surrounded by a yellow border. Other pieces that can legally be moved are surrounded by a
cyan-colored border. If a piece has already been selected to be moved, each empty square that it
can legally move to is highlighted with a green border. The game enforces the rule
that if the current player can jump one of the opponent's pieces, then the
player must jump. When a player's piece becomes a king, by reaching the
opposite end of the board, a big white "K" is drawn on the piece.
Here is a picture of the program early in a game.  It is black's turn
to move.  Black has selected the piece in the yellow-outlined square to be moved.
Black can click one of the squares outlined in green to complete the move, or
can click one of the squares outlined in cyan to select a different piece to be moved.</p>

<img src="checkers-game.png" width="400" height="336" alt="a game of checkers in progress"
      tex="checkers-game.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<p>I will only cover a part of the programming for this example. I encourage you
to read the complete source code, <sourceref href="Checkers.java"/>.  It's long and complex,
but with some study, you should understand all the techniques that it uses.  The program is
a good example of state-based, event-driven, object-oriented programming.</p>

<break/>

<p>The data about the pieces on the board are stored in a two-dimensional
array. Because of the complexity of the program, I wanted to divide it into
several classes. In addition to the main class, there are several nested classes.
One of these classes is <classname>CheckersData</classname>, which handles
the data for the board.  It is not directly responsible for any part of the graphics or
event-handling, but it provides methods that can be called by other
classes that handle graphics and events.  It is mainly this class that I want to talk about.</p>

<p>The <classname>CheckersData</classname> class has an instance variable named
<code>board</code> of type <code>int[][]</code>. 
The value of board is set to "<code>new&nbsp;int[8][8]</code>", 
an 8-by-8 grid of integers. The values stored in the grid are
defined as constants representing the possible contents of a square on a
checkerboard:</p>

<pre>static final int
          EMPTY = 0,           // Value representing an empty square.
          RED = 1,             // A regular red piece.
          RED_KING = 2,        // A red king.
          BLACK = 3,           // A regular black piece.
          BLACK_KING = 4;      // A black king.</pre>

<np>The constants <code>RED</code> and <code>BLACK</code> are also used in my program
(or, perhaps, misused) to represent the two players in the game. When a game is
started, the values in the array are set to represent the
initial state of the board. The grid of values looks like</np>

<img src="checkerboard-contents.png" width="526" height="254" bordered="true"
   tex="checkerboard-contents.eps" texscale="0.6"
   alt="Illustration of initial setup of a checkerboard"/>

<p>A regular black piece can only move "down" the grid. That is, the row number of the
square it moves to must be greater than the row number of the square it comes
from. A regular red piece can only move up the grid. Kings of either color
can move in both directions.</p>

<p>One function of the <classname>CheckersData</classname> class is to take care of changes
to the data structures that need to be made when one of the users moves a checker.
An instance method named
<code>makeMove()</code> is provided to do this. When a player moves a piece from
one square to another, the values of two elements in the array are
changed. But that's not all. If the move is a jump, then the piece that was
jumped is removed from the board. (The method checks whether the move is a jump
by checking if the square to which the piece is moving is two rows away from
the square where it starts.) Furthermore, a <code>RED</code> piece that moves to
row 0 or a <code>BLACK</code> piece that moves to row 7 becomes a king. Putting all
that into a subroutine is
good programming: the rest of the program doesn't have to worry about any of
these details. It just calls this <code>makeMove()</code> method:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Make the move from (fromRow,fromCol) to (toRow,toCol).  It is
 * ASSUMED that this move is legal!  If the move is a jump, the
 * jumped piece is removed from the board.  If a piece moves
 * to the last row on the opponent's side of the board, the 
 * piece becomes a king.
 */
void makeMove(int fromRow, int fromCol, int toRow, int toCol) {

   board[toRow][toCol] = board[fromRow][fromCol]; // Move the piece.
   board[fromRow][fromCol] = EMPTY; // The square it moved from is now empty.

   if (fromRow - toRow == 2 || fromRow - toRow == -2) {
         // The move is a jump.  Remove the jumped piece from the board.
      int jumpRow = (fromRow + toRow) / 2; // Row of the jumped piece.
      int jumpCol = (fromCol + toCol) / 2; // Column of the jumped piece.
      board[jumpRow][jumpCol] = EMPTY;
   }

   if (toRow == 0 &amp;&amp; board[toRow][toCol] == RED)
      board[toRow][toCol] = RED_KING;  // Red piece becomes a king.
   if (toRow == 7 &amp;&amp; board[toRow][toCol] == BLACK)
      board[toRow][toCol] = BLACK_KING;  // Black piece becomes a king.

}  // end makeMove()</pre>

<p>An even more important function of the <classname>CheckersData</classname> class is to
find legal moves on the board. In my program, a move in a Checkers game is
represented by an object belonging to the following class:</p>

<pre>/**
 * A CheckersMove object represents a move in the game of
 * Checkers.  It holds the row and column of the piece that is 
 * to be moved and the row and column of the square to which 
 * it is to be moved.  (This class makes no guarantee that 
 * the move is legal.)
 */
private static class CheckersMove {
     
   int fromRow, fromCol;  // Position of piece to be moved.
   int toRow, toCol;      // Square it is to move to.
   
   CheckersMove(int r1, int c1, int r2, int c2) {
        // Constructor.  Set the values of the instance variables.
      fromRow = r1;
      fromCol = c1;
      toRow = r2;
      toCol = c2;
   }
   
   boolean isJump() {
        // Test whether this move is a jump.  It is assumed that
        // the move is legal.  In a jump, the piece moves two
        // rows.  (In a regular move, it only moves one row.)
      return (fromRow - toRow == 2 || fromRow - toRow == -2);
   }
   
}  // end class CheckersMove.</pre>

<p>The <classname>CheckersData</classname> class has an instance method which finds all the
legal moves that are currently available for a specified player. This method is
a function that returns an array of type <atype>CheckersMove[]</atype>. The array
contains all the legal moves, represented as <classname>CheckersMove</classname> objects. The
specification for this method reads</p>

<pre>/**
 * Return an array containing all the legal CheckersMoves
 * for the specified player on the current board.  If the player
 * has no legal moves, null is returned.  The value of player
 * should be one of the constants RED or BLACK; if not, null
 * is returned.  If the returned value is non-null, it consists
 * entirely of jump moves or entirely of regular moves, since
 * if the player can jump, only jumps are legal moves.
 */
CheckersMove[] getLegalMoves(int player)</pre>

<np>A brief pseudocode algorithm for the method is</np>

<pre>Start with an empty list of moves
Find any legal jumps and add them to the list
if there are no jumps:
   Find any other legal moves and add them to the list
if the list is empty:
   return null
else:
   return the list</pre>

<np>Now, what is this "list"? We have to return the legal moves in an array. But
since an array has a fixed size, we can't create the array until we know how
many moves there are, and we don't know that until near the end of the method,
after we've already made the list! A neat solution is to use an
<classname>ArrayList</classname> instead of an array to hold the moves as we find them. 
In fact, I use an object defined by the parameterized type
<atype>ArrayList&lt;CheckersMove&gt;</atype> so that the list is
restricted to holding objects of type <classname>CheckersMove</classname>.  As we
add moves to the list, it will grow just as large as necessary. At the end of
the method, we can create the array that we really want and copy the data into
it:</np>

<pre>Let "moves" be an empty ArrayList&lt;CheckersMove&gt;
Find any legal jumps and add them to moves
if moves.size() is 0:  // There are no legal jumps!
   Find any other legal moves and add them to moves
if moves.size() is 0:  // There are no legal moves at all!
   return null
else:
   Let moveArray be an array of CheckersMoves of length moves.size()
   Copy the contents of moves into moveArray
   return moveArray</pre>

<p>Now, how do we find the legal jumps or the legal moves? The information we
need is in the <code>board</code> array, but it takes some work to extract it. We
have to look through all the positions in the array and find the pieces that
belong to the current player. For each piece, we have to check each square that
it could conceivably move to, and check whether that would be a legal move.
If we are looking for legal jumps, we want to look at squares that
are two rows and two columns away from the piece. There are four squares to consider.
Thus, the line in the
algorithm that says "Find any legal jumps and add them to moves" expands
to:</p>

<pre>For each row of the board:
   For each column of the board:
      if one of the player's pieces is at this location:
         if it is legal to jump to row + 2, column + 2
             add this move to moves
         if it is legal to jump to row - 2, column + 2
             add this move to moves
         if it is legal to jump to row + 2, column - 2
             add this move to moves
         if it is legal to jump to row - 2, column - 2
             add this move to moves</pre>

<p>The line that says "Find any other legal moves and add them to moves"
expands to something similar, except that we have to look at the four squares
that are one column and one row away from the piece. Testing whether a player
can legally move from one given square to another given square is itself
non-trivial. The square the player is moving to must actually be on the board,
and it must be empty. Furthermore, regular red and black pieces can only move
in one direction. I wrote the following utility method to check whether a
player can make a given non-jump move:</p>

<pre>/**
 * This is called by the getLegalMoves() method to determine 
 * whether the player can legally move from (r1,c1) to (r2,c2).
 * It is ASSUMED that (r1,c1) contains one of the player's 
 * pieces and that (r2,c2) is a neighboring square.
 */
private boolean canMove(int player, int r1, int c1, int r2, int c2) {
      
   if (r2 &lt; 0 || r2 &gt;= 8 || c2 &lt; 0 || c2 &gt;= 8)
      return false;  // (r2,c2) is off the board.
      
   if (board[r2][c2] != EMPTY)
      return false;  // (r2,c2) already contains a piece.

   if (player == RED) {
      if (board[r1][c1] == RED &amp;&amp; r2 &gt; r1)
          return false;  // Regular red piece can only move down.
       return true;  // The move is legal.
   }
   else {
      if (board[r1][c1] == BLACK &amp;&amp; r2 &lt; r1)
          return false;  // Regular black piece can only move up.
       return true;  // The move is legal.
   }
   
}  // end canMove()</pre>

<p>This method is called by my <code>getLegalMoves()</code> method to check whether
one of the possible moves that it has found is actually legal. I have a similar
method that is called to check whether a jump is legal. In this case, I pass to
the method the square containing the player's piece, the square that the player
might move to, and the square between those two, which the player would be
jumping over. The square that is being jumped must contain one of the
opponent's pieces. This method has the specification:</p>

<pre>/**
 * This is called by other methods to check whether
 * the player can legally jump from (r1,c1) to (r3,c3).
 * It is assumed that the player has a piece at (r1,c1), that
 * (r3,c3) is a position that is 2 rows and 2 columns distant
 * from (r1,c1) and that (r2,c2) is the square between (r1,c1)
 * and (r3,c3).
 */
private boolean canJump(int player, int r1, int c1, 
                                   int r2, int c2, int r3, int c3) { . . .</pre>

<p>Given all this, you should be in a position to understand the complete
<code>getLegalMoves()</code> method. It's a nice way to finish off this chapter,
since it combines several topics that we've looked at: one-dimensional arrays,
<classname>ArrayLists</classname>, and two-dimensional arrays:</p>

<pre>CheckersMove[] getLegalMoves(int player) {

   if (player != RED &amp;&amp; player != BLACK)
      return null;  // (This will not happen in a correct program.)

   int playerKing;  // The constant for a King belonging to the player.
   if (player == RED)
      playerKing = RED_KING;
   else
      playerKing = BLACK_KING;

   ArrayList&lt;CheckersMove&gt; moves = new ArrayList&lt;CheckersMove&gt;();  
               // Moves will be stored in this list.
   
   /*  First, check for any possible jumps.  Look at each square on
       the board.  If that square contains one of the player's pieces, 
       look at a possible jump in each of the four directions from that 
       square.  If there is a legal jump in that direction, put it in 
       the moves ArrayList.
   */

   for (int row = 0; row &lt; 8; row++) {
      for (int col = 0; col &lt; 8; col++) {
        if (board[row][col] == player || board[row][col] == playerKing) {
            if (canJump(player, row, col, row+1, col+1, row+2, col+2))
               moves.add(new CheckersMove(row, col, row+2, col+2));
            if (canJump(player, row, col, row-1, col+1, row-2, col+2))
               moves.add(new CheckersMove(row, col, row-2, col+2));
            if (canJump(player, row, col, row+1, col-1, row+2, col-2))
               moves.add(new CheckersMove(row, col, row+2, col-2));
            if (canJump(player, row, col, row-1, col-1, row-2, col-2))
               moves.add(new CheckersMove(row, col, row-2, col-2));
        }
      }
   }
   
   /*  If any jump moves were found, then the user must jump, so we 
       don't add any regular moves.  However, if no jumps were found, 
       check for any legal regular moves.  Look at each square on 
       the board.  If that square contains one of the player's pieces,
       look at a possible move in each of the four directions from 
       that square.  If there is a legal move in that direction, 
       put it in the moves ArrayList.
   */
   
   if (moves.size() == 0) {
      for (int row = 0; row &lt; 8; row++) {
         for (int col = 0; col &lt; 8; col++) {
           if (board[row][col] == player || board[row][col] == playerKing) {
              if (canMove(player,row,col,row+1,col+1))
                 moves.add(new CheckersMove(row,col,row+1,col+1));
              if (canMove(player,row,col,row-1,col+1))
                 moves.add(new CheckersMove(row,col,row-1,col+1));
              if (canMove(player,row,col,row+1,col-1))
                 moves.add(new CheckersMove(row,col,row+1,col-1));
              if (canMove(player,row,col,row-1,col-1))
                 moves.add(new CheckersMove(row,col,row-1,col-1));
           }
         }
      }
   }
   
   /* If no legal moves have been found, return null.  Otherwise, create
      an array just big enough to hold all the legal moves, copy the
      legal moves from the ArrayList into the array, and return the array. 
   */
   
   if (moves.size() == 0)
      return null;
   else {
      CheckersMove[] moveArray = new CheckersMove[moves.size()];
      for (int i = 0; i &lt; moves.size(); i++)
         moveArray[i] = moves.get(i);
      return moveArray;
   }

}  // end getLegalMoves</pre>


<p>The checkers program is complex, and you can be sure that it didn't just fall together.
It took a good deal of design work to decide what classes and objects would be used,
what methods should be written, and what algorithms the methods should use.
The complete source code is in the file <sourceref href="Checkers.java"/>.
Take a look!</p>


</subsection>

<endchapter/>


</section>