<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE exercises SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<exercises>

<exercise id="OOP.ex.1">
<exercise-question><p>In all versions of the
<classname>PairOfDice</classname> class in <localref href="OOP.2"/>, the instance
variables <code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code> are declared to be <code>public</code>.
They really should be <code>private</code>, so that they would be protected from being changed
from outside the class. Write another version of the <classname>PairOfDice</classname> class
in which the instance variables <code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code> are
<code>private</code>. Your class will need "getter" methods that can be used to find out the
values of <code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code>. (The idea is to protect their values
from being changed from outside the class, but still to allow the values to be
read.) Include other improvements in the class, including at least a <code>toString()</code> method. 
Test your class with a short program that counts how many times a pair of dice is
rolled, before the total of the two dice is equal to two.</p>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss>
<p>The versions of the <classname>PairOfDice</classname> class in Section 2 differ in how the
dice are initialized. I like the idea of initializing the dice to random
values, so I will work with the following version:</p>

<pre>public class PairOfDice {

    public int die1;   // Number showing on the first die.
    public int die2;   // Number showing on the second die.
    
    /**
     * Constructor creates a pair of dice and rolls them so that
     * they initially show some random value.
     */            
    public PairOfDice() {
        roll();  // Call the roll() method to roll the dice.
    }
    
    /**
     * Roll the dice by setting each die to be a random number between 1 and 6.
     */
    public void roll() {
        die1 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1;
        die2 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1;
    }
    
} // end class PairOfDice</pre>

<p>After a <classname>PairOfDice</classname> object has just been created, the number on each
die is definitely between 1 and 6, just like the number on a real die. Can we
be sure that this will always be true? Not if the instance variables
<code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code> are <code>public</code>, since they can be changed
from outside the class. There is nothing to stop someone from changing them to
42 and -17 or anything else. It's not good enough to say that you're not
supposed to do that with dice. I want an absolute guarantee that my dice
objects can only have the values that real dice could have. By making
<code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code> <code>private</code>, I can have that guarantee,
because the code that I write in the <classname>PairOfDice</classname> class is the only code
that will ever directly affect the values of the variables.</p>

<p>So, we will make <code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code> private, and add instance
methods <code>getDie1()</code> and <code>getDie2()</code> to return the values of
<code>die1</code> and <code>die2</code>.  These are "getter" methods that get the
value of a member variable, and their names follow the convention that the name of
a getter method consists of "get" followed by a capitalized version of the variable name.
It would still be useful to be able to set the values of the dice, but we want to
make it impossible to set the value to anything outside the range 1 to 6.  The solution
is to provide "setter" methods that throw an exception when the value is illegal.
</p>

<p>I also added the <code>toString()</code> method from <localref href="OOP.3.2"/>.
As for other improvements, I can foresee that
people who use my class will often be interested in the total on the dice, so
they will tend to say things like "<code>dice.getDie1() + dice.getDie2()</code>" a
lot. If this is going to be done over and over, why not provide a method in the
class to do it? So, I added a method <code>getTotal()</code> that returns
the total value showing on the two dice. The complete, modified
<classname>PairOfDice</classname> class is shown below.</p>

<p>(Here is another improvement that I thought about. We could modify the
<code>roll()</code> method so that in addition to rolling the dice, it would also
return an <ptype>int</ptype> value giving the total on the dice. For example, this
would allow us to replace "<code>dice.roll(); val = dice.getTotal()</code>" with
"<code>val = dice.roll()</code>". Since it's legal to call a function with a
subroutine call statement, we could still say "<code>dice.roll()</code>" if we just
want to roll the dice without recording the total immediately. However, I
decided that it was a little clearer to leave this feature out.)</p>

<p>The main program is easy, especially since we've done the same problem
before without using objects (in <localref href="control.ex.1"/>).
Note how the pair of dice object is used. To test whether or not the
total on the dice is 2, I use the test "<code>while (dice.getTotal() != 2)</code>".
Because of the <code>toString()</code> method,
I just have to say say</p>

<pre>System.out.println("The dice come up " + dice );</pre>

<np>to show the numbers on the two dice.</np>

</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre>

<b><newcode>The Modified PairOfDice Class</newcode></b>

     <prog name="PairOfDice">/**
      * An object of class PairOfDice represents a pair of dice,
      * where each die shows a number between 1 and 6.  The dice
      * can be rolled, which randomizes the numbers showing on the
      * dice.
      */
     public class PairOfDice {
     
        private int die1;   // Number showing on the first die.
        private int die2;   // Number showing on the second die.

        /**
         * Constructor creates a pair of dice and rolls them so that
         * they initially show some random value.
         */
        public PairOfDice() {
            roll();  // Call the roll() method to roll the dice.
        }
        
        /**
         * Roll the dice by setting each die to be a random number between 1 and 6.
         */
        public void roll() {
            die1 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1;
            die2 = (int)(Math.random()*6) + 1;
        }
                
        /**
         * Return the number showing on the first die.
         */ 
        public int getDie1() {
           return die1;
        }
        
        /**
         * Set the value of the first die.  Throws an IllegalArgumentException
         * if the value is not in the range 1 to 6.
         */
        public void setDie1( int value ) {
           if ( value &lt; 1 || value &gt; 6 )
              throw new IllegalArgumentException("Illegal dice value " + value);
           die1 = value;
        }
        
        /**
         * Return the number showing on the second die.
         */ 
        public int getDie2() {
           return die2;
        }
        
        /**
         * Set the value of the second die.  Throws an IllegalArgumentException
         * if the value is not in the range 1 to 6.
         */
        public void setDie2( int value ) {
           if ( value &lt; 1 || value &gt; 6 )
              throw new IllegalArgumentException("Illegal dice value " + value);
           die2 = value;
        }
        
        /**
         * Return the total showing on the two dice.
         */ 
        public int getTotal() {
           return die1 + die2;
        }
        
        /**
         * Return a String representation of a pair of dice, where die1
         * and die2 are instance variables containing the numbers that are
         * showing on the two dice.
         */
        public String toString() {
           if (die1 == die2)
              return "double " + die1;
           else
              return die1 + " and " + die2;
        }
        
     }  // end class PairOfDice</prog>
     
     
     
<b><newcode>The Main Program</newcode></b>
      
     <prog name="RollFor2">/** 
      * Rolls a pair of dice until the dice come up snake eyes
      * (with a total value of 2).  Counts and reports the
      * number of rolls.
      */
     public class RollFor2 {
     
        public static void main(String[] args) {
           
           PairOfDice dice;  // A variable that will refer to the dice.
           int rollCount;    // Number of times the dice have been rolled.
     
           dice = new PairOfDice();  // Create the PairOfDice object.
           rollCount = 0;
           
           /* Roll the dice until they come up snake eyes. */
           
           do {
               dice.roll();
               System.out.println("The dice come up " + dice );
               rollCount++;
           } while (dice.getTotal() != 2);
           
           /* Report the number of rolls. */
           
           System.out.println("\nIt took " + rollCount + " rolls to get a 2.");
           
           /* Now, generate an exception. */
            
           System.out.println();
           System.out.println("This program will now crash with an error");
           System.out.println("when it tries to set the value of a die to 42.");
           System.out.println();
           
           dice.setDie1(42);
           System.out.println(dice);  // This statement will not be executed!
           
        }
        
     }  // end class RollFor2</prog>
</pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>





<exercise id="OOP.ex.2">
<exercise-question><p>A common programming task
is computing statistics of a set of numbers. (A statistic is a number that
summarizes some property of a set of data.) Common statistics include the mean
(also known as the average) and the standard deviation (which tells how spread
out the data are from the mean). I have written a little class called
<classname>StatCalc</classname> that can be used to compute these statistics, as well as the
sum of the items in the dataset and the number of items in the dataset. You can
read the source code for this class in the file <sourceref href="StatCalc.java"/>.
If <code>calc</code> is a variable of
type <classname>StatCalc</classname>, then the following instance methods are available:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>calc.enter(item)&nbsp;</code> where
<code>item</code> is a number, adds the item to the dataset.</li>

<li><code>calc.getCount()&nbsp;</code> is a function
that returns the number of items that have been added to the dataset.</li>

<li><code>calc.getSum()&nbsp;</code> is a function
that returns the sum of all the items that have been added to the dataset.</li>

<li><code>calc.getMean()&nbsp;</code> is a function
that returns the average of all the items.</li>

<li><code>calc.getStandardDeviation()&nbsp;</code> is
a function that returns the standard deviation of the items.</li>
</ul>

<p>Typically, all the data are added one after the other by calling the
<code>enter()</code> method over and over, as the data become available. After all
the data have been entered, any of the other methods can be called to get
statistical information about the data. The methods <code>getMean()</code> and
<code>getStandardDeviation()</code> should only be called if the number of items is
greater than zero.</p>

<p>Modify the current source code, <sourceref href="StatCalc.java"/>, to add instance
methods <code>getMax()</code> and <code>getMin()</code>. The <code>getMax()</code> method
should return the largest of all the items that have been added to the dataset,
and <code>getMin()</code> should return the smallest. You will need to add two new
instance variables to keep track of the largest and smallest items that have
been seen so far.</p>

<p>Test your new class by using it in a program to compute statistics for a set
of non-zero numbers entered by the user. Start by creating an object of type
<classname>StatCalc</classname>:</p>

<pre>StatCalc  calc;   // Object to be used to process the data.
calc = new StatCalc();</pre>

<p>Read numbers from the user and add them to the dataset. Use 0 as a sentinel
value (that is, stop reading numbers when the user enters 0). After all the
user's non-zero numbers have been entered, print out each of the six statistics
that are available from <code>calc</code>.</p>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss>
<p>For the <classname>StatCalc</classname> class to handle minimums and maximums, some of
what must be added to the class is obvious. We need two new instance
variables, <code>min</code> and <code>max</code>, and two getter methods to return the values
of those instance variables. So, we can add these lines to the class
definition:</p>

<pre>private double min;   // Smallest item that has been entered.
private double max;   // Largest item that has been entered.

public double getMin() {
   return min;
}

public double getMax() {
   return max;
}</pre>

<np>But then there is the problem of making sure that <code>min</code> and
<code>max</code> have the right values. <code>min</code> records the smallest number
seen so far.  Every time we have a new number to add to
the dataset there is a possibility that <code>min</code> will change, so
we have to compare <code>min</code> with the newly added number. If the new number is
smaller than the current <code>min</code>, then the number becomes the new value of
<code>min</code> (since the new number is now the smallest number we have seen so
far). We do something similar for <code>max</code>. This has to be done whenever a
number is entered into the dataset, so it has to be added to the
<code>enter()</code> method, giving:</np>

<pre>public void enter(double num) {
      // This is not completely correct!
   count++;
   sum += num;
   squareSum += num*num;
   <newcode>if (num &gt; max)          // We have a new maximum.
      max = num;
   if (num &lt; min)          // We have a new minimum.
      min = num;</newcode>
}</pre>

<p>Unfortunately, if this is all we do, there is a <b>bug in our
program</b>! For example, if the dataset consists of the numbers 21, 17,
and 4, the computer will insist that the minimum is 0, rather than 4. The
problem is that the variables <code>min</code> and <code>max</code> are initialized to
zero. (If no initial value is provided for a numerical instance variable, it
gets the default initial value, zero.) Since <code>min</code> is 0, none of the
numbers in the dataset pass the test "<code>if&nbsp;(num&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;min)</code>", and therefore the value
of <code>min</code> never changes. A similar problem holds for <code>max</code>, but it
will only show up if all the numbers in the dataset are less than zero. For the
other instance variables, <code>count</code>, <code>sum</code>, and <code>squareSum</code>,
the default initial value of zero is correct. For <code>min</code> and
<code>max</code>, we have to do something different.</p>

<p>One possible way to fix the problem is to treat the first number entered as
a special case. When only one number has been entered, it's certainly the
largest number so far and also the smallest number so far, so it should be
assigned to both <code>min</code> and <code>max</code>. This can be handled in the
<code>enter()</code> method:</p>

<pre>public void enter(double num) {
      // (This is NOT the version I used in my final answer.)
   count++;
   sum += num;
   squareSum += num*num;
   if (count == 1) {  // This is the first number.
      max = num;
      min = num;
   }
   else {
      if (num &gt; max)     // We have a new maximum.
         max = num;
      if (num &lt; min)     // We have a new minimum.
         min = num;
   }
}</pre>

<np>This works fine. However, I decided to use an alternative approach. We would
be OK if we could initialize <code>min</code> to have a value that is bigger than
any possible number. Then, when the first number is entered, it definitely will
satisfy the test "<code>if (num &lt; min)</code>", and therefore 
the first number will become the value of
<code>min</code>. But to be "bigger than any possible number," <code>min</code> would
have to be infinity. The initial value for <code>max</code> has to be smaller than
any possible number, so <code>max</code> has to be initialized to negative
infinity. And that's what we'll do!</np>

<p>Recall from <localref href="basics.5"/> 
that the standard class <classname>Double</classname> contains constants
<code>Double.POSITIVE_INFINITY</code> and <code>Double.NEGATIVE_INFINITY</code> that
represent positive and negative infinity.  We can
use these named constants to provide initial values for the instance variables
<code>min</code> and <code>max</code>. So, the declarations become:</p>

<pre>private double max = Double.NEGATIVE_INFINITY;  // Largest item seen.
private double min = Double.POSITIVE_INFINITY;  // Smallest item seen.</pre>

<np>With this change, the <classname>StatCalc</classname> class works correctly. The complete
class is shown below.  (By the way, you might think about what happens if <code>getMin()</code>
or <code>getMax()</code> is called before any data has been entered.  What actually happens?
What should happen?  What is the minimum or maximum of a set of numbers that contains no
numbers at all?)</np>

<p>The main program is fairly straightforward, so just for fun I decided to
use a <classname>Scanner</classname> instead of <classname>TextIO</classname>
to read the user's input (see <localref href="basics.4.6"/>.
The user's data are read and
entered into the <classname>StatCalc</classname> object in a loop:</p>

<pre>do {
   System.out.print("? ");
   item = in.nextDouble();  // (in is the Scanner.)
   if (item != 0)
      calc.enter(item);
} while ( item != 0 );</pre>

<np>The subroutine call "<code>calc.enter(item);</code>" enters the user's item.
That is, it does all the processing necessary to include this data item in the
statistics it is computing. After all the data have been entered, the
statistics can be obtained by using function calls such as
"<code>calc.getMean()</code>". The statistics are output in statements such as:</np>

<pre>System.out.println("   Average:            " + calc.getMean());</pre>

<p>Note that a function call represents a value, and so can be used anyplace
where a variable or literal value could be used. I don't have to assign the
value of the function to a variable. I can use the function call directly in
the output statement.  Another note: In this program, I decided not to use
formatted output, since it seems appropriate to print the answers with
as much accuracy as possible.  For formatted output, the statement
used to print the mean could be something like:</p>

<pre>System.out.printf("    Average:            %10.3f%n", calc.getMean());</pre>

<np>The complete main program is shown below.</np>

<break/>

<p>Although that completes the exercise, one might wonder: Instead of modifying
the source code of <classname>StatCalc</classname>, could we make a subclass of
<classname>StatCalc</classname> and put the modifications in that? The answer is yes. We will need
need to use the slightly obscure special variable <code>super</code> that was
discussed in <localref href="OOP.6.2"/>.</p>

<p>The new instance variables and instance methods can simply be put into the
subclass. The problem arises with the <code>enter()</code> method. We have to
redefine this method so that it will update the values of <code>min</code> and
<code>max</code>. But it also has to do all the processing that is done by the
original <code>enter()</code> method in the <classname>StatCalc</classname> class. This is what
<code>super</code> is for. It lets us call a method from the superclass of the
class we are writing. So, the subclass can be written:</p>

<pre>class StatCalcWithMinMax extends StatCalc {

   private double max = Double.NEGATIVE_INFINITY;  // Largest item seen.
   private double min = Double.POSITIVE_INFINITY;  // Smallest item seen.

   public void enter(double num) {
      super.enter(num);  // Call the enter method from the StatCalc class.
      if (num &gt; max)  // Then do the extra processing for min and max.
         max = num;
      if (num &lt; min)
         min = num;
   }
 
   public double getMin() {
      return min;
   }
   
   public double getMax() {
      return max;
   }

}  // end class StatCalcWithMinMax</pre>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><b>Revised StatCalc Class.  Changes from the original are shown in &newcodestyle;.</b>

     <prog name="StatCalc">/* 
      * An object of class StatCalc can be used to compute several simple statistics
      * for a set of numbers.  Numbers are entered into the dataset using
      * the enter(double) method.  Methods are provided to return the following
      * statistics for the set of numbers that have been entered: The number
      * of items, the sum of the items, the average, the standard deviation,
      * <newcode>the maximum, and the minimum.</newcode>
      */
     public class StatCalc {
     
        private int count;   // Number of numbers that have been entered.
        private double sum;  // The sum of all the items that have been entered.
        private double squareSum;  // The sum of the squares of all the items.
        <newcode>private double max = Double.NEGATIVE_INFINITY;  // Largest item seen.
        private double min = Double.POSITIVE_INFINITY;  // Smallest item seen.</newcode>
     
        /**
         * Add a number to the dataset.  The statistics will be computed for all
         * the numbers that have been added to the dataset using this method.
         */
        public void enter(double num) {
           count++;
           sum += num;
           squareSum += num*num;
           <newcode>if (num &gt; max)
              max = num;
           if (num &lt; min)
              min = num;</newcode>
        }
     
        /**
         * Return the number of items that have been entered into the dataset.
         */
        public int getCount() {
           return count;
        }
     
        /**
         * Return the sum of all the numbers that have been entered.
         */
        public double getSum() {
           return sum;
        }
     
        /**
         * Return the average of all the items that have been entered.
         * The return value is Double.NaN if no numbers have been entered.
         */
        public double getMean() {
           return sum / count;  
        }
     
        /**
         * Return the standard deviation of all the items that have been entered.
         * The return value is Double.NaN if no numbers have been entered.
         */
        public double getStandardDeviation() {  
           double mean = getMean();
           return Math.sqrt( squareSum/count - mean*mean );
        }
        
        <newcode>/**
         * Return the smallest item that has been entered.
         * The return value will be infinity if no numbers have been entered. 
         */
        public double getMin() {
           return min;
        }
        
        /**
         * Return the largest item that has been entered.
         * The return value will be -infinity if no numbers have been entered. 
         */
        public double getMax() {
           return max;
        }</newcode>
     
     }  // end class StatCalc</prog>



<b><newcode>Main Program</newcode></b>

     <prog name="SimpleStats">/**
      * Computes and display several statistics for a set of non-zero
      * numbers entered by the user.  (Input ends when user enters 0.)
      * This program uses StatCalc.java.
      */
     
     import java.util.Scanner;

     public class SimpleStats {
   
       public static void main(String[] args) {
   
          Scanner in = new Scanner(System.in);
   
          StatCalc calc; // Computes stats for numbers entered by user.
          calc = new StatCalc();
   
          double item; // One number entered by the user.
   
          System.out.println("Enter your numbers.  Enter 0 to end.");
          System.out.println();
   
          do {
             System.out.print("? ");
             item = in.nextDouble();
             if (item != 0)
                calc.enter(item);
          } while (item != 0);
   
          System.out.println("\nStatistics about your data:\n");
          System.out.println("   Count:              " + calc.getCount());
          System.out.println("   Sum:                " + calc.getSum());
          System.out.println("   Minimum:            " + calc.getMin());
          System.out.println("   Maximum:            " + calc.getMax());
          System.out.println("   Average:            " + calc.getMean());
          System.out.println("   Standard Deviation: "
                 + calc.getStandardDeviation());
   
       } // end main()
   
    } // end SimpleStats</prog>
</pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>





<exercise>
<exercise-question><p>This problem uses the
<classname>PairOfDice</classname> class from <localref href="OOP.ex.1"/>
and the <classname>StatCalc</classname> class from <localref href="OOP.ex.2"/>.</p>

<p>The program in <localref href="subroutines.ex.4"/> performs
the experiment of counting how many times a pair of dice is rolled before a
given total comes up. It repeats this experiment 10000 times and then reports
the average number of rolls. It does this whole process for each possible total
(2, 3, &dots;, 12).</p>

<p>Redo that exercise. But instead of just reporting the average number of
rolls, you should also report the standard deviation and the maximum number of
rolls. Use a <classname>PairOfDice</classname> object to represent the dice. Use a
<classname>StatCalc</classname> object to compute the statistics. (You'll need a new
<classname>StatCalc</classname> object for each possible total, 2, 3, &dots;, 12. You can use a
new pair of dice if you want, but it's not required.)</p>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss>
<p>The program from <localref href="subroutines.ex.4"/> defines
a function, <code>rollFor(N)</code>, that performs the basic experiment once. It
rolls the dice until the total on the dice is <code>N</code>, and it returns the
number of rolls. Using a <classname>PairOfDice</classname> object, <code>dice</code>, the body of
this subroutine becomes</p>

<pre>int rollCt = 0;  // Number of rolls made.
do {
   dice.roll();
   rollCt++;
} while ( dice.getTotal() != N );
return rollCt;</pre>

<p>This is significantly simpler than the original version. But where does the
dice object come from? One possibility is to create a new <classname>PairOfDice</classname>
object at the beginning of the function. This will work, but then a new object
is created each time the function is called. In the program we are writing, the
function is called 110,000 times. It seems a waste to manufacture 110,000 pairs
of dice when one would do! To avoid this, I create the dice as a static member
variable:</p>

<pre>private static PairOfDice dice = new PairOfDice();</pre>

<np>The variable must be <code>static</code> since it is used in the <code>static</code>
function, <code>rollFor</code>. Since <code>dice</code> is a static member variable, it
is created and initialized when the class is first loaded and it exists as long
as the program is running. The <code>rollFor()</code> method always uses this one
pair of dice. (Some people might prefer to create the dice as a local variable
in the <code>main()</code> routine. The dice could be passed as a parameter to the
<code>rollFor()</code> method. Then, <code>rollFor(N,dice)</code> would mean "roll for
a total of <code>N</code> using this pair of dice." But in my opinion, the dice are not
logically a part of the interface of this subroutine, and I prefer to use the
member variable.)</np>

<p>The original program also had a method called <code>getAverageRollCount()</code>
to find the average number of rolls, when the basic experiment is repeated
10000 times. We could rename this to <code>getRollCountStats</code> and use it to
compute all the statistics, not just the average. The actual computation is to
be done by a <classname>StatCalc</classname> object. Let <code>stats</code> be a variable that
refers to that object. The results of each experiment will be fed into this
object, something like this:</p>

<pre>for ( int i = 0;  i &lt; 10000;  i++ ) {
      // Assume "total" is the number we are rolling for.
    rollCountThisExperiment = rollFor( total );  // Do one experiment.
    stats.enter( rollCountThisExperiment );      // Enter the data.
}</pre>

<np>At the end of this process, <code>stats</code> is ready to report the
statistics. All you have to do is call its functions, such as
<code>stats.getMean()</code>.</np>

<p>In my program, I use the named constant <code>NUMBER_OF_EXPERIMENTS</code>
instead of the literal number, 10000. I abbreviate the for loop to</p>

<pre>for ( int i = 0;  i &lt; NUMBER_OF_EXPERIMENTS;  i++ ) 
    stats.enter( rollFor(total) );</pre>

<np>and, since it has become so short, I deleted the subroutine and moved the
<code>for</code> loop into the <code>main()</code> routine. The <code>main()</code> routine
prints the output in neat columns, using formatted output. For example,
"<code>System.out.printf("%6d",total);</code>" prints the value of <code>total</code> in a column
of width 6. (The hardest part was figuring out how wide to make the columns!).
After printing out some headings for the columns, the <code>main()</code> routine
says</np>

<pre>for ( int total = 2;  total &lt;= 12;  total++ ) {
   StatCalc stats;  // An object that will compute the statistics.
   stats = new StatCalc();
   for ( int i = 0; i &lt; NUMBER_OF_EXPERIMENTS; i++ ) {
         // Do the experiment of counting the number of rolls
         // required to roll the desired total, and enter the
         // number of rolls into stats' dataset.
      stats.enter( rollFor(total) );
   }
   System.out.printf("%6d", total);
   System.out.printf("%18.3f", stats.getMean());
   System.out.printf("%19.3f", stats.getStandardDeviation());
   System.out.printf("%14.3f", stats.getMax());
   System.out.println();
}</pre>


<np>The body of the <code>for</code> loop processes one of the possible totals on a
pair of dice, and it produces one line of output with the statistics for that
total. A new <classname>StatCalc</classname> object is created for each execution of the
<code>for</code> loop. This is necessary because we want separate statistics for
each total. A single <classname>StatCalc</classname> object would just accumulate all the
data for all the possible values of total into a single dataset. It might be worth
noting that the five output statements in this method could be written as
a single statement:</np>

<pre>System.out.printf( "%6d%18.3f%19.3f%14.3f%n", total, stats.getMean(), 
        stats.getStandardDeveialtion(), stats.getMax() );</pre>

<break/>

<p>By the way, you might wonder what would happen if I had not eliminated the
<code>getRollCountStats()</code> subroutine? In that case, the statistics data is
generated in the subroutine and is used in the <code>main()</code> routine. So, the
same <classname>StatCalc</classname> object has to be used in both routines. There are
several ways to handle this. The variable, <code>stats</code>, could be a static
member variable. Then it could simply be used in both routines. Alternatively,
the <classname>StatCalc</classname> object could be passed as a parameter to the subroutine.
Or, as a final and best alternative, the object could be created in the subroutine and
sent back to the <code>main()</code> routine as a return value. Let's look at this
last possibility. The subroutine would be:</p>

<pre>static StatCalc getRollCountStats( int total ) {
    StatCalc calc;         // An object to compute the statistics.
    calc = new StatCalc();
    for ( int i = 0; i &lt; NUMBER_OF_EXPERIMENTS; i++ )
        calc.enter( rollFor(total) );
    return calc;  // Send back the object, with the statistics.
}</pre>

<np>In the main program, this would be used as follows:</np>

<pre>for ( int total = 2; total &lt;= 12; total++ ) {
   StatCalc stats;  // The stats for this total
   stats = getRollCountStats( total ); // Get stats from subroutine.
   System.out.printf("%6d", total);
   System.out.printf("%18.3f", stats.getMean());
   System.out.printf("%19.3f", stats.getStandardDeviation());
   System.out.printf("%14.3f", stats.getMax());
   System.out.println();
}</pre>

<p>Note in particular that not every object variable needs to be initialized
with a new object. In the case of the variable <code>calc</code> in the
<code>main()</code> routine, an object is computed elsewhere. The variable,
<code>calc</code>, is set to refer to that existing object.</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre>
<prog name="DiceRollStats2">/**
 * This program performs the following type of experiment:
 * Given a desired total roll, such as 7, roll a pair of
 * dice until the given total comes up, and count how many
 * rolls are necessary.  Now do the experiment over and over,
 * and find the average number of rolls.  The number of times
 * the experiment is repeated is given by the constant,
 * NUMBER_OF_EXPERIMENTS.  Several statistics are computed and
 * printed out for each possible roll = 2, 3, ..., 12:
 * the average number of rolls, the standard deviation,
 * and the maximum number of rolls.
 */

public class DiceRollStats2 {

   static final int NUMBER_OF_EXPERIMENTS = 10000;
   
   private static PairOfDice dice = new PairOfDice();
            // A single pair of dice, which will be used for all
            // the experiments.

   
   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
       System.out.println("Dice Total   Avg # of Rolls   Stand. Deviation   Max # of Rolls");
       System.out.println("----------   --------------   ----------------   --------------");

       for ( int total = 2;  total &lt;= 12;  total++ ) {
          StatCalc stats;  // An object that will compute the statistics.
          stats = new StatCalc();
          for ( int i = 0; i &lt; NUMBER_OF_EXPERIMENTS; i++ ) {
                // Do the experiment of counting the number of rolls
                // required to roll the desired total, and enter the
                // number of rolls into stats' dataset.
             stats.enter( rollFor(total) );
          }
          System.out.printf("%6d", total);
          System.out.printf("%18.3f", stats.getMean());
          System.out.printf("%19.3f", stats.getStandardDeviation());
          System.out.printf("%14.3f", stats.getMax());
          System.out.println();
       }
       
   } // end main
   
   /**
    * Roll the dice repeatedly until the total on the
    * two dice comes up to be N.  N MUST be one of the numbers
    * 2, 3, ..., 12.  (If not, this routine will go into an
    * infinite loop!).  The number of rolls is returned.
    */
   static int rollFor( int N ) {
       int rollCt = 0;  // Number of rolls made.
       do {
          dice.roll();
          rollCt++;
       } while ( dice.getTotal() != N );
       return rollCt;
   }

   
}  // end class DiceRollStats2</prog>
</pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>





<exercise>
<exercise-question><p>The <classname>BlackjackHand</classname>
class from <localref href="OOP.5.1"/> is an extension of the
<classname>Hand</classname> class from <localref href="OOP.4"/>. The instance
methods in the <classname>Hand</classname> class are discussed in that section. In addition to
those methods, <classname>BlackjackHand</classname> includes an instance method,
<code>getBlackjackValue()</code>, which returns the value of the hand for the game
of Blackjack. For this exercise, you will also need the <classname>Deck</classname> and
<classname>Card</classname> classes from <localref href="OOP.4"/>.</p>

<p>A Blackjack hand typically contains from two to six cards. Write a program
to test the <classname>BlackjackHand</classname> class. You should create a
<classname>BlackjackHand</classname> object and a <classname>Deck</classname> object. Pick a random number
between 2 and 6. Deal that many cards from the deck and add them to the hand.
Print out all the cards in the hand, and then print out the value computed for
the hand by <code>getBlackjackValue()</code>. Repeat this as long as the user wants
to continue.</p>

<p>In addition to <sourceref href="textio/TextIO.java">TextIO.java</sourceref>, your program will depend on 
<sourceref href="Card.java"/>, <sourceref href="Deck.java"/>, 
<sourceref href="Hand.java"/>, and <sourceref href="BlackjackHand.java"/>.</p>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss>
<p>This problem is mostly a warm-up for the <localref href="OOP.ex.5">next
one</localref>. It uses objects of three different types, <classname>Card</classname>,
<classname>Deck</classname>, and <classname>BlackjackHand</classname>. 
The <classname>Hand</classname> class is used
indirectly, as the superclass of <classname>BlackjackHand</classname>. To use these objects,
you need to know what methods are available in each class, so you should review
the information that you have about the classes before beginning the
program.</p>

<p>An algorithm for the program is</p>

<pre>Create a deck
repeat while user wants to continue:
    Shuffle the deck
    Create a new BlackjackHand
    Decide the number of cards in the hand
    Deal cards from the deck into the hand, and print them out
    Display the value of the hand</pre>

<np>Some variation is possible. You could use just one <classname>BlackjackHand</classname>
object, and remove all the cards from it between hands. The <classname>Hand</classname> class
includes an instance method, <code>clear()</code>, that could be used for this
purpose. Similarly, you could create a new <classname>Deck</classname> object each time
through the loop. Or, you might want to use one deck and shuffle it only when
the number of cards in the deck gets too small. You could say:</np>

<pre>if (deck.cardsLeft() &lt; 6)  
      deck.shuffle();</pre>

<p>Since we always want to do at least one hand, we can use a
<code>do..while</code> statement for the loop. Putting in some variable names, we
can refine the algorithm to</p>

<pre>deck  =  new Deck();
do:
    deck.shuffle();
    hand  =  new BlackjackHand();
    cardsInHand = a random number between 2 and 6
    Deal cards from deck into hand, and print them out.
    Display hand.getBlackjackValue()
    Ask if user wants to go again
while user wants to go again</pre>

<np>The number of cards in the hand is supposed to be a random number between 2
and 6. There are five possible values. The expression
"<code>(int)(Math.random()*5)</code>" has one of the 5 possible values 0, 1, 2, 3,
or 4. Adding 2 to the result gives one of the values 2, 3, 4, 5, or 6. So, the
number of cards can be computed as "<code>2&nbsp;+&nbsp;(int)(Math.random()*5)</code>".</np>

<p>Once we know the number of cards, we can use a <code>for</code> loop to deal
cards into the hand, one at a time. The function call <code>deck.dealCard()</code>
gets a card from the deck. Once we have a card, we can add it to the hand with
the subroutine call <code>hand.addCard(card)</code>. This allows us to refine the
algorithm to</p>

<pre>deck  =  new Deck();
do:
    deck.shuffle();
    hand  =  new BlackjackHand();
    cardsInHand = 2 + (int)(Math.random()*5)
    for i = 0 to cardsInHand:
        card  =  deck.dealCard()
        hand.addCard(card)
        Display the card
    Display hand.getBlackjackValue()
    Ask if user wants to go again
while user wants to go again</pre>

<np>Alternatively, dealing the cards and displaying them could be done in
separate <code>for</code> loops.</np>

<p>This algorithm can be translated pretty directly into the <code>main()</code>
routine of the program, which is shown below.</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="TestBlackjackHand">import textio.TextIO;

/**
 * Creates random blackjack hands, with 2 to 6 cards,
 * and prints out the blackjack value of each hand.
 * The user decides when to stop.
 */
public class TestBlackjackHand {

   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
      Deck deck;            // A deck of cards.
      Card card;            // A card dealt from the deck.
      BlackjackHand hand;   // A hand of from two to six cards.
      int cardsInHand;      // Number or cards in the hand.
      boolean again;        // Set to true if user wants to continue.
      
      deck = new Deck();    // Create the deck.

      do {
         deck.shuffle();
         hand = new BlackjackHand(); 
         cardsInHand = 2 + (int)(Math.random()*5);
         System.out.println();
         System.out.println();
         System.out.println("Hand contains:");
         for ( int i = 1; i &lt;= cardsInHand; i++ ) {
                // Get a card from the deck, print it out,
                //   and add it to the hand.
            card = deck.dealCard();
            hand.addCard(card);
            System.out.println("    " + card);
         }
         System.out.println("Value of hand is " + hand.getBlackjackValue());
         System.out.println();
         System.out.print("Again? ");
         again = TextIO.getlnBoolean();
      } while (again == true);
      
   }
   
}  // end class TestBlackjackHand</prog>
</pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>




   
<exercise id="OOP.ex.5">
<exercise-question><p>Write a program that lets
the user play Blackjack. The game will be a simplified version of Blackjack as
it is played in a casino. The computer will act as the dealer. As in the
previous exercise, your program will need the classes defined in 
<sourceref href="Card.java"/>, <sourceref href="Deck.java"/>, 
<sourceref href="Hand.java"/>, and <sourceref href="BlackjackHand.java"/>.
(This is the longest and
most complex program that has come up so far in the exercises.)</p>

<p>You should first write a subroutine in which the user plays one game. The
subroutine should return a <ptype>boolean</ptype> value to indicate whether the user
wins the game or not. Return <code>true</code> if the user wins, <code>false</code> if
the dealer wins. The program needs an object of class <classname>Deck</classname> and two
objects of type <classname>BlackjackHand</classname>, one for the dealer and one for the
user. The general object in Blackjack is to get a hand of cards whose value is
as close to 21 as possible, without going over. The game goes like this.</p>

<ul>
<li>First, two cards are dealt into each player's hand. If the dealer's hand has
a value of 21 at this point, then the dealer wins. Otherwise, if the user has
21, then the user wins. (This is called a "Blackjack".) Note that the dealer
wins on a tie, so if both players have Blackjack, then the dealer wins.</li>

<li>Now, if the game has not ended, the user gets a chance to add some cards to
her hand. In this phase, the user sees her own cards and sees
<b>one</b> of the dealer's two cards. (In a casino, the dealer deals
himself one card face up and one card face down. All the user's cards are dealt
face up.) The user makes a decision whether to "Hit", which means to add
another card to her hand, or to "Stand", which means to stop taking cards.</li>

<li>If the user Hits, there is a possibility that the user will go over 21. In
that case, the game is over and the user loses. If not, then the process
continues. The user gets to decide again whether to Hit or Stand.</li>

<li>If the user Stands, the game will end, but first the dealer gets a chance to
draw cards. The dealer only follows rules, without any choice. The rule is that
as long as the value of the dealer's hand is less than or equal to 16, the
dealer Hits (that is, takes another card). The user should see all the dealer's
cards at this point. Now, the winner can be determined: If the dealer has gone
over 21, the user wins. Otherwise, if the dealer's total is greater than or
equal to the user's total, then the dealer wins. Otherwise, the user wins.</li>
</ul>


<p>Two notes on programming: At any point in the subroutine, as soon as you
know who the winner is, you can say "<code>return true</code>;" or "<code>return
false</code>;" to end the subroutine and return to the main program. To avoid
having an overabundance of variables in your subroutine, remember that a
function call such as <code>userHand.getBlackjackValue()</code> can be used
anywhere that a number could be used, including in an output statement or in
the condition of an <code>if</code> statement.</p>

<p>Write a main program that lets the user play several games of Blackjack. To
make things interesting, give the user 100 dollars, and let the user make bets
on the game. If the user loses, subtract the bet from the user's money. If the
user wins, add an amount equal to the bet to the user's money. End the program
when the user wants to quit or when she runs out of money.</p>

</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss>
<p>Let's start by designing the main program. We want to give the user $100 for
betting on the games. Then, the user plays Blackjack games until the user runs
out of money or until the user wants to quit. We could ask the user after each
game whether she wants to continue. But instead of this, I just tell the user
to enter a bet amount of 0 if she wants to quit. We need variables to represent
the amount of money that the user has and the amount that the user bets on a
given game. Let <code>money</code> and <code>bet</code> be variables of type
<ptype>int</ptype> to represent these quantities. Then, we can write an algorithm for
the main program:</p>

<pre>Let money = 100
while (true):
    Input the user's bet
    if the bet is 0:
        Break out of the loop
    User plays a game of Blackjack
    if the user won the game
        Pay off the user's bet (money = money + bet)
    else
        Collect the user's bet (money = money - bet)
    If the user is out of money:
        Break out of the loop.</pre>

<p>Since the Blackjack game will take place in a subroutine, we need some way
for the <code>main()</code> routine to find out whether the user won. The exercise
says that the subroutine should be a function that returns a boolean value with
this information. We should record the return value and test it to see whether
the user won. The other point that needs some refinement is inputting the
user's bet. We better make sure that the user's bet is a reasonable amount,
that is, something between 0 and the amount of money the user has. So, the
algorithm can be refined as:</p>

<pre>Let money = 100
while (true):
    do {
        Ask the user to enter a bet
        Let bet = the user's response
    } while bet is &lt; 0 or &gt; money
    if  bet is 0:
        Break out of the loop
    Let userWins = playBlackjack()
    if userWins:
        Pay off the user's bet (money = money + bet)
    else
        Collect the user's bet (money = money - bet)
    If money == 0:
        Break out of the loop.</pre>

<np>This algorithm can be translated into the <code>main()</code> routine in the
program given below.</np>

<break/>

<p>Of course, the major part of the problem is to write the
<code>playBlackjack()</code> routine. Fortunately, the exercise gives what amounts
to a fairly detailed outline of the algorithm. Things are a little complicated
because the game can end at various points along the way. When this happens,
the subroutine ends immediately, and any remaining steps in the algorithm are
skipped. In outline, the game goes like this:</p>

<pre>Create and shuffle a deck of cards
Create two BlackjackHands, userHand and dealerHand
Deal two cards into each hand
Check if dealer has blackjack (if so, game ends)
Check if user has blackjack (if so, game ends)
User draws cards (if user goes over 21, game ends)
Dealer draws cards (if dealer goes over 21, games ends)
Check for winner</pre>

<p>The last three steps need to be expanded, again using the information stated
in the exercise. The user can draw several cards, so we need a loop. The loop
ends when the user wants to "stand". In the loop, if the value of
<code>userHand</code> goes over 21, then the whole subroutine ends. The dealer
simply draws cards in a loop as long as the value of <code>dealerHand</code> is 16
or less. Again, if the value goes over 21, the whole subroutine ends. In the
last step, we determine the winner by comparing the values of the two hands.
With these refinements, the algorithm becomes</p>

<pre>Create and shuffle a deck of cards
Create two BlackjackHands, userHand and dealerHand

Deal two cards into each hand
if dealer has blackjack
    User loses and the game ends now
If user has blackjack
    User wins and the game ends now

Repeat:
    Ask whether user wants to hit or stand
    if user stands:
        break out of loop
    if user hits:
        Give user a card
        if userHand.getBlackjackValue() &gt; 21:
            User loses and the game ends now

while  dealerHand.getBlackjackValue() &lt;= 16 :
    Give dealer a card
    if dealerHand.getBlackjackValue() &gt; 21:
        User wins and game ends now

if dealerHand.getBlackjackValue() &gt;= userHand.getBlackjackValue()
    User loses
else
    User wins</pre>

<p>This is ready to be translated into Java. One point of coding is the
question of how to deal a card to the user or to the dealer. If <code>deck</code>
refers to the object of type <classname>Deck</classname>, then the function call
<code>deck.dealCard()</code> returns the card we want. We can add the card to a
hand with the <code>addCard()</code> instance method from the <classname>Hand</classname> class.
We can do this in one step, if we want. For example, to deal two cards into
each hand, we just have to say</p>

<pre>dealerHand.addCard( deck.dealCard() );
dealerHand.addCard( deck.dealCard() );
userHand.addCard( deck.dealCard() );
userHand.addCard( deck.dealCard() );</pre>

<p>Of course, a lot of output statements have to be added to the algorithm to
keep the user informed about what is going on. For example, I expanded the step
where it says "Ask whether user wants to hit or stand" to</p>

<pre>Display all the cards in the user's hand
Display the user's total
Display the dealers face-up card, i.e. dealerHand.getCard(0)
Ask if user wants to hit or stand
Get user's response, and make sure it's legal</pre>

<np>The last step listed here expands to a loop that ends when the user inputs a
valid response, 'H' or 'S'. The first step uses a <code>for</code> loop
to display the cards in the user's hand:</np>

<pre>for ( int i = 0;  i &lt; userHand.getCardCount();  i++ )
     System.out.println("   " + userHand.getCard(i));</pre>

<np>The function call
<code>userHand.getCardCount()</code> gives the number of cards in the hand. The
cards are numbered from 0 to <code>userHand.getCardCount()&nbsp;-&nbsp;1</code>, and
<code>userHand.getCard(i)</code> is the card in the <code>i</code>-position. Of course,
to produce code like this, you have to make sure that you are familiar with the
methods in the classes that you are using.</np>

<p>Although there are many other details to get right, it's mostly routine from
here on. I encourage you to read the entire program below and make sure that
you understand it.</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="Blackjack">import textio.TextIO;

/**
 * This program lets the user play Blackjack.  The computer
 * acts as the dealer.  The user has a stake of $100, and
 * makes a bet on each game.  The user can leave at any time,
 * or will be kicked out when he loses all the money.
 * House rules:  The dealer hits on a total of 16 or less
 * and stands on a total of 17 or more.  Dealer wins ties.
 * A new deck of cards is used for each game.
 */
public class Blackjack {

   public static void main(String[] args) {
   
      int money;          // Amount of money the user has.
      int bet;            // Amount user bets on a game.
      boolean userWins;   // Did the user win the game?
      
      System.out.println("Welcome to the game of blackjack.");
      System.out.println();
      
      money = 100;  // User starts with $100.
   
      while (true) {
          System.out.println("You have " + money + " dollars.");
          do {
             System.out.println("How many dollars do you want to bet?  (Enter 0 to end.)");
             System.out.print("? ");
             bet = TextIO.getlnInt();
             if (bet &lt; 0 || bet &gt; money)
                 System.out.println("Your answer must be between 0 and " + money + '.');
          } while (bet &lt; 0 || bet &gt; money);
          if (bet == 0)
             break;
          userWins = playBlackjack();
          if (userWins)
             money = money + bet;
          else
             money = money - bet;
          System.out.println();
          if (money == 0) {
             System.out.println("Looks like you've run out of money!");
             break;
          }
      }
      
      System.out.println();
      System.out.println("You leave with $" + money + '.');
   
   } // end main()
   
 
   /**
    * Let the user play one game of Blackjack, with the computer as dealer.
    * @return true if the user wins the game, false if the user loses.
    */  
   static boolean playBlackjack() {

      Deck deck;                  // A deck of cards.  A new deck for each game.
      BlackjackHand dealerHand;   // The dealer's hand.
      BlackjackHand userHand;     // The user's hand.
      
      deck = new Deck();
      dealerHand = new BlackjackHand();
      userHand = new BlackjackHand();

      /*  Shuffle the deck, then deal two cards to each player. */
      
      deck.shuffle();
      dealerHand.addCard( deck.dealCard() );
      dealerHand.addCard( deck.dealCard() );
      userHand.addCard( deck.dealCard() );
      userHand.addCard( deck.dealCard() );
      
      System.out.println();
      System.out.println();
      
      /* Check if one of the players has Blackjack (two cards totaling to 21).
         The player with Blackjack wins the game.  Dealer wins ties.
      */
      
      if (dealerHand.getBlackjackValue() == 21) {
           System.out.println("Dealer has the " + dealerHand.getCard(0)
                                   + " and the " + dealerHand.getCard(1) + ".");
           System.out.println("User has the " + userHand.getCard(0)
                                     + " and the " + userHand.getCard(1) + ".");
           System.out.println();
           System.out.println("Dealer has Blackjack.  Dealer wins.");
           return false;
      }
      
      if (userHand.getBlackjackValue() == 21) {
           System.out.println("Dealer has the " + dealerHand.getCard(0)
                                   + " and the " + dealerHand.getCard(1) + ".");
           System.out.println("User has the " + userHand.getCard(0)
                                     + " and the " + userHand.getCard(1) + ".");
           System.out.println();
           System.out.println("You have Blackjack.  You win.");
           return true;
      }
      
      /*  If neither player has Blackjack, play the game.  First the user 
          gets a chance to draw cards (i.e., to "Hit").  The while loop ends 
          when the user chooses to "Stand".  If the user goes over 21,
          the user loses immediately.
      */
      
      while (true) {
          
           /* Display user's cards, and let user decide to Hit or Stand. */

           System.out.println();
           System.out.println();
           System.out.println("Your cards are:");
           for ( int i = 0; i &lt; userHand.getCardCount(); i++ )
              System.out.println("    " + userHand.getCard(i));
           System.out.println("Your total is " + userHand.getBlackjackValue());
           System.out.println();
           System.out.println("Dealer is showing the " + dealerHand.getCard(0));
           System.out.println();
           System.out.print("Hit (H) or Stand (S)? ");
           char userAction;  // User's response, 'H' or 'S'.
           do {
              userAction = Character.toUpperCase( TextIO.getlnChar() );
              if (userAction != 'H' &amp;&amp; userAction != 'S')
                 System.out.print("Please respond H or S:  ");
           } while (userAction != 'H' &amp;&amp; userAction != 'S');

           /* If the user Hits, the user gets a card.  If the user Stands,
              the loop ends (and it's the dealer's turn to draw cards).
           */

           if ( userAction == 'S' ) {
                   // Loop ends; user is done taking cards.
               break;
           }
           else {  // userAction is 'H'.  Give the user a card.  
                   // If the user goes over 21, the user loses.
               Card newCard = deck.dealCard();
               userHand.addCard(newCard);
               System.out.println();
               System.out.println("User hits.");
               System.out.println("Your card is the " + newCard);
               System.out.println("Your total is now " + userHand.getBlackjackValue());
               if (userHand.getBlackjackValue() &gt; 21) {
                   System.out.println();
                   System.out.println("You busted by going over 21.  You lose.");
                   System.out.println("Dealer's other card was the " 
                                                      + dealerHand.getCard(1));
                   return false;  
               }
           }
           
      } // end while loop
      
      /* If we get to this point, the user has Stood with 21 or less.  Now, it's
         the dealer's chance to draw.  Dealer draws cards until the dealer's
         total is &gt; 16.  If dealer goes over 21, the dealer loses.
      */

      System.out.println();
      System.out.println("User stands.");
      System.out.println("Dealer's cards are");
      System.out.println("    " + dealerHand.getCard(0));
      System.out.println("    " + dealerHand.getCard(1));
      while (dealerHand.getBlackjackValue() &lt;= 16) {
         Card newCard = deck.dealCard();
         System.out.println("Dealer hits and gets the " + newCard);
         dealerHand.addCard(newCard);
         if (dealerHand.getBlackjackValue() &gt; 21) {
            System.out.println();
            System.out.println("Dealer busted by going over 21.  You win.");
            return true;
         }
      }
      System.out.println("Dealer's total is " + dealerHand.getBlackjackValue());
      
      /* If we get to this point, both players have 21 or less.  We
         can determine the winner by comparing the values of their hands. */
      
      System.out.println();
      if (dealerHand.getBlackjackValue() == userHand.getBlackjackValue()) {
         System.out.println("Dealer wins on a tie.  You lose.");
         return false;
      }
      else if (dealerHand.getBlackjackValue() &gt; userHand.getBlackjackValue()) {
         System.out.println("Dealer wins, " + dealerHand.getBlackjackValue() 
                          + " points to " + userHand.getBlackjackValue() + ".");
         return false;
      }
      else {
         System.out.println("You win, " + userHand.getBlackjackValue() 
                          + " points to " + dealerHand.getBlackjackValue() + ".");
         return true;
      }

   }  // end playBlackjack()


} // end class Blackjack</prog>
</pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>

<exercise id="OOP.ex.6">
<exercise-question><p><localref href="subroutines.ex.7"/> asked you to write
a program that administers a 10-question addition quiz.  Rewrite that program
so that it uses the following class to represent addition questions:</p>
<pre><prog name="AdditionQuestion">public class AdditionQuestion {

    private int a, b;  // The numbers in the problem.

    public AdditionQuestion() { // constructor
        a = (int)(Math.random() * 50 + 1);
        b = (int)(Math.random() * 50);
    }

    public String getQuestion() {
        return "What is " + a + " + " + b + " ?";
    }

    public int getCorrectAnswer() {
        return a + b;
    }

}</prog></pre>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss><p>The original program used two arrays of type <ptype>int[]</ptype>
to represent the addition questions.  One array held the first number from each of
the ten problems, while the other array held the second number.  This representation is
an example of <newword>parallel arrays</newword>: The data for a single question is split
between two arrays.  (The arrays are called "parallel" because to see all the data for
a problem next to each other, you would have to lay the arrays down next to each other,
like parallel lines, so the i-th element in one array lies next to the i-th element in
the other array.)</p>
<p>The new version of the program can use an array of ten objects of type
<classname>AdditionQuestion</classname> to represent the quiz.  The data that we need for
any one question can now be found in the same place&mdash;the object that represents that
question.  This makes for a neater solution than using parallel arrays.</p>
<p>Some of the functionality
that we need to create, administer, and grade the quiz has been incorporated into
the <classname>AdditionQuestion</classname> class.  For example, the constructor in that
class already selects random numbers to be used in the problem, so creating a problem is
just a matter of calling the constructor, and there is no need to use random numbers when
making a problem in the <code>createQuiz()</code> method.  Also, to get the question
and correct answer for a problem, we can just call <code>questions[i].getQuestion()</code>
and <code>questions[i].getCorrectAnswer()</code>.  In fact, we can't get the question
any other way, since the two instance variables in
an <classname>ArithmeticQuestion</classname> are <code>private</code>.
One downside of this is that I couln't format the output from <code>gradeQuiz()</code>
as neatly as in the first version.</p>
<p>All-in-all, it is fairly straightforward to translate the
old version of the program into the new version. You can read my solution below.</p>
<p>By the way, I considered adding the user's answer to the <classname>AdditionQuestion</classname>
class, along with the correct answer, but the user's answer doesn't seem to me to be logically
part of a question.  So I think it makes more sense to keep it out of the object that
represents the question.</p>
<p>Remember that this program depends on the <classname>AdditionQuestion</classname> class that is given in the
statement of the problem.</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="AdditionQuizWithObjects">import textio.TextIO;

/**
 * This program administers a ten-question addition quiz to the user.  The numbers
 * for the problem are chosen at random.  The numbers and the answers are one or
 * two digits.  After asking the user the ten questions, the computer grades the
 * quiz, telling the user the correct answer for any problem they got wrong.
 */
public class AdditionQuizWithObjects {
    
    <newcode>private static AdditionQuestion[] questions;  // The questions for the quiz</newcode>

    private static int[] userAnswers;   // The user's answers to the ten questions.
    
    
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        System.out.println();
        System.out.println("Welcome to the addition quiz!");
        System.out.println();
        createQuiz();
        administerQuiz();
        gradeQuiz();
    }
    
    
    /**
     * Creates the <newcode>array of objects that holds the quiz questions</newcode>
     */
    private static void createQuiz() {
        <newcode>questions = new AdditionQuestion[10];
        for ( int i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++ ) {
            questions[i] = new AdditionQuestion();
        }</newcode>
    }
    
    
    /**
     * Asks the user each of the ten quiz questions and gets the user's answers.
     * The answers are stored in an array, which is created in this subroutine.
     */
    private static void administerQuiz() {
        userAnswers = new int[10];
        for (int i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++) {
            int questionNum = i + 1;
            System.out.printf("Question %2d:  <newcode>%s</newcode> ",
                                  questionNum, <newcode>questions[i].getQuestion())</newcode>;
            userAnswers[i] = TextIO.getlnInt();
        }
    }
    
    
    /**
     * Shows all the questions, with their correct answers, and computes a grade
     * for the quiz.  For each question, the user is told whether they got
     * it right.
     */
    private static void gradeQuiz() {
        System.out.println();
        System.out.println("Here are the correct answers:");
        int numberCorrect = 0;
        int grade;
        for (int i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++) {
            int questionNum = i + 1;
            System.out.printf("   Question <newcode>%2d:  %s  Correct answer is %d  </newcode>",
                questionNum, <newcode>questions[i].getQuestion(), questions[i].getCorrectAnswer()</newcode>);
            if ( userAnswers[i] == <newcode>questions[i].getCorrectAnswer()</newcode> ) {
                System.out.println("You were CORRECT.");
                numberCorrect++;
            }
            else {
                System.out.println("You said " + userAnswers[i] + ", which is INCORRECT.");
            }
        }
        grade = numberCorrect * 10;
        System.out.println();
        System.out.println("You got " + numberCorrect + " questions correct.");
        System.out.println("Your grade on the quiz is " + grade);
        System.out.println();
    }

} // end class AdditionQuizWithObjects</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>

<exercise id="OOP.ex.7">
<exercise-question><p>Rewrite the program from the <localref href="OOP.ex.6">previous exercise</localref>
so that it administers a quiz with several different kinds of questions.
In the previous exercise, you used
a class to represent addition questions.  For this exercise, you will use the following <code>interface</code>,
or an equivalent abstract class, to represent the more general idea of a question that has
an integer as its answer:</p>
<pre>public interface IntQuestion {
    public String getQuestion();
    public int getCorrectAnswer();
}</pre>
<np>You can make the <classname>AdditionQuestion</classname> class implement the interface
simply by adding "<code>implements IntQuestion</code>" to its definition.  Write a similar
class to represent subtraction questions.  When creating a subtraction problem, you should make
sure that the answer is not negative.</np>
<p>For the new program, use an array of type <atype>IntQuestion[]</atype> to hold the quiz
questions.  Include some addition questions and some subtraction questions in the quiz.
You can also add a couple non-math questions, including this one, created as an anonymous class:</p>
<pre>IntQuestion bigQuestion = new IntQuestion() {
    public String getQuestion() {
        return "What is the answer to the ultimate question " +
                 " of life, the universe, and everything?";
    }
    public int getCorrectAnswer() {
        return 42;
    }
};</pre>
</exercise-question>
<exercise-discuss><p>Where the solution to the previous exercise used an
array of <classname>AdditionQuestion</classname> to store addition problems,
the new program has to store questions of various types. An array of type
<atype>IntQuestion[]</atype> can hold any object that implements the
<classname>IntQuestion</classname> interface.  That includes 
objects of type <classname>AdditionQuestion</classname> as long as we modify that
class so that it implements <classname>IntQuestion</classname>.  But it can also
include other types of objects.  For one thing, we want to have subtraction 
problems.  We can implement subtraction with a class very similar to the class
for addition questions:</p>
<pre>class SubtractionQuestion implements IntQuestion {
    private int a, b;  // The numbers in the problem.
    public SubtractionQuestion() { // constructor
       a = (int)(Math.random() * 50 + 1);
       b = (int)(Math.random() * 50);
       <newcode>if (a - b &lt; 0) { // swap a and b so answer won't be negative
          int temp = a;
          a = b;
          b = temp;
       }</newcode>
   }
   public String getQuestion() {
       return "What is " + a + " - " + b + " ?";
    }
    public int getCorrectAnswer() {
       return a - b;
   }
}</pre>
<np>The exercise asks for subtraction problems for which the answer is not negative.
There are a number of ways to accomplish that.  For example, you could use a loop
that would continue selecting random values for <code>a</code> and <code>b</code>
as long as <code>a&nbsp;-&nbsp;b&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;0</code>.  You could choose
<i>b</i> and the <i>answer</i> randomly and then compute <i>a</i> as
<code>a&nbsp;=&nbsp;answer&nbsp;+&nbsp;b</code>. In my solution, I just swap
the values of <code>a</code> and <code>b</code> when <code>a&nbsp;-&nbsp;b&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;0</code>.</np>
<p>Creating the quiz becomes a more difficult problem in the new version, since
we need to use several different kinds of questions.  In my solution, the first seven
questions are math problems.  For each math problem, the program decides randomly whether
to make it an addition question or a subtraction question.  The last three questions
are created using anonymous classes, just like the example given in the exercise.
You can see my solution below.</p>
<p>But the three anonymous classes in my solution have a lot in common: They are the same except for
the particular string that is used to ask the question and the particular number
that is the correct answer.  A better approach would probably have been to create 
a class to represent such questions:</p>
<pre>public class GeneralQuestion implements IntQuestion {
    private String question;
    private int answer;
    public GeneralQuestion( String question, int answer ) {
        this.question = question;
        this.answer = answer;
    }
    public String getQuestion() {
        return question;
    }
    public int getCorrectAnswer() {
        return answer;
    }
}</pre>
<np>In that case, the subroutine for creating the quiz would become:</np>
<pre>private static void createQuiz() {
    questions = new IntQuestion[10];
    for ( int i = 0; i &lt; 7; i++ ) {
        if (Math.random() &lt; 0.5)
            questions[i] = new AdditionQuestion();
        else
            questions[i] = new SubtractionQuestion();
    }
    questions[7] = new GeneralQuestion(
                         "How many states are there in the United States?", 50 );
    questions[8] = new GeneralQuestion(
                         "In what year did the First World War begin?", 1914 );
    questions[9] = new GeneralQuestion(
                          "What is the answer to the ultimate question " +
                                "of life, the universe, and everything?", 42 );
}</pre>
<p>Aside from the declaration of the array <code>questions</code> 
and the routine for creating the quiz, everything else in the program can be exactly as
it was in the previous exercise.  (However, I did change the format of the output in
<code>gradeQuiz()</code> to make it look better for longer questions.)</p>
<p>In my solution, just to keep everything in one file, I nested the interface 
and the two classes that implement it inside the main program class.  It would probably be
better style to put them all in their own files.</p>
</exercise-discuss>
<exercise-code>
<pre><prog name="GeneralQuiz">import textio.TextIO;

/**
 * This program creates, administers, and grades a quiz made up of ten questions,
 * where each question has an integer answer.  The quiz includes some simple addition
 * problems, some subtraction problems, and some non-math questions.
 */
public class GeneralQuiz {

    // -------------------- Nested classes and interface -----------------------

    interface IntQuestion {
        public String getQuestion();
        public int getCorrectAnswer();
    }
    
    static class AdditionQuestion implements IntQuestion {
       private int a, b;  // The numbers in the problem.
       public AdditionQuestion() { // constructor
           a = (int)(Math.random() * 50 + 1);
           b = (int)(Math.random() * 50);
       }
       public String getQuestion() {
           return "What is " + a + " + " + b + " ?";
       }
       public int getCorrectAnswer() {
           return a + b;
       }
    }

    static class SubtractionQuestion implements IntQuestion {
       private int a, b;  // The numbers in the problem.
       public SubtractionQuestion() { // constructor
           a = (int)(Math.random() * 50 + 1);
           b = (int)(Math.random() * 50);
           if (b > a) { // swap a and b so answer won't be negative
              int temp = a;
              a = b;
              b = temp;
           }
       }
       public String getQuestion() {
           return "What is " + a + " - " + b + " ?";
       }
       public int getCorrectAnswer() {
           return a - b;
       }
    }
    
    // -------------------- The Program --------------------------------------

    private static IntQuestion[] questions;  // The questions for the quiz

    private static int[] userAnswers;   // The user's answers to the ten questions.
    
    
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        System.out.println();
        System.out.println("Welcome to the quiz");
        System.out.println();
        System.out.println("There are some math questions and a few non-math");
        System.out.println("questions, but the answer to every question is");
        System.out.println("an integer.");
        System.out.println();
        createQuiz();
        administerQuiz();
        gradeQuiz();
    }
    
    
    /**
     * Creates the array of objects that holds the quiz questions
     */
    private static void createQuiz() {
        questions = new IntQuestion[10];
        for ( int i = 0; i &lt; 7; i++ ) {
            if (Math.random() &lt; 0.5)
	            questions[i] = new AdditionQuestion();
	        else
	            questions[i] = new SubtractionQuestion();
        }
        questions[7] = new IntQuestion() {
              public String getQuestion() {
                  return "How many states are there in the United States?";
              }
              public int getCorrectAnswer() {
                  return 50;
              }
        };
        questions[8] = new IntQuestion() {
              public String getQuestion() {
                  return "In what year did the First World War begin?";
              }
              public int getCorrectAnswer() {
                  return 1914;
              }
        };
        questions[9] = new IntQuestion() {
              public String getQuestion() {
                  return "What is the answer to the ultimate question " +
                                "of life, the universe, and everything?";
              }
              public int getCorrectAnswer() {
                  return 42;
              }
        };
   }        
    
    
    /**
     * Asks the user each of the ten quiz questions and gets the user's answers.
     * The answers are stored in an array, which is created in this subroutine.
     */
    private static void administerQuiz() {
        userAnswers = new int[10];
        for (int i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++) {
            int questionNum = i + 1;
            System.out.printf("Question %2d:  %s ",
                                  questionNum, questions[i].getQuestion());
            userAnswers[i] = TextIO.getlnInt();
        }
    }
    
    
    /**
     * Shows all the questions, with their correct answers, and computes a grade
     * for the quiz.  For each question, the user is told whether they got
     * it right.
     */
    private static void gradeQuiz() {
        System.out.println();
        System.out.println("Here are the correct answers:");
        System.out.println();
        int numberCorrect = 0;
        int grade;
        for (int i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++) {
            System.out.println("Question number " + (i+1) + ":");
            System.out.println("    " + questions[i].getQuestion());
            System.out.println("    Correct answer:  " + questions[i].getCorrectAnswer());
            if ( userAnswers[i] == questions[i].getCorrectAnswer() ) {
                System.out.println("    You were CORRECT.");
                numberCorrect++;
            }
            else {
                System.out.println("    You said " + userAnswers[i] + ", which is INCORRECT.");
            }
            System.out.println();
        }
        grade = numberCorrect * 10;
        System.out.println();
        System.out.println("You got " + numberCorrect + " questions correct.");
        System.out.println("Your grade on the quiz is " + grade);
        System.out.println();
    }

} // end class GeneralQuiz
</prog></pre>
</exercise-code>
</exercise>


</exercises>