<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="threads.1" title="Introduction to Threads">

<p><start><big>L</big>ike people, computers</start> can <newword>multitask</newword>.  That
is, they can be working on several different tasks at the same time.  A computer that
has just a single central processing unit can't literally do two things at the same time,
any more than a person can,
but it can still switch its attention back and forth among several tasks.  Furthermore,
it is increasingly common for computers to have more than one processing unit, and
such computers can literally work on several tasks simultaneously.  It is likely that
from now on, most of the increase in computing power will come from adding additional
processors to computers rather than from increasing the speed of individual processors.
To use the full
power of these multiprocessing computers, a programmer must do <newword>parallel
programming</newword>, which means writing a program as a set of several tasks that
can be executed simultaneously.  Even on a single-processor computer, parallel programming
techniques can be useful, since some problems can be tackled most naturally by breaking
the solution into a set of simultaneous tasks that cooperate to solve the problem.</p>

<p>In Java, a single task is called a <newword>thread</newword>.  The term "thread"
refers to a "thread of control" or "thread of execution," meaning a sequence of instructions that are executed
one after another&mdash;the thread extends through time, connecting each instruction to
the next.  In a multithreaded program, there can be many threads of control, weaving
through time in parallel and forming the complete fabric of the program. (Ok, enough
with the metaphor, already!)  Every Java program has at least one thread; when the Java 
virtual machine runs your program, it creates a thread
that is responsible for executing the <code>main</code> routine of the program.
This main thread can in turn create other threads that can continue even after
the main thread has terminated.  In a GUI program, there is at least one additional
thread, which is responsible for handling events and drawing components on the screen.
In JavaFX, that thread is the application thread, which does all the work 
involved with handling events and drawing components on the screen.</p>
   
<p>Unfortunately, parallel programming is even more difficult than ordinary,
single-threaded programming.  When several threads are working together on a
problem, a whole new category of errors is possible.  This just means that
techniques for writing correct and robust programs are even more important for
parallel programming than they are for normal programming.  On the other
hand, fortunately, Java has a nice thread API that makes basic uses of
threads reasonably easy.  It also has a variety of standard classes to help with
some of the more tricky parts or to hide them entirely.
It won't be until midway through <localref href="threads.3"/>
that you'll learn about the low-level techniques that are necessary to handle the
trickiest parts of parallel programming.  In fact, a programmer can do a lot with threads
without ever learning about the low-level stuff.</p>

<subsection id="threads.1.1" title="Creating and Running Threads">

<p>In Java, a thread is represented by an object belonging to the class
<code>java.lang.Thread</code> (or to a subclass of this class).  The purpose
of a <classname>Thread</classname> object is to execute a single method and to
execute it just once.  This method represents the task to be carried out by the thread.
The method is executed in its own thread of control, which can run in parallel with
other threads.  When the execution of the thread's method is finished, either because the
method terminates normally or because of an uncaught exception, the thread
stops running.  Once this happens, there is no way to restart the thread or
to use the same <classname>Thread</classname> object to start another thread.</p>

<p>There are two ways to program a thread.  One is to create a subclass of
<classname>Thread</classname> and to define the method <code>public void run()</code>
in the subclass.  This <code>run()</code> method defines the task that will be
performed by the thread; that is, when the thread is started, it is the <code>run()</code>
method that will be executed in the thread.  For example, here is a simple, and 
rather useless, class that defines a thread that does nothing but print a message
on standard output:</p>   

<pre>public class NamedThread extends Thread {
   private String name;  // The name of this thread.
   public NamedThread(String name) {  // Constructor gives name to thread.
      this.name = name;
   }
   public void run() {  // The run method prints a message to standard output.
      System.out.println("Greetings from thread '" + name + "'!");
   }
}</pre>
   
<p>To use a <classname>NamedThread</classname>, you must of course create an object
belonging to this class.  For example,</p>
   
<pre>NamedThread greetings = new NamedThread("Fred");</pre>
   
<np>However, creating the object does not automatically start
the thread running or cause its <code>run()</code> method to be executed.
To do that, you must call the <code>start()</code> method in
the thread object.  For the example, this would be done with the statement</np>

<pre>greetings.start();</pre>
   
<np>The purpose of the <code>start()</code> method is to create the new thread of
control that will execute the <classname>Thread</classname> object's <code>run()</code>
method.  The new thread runs in parallel with the thread in which the <code>start()</code>
method was called, along with any other threads that already existed.  The <code>start()</code>
method returns immediately after starting the new thread of control, 
<b>without waiting for the thread to terminate</b>.  This means that
the code in the thread's <code>run()</code> method executes at the same time as the
statements that follow the call to the <code>start()</code> method.  Consider this
code segment:</np>

<pre>NamedThread greetings = new NamedThread("Fred");
greetings.start();
System.out.println("Thread has been started");</pre>

<np>After <code>greetings.start()</code> is executed, there are two threads.
One of them will print "Thread has been started" while the other one wants
to print "Greetings from thread 'Fred'!".  It is important to note that
<i>these messages can be printed in either order</i>.  The two threads run simultaneously
and will compete for access to standard output, so that they can print their messages.
Whichever thread happens to be the first to get access will be the first to
print its message.  In a normal, single-threaded program, things happen in a
definite, predictable order from beginning to end.  In a multi-threaded program,
there is a fundamental indeterminacy.  You can't be sure what order things will
happen in.  This indeterminacy is what makes parallel programming so difficult!</np>   
   
<p>Note that calling <code>greetings.start()</code> is <b>very</b> different from calling
<code>greetings.run()</code>.  Calling <code>greetings.run()</code> would execute
the <code>run()</code> method in the same thread, rather than creating a new thread.
This means that all the work of the <code>run()</code> method will be done before the
computer moves on to the statements that follow the call to <code>greetings.run()</code>.
There is no parallelism and no indeterminacy.</p>

<img src="threads-vs-subroutines.png" width="600" height="357" tex="threads-vs-subroutines.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<p>This discussion has assumed that the computer on which the program is running
has more than one processing unit, so that it is possible for the original thread
and the newly created thread to literally be executed at the same time.  However, it's
possible to create multiple threads even on a computer that has only one processor
(and, more generally, it is possible to create many more threads than there are
processors, on any computer).  In that case, the two threads will compete for
time on the processor.  However, there is still indeterminacy because the processor can 
switch from one thread to another at unpredictable times.  In fact, from the point
of view of the programmer, there is no difference between programming for a single-processor
computer and programming for a multi-processor computer, and we will mostly
ignore the distinction from now on.</p>

<break/>
   
<p>I mentioned that there are two ways to program a thread.  The first way was to
define a subclass of <classname>Thread</classname>.  The second is to define a
class that implements the interface <code>java.lang.Runnable</code>.  The
<classname>Runnable</classname> interface defines a single method,
<code>public void run()</code>.  Given a <classname>Runnable</classname>,
it is possible to create a <classname>Thread</classname> whose task is to
execute the <classname>Runnable's</classname> <code>run()</code> method.</p>

<p>The <classname>Thread</classname> class has a constructor that
takes a <classname>Runnable</classname> as its parameter.
When an object that implements the <classname>Runnable</classname> interface
is passed to that constructor, the <code>run()</code> method of the thread
will simply call the <code>run()</code> method from the <classname>Runnable</classname>,
and calling the thread's <code>start()</code> method will create a new thread of
control in which the <classname>Runnable's</classname> <code>run()</code> method 
is executed.  For example,
as an alternative to the <classname>NamedThread</classname> class, we could define
the class:</p>
   
<pre>public class NamedRunnable implements Runnable {
   private String name;  // The name of this Runnable.
   public NamedRunnable(String name) {  // Constructor gives name to object.
      this.name = name;
   }
   public void run() {  // The run method prints a message to standard output.
      System.out.println("Greetings from runnable '" + name +"'!");
   }
}</pre>
   
<np>To use this version of the class, we would create a <classname>NamedRunnable</classname>
object and use that object to create an object of type <classname>Thread</classname>:</np>

<pre>NamedRunnable greetings = new NamedRunnable("Fred");
Thread greetingsThread = new Thread(greetings);
greetingsThread.start();</pre>

<np>The advantage of doing things this way is that <b>any</b> object can
implement the <classname>Runnable</classname> interface and can contain a
<code>run()</code> method, which can then be executed in a separate thread.
That <code>run()</code> method has access to everything in the class, including
<code>private</code> variables and methods.  The disadvantage is that this
way of doing things is not very object-oriented: It violates the principle that
each object should have a single, clearly-defined responsibility.  Instead of
making some random object <classname>Runnable</classname> just so that you
can use it to make a thread, you can consider defining the thread using 
a nested class that is a subclass of the <classname>Thread</classname> class.  (See <localref href="OOP.8"/>.)
</np>
   
<p>Finally, I'll note that <classname>Runnable</classname> is a functional interface,
so that a <classname>Runnable</classname> object can be given as a lambda expression.
In particular, the parameter to <code>new&nbsp;Thread(r)</code> can be a
lambda expression. For example:</p>

<pre>Thread greetingsFromFred = new Thread( 
    () -> System.out.println("Greetings from Fred!")
);
greetingsFromFred.start();</pre>
   
<break/>
   
<p>To help you understand how multiple threads are executed in parallel, we consider
the sample program <sourceref href="ThreadTest1.java"/>.  This program creates
several threads.  Each thread performs exactly the same task.  The task is to count
the number of integers less than 5000000 that are prime. (The particular task
that is done is not important for our purposes here, as long as it is something
that takes a non-trivial amount of time.
This is a demo program; it would be silly in a real program to have multiple threads that
do the same thing, and the method that is used for counting the primes is not efficient.)  
This computation should take no more than a few seconds on a modern computer.  
The threads that perform this task are defined by the
following static nested class:</p>
   
<pre>/**
 * When a thread belonging to this class is run it will count the
 * number of primes between 2 and 5000000.  It will print the result
 * to standard output, along with its ID number and the elapsed
 * time between the start and the end of the computation.
 */
private static class CountPrimesThread extends Thread {
   int id;  // An id number for this thread; specified in the constructor.
   public CountPrimesThread(int id) {
      this.id = id;
   }
   public void run() {
      long startTime = System.currentTimeMillis();
      int count = countPrimes(2,5000000); // Counts the primes.
      long elapsedTime = System.currentTimeMillis() - startTime;
      System.out.println("Thread " + id + " counted " + 
            count + " primes in " + (elapsedTime/1000.0) + " seconds.");
   }
}</pre>

<np>The main program asks the user how many threads to run, and then creates and starts
the specified number of threads:</np>
   
<pre>public static void main(String[] args) {
   int numberOfThreads = 0;
   while (numberOfThreads &lt; 1 || numberOfThreads &gt; 25) {
      System.out.print("How many threads do you want to use  (1 to 25) ?  ");
      numberOfThreads = TextIO.getlnInt();
      if (numberOfThreads &lt; 1 || numberOfThreads &gt; 25)
         System.out.println("Please enter a number between 1 and 25 !");
   }
   System.out.println("\nCreating " + numberOfThreads 
                                           + " prime-counting threads...");
   CountPrimesThread[] worker = new CountPrimesThread[numberOfThreads];
   for (int i = 0; i &lt; numberOfThreads; i++)
      worker[i] = new CountPrimesThread( i );
   for (int i = 0; i &lt; numberOfThreads; i++)
      worker[i].start();
   System.out.println("Threads have been created and started.");
}</pre>

  
<np>It would be a good idea for you to compile and run the program.</np>

   
<p>When I ran the program with one thread on my old computer, it took 6.251 seconds for 
the computer to do the computation.  When I ran it using eight threads, the output was:</p>
   
<pre>Creating 8 prime-counting threads...
Threads have been created and started.
Thread 4 counted 348513 primes in 12.264 seconds.
Thread 2 counted 348513 primes in 12.569 seconds.
Thread 3 counted 348513 primes in 12.567 seconds.
Thread 0 counted 348513 primes in 12.569 seconds.
Thread 7 counted 348513 primes in 12.562 seconds.
Thread 5 counted 348513 primes in 12.565 seconds.
Thread 1 counted 348513 primes in 12.569 seconds.
Thread 6 counted 348513 primes in 12.563 seconds.
</pre>
   
<p>The second line was printed immediately after the first. At this point, the main
program has ended but the eight threads continued to run.  After a pause of about 12.5
seconds, all eight threads completed at about the same time.  The order in which the
threads complete is not the same as the order in which they were started, and
the order is indeterminate.  That is, if the program is run again, the order
in which the threads complete will probably be different.</p>
   
<p>On this computer, eight threads took about twice as long as one thread.
This is because the computer has four processors.  With eight threads
running on four processors&mdash;one-half processor per thread&mdash;each thread
was only actively being executed for about half of the time, so it took
twice as long to finish its task.  On a single-processor computer, eight
threads would take about eight times as long as one thread.  
On a computer with eight or more processors, eight threads might take no more time
than a single thread.  Because of overhead and other reasons, the actual speedup
will probably be a little smaller than this analysis indicates, but on a multiprocessor
machine, you should see a definite speedup.  What happens when you run the program
on your own computer?  How many processors do you have?</p>

<p>Whenever there are more threads to be run than there are processors
to run them, the computer divides its attention among all the runnable
threads by switching rapidly from one thread to another.  That is, each 
processor runs one thread for a while then switches to another thread and 
runs that one for a while, and so on.  Typically, these "context switches"
occur about 100 times or more per second.  The result is that the
computer makes progress on all the tasks, and it looks to the user as if
all the tasks are being executed simultaneously.  This is why in the sample
program, in which each thread has the same amount of work to do, all the
threads complete at about the same time:  Over any time period longer than
a fraction of a second, the computer's time is divided approximately equally
among all the threads.</p>
   


</subsection>



<subsection id="threads.1.2" title="Operations on Threads">


<p>Much of Java's thread API can be found in the <classname>Thread</classname>
class.  However, we'll start with a thread-related method in
<classname>Runtime</classname>, a class that allows a Java program to
get information about the environment in which it is running.
When you do parallel programming in order to spread the work among
several processors, you might want to take into account the number of
available processors.  You might, for example, want to create one
thread for each processor.  In Java, you can find out
the number of processors by calling the function</p>

<pre>Runtime.getRuntime().availableProcessors()</pre>
   
<np>which returns an <ptype>int</ptype> giving the number of processors that
are available to the Java Virtual Machine.  In some cases, this might be
less than the actual number of processors in the computer.</np>

<break/>

<p>A <classname>Thread</classname> object contains several useful methods
for working with threads.  Most important is the <code>start()</code> method,
which was discussed above.</p>

<p>Once a thread has been started, it will continue to run until its
<code>run()</code> method ends for some reason.  Sometimes, it's useful
for one thread to be able to tell whether another thread has terminated.
If <code>thrd</code> is an object of type <classname>Thread</classname>,
then the <ptype>boolean</ptype>-valued function <codedef>thrd.isAlive()</codedef>
can be used to test whether or not <code>thrd</code> has terminated.  A thread is "alive"
between the time it is started and the time when it terminates.  After the
thread has terminated it is said to be "dead."  (The rather gruesome metaphor
is also used when we refer to "killing" or "aborting" a thread.)  Remember that
a thread that has terminated cannot be restarted.</p>

<p>The static method <codedef>Thread.sleep(milliseconds)</codedef> causes the
thread that executes this method to "sleep" for the specified number of milliseconds.
A sleeping thread is still alive, but it is not running.  While a thread is sleeping,
the computer can  work on any other runnable threads (or on other programs).
<code>Thread.sleep()</code> can be used to insert a pause in the execution of a
thread.  The <code>sleep()</code> method can throw an exception of type
<classname>InterruptedException</classname>, which is a checked exception that
requires mandatory exception handling.
In practice, this means that the <code>sleep()</code> method is usually called inside a <code>try..catch</code>
statement that catches the potential <classname>InterruptedException</classname>:</p>
   
<pre>try {
   Thread.sleep(lengthOfPause);
}
catch (InterruptedException e) {
}</pre>
   
<np>One thread can <newword>interrupt</newword> another thread to wake it up when it is sleeping or
paused for certain other reasons.  A <classname>Thread</classname>, <code>thrd</code>,
can be interrupted by calling the method <codedef>thrd.interrupt()</codedef>. 
Doing so can be a convenient way to send a signal from one thread to another.
A thread knows it has been interrupted when it catches an <classname>InterruptedException</classname>.
Outside any <code>catch</code> handler for the exception, the
thread can check whether it has been interrupted by calling the static method
<codedef>Thread.interrupted()</codedef>.  This method tells whether the current thread&mdash;the
thread that executes the method&mdash;has been interrupted.  It also has the unusual property
of clearing the interrupted status of the thread, so you only get one chance to check for an
interruption.  In your own
programs, your threads are not going to be interrupted unless <b>you</b> interrupt them. So most
often, you are not likely to need to do anything in response to an <classname>InterruptedException</classname>
(except to <code>catch</code> it).
</np>

<p>Sometimes, it's necessary for one thread to wait for another thread to die.
This is done with the <code>join()</code> method from the <classname>Thread</classname> class.
Suppose that <code>thrd</code> is a <classname>Thread</classname>.  Then, if another
thread calls <codedef>thrd.join()</codedef>, that other thread will go to sleep until
<code>thrd</code> terminates.  If <code>thrd</code> is already dead when <code>thrd.join()</code>
is called, then it simply has no effect.  The <code>join()</code> method can throw an 
<classname>InterruptedException</classname>, which must be handled as usual.
As an example, the following code starts several threads, waits for them all to terminate,
and then outputs the elapsed time:</p>

<pre>CountPrimesThread[] worker = new CountPrimesThread[numberOfThreads];
long startTime = System.currentTimeMillis();
for (int i = 0; i &lt; numberOfThreads; i++) {
   worker[i] = new CountPrimesThread();
   worker[i].start();
}
for (int i = 0; i &lt; numberOfThreads; i++) {
   try {
      worker[i].join();  // Wait until worker[i] finishes, if it hasn't already.
   }
   catch (InterruptedException e) {
   }
}
// At this point, all the worker threads have terminated.
long elapsedTime = System.currentTimeMillis() - startTime;
System.out.println("Total elapsed time: " + (elapsedTime/1000.0) + " seconds");</pre>
   
<np>An observant reader will note that this code assumes that no <classname>InterruptedException</classname>
will occur.  To be absolutely sure that the thread <code>worker[i]</code> has terminated in an environment
where <classname>InterruptedExceptions</classname> are possible, you would have to do something like:</np>
   
<pre>while (worker[i].isAlive()) {
   try {
      worker[i].join();
   }
   catch (InterruptedException e) { 
   }
}</pre>

<p>Another version of the <code>join()</code> method takes an integer parameter that
specifies the maximum number of milliseconds to wait.  A call to <codedef>thrd.join(m)</codedef>
will wait until either <code>thrd</code> has terminated or until <code>m</code> milliseconds
have elapsed (or until the waiting thread is interrupted).
This can be used to allow a thread to wake up occasionally to perform some task
while it is waiting.  Here, for example, is a code segment that will
start a thread, <code>thrd</code>, and then will
output a period every two seconds as long as <code>thrd</code> continues to run:</p>

<pre>System.out.print("Running the thread ");
thrd.start();
while (thrd.isAlive()) {
   try {
      thrd.join(2000);
      System.out.print(".");
   }
   catch (InterruptedException e) {
   }
}
System.out.println(" Done!");</pre>



<break/>

<p>Threads have two properties that are occasionally useful: a daemon status and a
priority.  A <classname>Thread</classname> <code>thrd</code> can be designated as
a <newword>daemon thread</newword> by calling <codedef>thrd.setDaemon(true)</codedef>.
This must be done before the thread is started, and it can throw an exception of
type <classname>SecurityException</classname> if the calling thread is not allowed
to modify <code>thrd's</code> properties.  This has only one effect:  The Java Virtual
Machine will exit as soon as there are no <b>non-daemon</b> threads that are still
alive.  That is, the fact that a daemon thread is still alive is not enough to keep
the Java Virtual Machine running.  A daemon thread might exist, for example, only to provide
some service to other, non-daemon threads.  When there are no more non-daemon threads,
there will be no further call for the daemon thread's services, so the program might
as well shut down. (A call to <code>System.exit()</code> forces the JVM to terminate,
even if there are non-daemon threads still running.)</p>

<p>The priority of a thread is a more important property.
Every thread has a <newword>priority</newword>, specified as an integer.  A thread
with a greater priority value will be run in preference to a thread with a smaller priority.
For example, computations that can be done in the background, when no more important
thread has work to do, can be run with a low priority.  In the next section, we will see how 
this can be useful in GUI programs.  If <code>thrd</code> is of type <classname>Thread</classname>,
then <codedef>thrd.getPriority()</codedef> returns the integer that specifies <code>thrd</code>'s
priority, and <codedef>thrd.setPriority(p)</codedef> can be used to set its priority to a given
integer,&nbsp;<code>p</code>.
</p>

<p>Priorities cannot be arbitrary integers, and <code>thrd.setPriority()</code> will
throw an <classname>IllegalArgumentException</classname> if the specified priority
is not in the legal range for the thread. The range of legal priority values can
differ from one computer to another.  The range of legal values is specified by
the constants <code>Thread.MIN_PRIORITY</code> and <code>Thread.MAX_PRIORITY</code>,
but a given thread might be further restricted to values less than <code>Thread.MAX_PRIORITY</code>.
The default priority is given by <code>Thread.NORM_PRIORITY.</code>  To set <code>thrd</code>
to run with a priority value just below the normal priority, you can call</p>

<pre>thrd.setPriority( Thread.NORM_PRIORITY - 1 );</pre>

<p>Note that <code>thrd.setPriority()</code> can also throw an exception of type 
<classname>SecurityException</classname>, if the thread that calls the method is not
allowed to set the priority of <code>thrd</code> to the specified value.</p>   

<p>Finally, I'll note that the static method <codedef>Thread.currentThread()</codedef> returns the current
thread.  That is, the return value of this method is the thread that executed the method.  This allows a
thread to get a reference to itself, so that it can modify its own properties.  For
example,  you can determine the priority of the currently running
thread by calling <code>Thread.currentThread().getPriority()</code>.
</p>


   
</subsection>
   
<subsection id="threads.1.3" title='Mutual Exclusion with &leftquote;synchronized"'>
   
<p>It's pretty easy to program several threads to carry out completely independent tasks.
The real difficulty arises when threads have to interact in some way.
One way that threads interact is by sharing resources.
When two threads need access to the same resource, such as a variable
or a window on the screen, some care must be taken that they don't try to
use the same resource at the same time.  Otherwise, the situation could
be something like this:  Imagine several cooks sharing the use of just one measuring cup,
and imagine that Cook&nbsp;A fills the measuring cup with milk, only to
have Cook&nbsp;B grab the cup before Cook&nbsp;A has a chance to empty the
milk into his bowl.  There has to be some way for Cook&nbsp;A to claim
exclusive rights to the cup while he performs the two operations:
Add-Milk-To-Cup and Empty-Cup-Into-Bowl.</p>
   
<p>Something similar happens with threads, even with something as simple
as adding one to a counter.  The statement</p>

<pre>count = count + 1;</pre>
   
<np>is actually a sequence of three operations:</np>
   
<pre>Step 1.  Get the value of count
Step 2.  Add 1 to the value.
Step 3.  Store the new value in count</pre>
   
<np>Suppose that each of several threads performs these three steps.  Remember that it's possible for
two threads to run at the same time, and even if there is only one processor, it's
possible for that processor to switch from one thread to another at any point.
Suppose that while one thread is between Step&nbsp;2 and Step&nbsp;3, another thread
starts executing the same sequence of steps.  Since the first thread has not
yet stored the new value in <code>count</code>, the second thread reads the
<b>old</b> value of <code>count</code> and adds one to that old value.  Both threads
have computed the same new value for <code>count</code>, and both threads then go
on to store that value back into <code>count</code> by executing Step&nbsp;3. After
both threads have done so, the value of <code>count</code> has gone up 
only by 1 instead of by&nbsp;2!  This type of problem is called a
<newword>race condition</newword>.  This occurs when one thread is in the middle
of a multi-step operation, and another thread can change some value or condition
that the first thread is depending upon.  (The first thread is "in a race" to
complete all the steps before it is interrupted by another thread.)</np>

<p>Another
example of a race condition can occur in an <code>if</code> statement. 
Consider the following statement, which is meant to avoid a division-by-zero error:
</p>
   
<pre>if ( A != 0 ) {
   B = C / A;
}</pre>

<np>Suppose that this statement is executed by some thread.
If the variable <code>A</code> is shared by one or more other threads, and if nothing is
done to guard against the race condition, then it is possible that one of those other threads
will change the value of <code>A</code> to zero between the time that the first
thread checks the condition <code>A&nbsp;!=&nbsp;0</code> and the time that 
it does the division.  This means that the thread can end up dividing by zero,
even though it just checked that <code>A</code> was not zero!</np>
   
<p>To fix the problem of race conditions, there has to be some way for a thread
to get <newword>exclusive access</newword> to a shared resource.  This is not a trivial
thing to implement, but Java provides a high-level and relatively easy-to-use approach
to exclusive access.  It's done with <newword>synchronized methods</newword> and with the
<newword>synchronized statement</newword>.  These are used to protect shared
resources by making sure that only one thread at a time will try to access the resource.
Synchronization in Java actually provides only <newword>mutual exclusion</newword>,
which means that exclusive access to a resource is only guaranteed if <b>every</b> thread
that needs access to that resource uses synchronization.  Synchronization is like a cook
leaving a note that says, "I'm using the measuring cup."  This will get the cook exclusive
access to the cup&mdash;but only if all the cooks agree to check the note before
trying to grab the cup.</p>
   
<p>Because this is a difficult topic, I will start with a simple example.  Suppose that
we want to avoid the race condition that occurs when several threads all want to
add 1 to a counter.  We can do this by defining a class to represent the counter
and by using synchronized methods in that class.  A method is declared to be
synchronized by adding the reserved word <code>synchronized</code> as a modifier
to the definition of the method:</p>
   
<pre>public class ThreadSafeCounter {
   
   private int count = 0;  // The value of the counter.
   
   synchronized public void increment() {
      count = count + 1;
   }
   
   synchronized public int getValue() {
      return count;
   }
   
}</pre>
   
<np>If <code>tsc</code> is of type <classname>ThreadSafeCounter</classname>, then
any thread can call <code>tsc.increment()</code> to add 1 to the counter in a completely
safe way.  The fact that <code>tsc.increment()</code> is <code>synchronized</code> means
that only one thread can be in this method at a time; once a thread starts executing
this method, it is guaranteed that it will finish executing it before another
thread is allowed to access <code>count</code>.  There is
no possibility of a race condition.
Note that the guarantee depends on the fact that <code>count</code> is a <code>private</code>
variable.  This forces <b>all</b> access to <code>tsc.count</code> to occur in the
<code>synchronized</code> methods that are provided by the class. 
If <code>count</code> were <code>public</code>, it would be possible
for a thread to bypass the synchronization by, for example, saying <code>tsc.count++</code>.
This could change the value of <code>count</code> while another thread is in the
middle of <code>tsc.increment()</code>.  Remember that synchronization by itself does <b>not</b> guarantee
exclusive access; it only guarantees <b>mutual exclusion</b> among all the threads that are
synchronized.</np>
  
<p>However, the <classname>ThreadSafeCounter</classname> class does not prevent all possible
race conditions that might arise when using a counter.  Consider the <code>if</code>
statement:</p>

<pre>if ( tsc.getValue() == 10 ) {
   doSomething();
}</pre>
   
<np>where <code>doSomething()</code> is some method that requires the value of the counter
to be &nbsp;10.  There is still a race condition here, which occurs if a second thread
increments the counter between the time the first thread tests <code>tsc.getValue()&nbsp;==&nbsp;10</code>
and the time it executes <code>doSomething()</code>.  The first thread needs exclusive
access to the counter during the execution of the whole <code>if</code> statement.
(The synchronization in the <classname>ThreadSafeCounter</classname> class only gives it
exclusive access during the time it is evaluating <code>tsc.getValue()</code>.)
We can solve the race condition by putting the <code>if</code> statement in a <code>synchronized</code>
statement:</np>
   
<pre>synchronized(tsc) {
   if ( tsc.getValue() == 0 )
      doSomething();
}</pre>

<np>Note that the <code>synchronized</code> statement takes an object&mdash;<code>tsc</code> in
this case&mdash;as a kind of parameter.  The syntax of the <code>synchronized</code> statement
is:</np>
   
<pre>synchronized( <bnf>object</bnf> ) {
   <bnf>statements</bnf>
}</pre>
   
<np>In Java, mutual exclusion is always associated with an object; we say that the
synchronization is "on" that object.  For example, the <code>if</code> statement above
is "synchronized on <code>tsc</code>."  A synchronized instance method, such as those in the
class <classname>ThreadSafeCounter</classname>, is synchronized on the object that
contains the instance method.  In fact, adding the <code>synchronized</code> modifier
to the definition of an instance method is pretty much equivalent to putting the body
of the method in a <code>synchronized</code> statement of the form
<code>synchronized(this)&nbsp;{&dots;}</code>.  It is also possible to have
synchronized static methods; a synchronized static method is synchronized on
the special class object that represents the class containing the static method.</np>
   
<p>The real rule of synchronization in Java is this:  <b>Two threads cannot be
synchronized on the same object at the same time</b>; that is, they cannot simultaneously
be executing code segments that are synchronized on that object.  If one thread is synchronized
on an object, and a second thread tries to synchronize on the <b>same</b> object,
the second thread is forced to wait until the first thread has finished with the
object.  This is implemented using something called a <newword>synchronization lock</newword>.
Every object has a synchronization lock, and that lock can be "held" by only one
thread at a time.  To enter a synchronized statement or synchronized method,
a thread must obtain the associated object's lock.  If the lock is available,
then the thread obtains the lock and immediately begins executing the synchronized
code.  It releases the lock after it finishes executing the synchronized code.
If Thread&nbsp;A tries to obtain a lock that is already held by Thread&nbsp;B,
then Thread&nbsp;A has to wait until Thread&nbsp;B releases the lock.  In fact,
Thread&nbsp;A will go to sleep, and will not be awoken until the lock becomes
available.</p>

<p>The discussion of invariants in <localref href="robustness.2.3"/> mentioned
that reasoning about invariants becomes much more complicated when threads are
involved.  The problem is race conditions.  We would like our <classname>ThreadSafeCounter</classname> 
class to have the class invariant that "the value of <code>count</code> is the number of times that
<code>increment()</code> has been called."  In a single-threaded program, that would be
true even without synchronization.  However, in a multithreaded program, synchronization is
needed to ensure that the class invariant is really invariant.</p>

<break/>

<p>As a simple example of shared resources, we return to the prime-counting
problem.  In this case, instead of having every thread perform exactly the
same task, we'll do some real parallel processing.  The program will
count the prime numbers in a given range of
integers, and it will do so by dividing the work up among several
threads.  Each thread will be assigned a part of the full range of integers,
and it will count the primes in its assigned part.  At the end of its 
computation, the thread has to add its count to the overall total of primes
in the entire range.  The variable that represents the total is shared by
all the threads, since each thread has to add a number to the total.
If each thread just says</p>
   
<pre>total = total + count;</pre>
   
<np>then there is a (small) chance that two threads will try to do this
at the same time and that the final total will be wrong.  To prevent this
race condition, access to <code>total</code> has to be synchronized. My
program uses a synchronized method to add the counts to the total.  This
method is called once by each thread, and it is the only method in which
the value of <code>total</code> is changed:</np>
   
<pre>synchronized private static void addToTotal(int x) {
   total = total + x;
   System.out.println(total + " primes found so far.");
}</pre>
   
<p>The source code for the program can be found in <sourceref href="ThreadTest2.java"/>.
This program counts the primes in the range 3000001 to 6000000.  (The numbers are
rather arbitrary.)  The <code>main()</code> routine in this program creates between
1 and 5 threads and assigns part of the job to each thread.  It waits for
all the threads to finish, using the <code>join()</code> method as described above.
It then reports the total number of primes found, along with the elapsed time.  
Note that <code>join()</code> is required here, since it doesn't make sense to report the 
number of primes until all of the threads have finished.
If you run the program on a multiprocessor
computer, it should take less time for the program to run when you use more than
one thread.</p>

   
<break/>
   
<p>Synchronization can help to prevent race conditions, but it introduces the
possibility of another type of error, <newword>deadlock</newword>.
A deadlock occurs when a thread waits forever for a resource that it
will never get.  In the kitchen, a deadlock might occur if two very
simple-minded cooks both want to measure a cup of milk at the same
time.  The first cook grabs the measuring cup, while the second cook grabs
the milk.  The first cook needs the milk, but can't find it because the
second cook has it.  The second cook needs the measuring cup, but can't
find it because the first cook has it.  Neither cook can continue and
nothing more gets done.  This is deadlock.  Exactly the same thing
can happen in a program, for example if there are two threads (like the two cooks)
both of which need to obtain locks on the same two objects (like the milk and
the measuring cup) before they can proceed.  Deadlocks can easily occur,
unless great care is taken to avoid them.</p>


     
</subsection>
 

<subsection id="threads.1.4" title="Volatile Variables">

<p>Synchronization is only one way of controlling communication among threads.  
We will cover several other techniques later in the chapter.  For now, 
we finish this section with two such techniques: volatile variables
and atomic variables.</p>

<p>In general, threads communicate
by sharing variables and accessing those variables in synchronized methods or
synchronized statements.  However, synchronization is fairly expensive computationally,
and excessive use of it should be avoided.  So in some cases, it can make sense for
threads to refer to shared variables without synchronizing their access to those
variables.</p>
   
<p>However, a subtle problem arises when the value of a shared variable is set in one
thread and used in another.  Because of the way that threads are implemented in Java,
the second thread might not see the changed value of the variable immediately.  That is,
it is possible that a thread will continue to see the <b>old</b> value of
the shared variable for some time after the value of the variable has been changed
by another thread. This is because threads are allowed to <newword>cache</newword> shared data.
That is, each thread can keep its own local copy of the shared data.  When one thread
changes the value of a shared variable, the local copies in the caches of other threads
are not immediately changed, so the other threads can continue to see the old value,
at least briefly.</p>

<p>It is safe to use a shared variable in a synchronized method or statement, as long
all access to that variable is synchronized, using the same syncrhonization object
in all cases.  More precisely, any thread that accesses a variable in synchronized
code is guaranteed to see changes that were made by other threads, as long as the
changes were made in code that was synchronized on the same object.</p>
   
<p>It is possible to use a shared variable safely <b>outside</b> of synchronized code,
but in that case, the variable must be declared to be <newword>volatile</newword>.
The <code>volatile</code> keyword is a modifier that can be added to a global variable
declaration, as in</p>
   
<pre>private volatile int count;</pre>

<np>If a variable is declared to be <code>volatile</code>, no thread will keep
a local copy of that variable in its cache.  Instead, the thread will always use
the official, main copy of the variable.  This means that any change that is made to
the variable will immediately be visible to all threads.  This makes it safe
for threads to refer to <code>volatile</code> shared variables even outside of synchronized code.
Access to volatile variables is less efficient than access to 
non-volatile variables, but more efficient than using synchronization.
(Remember, though, that using a volatile variable does not solve race
conditions that occur, for example, when the value of the variable is
incremented.  The increment operation can still be interrupted by 
another thread.)</np>
   
<p>When the <code>volatile</code> modifier is applied to an object variable,
only the variable itself is declared to be volatile, not the contents of the
object that the variable points to.  For this reason, <code>volatile</code> is
used mostly for variables of simple types such as primitive types
or immutable types like <classname>String</classname>.</p>
   
<p>A typical example of using volatile variables is to send a signal from
one thread to another that tells the second thread to terminate.  The two threads
would share a variable</p>
   
<pre>volatile boolean terminate = false;</pre>
   
<np>The run method of the second thread would check the value of <code>terminate</code>
frequently, and it would end when the value of <code>terminate</code> becomes true:</np>
   
<pre>public void run() {
   while ( terminate == false ) {
      .
      .  // Do some work.
      .
   }
}</pre>
   
<np>This thread will run until some other thread sets the value of <code>terminate</code>
to true.  Something like this is really the only clean way for one thread to cause
another thread to die.</np>
   
<p>(By the way, you might be wondering why threads should use local data caches in the
first place, since it seems to complicate things unnecessarily.  Caching is allowed because
of the structure of multiprocessing computers.   In many multiprocessing computers,
each processor has some local memory that is directly connected to the processor.
A thread's cache can be stored in the local memory of the processor on which the thread is running.
Access to this local memory is much faster than access to the main memory that is shared by all processors, so it
is more efficient for a thread to use a local copy of a shared variable rather
than some "master copy" that is stored in main memory.)</p>

</subsection>
   
 

<subsection id="threads.1.5" title="Atomic Variables">

<p>The problem with a statement like "<code>count = count&nbsp;+&nbsp;1</code>" for
parallel programming is that it takes several steps to execute the statement.   The
statement is only correctly executed if those steps are completed without interruption.</p>

<p>An <newword>atomic</newword> operation is something that cannot be interrupted.
It is an all-or-nothing affair.  It cannot be partly completed.  Most computers
have operations that are atomic on the machine language level.  For example,
there might be  a machine language instruction that can atomically increment
the value in a memory location.  Such an instruction could be used without fear
of race conditions.</p>

<p>In a program, an operation can be atomic even if it is not literally atomic
on the machine language level.  An operation can be considered atomic if it
can never be <b>seen</b> by any thread as partly completed.  For example,
we can say that the  <classname>ThreadSafeCounter</classname> class that was 
defined above has an atomic increment operation.  Synchronization can be
seen as a way of ensuring that operations are, are least effectively, atomic.</p>

<p>Still, it would be nice to have atomic operations that don't require
synchronization, especially since such operations might be implemented
very efficiently on the hardware level.</p>

<p>Java has a package <code>java.util.concurrent.atomic</code> that defines
classes that implement atomic operations on several simple variable types.
We will look at the class <classname>AtomicInteger</classname>, which
defines some atomic operations on an integer value, including atomic add, increment, 
and decrement.  Suppose, for example, that we want to add some integer values
that are being produced by a number of different threads.  We can do that
with an <classname>AtomicInteger</classname> such as</p>

<pre>private static AtomicInteger total = new AtomicInteger();</pre>

<np>The total is created with an initial value of zero.
When a thread wants to add a value to the total, it can use the
method <code>total.addAndGet(x)</code>, which adds <code>x</code>
to the total and returns the new value of total after <code>x</code>
has been added.  This is an atomic operation, which cannot be
interrupted, so we can be sure that the value of total will be
correct in the end.  The sample program <sourceref href="ThreadTest3.java"/>
is a small variation on <sourceref href="ThreadTest2.java"/> that uses
an <classname>AtomicInteger</classname> instead of synchronization
to safely add up values from several threads.</np>

<p><classname>AtomicInteger</classname> had similar methods for adding one to the total and
subtracting one from the total: <code>total.incrementAndGet()</code>
and <code>total.decrementAndGet()</code>.  The method
<code>total.getAndSet(x)</code> sets the value of the total to
<code>x</code> and returns the previous value that <code>x</code>
is replacing.  All of these operations are done atomically (either because
they use atomic machine language instructions or because they 
use syncrhonization internally).</p>

<p>I should close with my usual warning: Using an atomic variable does not
automatically solve all race conditions involving that variable.  For example,
in the code</p>

<pre>int currentTotal = total.addAndGet(x);
System.out.println("Current total is " + currentTotal);</pre>

<np>it is possible that by the time the output statement is executed,
the total has been changed by another thread so that <code>currentTotal</code>
is no longer the current value of total!</np>

</subsection>

</section>
