<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<section id="threads.2" title="Programming with Threads">

<p><start><big>T</big>hreads introduce</start> new complexity into
programming, but they are an important tool and will only become more
essential in the future.  So, every programmer should know some of
the fundamental design patterns that are used with threads.
In this section, we will look at some basic techniques, with more
to come as the chapter progresses.</p>


<subsection id="threads.2.1" title="Threads Versus Timers">
<p>One of the most basic uses of threads is to perform some periodic
task at set intervals.  In fact, this is so basic that there is
a specialized class for performing this task&mdash;and you've
already worked with it.  The <classname>Timer</classname> class,
in package <code>javax.swing</code>, can generate a sequence of
<classname>ActionEvents</classname> separated by a specified
time interval.  Timers were introduced in <localref href="GUI1.5"/>,
where they were used to implement animations.  Behind the scenes,
a <classname>Timer</classname> uses a thread.  The thread sleeps most
of the time, but it wakes up periodically to generate the
events associated with the timer.  Before timers were introduced,
threads had to be used directly to implement a similar functionality.</p>

<p>In a typical use of a timer for animation, each event from the
timer causes a new frame of the animation to be computed and displayed.
In the response to the event, it is only necessary to update some
state variables and to repaint the display to reflect the changes.
A <classname>Timer</classname> to do that every thirty milliseconds
might be created like this:
</p>

<pre>Timer timer = new Timer( 30, new ActionListener() {
    public void actionPerformed(ActionEvent evt) {
        updateForNextFrame();
        display.repaint();
    }
} );
timer.start();</pre>

<p>Suppose that we wanted to do the same thing with a thread.  The <code>run()</code>
method of the thread would have to execute a loop
in which the thread sleeps for 30 milliseconds, then wakes up to do the
updating and repainting.  This could be implemented in a nested class as follows
using the method <code>Thread.sleep()</code> that was discussed in
<localref href="threads.1.2"/>:</p>

<pre>private class Animator extends Thread {
    public void run() {
       while (true) {
           try {
               Thread.sleep(30);
           }
           catch (InterruptedException e) {
           }
           updateForNextFrame();
           display.repaint();
       }
    }
}</pre>

<np>To run the animation, you would create an object belonging to this class
and call its <code>start()</code> method.  As it stands, there would be no way
to stop the animation once it is started.  One way to make it possible to stop
the animation would be to end the loop when a <code>volatile</code> <ptype>boolean</ptype>
variable, <code>terminate</code>, becomes <code>true</code>, as discussed in 
<localref href="threads.1.4"/>.  Since thread objects can only be executed once, 
in order to restart the animation after it has been stopped in this way, it would be necessary
to create a new thread.  In the <localref href="threads.3">next&nbsp;section</localref>,
we'll see some more versatile techniques for controlling threads.</np>

<p>There is a subtle difference between using threads and using timers for
animation.  The thread that is used by a Swing <classname>Timer</classname> does
nothing but generate events.  The event-handling code that is executed in response
to those events is actually executed in the Swing event-handling GUI thread, which also handles
repainting of components and responses to user actions.  This is important because
the Swing GUI is not <newword>thread-safe</newword>.  That is, it does not use
synchronization to avoid race conditions among threads trying to access GUI
components and their state variables.  As long as everything is done in the Swing event
thread, there is no problem.  A problem can arise when another thread manipulates
components or the variables that are also used in the GUI thread.  In the <classname>Animator</classname>
example given above, this could happen when the thread calls the
<code>updateForNextFrame()</code> method.  The variables that are modified in
<code>updateForNextFrame()</code> would also be used by the <code>paintComponent()</code>
method that draws the frame. There is a race condition here:  If these two methods 
are being executed simultaneously, there is a possibility that <code>paintComponent()</code>
will use inconsistent variable values&mdash;some appropriate for the new frame, some
for the previous frame.</p>

<p>One solution to this problem would be to declare both <code>paintComponent()</code> and 
<code>updateForNextFrame()</code> to be <code>synchronized</code> methods.  A better
solution in this case is to use a timer rather than a thread.  In practice, race
conditions might not be a problem for a simple animation, even if they are
implemented using threads.  But it can become a real issue when threads are used for
more complex tasks.</p>

<p>I should note that the <code>repaint()</code> method of a component can be
safely called from any thread, without worrying about synchronization.  Recall that
<code>repaint()</code> does not actually do any painting itself.  It just tells the
system to schedule a paint event.  The actual painting will be done later, in the
Swing event-handling thread.  I will also note that Java has another timer class,
<classname>java.util.Timer</classname>, that is appropriate for use in non-GUI programs.</p>

<p>The sample program <sourceref href="RandomArtWithThreads.java"/> uses a thread
to drive a very simple animation.  You can compare it to <sourceref chapter="6" href="RandomArt.java"/>,
from <localref href="GUI1.5"/>, which implemented the same animation with a timer.
In this example, the thread does nothing except to call <code>repaint()</code>, so
there is no need for synchronization.</p>

</subsection>


<subsection id="threads.2.2" title="Recursion in a Thread">

<p>Although timers should be used in preference to threads when possible,
there are times when it is reasonable to use a thread even for a straightforward
animation.  One reason to do so is when the thread is running a
recursive algorithm, and you want to repaint the display many times over the
course of the recursion.  (Recursion is covered in <localref href="recursion.1"/>.)
It's difficult to drive a recursive algorithm with a series of events from a timer; 
it's much more natural to use a single recursive method call to do the recursion, and
it's easy to do that in a thread.
</p>

<p>As an example, the program <sourceref href="QuicksortThreadDemo.java"/> uses an
animation to illustrate the recursive QuickSort algorithm for sorting an array.
In this case, the array contains colors, and the goal is to sort the colors into
a standard spectrum from red to violet.   In the program, the user randomizes 
the array and starts the sorting process by clicking the "Start" button below the display.  
The "Start" button changes to a "Finish" button that can be used to abort the sort
before it finishes on its own. (It's an interesting program to watch, and it might
even help you to understand QuickSort better, so you should try running it.)
</p>


<p>In this program, the display's <code>repaint()</code> method is called every time
the algorithm makes a change to the array.  Whenever this is done, the thread sleeps
for 100 milliseconds to allow time for the display to be repainted and for the user to
see the change.  There is also a longer delay, one full second, just after the 
array is randomized, before the sorting starts.  Since these delays occur at several
points in the code, <code>QuicksortThreadDemo</code> defines a <code>delay()</code>
method that makes the thread that calls it sleep for a specified period.  The
<code>delay()</code> method calls <code>display.repaint()</code> just before
sleeping.  While the animation thread sleeps, the event-handling thread will have
a chance to run and will have plenty of time to repaint the display.  (I didn't use
synchronization in this example, but it would have been a good idea to do so.)
</p>

<p>An interesting question is how to
implement the "Finish" button, which should abort the sort and terminate the thread.
Pressing this button causes the value of a <code>volatile</code> <ptype>boolean</ptype>
variable, <code>running</code>, to be set to <code>false</code>, as a signal to the
thread that it should terminate.
The problem is that this button can be clicked at any time, even when the algorithm
is many levels down in the recursion.  Before the thread can terminate, all of
those recursive method calls must return.  A nice way to cause that is to throw
an exception.  <code>QuickSortThreadDemo</code> defines a new exception class,
<classname>ThreadTerminationException</classname>, for this purpose.  The <code>delay()</code>
method checks the value of the signal variable, <code>running</code>.  If <code>running</code>
is <code>false</code>, the <code>delay()</code> method throws the exception that will
cause the recursive algorithm, and eventually the animation thread itself, to terminate.
Here, then, is the <code>delay()</code> method:</p>

<pre>private void delay(int millis) {
   if (! running)
      throw new ThreadTerminationException();
   display.repaint();
   try {
      Thread.sleep(millis);
   }
   catch (InterruptedException e) {
   }
   if (! running) // Check again, in case it changed during the sleep period.
      throw new ThreadTerminationException();
}</pre>

<np>The <classname>ThreadTerminationException</classname> is caught in the
thread's <code>run()</code> method:</np>

<pre>/**
 * This class defines the threads that run the recursive
 * QuickSort algorithm.  The thread begins by randomizing the
 * array, hue.  It then calls quickSort() to sort the entire array.
 * If quickSort() is aborted by a ThreadTerminationException,
 * which would be caused by the user clicking the Finish button,
 * then the thread will restore the array to sorted order before
 * terminating, so that whether or not the quickSort is aborted,
 * the array ends up sorted.
 */
private class Runner extends Thread {
   public void run() {
      try {
         for (int i = hue.length-1; i > 0; i--) { // Randomize array.
            int r = (int)((i+1)*Math.random());
            int temp = hue[r];
            hue[r] = hue[i];
            hue[i] = temp;
         }
         delay(1000);  // Wait one second before starting the sort.
         quickSort(0,hue.length-1);  // Sort the whole array, recursively.
      }
      catch (ThreadTerminationException e) { // User clicked "Finish".
         for (int i = 0; i &lt; hue.length; i++)
            hue[i] = i;  // restore original array values.
      }
      finally {// Make sure running is false and button label is correct. 
         running = false; 
         startButton.setText("Start");
         display.repaint();
      }
   }
}</pre>

<p>The program uses a variable, <code>runner</code>, of type <classname>Runner</classname>
to represent the thread that does the sorting.  When the user clicks the "Start" button,
the following code is executed to create and start the thread:</p>

<pre>startButton.setText("Finish");
runner = new Runner();
running = true;  // Set the signal before starting the thread!
runner.start();</pre>

<np>Note that the value of the signal variable <code>running</code> is set to
<code>true</code> before starting the thread.  If <code>running</code> were
<code>false</code> when the thread was started, the thread might see that
value as soon as it starts and interpret it as a signal to stop before doing
anything.  Remember that when <code>runner.start()</code> is called, <code>runner</code>
starts running in parallel with the thread that called it.</np>

<p>Stopping the thread is a little more interesting, because the thread might be sleeping
when the "Finish" button is pressed.  The thread has to wake up before it can act on the
signal that it is to terminate.  To make the thread a little more responsive, we can 
call <code>runner.interrupt()</code>, which will wake the thread if it is sleeping.
(See <localref href="threads.1.2"/>.)  This doesn't have much practical effect in this 
program, but it does make the program respond noticeably more quickly if the user
presses "Finish" immediately after pressing "Start," while the thread is sleeping for
a full second.</p>

</subsection>



<subsection id="threads.2.3" title="Threads for Background Computation">

<p>In order for a GUI program to be responsive&mdash;that is, to respond to
events very soon after they are generated&mdash;it's important that event-handling methods in the program
finish their work very quickly.  Remember that events go into a queue as they are generated,
and the computer cannot respond to an event until after the event-handler methods for previous
events have done their work.  This means that while one event handler is being executed,
other events will have to wait.  If an event handler takes a while to run, the
user interface will effectively freeze up during that time.  This can be very annoying
if the delay is more than a fraction of a second.  Fortunately, modern computers
can do an awful lot of computation in a fraction of a second.</p>

<p>However, some computations are too big to be done in event handlers.  The solution, in
that case, is to do the computation in another thread that runs in parallel with the
event-handling thread.  This makes it possible for the computer to respond to user
events even while the computation is ongoing.  We say that the computation is
done "in the background."</p>

<p>Note that this application of threads is very different from the previous example.
When a thread is used to drive a simple animation, it actually does very little work.  
The thread only has to wake up several times
each second, do a few computations to update state variables for the next frame of the animation,
and call <code>repaint()</code> to cause the next frame to be displayed.  There is 
plenty of time while the thread is sleeping for the computer to redraw the display
and handle any other events generated by the user.</p>

<p>When a thread is used for background computation, however, we want to keep the computer
as busy as possible working on the computation.  The thread will compete for processor
time with the event-handling thread; if you are not careful, event-handling&mdash;repainting
in particular&mdash;can still be delayed.  Fortunately, you can use thread priorities
to avoid the problem.  By setting the computation thread to run at a lower priority than
the event-handling thread, you make sure that events will be processed as quickly as
possible, while the computation thread will get all the extra processing time.  Since
event handling generally uses very little processing time, this means that most of
the processing time goes to the background computation, but the interface is still
very responsive.  (Thread priorities were discussed in <localref href="threads.1.2"/>.)</p>

<p>The sample program <sourceref href="BackgroundComputationDemo.java"/> is 
an example of background processing.  This program creates an image that takes
a while to compute.  The program uses some techniques for working with images
that will not be covered until <localref href="GUI2.1"/>, for now all that you 
need to know is that it takes some computation to compute the color of each pixel
in the image.  The image itself is a piece of a mathematical object known as
the Mandelbrot set.  We will use the same image in several examples in this chapter,
and will return to the Mandelbrot set in <localref href="GUI2.5"/>.</p>

<p>In outline, <code>BackgroundComputationDemo</code> is similar to the
<code>QuicksortThreadDemo</code> discussed above.  The computation is done in
a thread defined by a nested class, <classname>Runner</classname>.  A <code>volatile</code>
<ptype>boolean</ptype> variable, <code>running</code>, is used to control the thread.
If the value of <code>running</code> is set to <code>false</code>, the thread should
terminate.  The sample program has a button that the user clicks to start and to abort the
computation.  The difference is that the thread in this case is meant to run
continuously, without sleeping.  To allow the user to see that progress is being
made in the computation (always a good idea), every time the thread computes a row
of pixels, it copies those pixels to the image that is shown on the screen.
The user sees the image being built up line-by-line.</p>

<p>When the computation thread is created in response to the "Start" button,
we need to set it to run at a priority lower than the event-handling thread.
The code that creates the thread is itself running in the event-handling thread,
so we can use a priority that is one less than the priority of the thread
that is executing the code.  
Note that the priority is set inside a <code>try..catch</code> statement.
If an error occurs while trying to set the thread priority, the program will
still work, though perhaps not as smoothly as it would if the priority was
correctly set. Here is how the thread is created and started:
</p>

<pre>runner = new Runner();
try {
    runner.setPriority( Thread.currentThread().getPriority() - 1 );
}
catch (Exception e) {
    System.out.println("Error: Can't set thread priority: " + e);
}
running = true;  // Set the signal before starting the thread!
runner.start();</pre>

<p>The other major point of interest in this program is that we have
two threads that are both using the object that represents the image.
The computation thread accesses the image in order to set the color
of its pixels.  The event-handling thread accesses the same image
when it copies the image to the screen.  Since the image is a resource
that is shared by several threads, access to the image object should
be synchronized.  When the <code>paintComponent()</code> method copies
the image to the screen (using a method that we have not yet covered),
it does so in a <code>synchronized</code> statement:</p>

<pre>synchronized(image) {
    g.drawImage(image,0,0,null);
}</pre>

<np>When the computation thread sets the colors of a row of pixels
(using another unfamiliar method), it also uses <code>synchronized</code>:</np>

<pre>synchronized(image) {
    image.setRGB(0,row, width, 1, rgb, 0, width);
}</pre>

<np>Note that both of these statements are synchronized on the same object,
<code>image</code>.  This is essential.  In order to prevent the two code
segments from being executed simultaneously, the synchronization must be
on the same object.  I use the <code>image</code> object here because it is convenient, 
but just  about any object would do; it is <b>not</b> required that you synchronize
on the object to which you are trying to control access.</np>

<p>Although <code>BackgroundComputationDemo</code> works OK, there is one
problem:  The goal is to get the computation done as quickly as possible, using
all available processing time.  The program accomplishes that goal on a computer
that has only one processor.  But on a computer that has several processors,
we are still using only <b>one</b> of those processors for the computation.
It would be nice to get all the processors working on the problem.  To
do that, we need real parallel processing, with several computation threads.
We turn to that problem next.
</p>


</subsection>



<subsection id="threads.2.4" title="Threads for Multiprocessing">

<p>Our next example, <sourceref href="MultiprocessingDemo1.java"/>,
is a variation on <code>BackgroundComputationDemo</code>. Instead of
doing the computation in a single thread, <code>MultiprocessingDemo1</code> 
can divide the problem among several threads.  The user can select the number of
threads to be used.  Each thread is assigned one section of the
image to compute.  The threads perform their tasks in parallel.
For example, if there are two threads, the first thread computes 
the top half of the image while the second thread computes the
bottom half. Here is picture of the program nearing the end
of a computation using three threads.  The gray areas represent
parts of the image that have not yet been computed:</p>

<img src="multiprocessing-demo-1.png" width="362" height="278" alt="a partially computer Mandelbrot from MultiprocessingDemo1"
      tex="multiprocessing-demo-1.eps" texscale="0.75"/>
   
<np>You should try out the program.
On a multi-processor computer, the computation will complete more quickly
when using several threads than when using just one.  Note
that when using one thread, this program has the same behavior as the previous
example program.</np>

<p>The approach used in this example for dividing up the problem among
threads is not optimal.  We will see in the <localref href="threads.3">next&nbsp;section</localref>
how it can be improved.  However, <code>MultiprocessingDemo1</code> makes
a good first example of multiprocessing.</p>

<p>When the user clicks the "Start" button, the program has to create and start the
specified number of threads, and it has to assign a segment of the image to
each thread.  Here is how this is done:</p>

<pre>workers = new Runner[threadCount];  // Holds the computation threads.
int rowsPerThread;  // How many rows of pixels should each thread compute?
rowsPerThread  = height / threadCount;  // (height = vertical size of image)
running = true;  // Set the signal before starting the threads!
threadsCompleted = 0;  // Records how many of the threads have terminated.
for (int i = 0; i &lt; threadCount; i++) {
    int startRow;  // first row computed by thread number i
    int endRow;    // last row computed by thread number i
       // Create and start a thread to compute the rows of the image from
       // startRow to endRow.  Note that we have to make sure that
       // the endRow for the last thread is the bottom row of the image.
    startRow = rowsPerThread*i;
    if (i == threadCount-1)
        endRow = height-1;
    else
        endRow = rowsPerThread*(i+1) - 1;
    workers[i] = new Runner(startRow, endRow);
    try {
        workers[i].setPriority( Thread.currentThread().getPriority() - 1 );
    }
    catch (Exception e) {
    }
    workers[i].start();
}</pre>

<p>Beyond creating more than one thread, very few changes are needed to get
the benefits of multiprocessing.  Just as in  the previous example, 
each time a thread has computed the colors for a row of pixels, it copies that
row into the image, and synchronization is used in exactly the same way to
control access to the image.</p>

<p>One thing is new, however.  When all the threads have finished running,
the name of the button in the program changes from "Abort" to "Start Again",
and the pop-up menu, which has been disabled while the threads were running,
is re-enabled.  The problem is, how to tell when all the threads have
terminated?  (You might think about why we can't use <code>join()</code> to
wait for the threads to end, as was done in the example in <localref href="threads.1.2"/>;
at least, we certainly can't do that in the event-handling thread!)
In this example, I use an instance variable, <code>threadsCompleted</code>, 
to keep track of how many threads have terminated so far.  As each thread finishes, it calls
a method that adds one to the value of this variable.  (The method is called in the
<code>finally</code> clause of a <code>try</code> statement to make absolutely sure
that it is called.)  When the number of threads
that have finished is equal to the number of threads that were created, the
method updates the state of the program appropriately.  Here is the method:
</p>
<pre>synchronized private void threadFinished() {
    threadsCompleted++;
    if (threadsCompleted == workers.length) { // All threads have finished.
        startButton.setText("Start Again");
        startButton.setEnabled(true);
        running = false; // Make sure running is false after the threads end.
        workers = null;  // Discard the array that holds the threads.
        threadCountSelect.setEnabled(true); // Re-enable pop-up menu.
    }
}</pre>

<p>Note that this method is <code>synchronized</code>.  This is to avoid the
race condition when <code>threadsCompleted</code> is incremented.  Without the
synchronization, it is possible that two threads might call the method at the same
time.  If the timing is just right, both threads could read the same value for
<code>threadsCompleted</code> and get the same answer when they increment it.
The net result will be that <code>threadsCompleted</code>
goes up by one instead of by two.   One thread is not properly counted, and 
<code>threadsCompleted</code> will never become equal to the number of threads
created.  The program would hang in a kind of deadlock.  The problem would
occur only very rarely, since it depends on exact timing.  But in a large
program, problems of this sort can be both very serious and very hard to
debug.  Proper synchronization makes the error impossible.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="threads.2.5" title="The SwingUtilities Approach">

<p>Using <code>synchronized</code> is important for controlling access to shared
resources, but it does have some performance penalty.  In Java GUI programming, there
is an alternative.
The class <classname>SwingUtilities</classname> in package <code>javax.swing</code>
contains a variety of static methods that are useful in GUI programming.
One of those is</p>

<pre>public static invokeLater( Runnable task )</pre>

<np>In the statement <code>SwingUtilities.invokeLater(task)</code>, <code>task</code>
is an object that implements the <code>Runnable</code> interface and so has a
<code>run()</code> method.  The statement causes <code>task</code> to be added
to the GUI event queue.  The task's <code>run()</code> method will be executed 
some time later by the GUI thread, after any other events in the queue have
been processed.  Since the task is executed by the same thread that handles
events and repaints the screen, there is no problem with the task accessing
the same resources as the painting or event handling code.  This eliminates
the need for synchronizing access to those resources.</np>

<p>As an example, the sample program <sourceref href="BackgroundCompWithInvoke.java"/> is
a slight modification of <sourceref href="BackgroundComputationDemo.java"/>, which
was discussed earlier in this section.  In the revised version, <code>SwingUtilities.invokeLater</code>
replaces <code>synchronized</code>.  You can check the source code if you are interested.</p>

<p>After a thread calls <code>SwingUtilities.invokeLater(task)</code>, the thread continues
immediately without waiting for the <code>task</code> to be completed.  This is a problem
if the thread depends in some way on the results of the task.  The method
<code>SwingUtilities.invokeAndWait(task)</code> schedules the <code>task</code>
to be executed in the GUI thread, then blocks until the task has actually been completed.
That is, the thread that called <code>SwingUtilities.invokeAndWait</code> will go 
to sleep until it is notified that the task has been executed.  This method can throw
several types of checked exceptions, so it is usually called in a <code>try..catch</code>
statement.  You can consult Java documentation for more information.
</p>

</subsection>

</section>
