<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE quiz SYSTEM "../javanotes8.dtd" >

<quiz>

<question>
   <ques><p>A "black box" has an
interface and an implementation. Explain what is meant by the terms
<i>interface</i> and <i>implementation</i>.</p></ques>
   <ans><p>The interface of a black box is
its connection with the rest of the world, such as the name and parameters of a
subroutine or the dial for setting the temperature on a thermostat. The
implementation refers to internal workings of the black box. To use the black
box, you need to understand its interface, but you don't need to know anything
about the implementation.</p></ans>
</question>
   

<question>
   <ques><p>A subroutine is said to have
a <i>contract</i>. What is meant by the contract of a subroutine? When you want
to use a subroutine, why is it important to understand its contract? The
contract has both "syntactic" and "semantic" aspects. What is the syntactic
aspect? What is the semantic aspect?</p></ques>
   <ans><p>The contract of a subroutine
says what must be done to call the subroutine correctly and what it will do
when it is called. It is, in short, everything a programmer needs to know about
the subroutine in order to use it correctly. (It does not include the
"insides," or implementation, of the subroutine.)</p>
<p>The syntactic component of a subroutine's contract includes the name of the
subroutine, the number of parameters, and the type of each parameter. This is
the information needed to write a subroutine call statement that can be
successfully compiled. The semantic component of the contract specifies the
meaning of the subroutine, that is, the task that the subroutine performs. It
might also specify limitations on what parameter values the subroutine can
process correctly. The semantic component is not part of the program. It is
generally expressed in comments.</p></ans>
</question>
   

<question>
   <ques><p>Briefly explain how
subroutines can be useful in the top-down design of programs.</p></ques>
   <ans><p>Top-down refers to starting from
the overall problem to be solved, and breaking it up into smaller problems that
can be solved separately. When designing a program to solve the problem, you
can simply make up a subroutine to solve each of the smaller problems. Then you
can separately design and test each subroutine.</p></ans>
</question>
   

<question>
   <ques><p>Discuss the concept of
<i>parameters.</i> What are parameters for? What is the difference between
<i>formal parameters</i> and <i>actual parameters</i>?</p></ques>
   <ans><p>Parameters are used for
communication between a subroutine and the part of the program that calls the
subroutine. If a subroutine is thought of as a black box, then parameters are
part of the interface to that black box. Formal parameters are found in the
subroutine definition. Actual parameters are found in subroutine call
statements. When the subroutine is called, the values of the actual parameters
are assigned to the formal parameters before the body of the subroutine is
executed.</p></ans>
</question>
   

<question>
   <ques><p>Give two different reasons
for using named constants (declared with the <code>final</code> modifier).</p></ques>
   <ans><p>A constant has a meaningful
name, which makes the program easier to read. It's easier to understand what a
name like <code>INTEREST_RATE</code> is for than it is to figure out how a literal
number like 0.07 is being used.</p>
<p>A second reason for using named constants is that it's easy to modify the
value of the constant if that becomes necessary. If a literal value is used
throughout the program, the programmer has to track down each occurrence of the
value and change it. When a constant is used correctly, it is only necessary to
change the value assigned to the constant at one point in the program.</p>
<p>A third reason is that using the <code>final</code> modifier protects the value
of a variable from being changed. This is especially important for member
variables that are accessible from outside the class where they are
declared.</p></ans>
</question>
   

<question>
   <ques><p>What is an API? Give an example.</p></ques>
   <ans><p>An API is an Applications
Programming Interface. It is the interface to a "toolbox" of subroutines that
someone has written. It tells you what routines are available, how to call
them, and what they do, but it does not tell you how the subroutines are
implemented. An example is the standard Java API which describes the interfaces
of all the subroutines in all the classes that are available in such packages
as <code>java.lang</code> and <code>java.awt</code>.</p></ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>What might the following expression mean in a program?</p>
<pre>(a,b) -&gt; a*a + b*b + 1</pre>
</ques>
<ans><p>The operator "<code>-&gt;</code>" means that this is a "lambda expression,"
that is, an anonymous function.  There must be a functional interface that specifies
the type of this lambda expression.  It might, for example, be a functional interface
that defines a function <code>double&nbsp;f(double&nbsp;x,&nbsp;double&nbsp;y)</code>.
In any case, the function must take two numeric parameters (since the expression <code>a*a+b*b+1</code>
would only be defined when <i>a</i> and <i>b</i> are numeric), and it must return a
numeric value.  (Note that this expression can only be used in a context where the
compiler can deduce which functional interface applies.)
</p>
</ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>Suppose that <classname>SupplyInt</classname> is a functional interface that
defines the method <code>public&nbsp;int&nbsp;get()</code>.   Write a lambda expression of
type <classname>SupplyInt</classname> that gets a random integer in the range
1 to 6 inclusive.  Write another lambda expression of type
<classname>SupplyInt</classname> that gets an <ptype>int</ptype> by asking the user
to enter an integer and then returning the user's response. </p>
</ques>
<ans><p>A lambda expression of type <classname>SupplyInt</classname> has no parameters
and must compute and return a value of type <ptype>int</ptype>.  For the first
expression, the <ptype>int</ptype> value can be given as <code>(int)(1+Math.random()*6)</code>, so the
lambda expression takes the form</p>
<pre>() -&gt;  (int)(1+Math.random()*6)</pre>
<np>For the second lambda expression, at least two statements are needed, one to ask the
user for an integer and one to read the response.  The two statements must
be enclosed between braces, and a <code>return</code> is needed to
return the integer:</np>
<pre>() -&gt; {
    System.out.print( "Please enter an integer: " );
    return TextIO.getlnInt();  // Read an integer and return it.
}</pre>
<np>(This assumes that <classname>TextIO</classname> is available to the program.)</np>
</ans>
</question>
   

<question>
   <ques><p>Write a subroutine named
"stars" that will output a line of stars to standard output. (A star is the
character "*".) The number of stars should be given as a parameter to the
subroutine. Use a <i>for</i> loop. For example, the command "stars(20)" would
output</p>
<pre>********************</pre>
</ques>
   <ans><p>The subroutine could be written as follows:</p>
<pre>static void stars(int numberOfStars) {
     // output a line containing the specified number of stars
   for (int i = 0; i &lt; numberOfStars; i++) {
       System.out.print('*');
   }
   System.out.println();  // output carriage return after the *'s
}</pre>
</ans>
</question>
   

<question>
   <ques><p>Write a <code>main()</code>
routine that uses the subroutine that you wrote for Question 7 to output 10
lines of stars with 1 star in the first line, 2 stars in the second line, and
so on, as shown below.</p>
<pre>*
**
***
****
*****
******
*******
********
*********
**********</pre>
</ques>
   <ans><p>The <code>main()</code> routine can
use a <code>for</code> loop that calls the <code>stars()</code> subroutine ten times,
once to produce each line of output. (An occasional beginner's mistake in this
problem is to rewrite the body of the subroutine inside the <code>main()</code>
routine, instead of just calling it by name.) Here is the main routine&mdash;which
would, of course, have to be put together with the subroutine in a class in
order to be used.</p>
<pre>public static void main(String[] args) {
    int line;  // Line number, and also the number of stars on that line.
    for ( line = 1;  line &lt;= 10;  line++ ) {
        stars( line );
    }
}</pre>
</ans>
</question>
   

<question>
   <ques><p>Write a function named
<code>countChars</code> that has a <classname>String</classname> and a <ptype>char</ptype> as
parameters. The function should count the number of times the character occurs
in the string, and it should return the result as the value of the
function.</p></ques>
   <ans><p>The returned value will be of
type <ptype>int</ptype>. The function simply uses a <code>for</code> loop to look at each
character in the string. When the character in the string matches the parameter
value, it is counted.</p>
<pre>static int countChars( String str, char searchChar ) {
      // Count the number of times searchChar occurs in
      // str and return the result.
    int i;     // A position in the string, str.
    char ch;   // A character in the string.
    int count; // Number of times searchChar has been found in str.
    count = 0;
    for ( i = 0;  i &lt; str.length();  i++ ) {
        ch = str.charAt(i);  // Get the i-th character in str.
        if ( ch == searchChar )
           count++;
    }
    return count;
}</pre>
</ans>
</question>
   

<question>
   <ques><p>Write a subroutine with
three parameters of type <i>int.</i> The subroutine should determine which of
its parameters is smallest. The value of the smallest parameter should be
returned as the value of the subroutine.</p></ques>
   <ans><p>I'll call the subroutine
<code>smallest</code> and the three parameters <code>x</code>, <code>y</code>, and
<code>z</code>. The value returned by the subroutine has to be either <code>x</code> or
<code>y</code> or <code>z</code>. The answer will be <code>x</code> if <code>x</code> is less
than or equal to both <code>y</code> and <code>z</code>. The correct syntax for
checking this is "<code>if&nbsp;(x&nbsp;&lt;=&nbsp;y&nbsp;&amp;&amp;&nbsp;x&nbsp;&lt;= z)</code>". Similarly for
<code>y</code>. The only other remaining possibility is <code>z</code>, so there is no
necessity for making any further test before returning <code>z</code>.  (In fact, doing so would
be an error in Java, since with no "else" clause in the <code>if</code> statement, 
the compiler cannot determine that the function definitely returns a value in all possible
cases.)</p>
<pre>static int smallest(int x, int y, int z) {
   if (x &lt;= y &amp;&amp; x &lt;= z) {
      return x;
   }
   else if (y &lt;= x &amp;&amp; y &lt;= z) {
      return y;
   }
   else
      return z;
}</pre>
<p>Note: Since a return statement causes the computer to terminate the
execution of a subroutine anyway, this could also be written as follows,
without the <code>elses</code>:</p>
<pre>static int smallest(int x, int y, int z) {
   if (x &lt;= y &amp;&amp; x &lt;= z) {
      return x;
   }
   if (y &lt;= x &amp;&amp; y &lt;= z) {
      return y;
   }
   return z;
}</pre>
</ans>
</question>
   
<question>
<ques><p>Write a function that finds the average of the first <code>N</code> elements of
an array of type <ptype>double</ptype>.  The array and <code>N</code> are parameters to the
subroutine.
</p></ques>
<ans><p>Note that the array must be passed as a parameter of type <atype>double[]</atype>,
and that the value returned by the function will be a <ptype>double</ptype>.
For the value of <code>N</code> to make sense, it should be in the range
1 up to the length of the array.  My answer throws an <classname>IllegalArgumentException</classname>
if <code>N</code> is not in this range:</p>
<pre>static double average( double[] numbers, int N ) {
    if ( N &lt; 1 ) {
        throw new IllegalArgumentException("Can't find an average of " +
                       N + " numbers.");
    }
    if ( N &gt; numbers.length ) {
        throw new IllegalArgumentsExcpetion( N + 
                      " is more than the length of the array." );
    }
    double sum = 0;  // the sum of the N numbers
    for ( int i = 0; i &lt; N; i++ ) {
        sum = sum + numbers[i];  // add the i-th number to the sum
    }
    return sum/N;  // Return the average as the value of the function.
}</pre>
</ans>
</question>

<question>
<ques><p>Explain the purpose of the following function, and explain how it works:</p>
<pre>static int[] stripZeros( int[] list ) {
    int count = 0;
    for (int i = 0; i &lt; list.length; i++) {
        if ( list[i] != 0 )
            count++;
    }
    int[] newList;
    newList = new int[count];
    int j = 0;
    for (int i = 0; i &lt; list.length; i++) {
        if ( list[i] != 0 ) {
            newList[j] = list[i];
            j++;
        }
    }
    return newList;
}</pre>
</ques>
<ans><p>This function makes a copy of its parameter, except that it leaves out all the
elements of <code>list</code> that are equal to zero.  It builds a new array that contains
all the non-zero elements of <code>list</code>, and it returns that array as the value
of the function. 
(Note that this is an example of using an array type as the return type of a function.)</p>
<p>The function creates a new array to be the return value.  But to do that, it must
know how long to make the array.  The first five lines of the function definition
count the number of non-zero elements in <code>list</code>.  This is how many spaces
we need in the new array, so <code>count</code> is used as the length when the new
array is created.  The remainder of the function goes through the original <code>list</code>
and copies elements into <code>newList</code>.  An element is copied only if it is non-zero.
We have to keep track of how many spaces in <code>newList</code> have been filled so far.
That's what <code>j</code> is for.  This is the "partially filled array" pattern
from <localref href="control.7a.4"/>.
</p>
</ans>
</question>

</quiz>
