<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes7.dtd" >

<section id="subroutines.6" title="More on Program Design">

<p><start><big>U</big>nderstanding how programs work</start> is one thing.
Designing a program to perform some particular task is another thing
altogether. In <localref href="control.2"/>, I discussed how pseudocode and
stepwise refinement can be used to methodically develop an algorithm. We can
now see how subroutines can fit into the process.</p>
      
<p>Stepwise refinement is inherently a top-down process, but the process does
have a "bottom," that is, a point at which you stop refining the pseudocode
algorithm and translate what you have directly into proper program code.
In the absence of subroutines, the process would not bottom out until
you get down to the level of assignment statements and very primitive
input/output operations. But if you have subroutines lying around to perform
certain useful tasks, you can stop refining as soon as you've managed to
express your algorithm in terms of those tasks.</p>

<p>This allows you to add a bottom-up element to the top-down approach of
stepwise refinement. Given a problem, you might start by writing some
subroutines that perform tasks relevant to the problem domain. The subroutines
become a toolbox of ready-made tools that you can integrate into your algorithm
as you develop it. (Alternatively, you might be able to buy or find a software
toolbox written by someone else, containing subroutines that you can use in
your project as black boxes.)</p>

<p>Subroutines can also be helpful even in a strict top-down approach. As you
refine your algorithm, you are free at any point to take any sub-task in the
algorithm and make it into a subroutine. Developing that subroutine then
becomes a separate problem, which you can work on separately. Your main
algorithm will merely call the subroutine. This, of course, is just a way of
breaking your problem down into separate, smaller problems. It is still a
top-down approach because the top-down analysis of the problem tells you what
subroutines to write. In the bottom-up approach, you start by writing or
obtaining subroutines that are relevant to the problem domain, and you build
your solution to the problem on top of that foundation of subroutines.</p>

<subsection id="subroutines.6.1" title="Preconditions and Postconditions">

<p>When working with subroutines as building blocks, it is important to be
clear about how a subroutine interacts with the rest of the program. This
interaction is specified by the <newword>contract</newword> of the
subroutine, as discussed in <localref href="subroutines.1"/>. A convenient
way to express the contract of a subroutine is in terms of 
<newword>preconditions</newword> and <newword>postconditions</newword>.</p>

<p>A precondition of a subroutine is something that must be true when the
subroutine is called, if the subroutine is to work correctly. For example, for
the built-in function <code>Math.sqrt(x)</code>, a precondition is that the
parameter, <code>x</code>, is greater than or equal to zero, since it is not
possible to take the square root of a negative number. In terms of a contract,
a precondition represents an obligation of the <i>caller</i> of the subroutine.
If you call a subroutine without meeting its precondition, then there is no
reason to expect it to work properly. The program might crash or give incorrect
results, but you can only blame yourself, not the subroutine.</p>

<p>A postcondition of a subroutine represents the other side of the contract.
It is something that will be true after the subroutine has run (assuming that
its preconditions were met&mdash;and that there are no bugs in the subroutine).
The postcondition of the function <code>Math.sqrt()</code> is that the square of
the value that is returned by this function is equal to the parameter that is
provided when the subroutine is called. Of course, this will only be true if
the precondition&mdash;that the parameter is greater than or equal to zero&mdash;is
met. A postcondition of the built-in subroutine <code>System.out.print(x)</code> is
that the value of the parameter has been displayed on the screen.</p>

<p>Preconditions most often give restrictions on the acceptable values of
parameters, as in the example of <code>Math.sqrt(x)</code>. However, they can also
refer to global variables that are used in the subroutine.  Or if it only makes
sense to call the subroutine at certain times, the precondition might refer to 
the state that the program must be in when the subroutine is called.</p>

<p>The postcondition of a subroutine, on the other hand, 
specifies the task that it performs. For a function, the
postcondition should specify the value that the function returns.</p>

<p>Subroutines are sometimes described by comments that explicitly specify their
preconditions and postconditions. When you are given a pre-written subroutine,
a statement of its preconditions and postconditions tells you how to use it and
what it does. When you are assigned to write a subroutine, the preconditions
and postconditions give you an exact specification of what the subroutine is
expected to do. I will use this approach in the example that constitutes the
rest of this section. The comments are given in the form of
<localref href="subroutines.5.4">Javadoc comments</localref>, but I will explicitly
label the preconditions and postconditions.  (Many computer scientists think that new doc
tags <code>@precondition</code> and <code>@postcondition</code> should
be added to the Javadoc system for explicit labeling of preconditions
and postconditions, but that has not yet been done.)</p>

</subsection>

<subsection id="subroutines.6.2" title="A Design Example">

<p>Let's work through an example of program design using subroutines. In this
example, we will use pre-written subroutines as building blocks and we will also design
new subroutines that we need to complete the project.  The API that I will use here
is defined in <sourceref href="Mosaic.java"/>, which in turns depends on
<sourceref href="MosaicPanel.java"/>.  To compile and run a program that uses the
API, the classes <classname>Mosaic</classname> and <classname>MosaicPanel</classname>
must be available.  That is, the files <code>Mosaic.java</code> and
<code>MosaicPanel.java</code>, or the the corresponding compiled class files,
must be in the same folder as the class that defines the program.</p>

<p>So, suppose that I have found an already-written class called <code>Mosaic</code>.
This class allows a program to work with a window that displays little colored
rectangles arranged in rows and columns. The window can be opened, closed, and
otherwise manipulated with static member subroutines defined in the
<code>Mosaic</code> class.  In fact, the class defines a toolbox or API
that can be used for working with such windows.  Here are some of the
available routines in the API, with Javadoc-style comments. (Remeber that
a Javadoc comment comes before the thing that it is commenting on.)</p>
   
<pre>/**
 * Opens a "mosaic" window on the screen.
 *
 * Precondition:   The parameters rows, cols, w, and h are positive integers.
 * Postcondition:  A window is open on the screen that can display rows and
 *                   columns of colored rectangles.  Each rectangle is w pixels
 *                   wide and h pixels high.  The number of rows is given by
 *                   the first parameter and the number of columns by the
 *                   second.  Initially, all rectangles are black.
 *
 * Note:  The rows are numbered from 0 to rows - 1, and the columns are 
 * numbered from 0 to cols - 1.
 */
<newcode>public static void open(int rows, int cols, int w, int h)</newcode>
   
   
/**
 * Sets the color of one of the rectangles in the window.
 *
 * Precondition:   row and col are in the valid range of row and column numbers,
 *                   and r, g, and b are in the range 0 to 255, inclusive.
 * Postcondition:  The color of the rectangle in row number row and column
 *                   number col has been set to the color specified by r, g,
 *                   and b.  r gives the amount of red in the color with 0 
 *                   representing no red and 255 representing the maximum 
 *                   possible amount of red.  The larger the value of r, the 
 *                   more red in the color.  g and b work similarly for the 
 *                   green and blue color components.
 */
<newcode>public static void setColor(int row, int col, int r, int g, int b)</newcode>

   
/**
 * Gets the red component of the color of one of the rectangles.
 *
 * Precondition:   row and col are in the valid range of row and column numbers.
 * Postcondition:  The red component of the color of the specified rectangle is
 *                   returned as an integer in the range 0 to 255 inclusive.
 */
<newcode>public static int getRed(int row, int col)</newcode>

   
/**
 * Like getRed, but returns the green component of the color.
 */
<newcode>public static int getGreen(int row, int col)</newcode>

   
/**
 * Like getRed, but returns the blue component of the color.
 */
<newcode>public static int getBlue(int row, int col)</newcode>

   
/**
 * Tests whether the mosaic window is currently open.
 *
 * Precondition:   None.
 * Postcondition:  The return value is true if the window is open when this
 *                   function is called, and it is false if the window is
 *                   closed.
 */
<newcode>public static boolean isOpen()</newcode>

   
/**
 * Inserts a delay in the program (to regulate the speed at which the colors
 * are changed, for example).
 *
 * Precondition:   milliseconds is a positive integer.
 * Postcondition:  The program has paused for at least the specified number
 *                   of milliseconds, where one second is equal to 1000
 *                   milliseconds.
 */
<newcode>public static void delay(int milliseconds)</newcode></pre>
   
<p>Remember that these subroutines are members of the <code>Mosaic</code>
class, so when they are called from outside <code>Mosaic</code>, the name of the class
must be included as part of the name of the routine.  For example,
we'll have to use the name <code>Mosaic.isOpen()</code> rather than simply
<code>isOpen()</code>.</p>

<p>You'll notice that the comments on the subroutine don't specify what
happens when the preconditions are <b>not</b> met.  Although a subroutine
is not really obligated by its contract to do anything particular in that
case, it would be good to know what happens.  For example, if the
precondition, "row and col are in the valid range of row and column numbers,"
on the <code>setColor()</code> or <code>getRed()</code> routine is violated,
an <classname>IllegalArgumentException</classname> will be thrown.
Knowing that fact would allow you to write programs that catch and handle
the exception, and it would be good to document it with a <code>@throws</code>
doc tag in the Javadoc comment.
Other questions remain about the behavior of the subroutines.
For example, what happens if you call <code>Mosaic.open()</code> and there
is already a mosaic window open on the screen?  (In fact, the old one will
be closed, and a new one will be created.)  It's difficult to fully document
the behavior of a piece of software&mdash;sometimes, you just have to 
experiment or look at the full source code.</p>

<break/>

<p>My idea for a program is to use the <code>Mosaic</code> class as the basis for a neat
animation. I want to fill the window with randomly colored squares, and then
randomly change the colors in a loop that continues as long as the window is
open. "Randomly change the colors" could mean a lot of different things, but
after thinking for a while, I decide it would be interesting to have a
"disturbance" that wanders randomly around the window, changing the color of
each square that it encounters. Here's a picture showing what the contents of the window
might look like at one point in time:</p>

<img src="mosaic.png" width="400" height="320" alt="a 20-by-16 grid of randomly colored squares"
      tex="mosaic.eps" texscale="0.5"/>


<p>With basic routines for manipulating the window as a foundation, I can turn
to the specific problem at hand. A basic outline for my program is</p>

<pre>Open a Mosaic window
Fill window with random colors
Move around, changing squares at random</pre>

<np>Filling the window with random colors seems like a nice coherent task that I
can work on separately, so let's decide to write a separate subroutine to do
it. The third step can be expanded a bit more, into the steps: Start in the
middle of the window, then keep moving to new squares and changing the color
of those squares. This should continue as long as the mosaic window is still
open. Thus we can refine the algorithm to:</np>

<pre>Open a Mosaic window
Fill window with random colors
Set the current position to the middle square in the window
As long as the mosaic window is open:
   Randomly change color of the square at the current position
   Move current position up, down, left, or right, at random</pre>

<np>I need to represent the current position in some way. That can be done with
two <ptype>int</ptype> variables named <code>currentRow</code> and
<code>currentColumn</code> that hold the row number and the column number of 
the square where the disturbance is currently located.  I'll use 16 rows and 20 columns of squares in my
mosaic, so setting the current position to be in the center means setting
<code>currentRow</code> to 8 and <code>currentColumn</code> to 10. I already have a
subroutine, <code>Mosaic.open()</code>, to open the window, and I have a function,
<code>Mosaic.isOpen()</code>, to test whether the window is open. To keep the main
routine simple, I decide that I will write two more subroutines of my own to
carry out the two tasks in the while loop. The algorithm can then be written in
Java as:</np>

<pre>Mosaic.open(16,20,25,25)
fillWithRandomColors();
currentRow = 8;       // Middle row, halfway down the window.
currentColumn = 10;   // Middle column.
while ( Mosaic.isOpen() ) {
    changeToRandomColor(currentRow, currentColumn);
    randomMove();      
}</pre>

<np>With the proper wrapper, this is essentially the <code>main()</code> routine of
my program. It turns out I have to make one small modification: To prevent the
animation from running much, much too fast, the line "<code>Mosaic.delay(1);</code>" is added
to the <code>while</code> loop.</np>

<p>The <code>main()</code> routine is taken care of, but to complete the program, I
still have to write the subroutines <code>fillWithRandomColors()</code>,
<code>changeToRandomColor(int,int)</code>, and <code>randomMove()</code>. Writing each
of these subroutines is a separate, small task. The
<code>fillWithRandomColors()</code> routine is defined by the postcondition that
"each of the rectangles in the mosaic has been changed to a random color."
Pseudocode for an algorithm to accomplish this task can be given as:</p>

<pre>For each row:
   For each column:
      set the square in that row and column to a random color</pre>

<np>&leftquote;For each row" and "for each column" can be implemented as for loops. We've
already planned to write a subroutine <code>changeToRandomColor</code> that can be
used to set the color. (The possibility of reusing subroutines in several
places is one of the big payoffs of using them!) So,
<code>fillWithRandomColors()</code> can be written in proper Java as:</np>

<pre>static void fillWithRandomColors() {
   int row, column;
   for ( row = 0; row &lt; 16; row++ )
      for ( column = 0; column &lt; 20; column++ )
         changeToRandomColor(row,column);
}</pre>

<p>Turning to the <code>changeToRandomColor</code> subroutine, we already have a
method in the <code>Mosaic</code> class, <code>Mosaic.setColor()</code>, 
that can be used to change the
color of a square. If we want a random color, we just have to choose random
values for <code>r</code>, <code>g</code>, and <code>b</code>. According to the
precondition of the <code>Mosaic.setColor()</code> subroutine, these random values
must be integers in the range from 0 to 255. A formula for randomly selecting
such an integer is "<code>(int)(256*Math.random())</code>". So the random color
subroutine becomes:</p>

<pre>static void changeToRandomColor(int rowNum, int colNum) {
     int red = (int)(256*Math.random());
     int green = (int)(256*Math.random());  
     int blue = (int)(256*Math.random());
     Mosaic.setColor(rowNum,colNum,red,green,blue);  
}</pre>

<p>Finally, consider the <code>randomMove</code> subroutine, which is supposed to
randomly move the disturbance up, down, left, or right. To make a random choice
among four directions, we can choose a random integer in the range 0 to 3. If
the integer is 0, move in one direction; if it is 1, move in another direction;
and so on. The position of the disturbance is given by the variables
<code>currentRow</code> and <code>currentColumn</code>. To "move up" means to subtract
1 from <code>currentRow</code>. This leaves open the question of what to do if
<code>currentRow</code> becomes -1, which would put the disturbance above the
window (which would violate a precondition of several of the <classname>Mosaic</classname>
subroutines).
Rather than let this happen, I decide to move the disturbance to the
opposite edge of the grid by setting <code>currentRow</code> to 15. (Remember that
the 16 rows are numbered from 0 to 15.)  An alternative to jumping to the opposite
edge would be to simply do nothing in this case.  Moving the disturbance down, left, or
right is handled similarly. If we use a <code>switch</code> statement to decide
which direction to move, the code for <code>randomMove</code> becomes:</p>

<pre>int directionNum;
directionNum = (int)(4*Math.random());
switch (directionNum) {
   case 0:  // move up 
      currentRow--;
      if (currentRow &lt; 0)   // CurrentRow is outside the mosaic;
         currentRow = 15;   // move it to the opposite edge.
      break;
   case 1:  // move right
      currentColumn++;
      if (currentColumn &gt;= 20)
         currentColumn = 0;
      break; 
   case 2:  // move down
      currentRow++;
      if (currentRow &gt;= 16)
         currentRow = 0;
      break;
   case 3:  // move left
      currentColumn--;
      if (currentColumn &lt; 0)
         currentColumn = 19;
      break; 
}</pre>
   
</subsection>
   
<subsection id="subroutines.6.3" title="The Program">

<p>Putting this all together, we get the following complete program.  Note that I've added Javadoc-style
comments for the class itself and for each of the subroutines. The
variables <code>currentRow</code> and <code>currentColumn</code> are defined as static
members of the class, rather than local variables, because each of them is used
in several different subroutines.  You can find a copy of the source code in
<sourceref href="RandomMosaicWalk.java"/>.  Remember that this program actually 
depends on two other files, <sourceref href="Mosaic.java"/> and <sourceref href="MosaicPanel.java"/>.</p>

<pre>/**
 * This program opens a window full of randomly colored squares.  A "disturbance"
 * moves randomly around in the window, randomly changing the color of each
 * square that it visits.  The program runs until the user closes the window.
 */
public class RandomMosaicWalk {

    static int currentRow;    // Row currently containing the disturbance.
    static int currentColumn; // Column currently containing disturbance.

    /**
     * The main program creates the window, fills it with random colors,
     * and then moves the disturbance in a random walk around the window
     * as long as the window is open.
     */
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        Mosaic.open(16,20,25,25);
        fillWithRandomColors();
        currentRow = 8;   // start at center of window
        currentColumn = 10;
        while (Mosaic.isOpen()) {
            changeToRandomColor(currentRow, currentColumn);
            randomMove();
            Mosaic.delay(1);
        }
    }  // end main

    /**
     * Fills the window with randomly colored squares.
     * Precondition:   The mosaic window is open.
     * Postcondition:  Each square has been set to a random color. 
     */
    static void fillWithRandomColors() {
        int row, column;
        for ( row=0; row &lt; 16; row++ ) {
            for ( column=0; column &lt; 20; column++ ) {
                changeToRandomColor(row, column);  
            }
        }
    }  // end fillWithRandomColors

    /**
     * Changes one square to a new randomly selected color.
     * Precondition:   The specified rowNum and colNum are in the valid range
     *                 of row and column numbers.
     * Postcondition:  The square in the specified row and column has
     *                 been set to a random color.
     * @param rowNum the row number of the square, counting rows down
     *      from 0 at the top
     * @param colNum the column number of the square, counting columns over
     *      from 0 at the left
     */
    static void changeToRandomColor(int rowNum, int colNum) {
        int red = (int)(256*Math.random());    // Choose random levels in range
        int green = (int)(256*Math.random());  //     0 to 255 for red, green, 
        int blue = (int)(256*Math.random());   //     and blue color components.
        Mosaic.setColor(rowNum,colNum,red,green,blue);  
    }  // end changeToRandomColor

    /**
     * Move the disturbance.
     * Precondition:   The global variables currentRow and currentColumn
     *                 are within the legal range of row and column numbers.
     * Postcondition:  currentRow or currentColumn is changed to one of the
     *                 neighboring positions in the grid -- up, down, left, or
     *                 right from the current position.  If this moves the
     *                 position outside of the grid, then it is moved to the
     *                 opposite edge of the grid.
     */
    static void randomMove() {
        int directionNum; // Randomly set to 0, 1, 2, or 3 to choose direction.
        directionNum = (int)(4*Math.random());
        switch (directionNum) {
        case 0:  // move up 
            currentRow--;
            if (currentRow &lt; 0)
                currentRow = 15;
            break;
        case 1:  // move right
            currentColumn++;
            if (currentColumn &gt;= 20)
                currentColumn = 0;
            break; 
        case 2:  // move down
            currentRow ++;
            if (currentRow &gt;= 16)
                currentRow = 0;
            break;
        case 3:  // move left  
            currentColumn--;
            if (currentColumn &lt; 0)
                currentColumn = 19;
            break; 
        }
    }  // end randomMove

} // end class RandomMosaicWalk</pre>

</subsection>

</section>