<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes7.dtd" >

<section id="subroutines.7" title="The Truth About Declarations">

<p><start><big>N</big>ames are fundamental to programming</start>, as I said a
few chapters ago. There are a lot of details involved in declaring and using
names. I have been avoiding some of those details. In this section, I'll reveal
most of the truth (although still not the full truth) about declaring and using
variables in Java. The material in the subsections "Initialization
in Declarations" and "Named Constants" is
particularly important, since I will be using it regularly from now on.</p>

<subsection id="subroutines.7.1" title="Initialization in Declarations">

<p>When a variable declaration is executed, memory is allocated for the
variable. This memory must be initialized to contain some definite value before
the variable can be used in an expression. In the case of a local variable, the
declaration is often followed closely by an assignment statement that does the
initialization. For example,</p>

<pre>int count;    // Declare a variable named count.
count = 0;    // Give count its initial value.</pre>

<p>However, the truth about declaration statements is that it is legal to
include the initialization of the variable in the declaration statement. The
two statements above can therefore be abbreviated as</p>

<pre>int count = 0;  // Declare count and give it an initial value.</pre>

<np>The computer still executes this statement in two steps: Declare the
variable <code>count</code>, then assign the value 0 to the newly created variable.
The initial value does not have to be a constant.  It can be any expression. It
is legal to initialize several variables in one declaration statement. For
example,</np>

<pre>char firstInitial = 'D', secondInitial = 'E';
                
int x, y = 1;   // OK, but only y has been initialized!
  
int N = 3, M = N+2;  // OK, N is initialized 
                     //        before its value is used.</pre>

<np>This feature is especially common in <code>for</code> loops, since it makes it
possible to declare a loop control variable at the same point in the loop where
it is initialized.  Since the loop control variable generally has nothing to do
with the rest of the program outside the loop, it's reasonable to have its
declaration in the part of the program where it's actually used. For
example:</np>

<pre>for ( <newcode>int i = 0</newcode>;  i &lt; 10;  i++ ) {
   System.out.println(i);
}</pre>

<np>You should remember that this is simply an abbreviation for the
following, where I've added an extra pair of braces to show that <code>i</code> is
considered to be local to the <code>for</code> statement and no longer exists after
the <code>for</code> loop ends:</np>

<pre>{
   int i;
   for ( i = 0;  i &lt; 10;  i++ ) {
      System.out.println(i);
   }
}</pre>
   

<p>A member variable can also be initialized at the point where it is declared, just as
for a local variable.  For example:</p>

<pre>public class Bank {
   private static double interestRate = 0.05;
   private static int maxWithdrawal = 200;
     .
     .  // More variables and subroutines.
     .
}</pre>

<np>A static member variable is created as soon as the class is loaded by the
Java interpreter, and the initialization is also done at that time. In the case
of member variables, this is not simply an abbreviation for a declaration
followed by an assignment statement. Declaration statements are the only type
of statement that can occur outside of a subroutine. Assignment statements
cannot, so the following is illegal:</np>

<pre>public class Bank {
   private static double interestRate;
   interestRate = 0.05;  // <newcode>ILLEGAL:</newcode>
   .                     //    <newcode>Can't be outside a subroutine!</newcode>:
   .
   .</pre>

<p>Because of this, declarations of member variables often include initial
values.  In fact, as mentioned in <localref href="subroutines.2.4"/>, if no initial value is
provided for a member variable, then a default initial value is used. For
example, when declaring an integer member variable, <code>count</code>,
"<code>static int count;</code>" is equivalent to "<code>static&nbsp;int count&nbsp;=&nbsp;0;</code>".</p>

<p>Even array variables can be initialized.  An array contains several elements, not
just a single value.  To initialize an array variable, you can provide a list of
values, separated by commas, and enclosed between a pair of braces.  For example:</p>

<pre>int[] smallPrimes = { 2, 3, 5, 7, 11, 13, 17, 23, 29 };</pre>

<np>In this statement, an array of <ptype>int</ptype> of length 9 is created
and filled with the values in the list.  The length of the array is determined
by the number of items in the list.</np>

<p>Note that this syntax for initializing arrays <b>cannot</b> be used in assignment
statements.  It can only be used in a declaration statement at the time when the
array variable is declared.</p>

<p>It is also possible to initialize an array variable with an array created using
the <code>new</code> operator (which <b>can</b> also be used in assignment 
statements).  For example:</p>

<pre>String[] namelist = new String[100];</pre>

<np>but in that case, of course, all the array elements will have their default value.
</np>

</subsection>

<subsection id="subroutines.7.2" title="Named Constants">

<p>Sometimes, the value of a variable is not supposed to change after it is
initialized. For example, in the above example where <code>interestRate</code> is
initialized to the value <code>0.05</code>, it's quite possible that 0.05 is meant to be the
value throughout the entire program. In that case, the programmer is probably
defining the variable, <code>interestRate</code>, to give a meaningful name to the
otherwise meaningless number, <code>0.05</code>. It's easier to understand what's going on
when a program says "<code>principal += principal*interestRate;</code>" rather than
"<code>principal += principal*0.05;</code>".</p>

<p>In Java, the modifier "<code>final</code>" can be applied to a variable
declaration to ensure that the value stored in the variable cannot be changed after
the variable has been initialized. For example, if the member variable
<code>interestRate</code> is declared with</p>

<pre>public <newcode>final</newcode> static double interestRate = 0.05;</pre>

<np>then it would be impossible for the value of <code>interestRate</code> to change anywhere
else in the program. Any assignment statement that tries to assign a value to
<code>interestRate</code> will be rejected by the computer as a syntax error when
the program is compiled.  (A "final" modifier on a public interest rate makes a lot
of sense&mdash;a bank might want to publish its interest rate, but it certainly 
wouldn't want to let random people make changes to it!)</np>

<p>It is legal to apply the <code>final</code> modifier to local variables and even
to formal parameters, but it is most useful for member variables. I will often
refer to a static member variable that is declared to be <code>final</code> as a
<newword>named constant</newword>, since its value remains constant
for the whole time that the program is running. The readability of a program
can be greatly enhanced by using named constants to give meaningful names to
important quantities in the program. A recommended style rule for named
constants is to give them names that consist entirely of upper case letters,
with underscore characters to separate words if necessary. For example, the
preferred style for the interest rate constant would be</p>

<pre>public final static double INTEREST_RATE = 0.05;</pre>

<np>This is the style that is generally used in Java's standard classes, which
define many named constants. For example, we have already seen that the 
<classname>Math</classname> class contains a variable <code>Math.PI</code>.  This variable
is declared in the <classname>Math</classname> class as a "public final static" variable
of type <ptype>double</ptype>.  Similarly, the <code>Color</code> class
contains named constants such as <code>Color.RED</code> and <code>Color.YELLOW</code>
which are public final static variables of type <code>Color</code>.
Many named constants are created just to give meaningful names to be used as parameters
in subroutine calls. For example, the
standard class named <code>Font</code> contains named constants
<code>Font.PLAIN</code>, <code>Font.BOLD</code>, and <code>Font.ITALIC</code>. These
constants are used for specifying different styles of text when calling various
subroutines in the <code>Font</code> class.</np>
   
<p>Enumerated type constants (see <localref href="basics.3.3"/>) are also examples of named
constants.  The enumerated type definition</p>
   
<pre>enum Alignment { LEFT, RIGHT, CENTER }</pre>
   
<np>defines the constants <code>Alignment.LEFT</code>, <code>Alignment.RIGHT</code>,
and <code>Alignment.CENTER</code>.  Technically, <classname>Alignment</classname> is
a class, and the three constants are public final static members of that class.  Defining the
enumerated type is similar to defining three constants of type, say, <ptype>int</ptype>:
</np>
   
<pre>public static final int ALIGNMENT_LEFT = 0;
public static final int ALIGNMENT_RIGHT = 1;
public static final int ALIGNMENT_CENTER = 2;</pre>
   
<np>In fact, this is how things were generally done before the introduction of enumerated
types, and it is what is done with the constants <code>Font.PLAIN</code>, <code>Font.BOLD</code>, 
and <code>Font.ITALIC</code> mentioned above.
Using the integer constants, you could define a variable  of type
<ptype>int</ptype> and assign it the values <code>ALIGNMENT_LEFT</code>,
<code>ALIGNMENT_RIGHT</code>, or <code>ALIGNMENT_CENTER</code> to represent different
types of alignment.  The only problem with this is that the computer has no way of
knowing that you intend the value of the variable to represent an alignment, and it
will not raise any objection if the value that is assigned to the variable is not
one of the three valid alignment values.
With the enumerated type, on the other hand, the only values
that can be assigned to a variable of type <classname>Alignment</classname> are
the constant values that are listed in the definition of the enumerated type.  
Any attempt to assign an invalid value to the variable is a syntax error which
the computer will detect when the program is compiled.  This extra
safety is one of the major advantages of enumerated types.</np> 
   
<break/>

<p>Curiously enough, one of the major reasons to use named constants is that
it's easy to change the value of a named constant. Of course, the value can't
change while the program is running. But between runs of the program, it's easy
to change the value in the source code and recompile the program. Consider the
interest rate example. It's quite possible that the value of the interest rate
is used many times throughout the program. Suppose that the bank changes the
interest rate and the program has to be modified. If the literal number 0.05
were used throughout the program, the programmer would have to track down each
place where the interest rate is used in the program and change the rate to the
new value. (This is made even harder by the fact that the number 0.05 might
occur in the program with other meanings besides the interest rate, as well as
by the fact that someone might have, say, used 0.025 to represent half the interest
rate.) On the other hand, if the named constant <code>INTEREST_RATE</code> is
declared and used consistently throughout the program, then only the single
line where the constant is initialized needs to be changed.</p>

<p>As an extended example, I will give a new version of the
<code>RandomMosaicWalk</code> program from the <localref href="subroutines.6">previous
section</localref>. This version uses named constants to represent the number of rows
in the mosaic, the number of columns, and the size of each little square. The
three constants are declared as <code>final</code> <code>static</code> member variables
with the lines:</p>

<pre>final static int ROWS = 20;        // Number of rows in mosaic.
final static int COLUMNS = 30;     // Number of columns in mosaic.
final static int SQUARE_SIZE = 15; // Size of each square in mosaic.</pre>

<p>The rest of the program is carefully modified to use the named constants.
For example, in the new version of the program, the Mosaic window is opened
with the statement</p>

<pre>Mosaic.open(ROWS, COLUMNS, SQUARE_SIZE, SQUARE_SIZE);</pre>

<np>Sometimes, it's not easy to find all the places where a named constant
needs to be used. If you don't use the named constant consistently, you've
more or less defeated the purpose.  It's always a good idea to run a program using several
different values for any named constant, to test that it works properly in all
cases.</np>

<p>Here is the complete new program, <code>RandomMosaicWalk2</code>, with all
modifications from the previous version shown in &newcodestyle;.
I've left out some of the comments to save space.
</p>

<pre>public class RandomMosaicWalk2 {

    <newcode>final static int ROWS = 20;        // Number of rows in mosaic.
    final static int COLUMNS = 30;     // Number of columns in mosaic.
    final static int SQUARE_SIZE = 15; // Size of each square in mosaic.</newcode>

    static int currentRow;    // Row currently containing the disturbance.
    static int currentColumn; // Column currently containing the disturbance.
 
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        <newcode>Mosaic.open( ROWS, COLUMNS, SQUARE_SIZE, SQUARE_SIZE )</newcode>;
        fillWithRandomColors();
        <newcode>currentRow = ROWS / 2</newcode>;   // start at center of window
        <newcode>currentColumn = COLUMNS / 2</newcode>;
        while (Mosaic.isOpen()) {
            changeToRandomColor(currentRow, currentColumn);
            randomMove();
            Mosaic.delay(1);
        }
    }  // end main

    static void fillWithRandomColors() {
         for (<newcode>int row=0; row &lt; ROWS; row++</newcode>) {
            for (<newcode>int column=0; column &lt; COLUMNS; column++</newcode>) {
                changeToRandomColor(row, column);  
            }
         }
    }  // end fillWithRandomColors
 
    static void changeToRandomColor(int rowNum, int colNum) {
         int red = (int)(256*Math.random());    // Choose random levels in range
         int green = (int)(256*Math.random());  //     0 to 255 for red, green, 
         int blue = (int)(256*Math.random());   //     and blue color components.
         Mosaic.setColor(rowNum,colNum,red,green,blue);  
     }  // end changeToRandomColor
 
     static void randomMove() {
         int directionNum; // Randomly set to 0, 1, 2, or 3 to choose direction.
         directionNum = (int)(4*Math.random());
         switch (directionNum) {
            case 0:  // move up 
               currentRow--;
               if (currentRow &lt; 0)
                  <newcode>currentRow = ROWS - 1;</newcode>
               break;
            case 1:  // move right
               currentColumn++;
               if (<newcode>currentColumn &gt;= COLUMNS</newcode>)
                  currentColumn = 0;
               break; 
            case 2:  // move down
               currentRow++;
               if (<newcode>currentRow &gt;= ROWS</newcode>)
                  currentRow = 0;
               break;
            case 3:  // move left  
               currentColumn--;
               if (currentColumn &lt; 0)
                  <newcode>currentColumn = COLUMNS - 1</newcode>;
               break; 
         }
     }  // end randomMove
 
} // end class RandomMosaicWalk2</pre>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="subroutines.7.3" title="Naming and Scope Rules">

<p>When a variable declaration is executed, memory is allocated for that
variable. The variable name can be used in at least some part of the program
source code to refer to that memory or to the data that is stored in the
memory. The portion of the program source code where the variable is valid
is called the <newword>scope</newword> of the variable. Similarly, we
can refer to the scope of subroutine names and formal parameter names.</p>

<p>For static member subroutines, scope is straightforward. The scope of a
static subroutine is the entire source code of the class in which it is
defined. That is, it is possible to call the subroutine from any point in the
class, including at a point in the source code before the point where the definition
of the subroutine appears. It is even possible to call a subroutine from within itself. This is an
example of something called "recursion," a fairly advanced topic that we will
return to in <localref href="recursion"/>.  If the subroutine is not <code>private</code>,
it can also be accessed from outside the class where it is defined, using its full name.</p>

<p>For a variable that is declared as a static member variable in a class, the
situation is similar, but with one complication. It is legal to have a local
variable or a formal parameter that has the same name as a member variable. In
that case, within the scope of the local variable or parameter, the member
variable is <newword>hidden</newword>. Consider, for example, a class
named <code>Game</code> that has the form:</p>

<pre>public class Game {

    static int count;  // member variable
 
    static void playGame() {
        int count;  // local variable
          .
          .   // Some statements to define playGame()
          .
    }
    
    .
    .   // More variables and subroutines.
    .
 
}  // end Game</pre>

<p>In the statements that make up the body of the <code>playGame()</code>
subroutine, the name "<code>count</code>" refers to the local variable. In the rest
of the <code>Game</code> class, "<code>count</code>" refers to the member variable
(unless hidden by other local variables or parameters named <code>count</code>).
However, the member variable named
<code>count</code> can also be referred to by the full name <code>Game.count</code>.
Usually, the full name is only used outside the class where <code>count</code> is
defined. However, there is no rule against using it inside the class. The full
name, <code>Game.count</code>, can be used inside the <code>playGame()</code>
subroutine to refer to the member variable instead of the local variable. 
So, the full scope rule 
is that the scope of a static member variable includes the entire
class in which it is defined, but where the simple name of the member variable
is hidden by a local variable or formal parameter name, the member variable
must be referred to by its full name of the form <bnf>className</bnf>.<bnf>variableName</bnf>. 
(Scope rules for non-static members
are similar to those for static members, except that, as we shall see,
non-static members cannot be used in static subroutines.)</p>

<p>The scope of a formal parameter of a subroutine is the block that makes up
the body of the subroutine. The scope of a local variable extends from the
declaration statement that defines the variable to the end of the block in
which the declaration occurs. As noted above, it is possible to declare a loop
control variable of a <code>for</code> loop in the <code>for</code> statement, as in
"<code>for (int i=0; i &lt; 10; i++)</code>". The scope of such a declaration is
considered as a special case: It is valid only within the <code>for</code>
statement and does not extend to the remainder of the block that contains the
<code>for</code> statement.</p>

<p>It is not legal to redefine the name of a formal parameter or local variable
within its scope, even in a nested block. For example, this is not allowed:</p>

<pre>void  badSub(int y) {
    int x;
    while (y &gt; 0) {
       int x;  // <newcode>ERROR:  x is already defined.</newcode>
         .
         .
         .
    }
 }</pre>

<np>In many languages, this would be legal; the declaration of <code>x</code> in the
<code>while</code> loop would hide the original declaration.  It is not legal in
Java; however, once the block in which a variable is declared ends, its name
does become available for reuse in Java. For example:</np>

<pre>void goodSub(int y) {
   while (y &gt; 10) {
      int x;
        .
        .
        .
      // The scope of x ends here.
   }
   while (y &gt; 0) {
      int x;  // OK: Previous declaration of x has expired.
       .
       .
       .
   }
}</pre>

<p>You might wonder whether local variable names can hide subroutine names.
This can't happen, for a reason that might be surprising. There is no rule that
variables and subroutines have to have different names. The computer can always
tell whether a name refers to a variable or to a subroutine, because a
subroutine name is always followed by a left parenthesis. It's perfectly legal
to have a variable called <code>count</code> and a subroutine called <code>count</code>
in the same class. (This is one reason why I often write subroutine names with
parentheses, as when I talk about the <code>main()</code> routine. It's a good idea
to think of the parentheses as part of the name.) Even more is true: It's legal
to reuse class names to name variables and subroutines. The syntax rules of
Java guarantee that the computer can always tell when a name is being used as a
class name. A class name is a type, and so it can be used to declare variables and formal parameters
and to specify the return type of a function. This means that you could legally
have a class called <code>Insanity</code> in which you declare a function</p>

<pre>static  Insanity  Insanity( Insanity Insanity ) { ... }</pre>

<p>The first <code>Insanity</code> is the return type of the function. The second
is the function name, the third is the type of the formal parameter, and the
fourth is the name of the formal parameter. However, please remember that not everything
that is possible is a good idea!</p>
   
</subsection>

<endchapter/>

</section>