<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="robustness.1" title="Introduction to Correctness and Robustness">

<p><start><big>A</big> program</start> is <newword>correct</newword>
if it accomplishes the task that it was designed to perform. 
It is <newword>robust</newword> if it can handle illegal inputs and other unexpected
situations in a reasonable way. For example, consider a program that is
designed to read some numbers from the user and then print the same numbers in
sorted order. The program is correct if it works for any set of input numbers.
It is robust if it can also deal with non-numeric input by, for example,
printing an error message and ignoring the bad input. A non-robust program
might crash or give nonsensical output in the same circumstance.</p>

<p>Every program should be correct. (A sorting program that doesn't sort
correctly is pretty useless.) It's not the case that every program needs to be
completely robust. It depends on who will use it and how it will be used. For
example, a small utility program that you write for your own use doesn't have
to be particularly robust.</p>

<p>The question of correctness is actually more subtle than it might appear. A
programmer works from a specification of what the program is supposed to do.
The programmer's work is correct if the program meets its specification. But
does that mean that the program itself is correct? What if the specification is
incorrect or incomplete? A correct program should be a correct implementation
of a complete and correct specification. The question is whether the
specification correctly expresses the intention and desires of the people for
whom the program is being written. This is a question that lies largely outside
the domain of computer science.</p>

<subsection id="robustness.1.1" title="Horror Stories">

<p>Most computer users have personal experience with programs that don't work
or that crash. In many cases, such problems are just annoyances, but even on a
personal computer there can be more serious consequences, such as lost work or
lost money. When computers are given more important tasks, the consequences of
failure can be proportionately more serious.</p>

<p>About twenty-three years ago, the failure of two multi-million dollar space missions to
Mars was prominent in the news. Both failures were probably due to software
problems, but in both cases the problem was not with an incorrect program as
such. In September 1999, the Mars Climate Orbiter burned up in the Martian
atmosphere because data that was expressed in English units of measurement
(such as feet and pounds) was entered into a computer program that was designed
to use metric units (such as centimeters and grams). A few months later, the
Mars Polar Lander probably crashed because its software turned off its landing
engines too soon. The program was supposed to detect the bump when the
spacecraft landed and turn off the engines then. It has been determined that
deployment of the landing gear might have jarred the spacecraft enough to
activate the program, causing it to turn off the engines when the spacecraft
was still high above the ground. The unpowered spacecraft would then have fallen to the
Martian surface. A more robust system would have checked the altitude before
turning off the engines!</p>

<p>There are many equally dramatic stories of problems caused by incorrect or
poorly written software. Let's look at a few incidents recounted in the book
<i>Computer Ethics</i> by Tom Forester and Perry Morrison. (This book
covers various ethical issues in computing. It, or something like it, is
essential reading for any student of computer science.)</p>

<ul>
<li>In 1985 and 1986, one person was killed and several were injured by excess
radiation, while undergoing radiation treatments by a mis-programmed
computerized radiation machine. In another case, over a ten-year period ending
in 1992, almost 1,000 cancer patients received radiation dosages that were 30%
less than prescribed because of a programming error.</li>
<li>In 1985, a computer at the Bank of New York started destroying records of
on-going security transactions because of an error in a program. It took less
than 24 hours to fix the program, but by that time, the bank was out $5,000,000
in overnight interest payments on funds that it had to borrow to cover the
problem.</li>
<li>The programming of the inertial guidance system of the F-16 fighter plane
would have turned the plane upside-down when it crossed the equator, if the
problem had not been discovered in simulation. The Mariner 18 space probe was
lost because of an error in one line of a program. The Gemini V space capsule
missed its scheduled landing target by a hundred miles, because a programmer
forgot to take into account the rotation of the Earth.</li>
<li>In 1990, AT&amp;T's long-distance telephone service was disrupted throughout
the United States when a newly loaded computer program proved to contain a
bug.</li>
</ul>

<p>Of course, there have been more recent problems.  For example, 
computer software error contributed to the 
<tex>Northeast Blackout</tex><web><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northeast_Blackout_of_2003">Northeast&nbsp;Blackout</a></web>
of 2003, one of the largest power outages in history. 
In 2006, the Airbus A380 was <tex>delayed</tex><web><a href="http://www.cadalyst.com/cad/product-design/what-grounded-airbus-a380-10903">delayed</a></web>
by software incompatibility problems, at a cost of perhaps billions of dollars.
In 2007, a software problem grounded thousands of planes at the Los Angeles International Airport.
On May 6, 2010,
a flaw in an automatic trading program apparently <tex>resulted in</tex>
<web><a href="http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9189179/Regulators_blame_computer_algorithm_for_stock_market_flash_crash_">resulted&nbsp;in</a></web> a 1000-point drop
in the Dow Jones Industrial Average.</p>

<p>These are just a few examples. Software problems are all too common. As
programmers, we need to understand why that is true and what can be done about
it.</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="robustness.1.2" title="Java to the Rescue">

<p>Part of the problem, according to the inventors of Java, can be traced to
programming languages themselves. Java was designed to provide some protection
against certain types of errors. How can a language feature help prevent
errors? Let's look at a few examples.</p>

<p>Some programming languages do not require variables to be declared. In
such languages, when a variable name is used in a program, the variable is
created automatically. You might consider this more convenient than having to
declare every variable explicitly, but there is an unfortunate consequence: An
inadvertent spelling error might introduce an extra variable that you had no
intention of creating. This type of error was responsible, according to one
famous story, for yet another lost spacecraft. In the <code>FORTRAN</code>
programming language, the command "<code>DO 20 I = 1,5</code>" is the first
statement of a counting loop. Now, spaces are insignificant in <code>FORTRAN</code>, so this
is equivalent to "<code>DO20I=1,5</code>". On the other hand, the command
"<code>DO20I=1.5</code>", with a period instead of a comma, is an assignment
statement that assigns the value <code>1.5</code> to the variable <code>DO20I</code>.
Supposedly, the inadvertent substitution of a period for a comma in a statement
of this type caused a rocket to blow up on take-off. Because <code>FORTRAN</code>
doesn't require variables to be declared, the compiler would be happy to accept
the statement "<code>DO20I=1.5</code>." It would just create a new variable named
<code>DO20I</code>. If <code>FORTRAN</code> required variables to be declared, the
compiler would have complained that the variable <code>DO20I</code> was
undeclared.</p>

<p>While most programming languages today do require variables to be declared,
there are other features in common programming languages that can cause
problems. Java has eliminated some of these features. Some people complain that
this makes Java less efficient and less powerful. While there is some justice
in this criticism, the increase in security and robustness is probably worth
the cost in most circumstances. The best defense against some types of errors
is to design a programming language in which the errors are impossible. In
other cases, where the error can't be completely eliminated, the language can
be designed so that when the error does occur, it will automatically be
detected. This will at least prevent the error from causing further harm, and
it will alert the programmer that there is a bug that needs fixing. Let's look
at a few cases where the designers of Java have taken these approaches.</p>

<p>An array is created with a certain number of locations, numbered from zero
up to some specified maximum index. It is an error to try to use an array
location that is outside of the specified range. In Java, any attempt to do so
is detected automatically by the system. In some other languages, such as C and
C++, it's up to the programmer to make sure that the index is within the legal
range. Suppose that an array, <code>A</code>, has three locations, <code>A[0]</code>,
<code>A[1]</code>, and <code>A[2]</code>. Then <code>A[3]</code>, <code>A[4]</code>, and so on
refer to memory locations beyond the end of the array. In Java, an attempt to
store data in <code>A[3]</code> will be detected. The program will be terminated
(unless the error is "caught", as discussed in <localref href="control.7"/>). 
In C or C++, the computer will just go ahead and store the data in
memory that is not part of the array. Since there is no telling what that
memory location is being used for, the result will be unpredictable. The
consequences could be much more serious than a terminated program. (See, for
example, the discussion of buffer overflow errors later in this section.)</p>

<p>Pointers are a notorious source of programming errors. In Java, a variable
of object type holds either a pointer to an object or the special value
<code>null</code>. Any attempt to use a <code>null</code> value as if it were a pointer
to an actual object will be detected by the system. In some other languages,
again, it's up to the programmer to avoid such null pointer errors. In my first
Macintosh computer, a long time ago, a <code>null</code> pointer was actually implemented as if it
were a pointer to memory location zero. A program could use a null pointer to
change values stored in memory near location zero. Unfortunately, the Macintosh
stored important system data in those locations. Changing that data could cause
the whole system to crash, a consequence more severe than a single failed
program.</p>

<p>Another type of pointer error occurs when a pointer value is pointing to an
object of the wrong type or to a segment of memory that does not even hold a
valid object at all. These types of errors are impossible in Java, which does
not allow programmers to manipulate pointers directly. In other languages, it
is possible to set a pointer to point, essentially, to any location in memory.
If this is done incorrectly, then using the pointer can have unpredictable
results.</p>

<p>Another type of error that cannot occur in Java is a memory leak. In Java,
once there are no longer any pointers that refer to an object, that object is
"garbage collected" so that the memory that it occupied can be reused. In other
languages, it is the programmer's responsibility to return unused memory to the
system. If the programmer fails to do this, unused memory can build up, leaving
less memory for programs and data. There is a story that many common programs
for older Windows computers had so many memory leaks that the computer would run out
of memory after a few days of use and would have to be restarted.</p>

<p>Many programs have been found to suffer from <newword>buffer overflow errors</newword>. 
Buffer overflow errors often make the news because they
are responsible for many network security problems. When one computer receives
data from another computer over a network, that data is stored in a buffer. The
buffer is just a segment of memory that has been allocated by a program to hold
data that it expects to receive. A buffer overflow occurs when more data is
received than will fit in the buffer. The question is, what happens then? If
the error is detected by the program or by the networking software, then the
only thing that has happened is a failed network data transmission. The real
problem occurs when the software does not properly detect buffer overflows. In
that case, the software continues to store data in memory even after the buffer
is filled, and the extra data goes into some part of memory that was not
allocated by the program as part of the buffer. That memory might be in use for
some other purpose. It might contain important data. It might even contain part
of the program itself. This is where the real security issues come in. Suppose
that a buffer overflow causes part of a program to be replaced with extra data
received over a network. When the computer goes to execute the part of the
program that was replaced, it's actually executing data that was received from
another computer. That data could be anything. It could be a program that
crashes the computer or takes it over. A malicious programmer who finds a
convenient buffer overflow error in networking software can try to exploit that
error to trick other computers into executing his programs.</p>

<p>For software written completely in Java, buffer overflow errors are
impossible. The language simply does not provide any way to store data into
memory that has not been properly allocated. To do that, you would need a
pointer that points to unallocated memory or you would have to refer to an
array location that lies outside the range allocated for the array. As
explained above, neither of these is possible in Java. (However, there could
conceivably still be errors in Java's standard classes, since some of the
methods in these classes are actually written in the C programming language
rather than in Java.  In fact, Java's internal security errors have at
times been a problem for the language.)</p>

<p>It's clear that language design can help prevent errors or detect them when
they occur. Doing so involves restricting what a programmer is allowed to do.
Or it requires tests, such as checking whether a pointer is <code>null</code>, that
take some extra processing time. Some programmers feel that the sacrifice of
power and efficiency is too high a price to pay for the extra security. In some
applications, this is true. However, there are many situations where safety and
security are primary considerations. Java is designed for such situations.</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="robustness.1.3" title="Problems Remain in Java">

<p>There is one area where the designers of Java chose not to detect errors
automatically: numerical computations. In Java, a value of type <ptype>int</ptype> is
represented as a 32-bit binary number. With 32 bits, it's possible to represent
a little over four billion different values. The values of type <ptype>int</ptype>
range from -2147483648 to 2147483647. What happens when the result of a
computation lies outside this range? For example, what is
<code>2147483647&nbsp;+&nbsp;1</code>? And what is <code>2000000000&nbsp;*&nbsp;2</code>? The
mathematically correct result in each case cannot be represented as a value of
type <ptype>int</ptype>. These are examples of <newword>integer overflow</newword>. 
In most cases, integer overflow should be considered an error.
However, Java does not automatically detect such errors. For example, it will
compute the value of <code>2147483647&nbsp;+&nbsp;1</code> to be the negative number,
<code>-2147483648</code>. (What happens is that any extra bits beyond the 32-nd bit in the
correct answer are discarded. Values greater than 2147483647 will "wrap around"
to negative values. Mathematically speaking, the result is always "correct
modulo 2<sup>32</sup>.")</p>

<p>For example, consider the 3N+1 program, which was discussed in
<localref href="control.2.2"/>. Starting from a positive integer
<code>N</code>, the program computes a certain sequence of integers:</p>

<pre>while ( N != 1 ) {
   if ( N % 2 == 0 )  // If N is even...
      N = N / 2;
   else
      N = 3 * N + 1;
   System.out.println(N);
}</pre>

<np>But there is a problem here: If <code>N</code> is too large, then the value of
<code>3*N+1</code> will not be mathematically correct because of integer overflow.
The problem arises whenever <code>3*N+1 &gt; 2147483647</code>, that is when <code>N
&gt; 2147483646/3</code>. For a completely correct program, we should check for
this possibility <b>before</b> computing <code>3*N+1</code>:</np>

<pre>while ( N != 1 ) {
   if ( N % 2 == 0 )  // If N is even...
      N = N / 2;
   else {
      if (N &gt; 2147483646/3) {
         System.out.println("Sorry, but the value of N has become");
         System.out.println("too large for your computer!");
         break;
      }
      N = 3 * N + 1;
   }
   System.out.println(N);
}</pre>

<p>(Be sure you understand why we can't just test "<code>if (3*N+1 &gt; 2147483647)</code>".)
The problem here is not that the original algorithm for computing
<code>3N+1</code> sequences was wrong. The problem is that it just can't be
correctly implemented using 32-bit integers. Many programs ignore this type of
problem. But integer overflow errors have been responsible for their share of
serious computer failures, and a completely robust program should take the
possibility of integer overflow into account. (The infamous "Y2K" bug at the start of
the year 2000 was, in fact, just this sort of error.)</p>

<p>For numbers of type <ptype>double</ptype>, there are even more problems. There are
still overflow errors, which occur when the result of a computation is outside
the range of values that can be represented as a value of type <ptype>double</ptype>.
This range extends up to about 1.7 times 10 to the power 308. Numbers beyond
this range do not "wrap around" to negative values. Instead, they are
represented by special values that have no real numerical equivalent. The special values
<code>Double.POSITIVE_INFINITY</code> and <code>Double.NEGATIVE_INFINITY</code>
represent numbers outside the range of legal values. For example, <code>20&nbsp;*&nbsp;1e308</code> is
computed to be <code>Double.POSITIVE_INFINITY</code>. Another special value of type
<ptype>double</ptype>, <code>Double.NaN</code>, represents an illegal or undefined
result. ("NaN" stands for "Not a Number".) For example, the result of dividing zero
by zero or taking the square root of a negative number is <code>Double.NaN</code>.
You can test whether a number <code>x</code> is this special not-a-number value by
calling the <ptype>boolean</ptype>-valued function <code>Double.isNaN(x)</code>.</p>

<p>For real numbers, there is the added complication that most real numbers can
only be represented approximately on a computer. A real number can have an
infinite number of digits after the decimal point. A value of type
<ptype>double</ptype> is only accurate to about 15 digits. The real number 1/3, for
example, is the repeating decimal <code>0.333333333333...</code>, and there is no way to
represent it exactly using a finite number of digits. Computations with real
numbers generally involve a loss of accuracy. In fact, if care is not
exercised, the result of a large number of such computations might be
completely wrong! There is a whole field of computer science, known as
<newword>numerical analysis</newword>, which is devoted to studying
algorithms that manipulate real numbers.</p>


<p>So you see that not all possible errors are avoided or detected automatically in Java. 
Furthermore, even when an error is detected automatically, the system's default response is
to report the error and terminate the program. This is hardly robust behavior!
So, a Java programmer still needs to learn techniques for avoiding and dealing with
errors. These are the main topics of the next three sections.</p>

</subsection>
      
</section>