<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="robustness.3" title="Exceptions and try..catch">
   
<p><start><big>G</big>etting a program to work</start> under ideal circumstances
is usually a lot easier than making the program <newword>robust</newword>. 
A robust program can survive unusual or "exceptional"
circumstances without crashing. One approach to writing robust programs is to
anticipate the problems that might arise and to include tests in the program
for each possible problem. For example, a program will crash if it tries to use
an array element <code>A[i]</code>, when <code>i</code> is not within the declared
range of indices for the array <code>A</code>. A robust program must anticipate the
possibility of a bad index and guard against it.  One way to do this is to
write the program in a way that ensures (as a postcondition of the code that
precedes the array reference) that the index is in the legal range.
Another way is to test whether the index value is legal before using it in the array.
This could be done with an <code>if</code> statement:</p>

<pre>if (i &lt; 0 || i &gt;= A.length) {
   ...  // Do something to handle the out-of-range index, i
}
else {
   ...  // Process the array element, A[i]
}</pre>

<np>There are some problems with this approach. It is difficult and sometimes
impossible to anticipate all the possible things that might go wrong. It's not
always clear what to do when an error is detected. Furthermore, trying to
anticipate all the possible problems can turn what would otherwise be a
straightforward algorithm into a messy tangle of <code>if</code> statements.</np>
   
<subsection id="robustness.3.1" title="Exceptions and Exception Classes">

<p>We have already seen in <localref href="control.7"/>
that Java provides a neater, more structured alternative
technique for dealing with errors that can occur while a program is running. The
technique is referred to as <newword>exception handling</newword>.  The
word "exception" is meant to be more general than "error." It includes any
circumstance that arises as the program is executed which is meant to be
treated as an exception to the normal flow of control of the program. An
exception might be an error, or it might just be a special case that you would
rather not have clutter up your elegant algorithm.</p>

<p>When an exception occurs during the execution of a program, we say that the
exception is <newword>thrown</newword>. When this happens, the normal
flow of the program is thrown off-track, and the program is in danger of
crashing. However, the crash can be avoided if the exception is 
<newword>caught</newword> and handled in some way.  An exception can be thrown in
one part of a program and caught in a different part. An exception that is not
caught will generally cause the program to crash. (More exactly, the thread
that throws the exception will crash. In a multithreaded program, it is
possible for other threads to continue even after one crashes.  We will
cover threads in <localref href="threads"/>. In particular, GUI
programs are multithreaded, and parts of the program might continue to
function even while other parts are non-functional because of exceptions.)</p>

<p>By the way, since Java programs are executed by a Java interpreter, having a
program crash simply means that it terminates abnormally and prematurely. It
doesn't mean that the Java interpreter will crash. In effect, the interpreter
catches any exceptions that are not caught by the program. The interpreter
responds by terminating the program. In many other programming languages, a
crashed program will sometimes crash the entire system and freeze the computer
until it is restarted. With Java, such system crashes should be impossible&mdash;which 
means that when they happen, you have the satisfaction of blaming the
system rather than your own program.</p>

<p>Exceptions were introduced in <localref href="control.7"/>, along with the
<code>try..catch</code> statement, which is used to catch and handle exceptions.
However, that section did not cover the complete syntax of <code>try..catch</code>
or the full complexity of exceptions.  In this section, we cover these topics in
full detail.</p>
   
<break/>
   
<p>When an exception occurs, the thing that is actually "thrown" is an object.
This object can carry information (in its instance variables) from the point
where the exception occurs to the point where it is caught and handled. This
information always includes the <newword>subroutine call stack</newword>, 
which is a list of the subroutines that were being executed when
the exception was thrown. (Since one subroutine can call another, several
subroutines can be active at the same time.) Typically, an exception object
also includes an error message describing what happened to cause the exception,
and it can contain other data as well.   All exception objects must belong to
a subclass of the standard class <code>java.lang.Throwable</code>. 
In general, each different type of exception is represented by
its own subclass of <classname>Throwable</classname>, and these subclasses
are arranged in a fairly complex class hierarchy that shows the relationship
among various types of exception.
<classname>Throwable</classname> has two direct
subclasses, <classname>Error</classname> and <classname>Exception</classname>. 
These two subclasses in turn
have many other predefined subclasses. In addition, a programmer can create new
exception classes to represent new types of exception.</p>

<p>Most of the subclasses of the class <classname>Error</classname> represent serious errors
within the Java virtual machine that should ordinarily cause program
termination because there is no reasonable way to handle them. In general, you should not
try to catch and handle such errors.  An example is a
<classname>ClassFormatError</classname>, which occurs when the Java virtual machine finds
some kind of illegal data in a file that is supposed to contain a compiled Java
class. If that class was being loaded as part of the program, then there is
really no way for the program to proceed.</p>

<p>On the other hand, subclasses of the class <classname>Exception</classname> represent
exceptions that are meant to be caught. In many cases, these are exceptions
that might naturally be called "errors," but they are errors in the program or
in input data that a programmer can anticipate and possibly respond to in some
reasonable way. (However, you should avoid the temptation of saying, "Well,
I'll just put a thing here to catch all the errors that might occur, so my
program won't crash." If you don't have a reasonable way to respond to the
error, it's best just to let the program crash, because trying to go on
will probably only lead to worse things down the road&mdash;in the worst case, a
program that gives an incorrect answer without giving you any indication that
the answer might be wrong!)</p>

<p>The class <classname>Exception</classname> has its own subclass,
<classname>RuntimeException</classname>. This class groups together many common exceptions,
including all those that have been covered in previous sections.  For example,
<classname>IllegalArgumentException</classname> and <classname>NullPointerException</classname>
are subclasses of <classname>RuntimeException</classname>.
A <classname>RuntimeException</classname> generally
indicates a bug in the program, which the programmer should fix.
<classname>RuntimeExceptions</classname> and <classname>Errors</classname> share the property that a
program can simply ignore the possibility that they might occur. ("Ignoring"
here means that you are content to let your program crash if the exception
occurs.) For example, a program does this every time it uses an array reference
like <code>A[i]</code> without making arrangements to catch a possible
<classname>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</classname>. For all other exception classes
besides <classname>Error</classname>, <classname>RuntimeException</classname>, and their subclasses,
exception-handling is "mandatory" in a sense that I'll discuss below.</p>

<p>The following diagram is a class hierarchy showing the class
<code>Throwable</code> and just a few of its subclasses. Classes that require
mandatory exception-handling are shown in red:</p>

<img src="exception-hierarchy.png" width="561" height="347" tex="exception-hierarchy.eps" texscale="0.7"
   alt="Partial class hierarchy for Throwable objects" bordered="true" />
   
<p>The class <classname>Throwable</classname> includes several instance methods that can
be used with any exception object.  If <code>e</code> is of type <classname>Throwable</classname>
(or one of its subclasses), then <code>e.getMessage()</code> is a function that returns a
<classname>String</classname> that describes the exception.  The function <code>e.toString()</code>,
which is used by the system whenever it needs a string representation of the object,
returns a <classname>String</classname> that contains the name of the class to which the
exception belongs as well as the same string that would be returned by <code>e.getMessage()</code>.
And the method <code>e.printStackTrace()</code> writes a stack trace to standard output that tells
which subroutines were active when the exception occurred.
A stack trace can be very useful when you
are trying to determine the cause of the problem.  (Note that if an exception is <b>not</b>
caught by the program, then the default response to the exception  prints the stack trace to standard output.)</p>

</subsection>
   
<subsection id="robustness.3.2" title="The try Statement">
   
<p>To catch exceptions in a Java program, you need a <code>try</code> statement.
We have been using such statements since <localref href="control.7"/>, but the
full syntax of the <code>try</code> statement is more complicated than what
was presented there.  The <code>try</code> statements that we have used so
far had a syntax similar to the following example:</p>

<pre>try {
    double determinant = M[0][0]*M[1][1] - M[0][1]*M[1][0];
    System.out.println("The determinant of M is " + determinant);
}
catch ( ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException e ) {
   System.out.println("M is the wrong size to have a determinant.");
   e.printStackTrace();
}</pre>

<np>Here, the computer tries to execute the block of statements following the word
"<code>try</code>". If no exception occurs during the execution of this block, then
the "<code>catch</code>" part of the statement is simply ignored. However, if an
exception of type
<classname>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</classname> occurs, then the computer jumps
immediately to the <code>catch</code> clause of the <code>try</code> statement.
This block of statements is said to be an <newword>exception handler</newword> for
<classname>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</classname>. By handling the exception in this way,
you prevent it from crashing the program.  Before the body of the <code>catch</code> clause
is executed, the object that represents the exception is assigned to the variable <code>e</code>,
which is used in this example to print a stack trace.</np>
   
<p>However, the full syntax of the <code>try</code> statement has many options.
It will take a while to go through them.  For one thing, a <code>try..catch</code>
statement can have more than one
<code>catch</code> clause.  This makes it possible to catch several different types
of exception with one <code>try</code> statement.  In the above example, in addition
to the possible <classname>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</classname>, there is a
possible <classname>NullPointerException</classname> which will occur if the value
of <code>M</code> is <code>null</code>.  We can handle both possible exceptions by
adding a second <code>catch</code> clause to the <code>try</code> statement:</p>

<pre>try {
    double determinant = M[0][0]*M[1][1] - M[0][1]*M[1][0];
    System.out.println("The determinant of M is " + determinant);
}
catch ( ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException e ) {
   System.out.println("M is the wrong size to have a determinant.");
}
catch ( NullPointerException e ) {
   System.out.print("Programming error!  M doesn't exist." + );
}</pre>
   
<p>Here, the computer tries to execute the statements in the <code>try</code> clause.
If no error occurs, both of the <code>catch</code> clauses are skipped.  If an
<classname>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</classname> occurs, the computer executes
the body of the first <code>catch</code> clause and skips the second one.  If a
<classname>NullPointerException</classname> occurs, it jumps to the second
<code>catch</code> clause and executes that.</p>

<p>Note that both <classname>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</classname> and
<classname>NullPointerException</classname> are subclasses of <classname>RuntimeException</classname>. It's
possible to catch all <classname>RuntimeExceptions</classname> with a single <code>catch</code>
clause. For example:</p>

<pre>try {
    double determinant = M[0][0]*M[1][1] - M[0][1]*M[1][0];
    System.out.println("The determinant of M is " + determinant);
}
catch ( RuntimeException err ) {
   System.out.println("Sorry, an error has occurred.");
   System.out.println("The error was: " + err);
}</pre>

<np>The <code>catch</code> clause in this <code>try</code> statement will catch
any exception belonging to class <classname>RuntimeException</classname> or to
any of its subclasses.  This shows why exception classes are organized into a
class hierarchy. It allows you the option of casting your net narrowly to catch
only a specific type of exception. Or you can cast your net widely to catch a
wide class of exceptions.  Because of subclassing, when there are multiple <code>catch</code> clauses
in a <code>try</code> statement, it is possible that a given exception might
match several of those <code>catch</code> clauses.  For example, an exception of
type <classname>NullPointerException</classname> would match <code>catch</code>
clauses for <classname>NullPointerException</classname>, <classname>RuntimeException</classname>,
<classname>Exception</classname>, or <classname>Throwable</classname>.  In this
case, only the <b>first</b> <code>catch</code> clause that matches the exception
is executed.</np>

<p>Of course, catching <classname>RuntimeException</classname> would catch many more
types of exception than the two that we are interested in.  It is possible to
combine several specific exception types in a single <code>catch</code> clause.
For example,</p>

<pre>try {
    double determinant = M[0][0]*M[1][1] - M[0][1]*M[1][0];
    System.out.println("The determinant of M is " + determinant);
}
catch ( <newcode>NullPointerException</newcode> | <newcode>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</newcode> err ) {
   System.out.println("Sorry, an error has occurred.");
   System.out.println("The error was: " + err);
}</pre>

<np>Here, the two exception types are combined with a&nbsp;"<code>|</code>", the vertical line
character that is also used in the boolean <b>or</b> operator.  This example
will catch errors of type <classname>NullPointerException</classname>
or <classname>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</classname>, and no other types.</np>

<p>The example I've been using here is not realistic, because you are not very
likely to use exception-handling to guard against null pointers and bad array
indices. This is a case where careful programming is better than exception
handling: Just be sure that your program assigns a reasonable,
non-<code>null</code> value to the array <code>M</code>. You would certainly resent it
if the designers of Java forced you to set up a <code>try..catch</code>
statement every time you wanted to use an array! This is why handling of
potential <classname>RuntimeExceptions</classname> is not mandatory. There are just too many
things that might go wrong! (This also shows that exception-handling does not
solve the problem of program robustness. It just gives you a tool that will in
many cases let you approach the problem in a more organized way.)</p>
   
<break/>
   
<p>I have still not completely specified the syntax of the <code>try</code> statement.
The next variation is the possibility of a <newword>finally clause</newword>
at the end of a <code>try</code> statement.  With this addition, syntax of the <code>try</code>
statement can be described as:</p>

<pre>try {
   <bnf>statements</bnf>
}
<bnf>optional-catch-clauses</bnf>
<bnf>optional-finally-clause</bnf></pre>

<np>Note that the <code>catch</code> clauses are also listed as optional.
The <code>try</code> statement can include zero or more <code>catch</code> clauses and,
optionally, a <code>finally</code> clause.  The <code>try</code> statement <b>must</b> include
one or the other.  That is, a <code>try</code> statement can have
either a <code>finally</code> clause, or one or more <code>catch</code> clauses, or both.  The
syntax for a <code>catch</code> clause is</np>

<pre>catch ( <bnf>exception-class-names</bnf> <bnf>variable-name</bnf> ) {
   <bnf>statements</bnf>
}</pre>

<np>where <bnf>exception-class-names</bnf> can be a single exception class or several classes separated
by&nbsp;"<code>|</code>".
The syntax for a <code>finally</code> clause is</np>

<pre>finally {
   <bnf>statements</bnf>
}</pre>

<p>The semantics of the <code>finally</code> clause is that the block of statements
in the <code>finally</code> clause is guaranteed to be executed as the last step in
the execution of the try statement, whether or not any exception occurs and
whether or not any exception that does occur is caught and handled. The
<code>finally</code> clause is meant for doing essential cleanup that under no
circumstances should be omitted.  One example of this type of cleanup is
closing a network connection.  Although you don't yet know enough about networking
to look at the actual programming in this case, we can consider some pseudocode:</p>
   
<pre>try {
   open a network connection
   communicate over the connection
}
catch ( IOException e ) {
   report the error
}
finally {
   if the connection was successfully opened
      close the connection
}</pre>
   
<np>The <code>finally</code> clause
ensures that the network connection will definitely be closed, whether or
not an error occurs during the communication.  The pseudocode in this
example follows a general pattern that can be used to robustly obtain a resource, 
use the resource, and then release the resource.</np>

<break/>

<p>The pattern of obtaining a resource, then using the resource, and then releasing
the resource is very common.  Note that the resource can only be released if no error occurred
while obtaining it.  And, if it was successfully obtained, then it should be
closed whether or not an error occurs while using it.  This pattern is so common
that it leads to one last option in the <code>try</code> statement syntax.
With this option, you only need code to obtain the resource, and you don't need
to worry about releasing it.  That will happen automatically at the end of the
<code>try</code> statement.</p>

<p>In order for this to work, the resource must be represented by an object that
implements an interface named <classname>AutoCloseable</classname>, which defines
a single method named <code>close()</code>, with no parameters.  Standard Java
classes that represent things like files and network connections already implement
<classname>AutoClosable</classname>.  So does the <classname>Scanner</classname>
class, which was introduced in <localref href="basics.4.6"/>.  In that section, 
I showed how to use a Scanner to read from <code>System.in</code>.  Although
I didn't do it in that section, it's considered good form to close a Scanner
after using it.  Here is an example that uses the  pattern in a 
<code>try</code> statement to make sure that the Scanner is closed automatically:</p>

<pre>try( Scanner in = new Scanner(System.in) ) {
    // Use the Scanner to read from standard input
}
catch (Exception e) {
    // ... some error occurred while using the Scanner
}</pre>

<np>The statement that allocates the <classname>Scanner</classname> goes in parentheses after
the word "try".  The statement must have the form of a variable declaration
that includes an initialization of the variable.  The variable is
local to the <code>try</code> statement.  (You can actually declare several
variables in the parentheses, separated by semicolons.)  In this 
example, we can be sure that <code>in.close()</code> will definitely be
called by the system at the end of the <code>try</code> statement, as long
as the Scanner was successfully initialized.</np>

<p>This is all getting quite complicated, and I won't continue the discussion
here.  The sample program <sourceref href="TryStatementDemo.java"/> demonstrates
a <code>try</code> statement with all its options, and it includes a lot of comments
to help you understand what can happen when you run the program.</p>



</subsection>
   
<subsection id="robustness.3.3" title="Throwing Exceptions">

<p>There are times when it makes sense for a program to deliberately throw an
exception. This is the case when the program discovers some sort of exceptional
or error condition, but there is no reasonable way to handle the error at the
point where the problem is discovered. The program can throw an exception in
the hope that some other part of the program will catch and handle the
exception.  This can be done with a <newword>throw statement</newword>.
You have already seen an example of this in <localref href="subroutines.3.6"/>.
In this section, we cover the <code>throw</code> statement more fully.
The syntax of the <code>throw</code> statement is:</p>

<pre>throw  <bnf>exception-object</bnf> ;</pre>

<np>The <bnf>exception-object</bnf> must be an object
belonging to one of the subclasses of <code>Throwable</code>. Usually, it will in
fact belong to one of the subclasses of <code>Exception</code>. In most cases, it
will be a newly constructed object created with the <code>new</code> operator. For
example:</np>

<pre>throw new ArithmeticException("Division by zero");</pre>

<np>The parameter in the constructor becomes the error message in the exception
object; if <code>e</code> refers to the object, the error message can be retrieved
by calling <code>e.getMessage()</code>.
(You might find this example a bit odd, because you might expect the
system itself to throw an <classname>ArithmeticException</classname> when an attempt is made
to divide by zero. So why should a programmer bother to throw the exception?
Recall that if the numbers that are being divided are of
type <ptype>int</ptype>, then division by zero will indeed throw an
<classname>ArithmeticException</classname>. However, no arithmetic operations with
floating-point numbers will ever produce an exception. Instead, the special
value <code>Double.NaN</code> is used to represent the result of an illegal
operation.  In some situations, you might prefer to throw an 
<classname>ArithmeticException</classname> when a real number is divided by zero.)</np>

<p>An exception can be thrown either by the system or by a <code>throw</code>
statement. The exception is processed in exactly the same way in either case.
Suppose that the exception is thrown inside a <code>try</code> statement. If that
<code>try</code> statement has a <code>catch</code> clause that handles that type of
exception, then the computer jumps to the <code>catch</code> clause and executes
it. The exception has been <newword>handled</newword>. After handling
the exception, the computer executes the <code>finally</code> clause of the
<code>try</code> statement, if there is one. It then continues normally with the
rest of the program, which follows the <code>try</code> statement. If the exception
is not immediately caught and handled, the processing of the exception will
continue.</p>

<p>When an exception is thrown during the execution of a subroutine and the
exception is not handled in the same subroutine, then that subroutine is
terminated (after the execution of any pending <code>finally</code> clauses). Then
the routine that called that subroutine gets a chance to handle the exception.
That is, if the subroutine was called inside a <code>try</code> statement that has
an appropriate <code>catch</code> clause, then <b>that</b> <code>catch</code> clause will be
executed and the program will continue on normally from there. Again, if the second
routine does not handle the exception, then it also is terminated and the
routine that called <b>it</b> (if any) gets the next shot at the exception. The
exception will crash the program only if it passes up through the entire chain
of subroutine calls without being handled.  This is called "unwinding the call stack."</p>

<p>A subroutine that might generate an exception can announce this fact by
adding a clause "<code>throws</code> <bnf>exception-class-name</bnf>" 
to the header of the routine. For example:</p>

<pre>/**
 * Returns the larger of the two roots of the quadratic equation
 * A*x*x + B*x + C = 0, provided it has any roots.  If A == 0 or
 * if the discriminant, B*B - 4*A*C, is negative, then an exception
 * of type IllegalArgumentException is thrown.
 */
static public double root( double A, double B, double C ) 
                              <newcode>throws IllegalArgumentException</newcode> {
    if (A == 0) {
      throw new IllegalArgumentException("A can't be zero.");
    }
    else {
       double disc = B*B - 4*A*C;
       if (disc &lt; 0)
          throw new IllegalArgumentException("Discriminant &lt; zero.");
       return  (-B + Math.sqrt(disc)) / (2*A);
    }
}</pre>

<p>As discussed in the <localref href="robustness.2">previous section</localref>, 
the computation
in this subroutine has the preconditions that <code>A&nbsp;!=&nbsp;0</code> and <code>B*B-4*A*C
&gt;=&nbsp;0</code>. The subroutine throws an exception of type
<classname>IllegalArgumentException</classname> when either of these preconditions is
violated. When an illegal condition is found in a subroutine, throwing an
exception is often a reasonable response.  If the program that called the
subroutine knows some good way to handle the error, it can catch the exception.
If not, the program will crash&mdash;and the programmer will know that the program
needs to be fixed.</p>
   
<p>A <code>throws</code> clause in a subroutine heading can declare several different
types of exception, separated by commas.  For example:</p>
   
<pre>void processArray(int[] A) throws NullPointerException, 
                                         ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException { ...</pre>

</subsection>

<subsection id="robustness.3.4" title="Mandatory Exception Handling">

<p>In the preceding example, declaring that the subroutine <code>root()</code> can
throw an <classname>IllegalArgumentException</classname> is just a courtesy to potential
readers of this routine. This is because handling of
<classname>IllegalArgumentExceptions</classname> is not "mandatory." A routine can throw an
<classname>IllegalArgumentException</classname> without announcing the possibility. And a
program that calls that routine is free either to catch or to ignore the
exception, just as a programmer can choose either to catch or to ignore an
exception of type <classname>NullPointerException</classname>.</p>

<p>For those exception classes that require mandatory handling, the situation
is different. If a subroutine can throw such an exception, that fact
<b>must</b> be announced in a <code>throws</code> clause in the routine definition.
Failing to do so is a syntax error that will be reported by the compiler.
Exceptions that require mandatory handling are called <newword>checked exceptions</newword>.
The compiler will check that such exceptions are handled by the program.</p>

<p>Suppose that some statement in the body of a subroutine can generate a
checked exception, one that requires mandatory handling. The statement could be a
<code>throw</code> statement, which throws the exception directly, or it could be a
call to a subroutine that can throw the exception. In either case, the
exception <b>must</b> be handled. This can be done in one of two ways: The first way
is to place the statement in a <code>try</code> statement that has a <code>catch</code>
clause that handles the exception; in this case, the exception is handled within the
subroutine, so that no caller of the subroutine can ever see the exception.
The second way is to declare that the subroutine can throw the exception. This is done by
adding a "<code>throws</code>" clause to the subroutine heading, which alerts any callers
to the possibility that the exception might be generated when the subroutine is executed.
The caller will, in turn, be forced either to handle the exception in a <code>try</code>
statement or to declare the exception in a <code>throws</code> clause in its own
header.</p>

<p>Exception-handling is mandatory for any exception class that is <b>not</b> a
subclass of either <classname>Error</classname> or <classname>RuntimeException</classname>. 
These checked exceptions generally represent conditions that are outside the
control of the programmer. For example, they might represent bad input or an
illegal action taken by the user.  There is no way to <b>avoid</b> such errors,
so a robust program has to be prepared to handle them.  The design of Java makes it 
impossible for programmers to ignore the possibility of such errors.</p>

<p>Among the checked exceptions are several that can
occur when using Java's input/output routines. This means that you can't even
use these routines unless you understand something about exception-handling.
<localref href="IO"/> deals with input/output and uses checked exceptions
extensively.</p>
   
</subsection>
   
<subsection id="robustness.3.5" title="Programming with Exceptions">
   
<p>Exceptions can be used to help write robust
programs. They provide an organized and structured approach to robustness.
Without exceptions, a program can become cluttered with <code>if</code> statements
that test for various possible error conditions. With exceptions, it becomes
possible to write a clean implementation of an algorithm that will handle all
the normal cases. The exceptional cases can be handled elsewhere, in a
<code>catch</code> clause of a <code>try</code> statement.</p>

<p>When a program encounters an exceptional condition and has no way of
handling it immediately, the program can throw an exception. In some cases, it
makes sense to throw an exception belonging to one of Java's predefined
classes, such as <classname>IllegalArgumentException</classname> or <classname>IOException</classname>.
However, if there is no standard class that adequately represents the
exceptional condition, the programmer can define a new exception class. The new
class must extend the standard class <classname>Throwable</classname> or one of its
subclasses. In general, if the programmer does <b>not</b> want to require
mandatory exception handling,
the new class will extend <classname>RuntimeException</classname> (or
one of its subclasses).  To create a new checked exception class, which <b>does</b> require
mandatory handling, the programmer can extend one of the other subclasses of
<classname>Exception</classname> or can extend <classname>Exception</classname> itself.</p>

<p>Here, for example, is a class that extends <classname>Exception</classname>, and therefore
requires mandatory exception handling when it is used:</p>

<pre>public class ParseError extends Exception {
   public ParseError(String message) {
         // Create a ParseError object containing
         // the given message as its error message.
      super(message);
   }
}</pre>

<np>The class contains only a constructor that makes it possible to create a
<classname>ParseError</classname> object containing a given error message. (The statement
"<code>super(message)</code>" calls a constructor in the superclass,
<classname>Exception</classname>. See <localref href="OOP.6.3"/>.) Of course the
class inherits the <code>getMessage()</code> and <code>printStackTrace()</code>
routines from its superclass. If <code>e</code> refers to an object of type
<classname>ParseError</classname>, then the function call <code>e.getMessage()</code> will
retrieve the error message that was specified in the constructor. But the main
point of the <classname>ParseError</classname> class is simply to exist. When an object of
type <classname>ParseError</classname> is thrown, it indicates that a certain type of error
has occurred. (<newword>Parsing</newword>, by the way, refers to
figuring out the syntax of a string. A <classname>ParseError</classname> would indicate,
presumably, that some string that is being processed by the program does not have the
expected form.)</np>

<p>A <code>throw</code> statement can be used in a program to throw an error of
type <classname>ParseError</classname>. The constructor for the <classname>ParseError</classname> object
must specify an error message. For example:</p>

<pre>throw new ParseError("Encountered an illegal negative number.");</pre>

<np>or</np>

<pre>throw new ParseError("The word '" + word 
                               + "' is not a valid file name.");</pre>

<p>Since <classname>ParseError</classname> is defined as a subclass of <classname>Exception</classname>,
it is a checked exception.
If the <code>throw</code> statement does not occur in a <code>try</code> statement
that catches the error, then the subroutine that contains the <code>throw</code>
must declare that it can throw a <classname>ParseError</classname> by
adding the clause "<code>throws ParseError</code>" to the subroutine heading. For
example,</p>

<pre>void getUserData() throws ParseError {
   . . .
}</pre>

<np>This would not be required if <classname>ParseError</classname> were defined as a subclass
of <classname>RuntimeException</classname> instead of <classname>Exception</classname>, since in that case
<classname>ParseErrors</classname> would not be checked exceptions.</np>

<p>A routine that wants to handle <classname>ParseErrors</classname> can use a <code>try</code>
statement with a <code>catch</code> clause that catches <classname>ParseErrors</classname>. For
example:</p>

<pre>try {
   getUserData();
   processUserData();
}
catch (ParseError pe) {
   . . .  // Handle the error
}</pre>

<np>Note that since <classname>ParseError</classname> is a subclass of <classname>Exception</classname>, a
<code>catch</code> clause of the form "<code>catch (Exception e)</code>" would also
catch <classname>ParseErrors</classname>, along with any other object of type
<classname>Exception</classname>.</np>

<p>Sometimes, it's useful to store extra data in an exception object. For
example,</p>

<pre>class ShipDestroyed extends RuntimeException {
   Ship ship;  // Which ship was destroyed.
   int where_x, where_y;  // Location where ship was destroyed.
   ShipDestroyed(String message, Ship s, int x, int y) {
         // Constructor creates a ShipDestroyed object
         // carrying an error message plus the information
         // that the ship s was destroyed at location (x,y)
         // on the screen. 
       super(message);
       ship = s;
       where_x = x;
       where_y = y;
   }
}</pre>

<np>Here, a <classname>ShipDestroyed</classname> object contains an error message and some
information about a ship that was destroyed. This could be used, for example,
in a statement:</np>

<pre>if ( userShip.isHit() )
   throw new ShipDestroyed("You've been hit!", userShip, xPos, yPos);</pre>

<p>Note that the condition represented by a <classname>ShipDestroyed</classname> object might
not even be considered an error. It could be just an expected interruption to
the normal flow of a game. Exceptions can sometimes be used to handle such
interruptions neatly.</p>

<break/>

<p>The ability to throw exceptions is particularly useful in writing
general-purpose methods and classes that are meant to be used in more than
one program. In this case, the person writing the method or class often has
no reasonable way of handling the error, since that person has no way of
knowing exactly how the method or class will be used. In such
circumstances, a novice programmer is often tempted to print an error message
and forge ahead, but this is almost never satisfactory since it can lead to
unpredictable results down the line. Printing an error message and terminating
the program is almost as bad, since it gives the program no chance to handle
the error.</p>

<p>The program that calls the method or uses the class needs to know that
the error has occurred. In languages that do not support exceptions, the only
alternative is to return some special value or to set the value of some global
variable to indicate that an error has occurred. For example, the
<code>readMeasurement()</code> function in <localref href="robustness.2.2"/> returns
the value <code>-1</code> if the user's input is illegal. However, this only does any good
if the main program bothers to test the return value.  It is very easy to be lazy about
checking for special return values every time a subroutine is called.
And in this case, using
<code>-1</code> as a signal that an error has occurred makes it impossible to allow
negative measurements.  Exceptions are a cleaner way for a subroutine to react
when it encounters an error.</p>

<p>It is easy to modify the <code>readMeasurement()</code> function to use
exceptions instead of a special return value to signal an error. My modified
subroutine throws a <classname>ParseError</classname> when the user's input is illegal, where
<classname>ParseError</classname> is the subclass of <classname>Exception</classname> that was defined
above. (Arguably, it might be reasonable to avoid
defining a new class by using the standard exception class
<classname>IllegalArgumentException</classname> instead.) The changes from the original
version are shown in &newcodestyle;:</p>

<pre>
/**
 * Reads the user's input measurement from one line of input.
 * Precondition:   The input line is not empty.
 * Postcondition:  If the user's input is legal, the measurement
 *                 is converted to inches and returned.
 <newcode>* @throws ParseError if the user's input is not legal.</newcode>
 */
static double readMeasurement() <newcode>throws ParseError</newcode> {

   double inches;  // Total number of inches in user's measurement.
   
   double measurement;  // One measurement, 
                        //   such as the 12 in "12 miles."
   String units;        // The units specified for the measurement,
                        //   such as "miles."
   
   char ch;  // Used to peek at next character in the user's input.

   inches = 0;  // No inches have yet been read.

   skipBlanks();
   ch = TextIO.peek();
   
   /* As long as there is more input on the line, read a measurement and
      add the equivalent number of inches to the variable, inches.  If an
      error is detected during the loop, end the subroutine immediately
      by <newcode>throwing a ParseError.</newcode> */

   while (ch != '\n') {
   
       /* Get the next measurement and the units.  Before reading
          anything, make sure that a legal value is there to read. */
   
       if ( ! Character.isDigit(ch) ) {
           <newcode>throw new ParseError("Expected to find a number, but found " + ch);</newcode>
       }
       measurement = TextIO.getDouble();
       
       skipBlanks();
       if (TextIO.peek() == '\n') {
          <newcode>throw new ParseError("Missing unit of measure at end of line.");</newcode>
       }
       units = TextIO.getWord();
       units = units.toLowerCase();
       
       /* Convert the measurement to inches and add it to the total. */
       
       if (units.equals("inch") 
               || units.equals("inches") || units.equals("in")) {
           inches += measurement;
       }
       else if (units.equals("foot") 
                  || units.equals("feet") || units.equals("ft")) {
           inches += measurement * 12;
       }
       else if (units.equals("yard") 
                  || units.equals("yards") || units.equals("yd")) {
           inches += measurement * 36;
       }
       else if (units.equals("mile") 
                  || units.equals("miles") || units.equals("mi")) {
           inches += measurement * 12 * 5280;
       }
       else {
           <newcode>throw new ParseError("\"" + units 
                                + "\" is not a legal unit of measure.");</newcode>
       }
     
       /* Look ahead to see whether the next thing on the line is 
          the end-of-line. */
      
       skipBlanks();
       ch = TextIO.peek();
       
   }  // end while
   
   return inches;
   
} // end readMeasurement()</pre>

<np>In the main program, this subroutine is called in a <code>try</code> statement
of the form</np>

<pre>try {
   inches = readMeasurement();
}
catch (ParseError e) {
   . . .  // Handle the error.
}</pre>

<p>The complete program can be found in the file <sourceref href="LengthConverter3.java"/>.
From the user's
point of view, this program has exactly the same behavior as the program
<sourceref href="LengthConverter2.java">LengthConverter2</sourceref>
from the <localref href="robustness.2">previous section</localref>. 
Internally, however, the programs are significantly
different, since <code>LengthConverter3</code> uses exception handling.</p>

</subsection>

</section>