<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../javanotes9.dtd" >

<section id="robustness.4" title="Assertions and Annotations">

<p><start><big>I</big>n this short section</start>, we look briefly 
at two features of Java that are not covered or used elsewhere in this
textbook, assertions and annotations.  They are included here for 
completeness, but they are mostly meant for more advanced programming.
(Annotations, in particular, don't really belong in this chapter, 
but I could not find a better place to put my short introduction
to the topic.)</p>
 
<subsection id="robustness.4.1" title="Assertions">

<p>Recall that a precondition is a condition that must be true at a certain
point in a program, for the execution of the program to continue correctly from
that point.  In the case where there is a chance that the precondition might not
be satisfied&mdash;for example, if it depends on input from the user&mdash;then
it's a good idea to insert an <code>if</code> statement to test it.
But then the question arises, What should be done if the precondition does not
hold? One option is to throw an exception. This will terminate the program,
unless the exception is caught and handled elsewhere in the program.</p>
   
<p>In many cases, of course, instead of using an <code>if</code> statement to 
<i>test</i> whether a precondition holds, a programmer tries to write the program
in a way that will <i>guarantee</i> that the precondition holds.  In that case,
the test should not be necessary, and the <code>if</code> statement can be
avoided.  The problem is that programmers are not perfect.  In spite of the programmer's
intention, the program might contain a bug that screws up the precondition.
So maybe it's a good idea to check the precondition after all&mdash;at least during the
debugging phase of program development.</p>

<p>Similarly, a postcondition is a condition that is true at a certain point in the program 
as a consequence of the code that has been executed before that point.  Assuming
that the code is correctly written, a postcondition is guaranteed to be true,
but here again testing whether a desired postcondition is <b>actually</b> true
is a way of checking for a bug that might have screwed up the postcondition.
This is something that might be desirable during debugging.</p>

<p>And the same thing applies to loop invariants and class invariants.  These
are things that <b>should</b> be true at certain points in a program.  If they
are not true at those points, it means that the program contains a bug.</p>
   
<p>The programming languages C and C++ have always had a facility for adding
what are called <newword>assertions</newword> to a program. These
assertions take the form "<code>assert(</code><bnf>condition</bnf><code>)</code>", 
where <bnf>condition</bnf> is a <ptype>boolean</ptype>-valued expression. This
condition expresses a precondition or postcondition that should hold at that point in the program.
When the computer encounters an assertion during the execution of the program,
it evaluates the condition. If the condition is false, the program is
terminated.  Otherwise, the program continues normally.  This allows the
programmer's belief that the condition is true to be tested; if it is not
true, that indicates that the part of the program that preceded the assertion
contained a bug.  One nice thing about assertions in C and C++ is that they can be
"turned off" at compile time. That is, if the program is compiled in one way,
then the assertions are included in the compiled code. If the program is
compiled in another way, the assertions are not included. During debugging, the
first type of compilation is used, with assertions turned on. The release version of the program is
compiled with assertions turned off. The release version will be more
efficient, because the computer won't have to evaluate all the assertions.</p>
   
<p>Although early versions of Java did not have assertions, an assertion facility similar 
to the one in C/C++ has been available in Java since version 1.4.  As with the
C/C++ version, Java assertions can be turned on during debugging and turned off
during normal execution.  In Java, however, assertions are turned on and off
at run time rather than at compile time.  An assertion in the Java source code
is always included in the compiled class file.  When the program is run in the normal
way, these assertions are ignored; since the condition in the assertion is not
evaluated in this case, there is little or no performance penalty for having the
assertions in the program.  When the program is being debugged, it can be run
with assertions enabled, as discussed below, and then the assertions can be
a great help in locating and identifying bugs.</p>
   

<break/>
   
<p>An <newword>assertion statement</newword> in Java takes one of the following two forms:</p>
   
<pre>assert <bnf>condition</bnf> ;</pre>
  
<np>or</np>
    
<pre>assert <bnf>condition</bnf> : <bnf>error-message</bnf> ;</pre>

<np>where <bnf>condition</bnf> is a <ptype>boolean</ptype>-valued expression
and <bnf>error-message</bnf> is a string or an expression of type <classname>String</classname>.
The word "<code>assert</code>" is a reserved word in Java, which cannot be used as
an identifier.  An assertion statement can be used anyplace in Java where a statement is legal.</np>
   
<p>If a program is run with assertions disabled, an assertion statement is equivalent to
an empty statement and has no effect.  When assertions are enabled and an assertion statement
is encountered in the program, the <bnf>condition</bnf> 
in the assertion is evaluated.  If the value is <code>true</code>, the program proceeds normally.
If the value of the condition is <code>false</code>, then an exception of type
<code>java.lang.AssertionError</code> is thrown, and the program will crash (unless the
error is caught by a <code>try</code> statement).  If the <code>assert</code> statement
includes an <bnf>error-message</bnf>, then the error message string becomes the message
in the <classname>AssertionError</classname>.</p>
   
<p>So, the statement "<code>assert <bnf>condition</bnf> : <bnf>error-message</bnf>;"</code> is
similar to</p>   
   
<pre>if ( <bnf>condition</bnf> == false )
    throw new AssertionError( <bnf>error-message</bnf> );</pre>
   
<np>except that the <code>if</code> statement is executed whenever the program is
run, and the <code>assert</code> statement is executed only when the program is
run with assertions enabled.</np>
   
<p>The question is, when to use assertions instead of exceptions? The general
rule is to use assertions to test conditions that should definitely be true,
if the program is written correctly.  Assertions are useful for testing a program 
to see whether or not it is correct and for finding the errors in an incorrect program.
After testing and debugging, when the program is used in the normal way, the
assertions in the program will be ignored.  However, if a problem turns up later,
the assertions are still there in the program to be used to help locate the
error.  If someone writes to you to say that your program doesn't work when
he does such-and-such, you can run the program with assertions enabled, do
such-and-such, and hope that the assertions in the program will help you
locate the point in the program where it goes wrong.</p>
   
<p>Consider, for example, the <code>root()</code> method from <localref href="robustness.3.3"/>
that calculates a root of a quadratic equation.  If you believe that your program will
always call this method with legal arguments, then it would make sense to write the
method using assertions instead of exceptions:</p>
   
<pre>/**
 * Returns the larger of the two roots of the quadratic equation
 *     A*x*x + B*x + C = 0.  
 * Precondition: A != 0 and B*B - 4*A*C &gt;= 0.
 */
static public double root( double A, double B, double C )  {
   assert A != 0 : "Leading coefficient of quadratic equation cannot be zero.";
   double disc = B*B - 4*A*C;
   assert disc &gt;= 0 : "Discriminant of quadratic equation cannot be negative.";
   return  (-B + Math.sqrt(disc)) / (2*A);
}</pre>

<np>The assertions are not checked when the program is run in the normal way.  If you
are correct in your belief that the method is never called with illegal arguments,
then checking the conditions in the assertions would be unnecessary.  If your belief
is not correct, the problem should turn up during testing or debugging, when the program is
run with the assertions enabled.</np>
   
<p>If the <code>root()</code> method is part of a software library that you
expect other people to use, then the situation is less clear.  Oracle's
Java documentation advises that assertions should <b>not</b> be used for checking
the contract of public methods:  If the caller of a method violates the contract
by passing illegal parameters, then an exception should be thrown.  This will enforce
the contract whether or not assertions are enabled.  (However, while it's true
that Java programmers <i>expect</i> the contract of a method to be enforced with
exceptions, there are reasonable arguments for using assertions instead, in some
cases.)  One might say that assertions are for <b>you</b>, to help you in
debugging your code, while exceptions are for people who use your code, to alert
them that they are misusing it.</p>
   
<p>On the other hand, it never hurts to use an assertion to check a postcondition
or an invariant.  These are conditions that are definitely expected to be true
in any bug-free program, so an assertion is the natural way to check the
condition while debugging, without imposing an efficiency penalty when
the program is executed normally.   If the postcondition or invariant is 
false, there is a bug, and that is something that needs to be found during 
the testing and debugging phase of programming.</p>
   
<break/>

<p>To have any effect, assertions must be <b>enabled</b> when the program is run.
How to do this depends on what programming environment you are using.  (See
<localref href="basics.6"/> for a discussion of programming environments.)
In the usual command line environment, assertions are enabled by adding the 
option <code>-enableassertions</code> to the <code>java</code> command that 
is used to run the program.  For example, if the class that contains the main 
program is <classname>RootFinder</classname>, then the command</p>
   
<pre>java  -enableassertions  RootFinder</pre>

<np>will run the program with assertions enabled.  
The <code>-enableassertions</code>
option can be abbreviated to <code>-ea</code>, so the command can alternatively
be written as</np>
   
<pre>java  -ea  RootFinder</pre>
   
<p>In fact, it is possible to enable assertions in just part of a program.
An option of the form
"<code>-ea:<bnf>class-name</bnf></code>"
enables only the assertions in the specified class.  Note that there are no
spaces between the <code>-ea</code>, the ":", and the name of the class.  To
enable all the assertions in a package and in its sub-packages, you can use
an option of the form "<code>-ea:<bnf>package-name</bnf>...</code>".
To enable assertions in the "default package" (that is, classes that are not specified to
belong to a package, like almost all the classes in this book), use
"<code>-ea:...</code>".  For
example, to run a Java program named "MegaPaint" with assertions enabled for every class
in the packages named "paintutils" and "drawing", you would use the command:</p>

<pre>java  -ea:paintutils...  -ea:drawing...  MegaPaint</pre>
   
<p>If you are using the Eclipse integrated development environment, you can
specify the <code>-ea</code> option by creating a <newword>run configuration</newword>.
Right-click the name of the main program class in the Package Explorer pane,
and select "Run As" from the pop-up menu and then "Run&dots;" from the
submenu.  This will open a dialog box where you can manage run configurations.
The name of the project and of the main class will be already be filled in.
Click the "Arguments" tab, and enter <code>-ea</code> in the box
under "VM Arguments".  The contents of this box are added to the <code>java</code>
command that is used to run the program.  You can enter other options
in this box, including more complicated <code>enableassertions</code> options such 
as <code>-ea:paintutils...</code>.  When you click the "Run" button,
the options will be applied.  Furthermore, they will be applied whenever
you run the program, unless you change the run configuration or add a
new configuration.  Note that it is possible to make two run configurations
for the same class, one with assertions enabled and one with assertions
disabled.</p>
   
</subsection>
  
<subsection id="robustness.4.2" title="Annotations">

<p>The term "annotation" commonly refers to notes added to or written alongside a
main text, to help you understand or appreciate the text.  An annotation
might be a note that you make to yourself in the margin of a book.
It might be a footnote added to an old novel by an editor to explain
the historical context of some event.  The annotation is metadata or "metatext,"
that is, text written <i>about</i> the main text rather than as
<i>part of</i> the main text itself.</p>

<p>Comments on a program are actually a kind of annotation.  Since they
are ignored by the compiler, they have no effect on the meaning of
the program.  They are there to explain that meaning to a human
reader.  It is possible, of course, for another computer program
(not the compiler) to process comments.  That's what is done in the
case of Javadoc comments, which are processed by a program that
uses them to create API documentation.  But comments are only
one type of metadata that might be added to programs.</p>

<p>In Java 5.0, a new feature called <newword>annotations</newword>
was added to the Java language to make it easier to create new kinds
of metadata for Java programs.  This has made it possible for programmers
to devise new ways of annotating programs, and to write programs
that can read and use their annotations.</p>

<p>Java annotations have no direct effect on the program that
they annotate.  But they do have many potential uses.  Some
annotations are used to make the programmer's intent more
explicit. Such annotations might be checked by a compiler
to make sure that the code is consistent with the programmer's
intention.  For example, <code>@Override</code> is a standard
annotation that can be used to annotate method definitions.
It means that the method is intended to override (that is replace)
a method with the same signature that was defined in some
superclass.  A compiler can check that the superclass
method actually exists; if not, it can inform the programmer.
An annotation used in this way is an aid to writing correct
programs, since the programmer can be warned about a potential
error in advance, instead of having to hunt it down later
as a bug.</p>

<p>To annotate a method definition with the <code>@Override</code>
annotation,
simply place it in front of the definition.  Syntactically,
annotations are modifiers that are used in much the same way
as built-in modifiers like "public" and "final."  For example,
</p>

<pre>@Override public void WindowClosed(WindowEvent evt) { ... }</pre>

<np>If there is no <code>"WindowClosed(WindowEvent)"</code> method
in any superclass, then the compiler can issue an error.  In fact,
this example is based on a hard-to-find bug that I once introduced
when trying to override a method named "windowClosed" with
a method that I called "WindowClosed" (with an upper case "W").
If the <code>@Override</code> annotation had existed at that time&mdash;and
if I had used it&mdash;the compiler could have rejected my code
and saved me the trouble of tracking down the bug.
</np>

<p>(Annotations are a fairly advanced feature, and I might not have
mentioned them in this textbook, except that the <code>@Override</code>
annotation can show up in code generated by Eclipse and other integrated
development environments.)</p>

<p>There are two other standard annotations. One is <code>@Deprecated</code>,
which can be used to mark deprecated classes, methods, and variables.
(A deprecated item is one that is considered to be obsolete, but is
still part of the Java language for backwards compatibility for old code.)
Use of this annotation would allow a compiler to generate warnings
when the deprecated item is used.
</p>

<p>The other standard annotation is <code>@SurpressWarnings</code>,
which can be used by a compiler to turn off warning messages that
would ordinarily be generated when a class or method is compiled.
<code>@SuppressWarnings</code> is an example of an annotation that
has a parameter.  The parameter tells what class of warnings
are to be suppressed.  For example, when a class or method is
annotated with</p>

<pre>@SuppressWarnings("deprecation")</pre>

<np>then no warnings about the use of deprecated items will be emitted
when the class or method is compiled.  There are other types of
warning that can be suppressed; unfortunately the list of warnings
and their names is not standardized and will vary from one compiler
to another.</np>

<p>Note, by the way, that the syntax for annotation parameters&mdash;especially
for an annotation that accepts multiple parameters&mdash;is not
the same as the syntax for method parameters.  I won't cover
the annotation syntax here.</p>

<p>Programmers can define new annotations for use in their code.
Such annotations are ignored by standard compilers and programming
tools, but it's possible to write programs that can understand the
annotations and check for their presence in source code.  It is even
possible to create annotations that will be retained at run-time and
become part of the running program.  In that case, a program
can check for annotations in the actual compiled code that is being 
executed, and take actions that depend on the presence of the annotation
or the values of its parameters.</p>

<p>Annotations can help programmers to write correct programs.
To use an example from the Java documentation, they can help
with the creation of "boilerplate" code&mdash;that is, code that
has a very standardized format and that can be generated mechanically.
Often, boilerplate code is generated based on other code.  Doing
that by hand is a tedious and error-prone process.  A simple
example might be code to save certain aspects of a program's state
to a file and to restore it later.  The code for reading and writing
the values of all the relevant state variables is highly repetitious.
Instead of writing that code by hand, a programmer could use an
annotation to mark the variables that are part of the state
that is to be saved.  A program could then be used to check for
the annotations and generate the save-and-restore code.  In fact,
it would even be possible to do without that code altogether, if the program
checks for the presence of the annotation at run time to decide
which variables to save and restore.
</p>


</subsection>

</section>
